<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16581520</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1693763</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="other">CI60005</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.0005</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.i1.pg20</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="other">ci060005</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <series-title>Article</series-title>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Supra-clavicular lymph node metastatic spread in patients with ovarian cancer disclosed at <sup>18</sup>F-FDG-PET/CT: an unusual finding</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fanti</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nanni</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Castellucci</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Farsad</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rampin</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gross</surname>
            <given-names>M D</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x2021;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mariani</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">&#xA7;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rubello</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>*</label>Nuclear Medicine Service &#x2013; PET Unit, S Orsola-Malighi Hospital, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>&#x2020;</label>Nuclear Medicine Service &#x2013; PET Unit, S Maria della Misericordia Hospital, Rovigo, Italy</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>&#x2021;</label>Nuclear Medicine Service &#x2013; PET Unit, Veteran Affairs Hospital, Michigan, Ann Arbor, USA</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>&#xA7;</label>Regional Center of Nuclear Medicine, University of Pisa, Pisa, Italy</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">Corresponding address: Domenico Rubello, MD, Nuclear Medicine Service &#x2013; PET Unit, S Maria della Misericordia Hospital, Istituto Oncologico Veneto (IOV), Viale Tre Martiri, 140, 45100, Rovigo, Italy. Email: <email>domenico.rubello@libero.it</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>20</fpage>
      <lpage>23</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tumoral dissemination of ovarian cancer most commonly occurs through the intra-peritoneal route; nevertheless, although it is rare, ovarian cancer may also metastasise through the lymphatic channels. Lymphatic diffusion of ovarian cancer usually involves pelvic and retro-peritoneal lymph nodes. Extra-abdominal lymph nodes are rarely involved and their detection may represent a challenge for the oncologist. We describe here two patients studied for ovarian cancer by [<sup>18</sup>F]fluoro-2-deoxy-D-glucose (<sup>18</sup>F-FDG) positron emission tomography (PET)/computed tomography (CT): one case during pre-operative staging, the other for restaging after surgery. In both cases PET examination identified extra-abdominal lymph node tumoral spread in the left supra-clavicular space; biopsy led to a final diagnosis of recurrent ovarian cancer. Previous reports in the literature on tumoral spread of ovarian cancer to the supra-clavicular nodes are rare, however this possible site of metastatic involvement has to be kept in mind by oncologists and our data show that the <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT may be useful to disclose this unusual supra-diaphragmatic lymphatic diffusion of metastatic lymphatic ovarian cancer. </p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <kwd><sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT</kwd>
        <kwd>ovarian cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>disease recurrence</kwd>
        <kwd>supra-clavicular lymph nodes</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Ovarian cancer has the highest mortality rate of all gynaecologic malignancies in Europe and in the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>]. This happens primarily because ovarian cancer presents at a relatively advanced stage of the disease.</p>
      <p>Dissemination of ovarian cancer is most common by the intra-peritoneal route so that in the majority of patients disease most frequently remains confined to the peritoneal cavity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>]. Nevertheless, ovarian cancer may also metastasize through lymphatic channels; for this reason a lymph node metastasis classification has been introduced into the FIGO staging.</p>
      <p>The prognostic significance of lymph node metastasis(es) in ovarian cancer is still controversial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>] and researchers have paid most attention to investigating the prognostic impact of para-aortic lymph node metastasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>]. Indeed, very few papers describe extra-abdominal lymph node involvement in this type of tumour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>Positron emission tomography (PET) with [<sup>18</sup>F]fluoro-2-deoxy-D-glucose (FDG) has emerged as an extremely useful technique in clinical oncology. A high accuracy of <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET has been proven for evaluating patients with ovarian tumours, both for the assessment of ovarian neoplasms before treatment and for the evaluation of cancer recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Recently hybrid PET/computed tomography (CT) has been introduced in clinical practice, combining the information derived from the functional imaging of <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET with the detailed morphological data of CT. Preliminary reports indicate a potential usefulness of this technique for the precise identification of cancer spread [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>]. In particular, in ovarian cancer <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT was found to be particularly useful in identifying abdominal recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>].</p>
      <p>We describe here two patients studied for ovarian cancer. In both cases <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT allowed us to identify extra-abdominal lymph node involvement in the left supra-clavicular space. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>PET technique</title>
        <p>Each patient, fasted for at least 6 h, was intravenously injected with 5.3 MBq /kg of <sup>18</sup>F-FDG; images were recorded 60&#x2013;90 min after tracer administration using a Discovery LS-ST4 scanner (General Electric Medical System, Waukesha, WI). The CT parameters were as follows: 140 kV, 90 mA, 0.8 s per tube rotation, 30 mm table speed per gantry rotation. Multi-slice technology allowed the acquisition of four slices per tube rotation with a thickness of 5 mm. PET studies were performed acquiring 4 min of emission data per bed position and 35 transaxial images were reconstructed for each bed. Scaled CT images were used for non-uniform attenuation correction of PET emission scans. Total scan time was approximately 20 min. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case report 1</title>
        <p>A 51-year-old patient was operated on June 2003 for a pelvic tumour. Pre-surgical diagnostic work-up included abdominal-pelvic CT and ultrasound; a large pelvic mass likely originating from the left ovary was depicted. At laparoscopy a 10 cm mass characterised by a combination of solid and cystic areas with involvement of both annexials was found. The patient was operated on by laparotomy, and total hysterectomy plus bilateral annexial resection and peritoneal washing were performed. Histology indicated a poorly differentiated cancer, infiltrating the myometrium; the peritoneal fluid was positive for cancerous cells. The patient was then scheduled for chemotherapy. Before an <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT scan was obtained. PET/CT revealed multiple sites of increased glycolytic metabolism in lymph nodes: iliac bilaterally, left lumbar, para-caval and also left supra-clavicular/latero-cervical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1 F2">Figs 1 and 2</xref>). The presence of supra-clavicular lymph nodes was confirmed by ultrasound and CT, and the final diagnosis of metastatic ovarian cancer was reached by biopsy. The patient was then treated by chemotherapy (carboplatin plus taxol plus topotecan) obtaining a good response (a reduction of Ca125 from 273 to 14). The post-treatment PET/CT was negative.     </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case report 2</title>
        <p>A 65-year-old patient was admitted to our hospital in July 2003 for complete staging and subsequently surgery for a pelvic tumour. The patient had already undergone hysterectomy in 1982 for fibrocystic endometriosis. Ultrasound demonstrated the presence of a pelvic mass with non-homogeneous echogenicity; abdominal-pelvic CT confirmed the presence of a large mass (17&#xD7;12&#xD7;14 cm) and also showed lymph nodal involvement at para-aortic, para-caval, retro-crural levels. <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT was therefore performed for staging. PET/CT showed an intense radio-tracer uptake in the pelvic mass, and also revealed multiple hypermetabolic lymph nodes in the para-aortic, para-caval, retro-crural and left supra-clavicular regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3 F4">Figs 3 and 4</xref>). Biopsy confirmed a metastatic spread of ovarian cancer. The patient was then operated on by laparotomy, with mass excision and bilateral annexiectomy. Histology showed a poorly differentiated serum-papillary carcinoma. At discharge the patient was scheduled for chemotherapy, but she refused further treatment.     </p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Ovarian cancer tends physiologically to metastasise via the lymphatic channels, mainly the intra-peritoneal route and understanding of the sites of spread is crucial for disease treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>]. Lymphatic diffusion of ovarian cancer is commonly retained to involve mainly pelvic lymph nodes and, subsequently, retro-peritoneal lymph nodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Data from the literature concerning extra-abdominal lymph node involvement are very poor. In this respect, it is worth noting that a recent review on this topic did not take into account the prevalence of extra-abdominal positive nodes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>]. The same occurred in a recent paper reviewing nodal metastasis in ovarian cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>]. Conversely, Cormio and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>] reviewed 162 patients with epithelial ovarian carcinoma and reported five cases of extra-abdominal lymphatic spread. Interestingly, Zang and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>] described their 10-years of experience of patients with ovarian cancer presenting initially with extra-abdominal metastases and reported a significant number of cases with supra-clavicular and inguinal lymph nodes metastases (6 and 5 cases, respectively). Apart from these two papers, a case report described left internal mammary lymph node involvement in a patient with serious borderline ovarian tumour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>]; two cases of intra-mammary lymph node metastases were described: in a case of early-staged ovarian cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>] and in a case of a borderline papillary ovarian tumour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>]. Lastly, we found few cases of axillary lymph nodes calcification in patients with metastatic ovarian carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>]. These sporadic reports in the literature clearly indicate that extra-abdominal lymph node spread in ovarian cancer is possible although rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>].</p>
      <p>On the basis of our findings, it may be speculated that <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT is a useful tool and it may be particularly useful to detect unusual extra-abdominal nodal involvement in ovarian cancer.</p>
      <p>Further studies on a higher number of patients are required to elucidate the potential role of <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT in evaluating lymphatic metastatic spread of ovarian cancer. </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="b1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wingo</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tong</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bolden</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cancer statistics</article-title>
          <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7528632</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seidman</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurman</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pathology of ovarian carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Hematol Oncol Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>909</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12959182</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuruchi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsukamoto</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akazawa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saito</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaku</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship between paraaortic lymph node involvement and intraperitoneal spread in patients with ovarian cancer&#x2014;a multivariate analysis</article-title>
          <source>Gynecol Oncol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8482561</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kamura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeon</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lymph node metastasis in a gynecologic malignancy</article-title>
          <source>Yonsei Med J</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12497663</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cormio</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossi</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cazzolla</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Resta</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loverro</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greco</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Distant metastases in ovarian carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Int J Gynecol Cancer</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>125</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12657111</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zang</surname>
              <given-names>RY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>MQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>ZT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epithelial ovarian cancer presenting initially with extraabdominal or intrahepatic metastases: a preliminary report of 25 cases and literature review</article-title>
          <source>Am J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>416</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10955875</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Torizuka</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nobezawa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanno</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Futatsubashi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoshikawa</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okada</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ovarian cancer recurrence: role of whole-body positron emission tomography using 2-[fluorine-18]-fluoro-2-deoxy-D-glucose</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>797</fpage>
          <lpage>803</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029554</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schroder</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zimny</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rudlowski</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bull</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rath</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of 18 F-fluoro-deoxyglucose positron emission tomography (18 F-FDG PET) in diagnosis of ovarian cancer</article-title>
          <source>Int J Gynecol Cancer</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>117</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11240752</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ell</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von Schulthess</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>PET-CT: a matter opinion?</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Nucl Med</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>470</fpage>
          <lpage>1</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10">
        <label>10</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pannu</surname>
              <given-names>HK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cohade</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bristow</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fishman</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wahl</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>PET-CT detection of abdominal recurrence of ovarian cancer: radiologic-surgical correlation</article-title>
          <source>Abdom Imaging</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>398</fpage>
          <lpage>403</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15354347</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11">
        <label>11</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Di Re</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baiocchi</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Value of lymph node assessment in ovarian cancer: status of the art at the end of the second millennium</article-title>
          <source>Int J Gynecol Cancer</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>435</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11240711</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12">
        <label>12</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tangjitgamol</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manusirivithaya</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheanakul</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leelahakorn</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spripramote</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thawaramara</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Can we rely on the size of lymph node in determining nodal metastasis in ovarian carcinoma?</article-title>
          <source>Int J Gynecol Cancer</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <lpage>302</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12801259</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13">
        <label>13</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chamberlin</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eltabbakh</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mount</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leavitt</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metastatic serous borderline ovarian tumor in an internal mammary lymph node: case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Gynecol Oncol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>212</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11426990</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14">
        <label>14</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tepedino</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fusco</surname>
              <given-names>EF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Del Priore</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intra-mammary lymph node metastases in an early stage ovarian cancer of low malignant potential</article-title>
          <source>Int J Gynaecol Obstet</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>287</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11102630</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15">
        <label>15</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moreira</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waisman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cangiarella</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metastatic Borderline papillary ovarian tumor in an intramammary lymph node</article-title>
          <source>Breast J</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>309</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12199761</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16">
        <label>16</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Singer</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blankstein</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koenigsberg</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mercado</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pile-Spellman</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mammography appearance of axillary lymph node calcification in patients with metastatic ovarian carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>176</volume>
          <fpage>1437</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11373209</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17">
        <label>17</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamoto</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saga</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishimori</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical value of positron emission tomography with FDG for recurrent ovarian cancer</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>176</volume>
          <fpage>1449</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11373212</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec sec-type="display-objects">
      <title>Figures and Tables</title>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>  <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT scan showing multiple sites of increased FDG uptake in abdominal lymph nodes but also in the left supra-clavicular region. </p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ci06002001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>  <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT scan: (a) CT image, (b) PET image, (c) fusion PET/CT image. Focal area of highly increased FDG uptake is shown in the left supra-clavicular lymph nodes. </p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ci06002002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>  <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT scan revealing increased FDG uptake in the pelvic mass and in multiple abdominal lymph nodes (para-aortic, para-caval, retro-crural), but also in the left supra-clavicular lymph nodes. </p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ci06002003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>  <sup>18</sup>F-FDG PET/CT scan: coronal images, (a) CT image, (b) PET image, (c) PET/CT fusion image. A focal area of intense FDG uptake is shown in the left supra-clavicular lymph nodes. </p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ci06002004"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
