<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Obstet Gynecol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDOG</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Infectious Diseases in Obstetrics and Gynecology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1064-7449</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1098-0997</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485796</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1581461</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/IDOG/2006/15614</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinical Study</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Septic Pelvic Thrombophlebitis: Diagnosis and Management</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Garcia</surname>
            <given-names>Javier</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="a" ref-type="aff"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Aboujaoude</surname>
            <given-names>Ramzi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="a" ref-type="aff"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Apuzzio</surname>
            <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="a" ref-type="aff"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alvarez</surname>
            <given-names>Jesus R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="a" ref-type="aff"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="a">Obstetrics, gynecology, and Women's Health Department, New Jersey Medical School, University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey, Newark, NJ 07103, USA</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">*Ramzi Aboujaoude: <email>ramziajaoude@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2006</volume>
      <elocation-id>15614</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2006 Javier Garcia et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Septic pelvic thrombophlebitis (SPT) was initially diagnosed and
described in the late 1800's. The entity had a high incidence and
mortality during this period of time, and a surgical therapeutic
approach was the treatment of choice. Since then, the diagnosis,
incidence, and management of the entity evolved. This evolution
followed the development of newer diagnostic tools such as
computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and a
better understanding of the pathophysiology of the disease. The
treatment of SPT has had significant changes as well, from a
surgical approach at the end of the 19th century to a
medical approach after the 1960's. By using an adequate
broad-spectrum antibiotic therapy, mortality has decreased.
However, controversy in the management of this entity remains
even till today.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="background">
      <title>BACKGROUND</title>
      <p>The entity of septic pelvic thrombophlebitis has evolved profoundly over the last century. The bulk of cases in early reports was mostly obstetric, with a significant number of following abortions. Gynecologic cases with this complication
represented the minority.</p>
      <p>By the end of the 19th century, von Recklinhausen described
an entity in which pelvic infection was characterized by
thrombosis of one or both ovarian veins while the remaining
pelvis was normal, proposing surgical excision as the therapeutic
approach.</p>
      <p>The first successful cases of pelvic vein ligation as a treatment
for puerperal pyemia were reported between 1898 and 1902 by a
number of German physicians including Bumm, Freund, and
Trendelenburg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. In 1951 Collins published his experience with 202 women
who underwent surgical intervention and proposed a pathogenic
model for suppurative pelvic thrombophlebitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>The incidence of the disease has been dynamic; a clear example is
the experience at the Charity Hospital in New Orleans, where between 1941 and 1969, Collins reported a total of 202 cases. A later report (1974&#x2013;1981) described only three cases in the same institution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. This observation was similar to
the experience gathered from Grady Memorial Hospital and Emory
University Hospital by Josey and Staggers who determined the incidence to be 0.05  percent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In the
following decade (1980 to 1989), Dunnihoo et al calculated a
similar incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Finally, in 1999, Brown and colleagues published a five-year survey of patients delivered at Parkland
Hospital finding an overall incidence of 1 : 3000 deliveries. The
incidence for vaginal delivery was 1 : 9000 compared to 1 : 800
for cesarean section [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Mortality has had a drastic change. Reviews by Williams and Miller
reported an average mortality of roughly 50% during the first
quarter of the twentieth century in patients undergoing surgery.
Collins (1951) reported a 90% survival after the ligation of
inferior vena cava and ovarian veins. During the decade of the
1980's, mortality was reported to be 4.4 percent 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>In 1999 after following a total of 44922 deliveries, 69 patients
carried the diagnosis of prolonged infection. Fifteen patients
were found to have pelvic thrombophlebitis, however, no
complication or death was reported in either group 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASES</title>
      <p>We report two cases which are typical of the eight cases in which
the diagnosis of septic pelvic thrombophlebitis was suspected in
the past two years. These cases highlight the risk factors that
may be associated to the development of septic pelvic
thrombophlebitis, the management, and treatment of the entity.</p>
      <p>Case 1</p>
      <p>A 28-year-old primigravid underwent a cesarean section
secondary to having a breech presentation and rupture of
membranes at 36 weeks gestation. The cesarean section was
uncomplicated, but on postpartum day one the patient was having
fever and uterine tenderness. A diagnosis of postpartum
endometritis was made and the infection was treated with
Ertapenem 1 g intravenously daily. After 48 hours of antibiotics,
the patient denied uterine tenderness and her WBC count was
12000/mm<sup>3</sup>. Nevertheless, the patient continued to spike fevers
and on postpartum day four an abdominal CT scan was obtained. A
right ovarian vein thrombosis was noted on the imaging and the
patient started therapeutic enoxaparin. After 48 hours of
anticoagulation, the patient was afebrile and asymptomatic. The
patient was discharged home after being anticoagulated with
warfarin and after 6 weeks a CT scan was repeated. The right
ovarian thrombosis was not present in the images and warfarin was
discontinued.</p>
      <p>Case 2</p>
      <p>A 32-year-old patient underwent a successful in vitro
fertilization. At 25 weeks gestation the patient had preterm
premature rupture of membranes. The patient was started on
penicillin G and a course of steroids was given. After 1 week of expectant
management, the patient started to have contractions and a
diagnostic amniocentesis was performed. An intraamniotic infection
was diagnosed and a classical cesarean section was performed. The
patient was started on gentamicin and clindamycin
intraoperatively. After 24 hours of antibiotics, the patient
continued to have fever and ampicillin was added. On postpartum
day 4, the patient complained of pelvic pain and continued to have
fever spikes to 101 F. The patient's urinalysis, urine, and blood
cultures were negative and her WBC count was 17000/mm<sup>3</sup>. The
patient was anticoagulated with enoxaparin after a clinical
diagnosis of septic pelvic thrombophlebitis that was suspected and
an abdominal CT scan was ordered. The CT scan was negative, but
after 24 hours of enoxaparin, the patient became afebrile and her
pelvic pain diminished. After 2 days with enoxaparin a WBC count
was repeated showing a decrease to 12000/mm<sup>3</sup>. The patient was
discharged home on enoxaparin for another week and was followed in
clinic for her postoperative appointment. Her pelvic pain was
minimal and the rest of her recovery was uncomplicated.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Pathophysiology</title>
        <p>The pathophysiology of pelvic thrombophlebitis as a progression
of a pelvic infection was first elucidated by Collins and later
Duff, Gibbs, and others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p>
        <p>The pathogenesis is thought to include injury to the intima of the
pelvic vein caused by a spreading uterine infection, bacteremia,
and endotoxins, which can also occur secondary to the trauma of
delivery or surgery. In this setting, Virchow's triad is completed
due to the contribution of pregnancy as a well-known
hypercoagulable state, and the reduction of blood flow in dilated
uterine and ovarian veins during the postpartum period which
causes venous stasis. Phlebographic studies have demonstrated a
left to right venous flow in upright position, which may explain
the dextro-prevalence of ovarian vein thrombosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Diagnostic approach</title>
        <p>A suspicion of SPT should arise when fever, which usually follows
a spiking pattern, fails to respond to standard broad-spectrum
antibiotic therapy. Septic pelvic thrombophlebitis was diagnosed
in 20 percent of patients with prolonged febrile morbidity,
defined as more than five days of fever regardless of appropriate
antimicrobial treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
        <p>Patients often complain of flank and lower abdominal pain,
typically described as noncolicky and constant. Pain may be of
variable intensity and may radiate to the groin or upper abdomen,
and paralytic ileus may occur.</p>
        <p>Upon physical examination, the patient usually does not appear
toxic, there may be tenderness to palpation in the lower abdomen,
and an occasional tender abdominal mass described as rope or
sausage-shape may be identified. This represents the most
diagnostic finding in an abdominal exam, but it is rare.</p>
        <p>Other clinical characteristics of septic pelvic thrombophlebitis
have changed over time. Pulmonary emboli, was considered a
criterion for diagnosis of the condition. Initial reports
described pulmonary embolic phenomena to be frequent, small, and
multiple [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p>
        <p>During the decades of the 1960's through 1970's, some authors
reported that 32 to 38 percent of patients with septic pelvic
thrombophlebitis had evidence of pulmonary emboli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Most of these diagnoses were made only on the basis of radiographic
findings. However, other contemporary investigators demonstrated
an incidence of pulmonary embolism in a range of 2.7%. The
latest series (1999) did not report a single embolic event after
following up 44922 patients over a 3-year period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Refinements in the diagnostic methodology as well as
implementation of earlier and more effective treatment are likely
the reasons responsible for the remarkable decline in the
incidence of embolic events.</p>
        <p>Diagnostic tools like computed tomography (CT) and magnetic
resonance imaging (MRI) are used to provide confirmation of
pelvic thrombophlebitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Tomographic criteria for
diagnosis include (1) enlargement of the vein involved, (2) low
density lumen within the vessel wall, and (3) sharp enhancement
of the vessel wall. When using MRI the thrombosed vessel will
appear bright whereas normal blood flow looks dark.</p>
        <p>It is believed that both methods are comparable. MRI offers a
better visualization of soft tissue changes, being able to
evaluate the resolution of edema and inflammatory signs. However,
both techniques have their limitations related to visualizing
smaller vessels such as uterine, cervical, and other smaller
pelvic branches.</p>
        <p>Anecdotal experiences with pelvic ultrasound used for the
diagnosis of ovarian vein thrombosis revealed a limited utility; nevertheless, ultrasonography may have a role in monitoring treatment response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p>
        <p>The only laboratory test that may aid in the diagnosis and
management of the disease is a complete blood count with blood
cultures. Nevertheless, blood cultures provide identification of a microorganism in less than 35 percent of the cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Management and treatment</title>
        <p>By the turn of the century, surgical excision of the thrombosed
vein was the treatment of choice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. After publishing the experience at the Charity Hospital in New Orleans in 1951,
Collins advocated the ligature of the inferior vena cava and
ovarian veins as the optimal treatment reporting an improvement
in mortality rates after the procedure.</p>
        <p>During the late sixties, heparin anticoagulation in conjunction
with antibiotic coverage gained general acceptance and proved to
be safe. These reports were observational, patient samples were
small and heterogeneous, and the diagnosis of pelvic septic
thrombophlebitis was presumptive in most of the cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p>
        <p>The absence of a definitive diagnostic technique made it
difficult to corroborate a clinical suspicion and compare the
effectiveness of treatment regimens proposed.</p>
        <p>It was believed that the diagnosis of septic pelvic
thrombophlebitis depended on a rapid return to normal temperature
after heparin was given, an observation that is currently being
questioned.</p>
        <p>In the last 20 years, the introduction of computed tomography and
magnetic resonance imaging has revolutionized the diagnosis of
pelvic thrombophlebitis allowing investigators to assess response
to heparin therapy. Several observational studies questioning the
efficacy of anticoagulation were followed by Brown and associates,
who prospectively gathered a total of 14 cases over a three-year
period at Parkland Hospital (Dallas); one group of patients was
randomized to antimicrobial therapy with the addition of heparin,
others were assigned to antibiotics alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Duration of fever and hospital stay was similar in both groups. Furthermore,
neither thromboembolic events nor reinfection were reported
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The Brown et al study does not support the empiric use of anticoagulants for SPT.</p>
        <p>Antibiotic management follows the experience of Di Zerega
 et al (1979), who determined that response to Clindamycin and
Gentamycin in women with endometritis following a cesarean
delivery was adequate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Since then, many comparative studies with novel single and multiagent antibiotic therapies
failed to demonstrate superior efficacy. In 1988 Walmer
et al associated failure of the Clindamycin-Gentamycin combination
with enterococcal infection. Addition of ampicillin resulted in
the &#x201C;triple antibiotic regimen&#x201D; model. Most institutions
recommend this regimen for treatment of puerperal infections;
however, if fever persists after 5 days of antibiotics, it is
suggested to use an alternative antibiotic agent. Imipenem or
ertapenem, with its broad spectrum and anti-pseudomonal activity,
represent a reasonable selection.</p>
        <p>The incidence of septic pelvic thrombophlebitis is likely to
rise, as the cesarean section rates continue to climb. It is
still recommended to treat this entity with broad spectrum
antibiotics. Nevertheless, there are no recommendations available
to guide physicians in regards to anticoagulation therapy. Only
heparin use has been described but is controversial as seen by
Brown et al study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. However, for those who prescribe anticoagulant therapy, can low molecular weight heparin
anticoagulation therapy be used instead of unfractionated
heparin? How long should the patient be anticoagulated? Is there
a role for anticoagulation with oral warfarin? Is there a role of
anticoagulation therapy in the management of septic pelvic
thrombophlebitis? These are the questions for which there are no
answers yet and further randomized studies should be done.</p>
        <p>In our retrospective review, we have had the experience of
successfully managing eight cases of septic pelvic
thrombophlebitis over the last 2 years. We used anticoagulation
therapy in all cases in addition to broad spectrum antibiotic
therapy. When patients did not respond to broad spectrum
antibiotics after 5 days, SPT was suspected, anticoagulation was
initiated with subcutaneous enoxaparin and a CT scan or MRI of
the pelvis was ordered. If the imaging showed a small pelvic
thrombosed vessel, therapeutic enoxaparin would be continued for
2 weeks. If the pelvic imaging was negative, then therapeutic
enoxaparin was given only for 1 week. The only instance were a
patient was converted to oral warfarin and maintained in
therapeutic dosage for 3 months was if a right ovarian vein
thrombosis was seen. A follow up with pelvic MRI was done 3
months after treatment. The cases that we managed fit into the
three categories described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dunnihoo</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gallaspy</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wise</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Otterson</surname>
              <given-names>WN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Postpartum ovarian vein thrombophlebitis: a review</article-title>
          <source>
            <italic>Obstetrical and Gynecological Survey</italic>
          </source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>415</fpage>
          <lpage>427</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1876354</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ligation of extension of the pelvic veins in the treatment of puerperal pyemia</article-title>
          <source>
            <italic>Am J Obstet</italic>
          </source>
          <year>1909</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>758</fpage>
          <lpage>789</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stettler</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Twickler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunningham</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Puerperal septic pelvic thrombophlebitis: incidence and response to heparin therapy</article-title>
          <source>
            <italic>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic>
          </source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>181</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>143</fpage>
          <lpage>148</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10411810</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Collins</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>MacCallum</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>EW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weinstein</surname>
              <given-names>BB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Collins</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Suppurative pelvic thrombophlebitis. I. Incidence, pathology, and etiology</article-title>
          <source>
            <italic>Surgery</italic>
          </source>
          <year>1951</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>298</fpage>
          <lpage>310</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14855228</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Collins</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Suppurative pelvic thrombophlebitis. A study of 202 cases in which the disease was treated by ligation of the vena cava and ovarian vein</article-title>
          <source>
            <italic>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic>
          </source>
          <year>1970</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>681</fpage>
          <lpage>687</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5471237</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Witlin</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sibai</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Postpartum ovarian vein thrombosis after vaginal delivery: a report of 11 cases</article-title>
          <source>
            <italic>Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic>
          </source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <issue>5 I</issue>
          <fpage>775</fpage>
          <lpage>780</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7724112</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Josey</surname>
              <given-names>WE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Staggers</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Heparin therapy in septic pelvic thrombophlebitis: a study of 46 cases</article-title>
          <source>
            <italic>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic>
          </source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>228</fpage>
          <lpage>233</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4413660</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dizerega</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yonekura</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ledger</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A comparison of clindamycin-gentamicin and penicillin-gentamicin in the treatment of post-cesarean section endomyometritis</article-title>
          <source>
            <italic>American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic>
          </source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>134</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>238</fpage>
          <lpage>242</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">453256</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec sec-type="display-objects">
      <title>Figures and Tables</title>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Diagnosis and management for presumed septic pelvic thrombophlebitis.</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT or MRI findings</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotics</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anticoagulation</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of treatment</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final outcome</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                <hr/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right ovarian vein thrombosis</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ertapenem or gentamicin, ampicillin, clindamycin (7 days)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enoxaparin (1 mg/Kg), warfarin (INR 2.5)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x2013;6 months warfarin</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Repeat CT scan after 3 months. If negative, stop anticoagulation. If still positive for thrombi, anticoagulate for 3 additional months</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                <hr/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelvic branch vein thrombosis</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ertapenem or gentamicin, ampicillin, clindamycin (7 days)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enoxaparin (1 mg/Kg)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 weeks</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No repeat imaging necessary</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
                <hr/>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative for pelvic thrombi</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ertapenem or gentamicin, ampicillin, clindamycin (7 days)</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enoxaparin (1 mg/Kg)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 week</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No repeat imaging necessary</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
