<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report" xml:lang="EN">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19402969</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2687036</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-1562</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1505.081562</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Dispatch</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Babesiosis Acquired through Blood Transfusion, California, USA</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Babesiosis Acquired through Blood Transfusion</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Ngo</surname>
            <given-names>Van</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Civen</surname>
            <given-names>Rachel</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">Los Angeles County Department of Public Health, Los Angeles, CA, USA</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: Van Ngo, Los Angeles County Department of Public Health, 313 N Figueroa Ave #212, Los Angeles, CA 90012, USA; email: <email xlink:href="vngo@ph.lacounty.gov">vngo@ph.lacounty.gov</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>785</fpage>
      <lpage>787</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Babesiosis was reported in a California resident who received a transfusion of blood products collected in the disease-endemic northeastern region of the United States. Babesiosis should be considered year-round in the diagnosis of febrile and afebrile patients with abnormal blood cell counts who have received blood products from disease-endemic areas.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author" xml:lang="EN">
        <title>Keywords: </title>
        <kwd>Vector-borne infections</kwd>
        <kwd>babesiosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Babesia microti</kwd>
        <kwd>blood transfusion</kwd>
        <kwd>dispatch</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Babesiosis is an infection of red blood cells (RBCs) caused by various species of the protozoan genus <italic>Babesia</italic>. Most human infections reported in the United States are attributed to <italic>B. microti</italic> and occur most frequently in the Northeast and less commonly in the Midwest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Infrequently, babesiosis cases have been documented in California and Washington; however, these cases were caused by local <italic>Babesia</italic>-like isolates, including <italic>B. duncani</italic> and a <italic>B. divergens</italic>&#x2013;like parasite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref><italic>&#x2013;</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). <italic>B. microti</italic> infection is often asymptomatic but can potentially be severe and even fatal, especially in the elderly, asplenics, and other immunosuppressed persons. Symptoms can be nonspecific, mimicking many systemic infectious diseases, and include fever, chills, myalgias, fatigue, and jaundice caused by hemolytic anemia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>).</p>
    <p>Babesiosis is transmitted primarily through the bite of an infected tick, typically <italic>Ixodes</italic> spp., although occasionally transmission occurs via transfusion of blood products collected from asymptomatic infected donors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). More than 50 transfusion-related cases have been reported in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). This report describes a transfusion-acquired case of babesiosis caused by <italic>B. microti</italic> in a resident of Los Angeles County, California.</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>The Case</title>
      <p>On February 12, 2007, a 58-year-old man with metastatic esophageal cancer was admitted to an acute care facility for evaluation of hematemesis and normocytic anemia. The initial examination showed he had hypotension without fever, joint swelling, headaches, or rash. Laboratory evaluation showed a hemoglobin concentration of 8.4 mg/dL, a platelet count of 71,000/mm<sup>3</sup>, and a leukocyte count of 3.5 &#xD7; 10<sup>3</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup> with 19% bands. Results of liver function tests showed mild elevations in levels of aspartate transaminase (202 mg/dL), alanine transaminase (33 mg/dL), and total bilirubin (0.7 mg/dL).</p>
      <p>An abnormal blood cell count prompted a manual differential count. <italic>Babesia</italic> spp. was identified on a peripheral smear and subsequently confirmed at the Los Angeles County Public Health Laboratory. The result of PCR analysis performed by a commercial laboratory was positive and highly specific for <italic>B. microti</italic> DNA, a result confirmed by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table</xref>). The commercial laboratory also performed indirect fluorescent antibody (IFA) testing for <italic>B. microti</italic> and found both acute and convalescent specimens to be negative. Confirmatory testing at CDC corroborated the negative result for the acute specimen but showed the convalescent specimen, collected 8 days after onset, to be positive for <italic>B. microti</italic>, with a total antibody titer of 64. The patient was treated with azithromycin and atovaquone for 7 days, given 2 blood transfusions for anemia, and discharged in stable condition on February 16, 2007.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Results of serologic testing and PCR analyses of specimens collected from a California resident with babesiosis and donors of packed red blood cells, 2007*</title>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <col width="68" span="1"/>
          <col width="72" span="1"/>
          <col width="90" span="1"/>
          <col width="120" span="1"/>
          <col width="72" span="1"/>
          <col width="59" span="1"/>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Specimen source</th>
              <th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Residence</th>
              <th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Date of transfusion&#x2020;</th>
              <th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Date of specimen collection</th>
              <th valign="bottom" colspan="2" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1"><italic>B. microti</italic> test results<hr/></th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th valign="bottom" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">PCR</th>
              <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IFA</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">California</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 12</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&lt;</underline>8&#x2021;</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 20</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#x2013;</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Donor 1</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maine</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 1</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 26</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Donor 2</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maine</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 1</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 26</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#x2013;</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&lt;</underline>8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Donor 3</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">California</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 22</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 21</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#x2013;</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&lt;</underline>8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Donor 4</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">California</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 23</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 22</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#x2013;</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&lt;</underline>8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Donor 5</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">California</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 24</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 21</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#x2013;</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&lt;</underline>8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Donor 6</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">California</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan 24</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feb 21</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#x2013;</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>&lt;</underline>8</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <p>*IFA, immunofluorescent antibody.&#x2028;&#x2020;Involving blood products from specified donor.&#x2028;&#x2021;<underline>&lt;</underline>8 is considered a negative titer for total <italic>B. microti</italic> antibody. IFA tests conducted at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Reference Diagnostic Laboratory.</p>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Before admission, the patient had visited an oncology clinic numerous times for treatment related to his esophageal cancer: radiation therapy in October 2006, 3 chemotherapy courses from October 2006 through February 2007, and blood transfusions in January 2007. The patient received 6 units of packed red blood cells (PRBCs) and 2 units of fresh frozen plasma (FFP) over several clinic visits on January 1 and January 22&#x2013;24, 2007.</p>
      <p>The patient was in Salt Lake City, Utah, from January 13 through January 20, 2007; however, because of poor health, he did not engage in any outdoor activities. At least a year before his admission in 2006, the patient visited an undeveloped property near Klamath Falls, Oregon, where he spent time outdoors. He could not recall ever incurring a tick bite, seeing ticks, or having any animal contact.</p>
      <p>The Table summarizes the serologic and PCR results for specimens collected from the patient and 6 PRBC donors. The PRBC units came from 2 blood banks: 1 in Maine (2 units) and 1 in California (4 units). A blood donor from Maine tested positive for <italic>B. microti</italic> by IFA, with a total antibody titer 256, but tested negative <italic>B. microti</italic> by PCR. Testing of specimens from remaining PRBC donors yielded negative results. Specimens from FFP donors were not tested because of the low risk for <italic>Babesia</italic> spp. transmission associated with plasma products.</p>
      <p>The implicated donor was a 49-year-old male resident of Maine, where babesiosis is less common than in other states in the northeast. For example, whereas Maine typically reports &lt;12 cases annually, Rhode Island has reported up to 61 cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref><italic>,</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). However, the donor resided in the southern coastal region of the state, where Maine&#x2019;s cases are concentrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). He frequented tick-infested areas and is likely to have become infected in late August 2006, when he sought treatment for fever, chills, weight loss, and fatigue and was tested for various infections, including Lyme disease and ehrlichiosis. At that time, he was not tested for babesiosis. His health improved without a specific diagnosis or treatment, and he remained asymptomatic, but he evidently was parasitemic when he donated blood on December 20, 2006. Blood products from this donation were included in the transfusion the patient received on January 1, 2007. Between October 2005 and the blood donation on December 20, 2006, the donor made 3 donations.</p>
      <p>All other recipients of blood products from this donor were residents of Maine. They were notified of the need for serologic testing; none were reported to be infected (V. Rea, pers. comm.).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Babesiosis was documented in a man with metastatic cancer who resided in an area nonendemic for <italic>B. microti</italic>. On the basis of laboratory and epidemiologic information, we concluded that the patient acquired the infection via transfusion of infected PRBCs donated in a disease-endemic area thousands of miles away. The 12-day period from donation to transfusion was within the maximum 35 days that <italic>B. microti</italic> has been known to remain viable in refrigerated blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>). The period from time of transfusion exposure until positive smear was &#x2248;6 weeks; incubation periods for transfusion-related cases have ranged from weeks to many months (B. Herwaldt, pers. comm.). We had tentatively hypothesized that the patient might have acquired the infection in Oregon, where he spent substantial time outdoors, but remained asymptomatic until he became ill with cancer; however, we rejected this hypothesis because human cases of babesiosis have never been documented in Oregon (or in Utah where the man also visited) and because infections acquired in western states are more likely to be caused by local <italic>Babesia</italic> agents.</p>
      <p>This case demonstrates that, even among transfused patients who show atypical symptoms of babesiosis, the possibility of infection should be considered if they have received blood products from disease-endemic areas and display abnormal blood cell counts, such as low iron and low leukocyte counts. Generalized debilitation associated with cancer and chemotherapy may have masked <italic>Babesia</italic>-related symptoms in this patient and undermined his immune response. This case also underscores the widening seasonal and geographic boundaries of babesiosis. Tick-borne babesiosis usually peaks from July through September (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>), but because asymptomatic <italic>Babesia</italic> infection can persist for months to years, especially in untreated persons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref><italic>,</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), transfusion-associated infection can occur throughout the year. Geographic limitations in babesiosis are virtually erased by the mobility of donors and blood products. The blood bank involved in this case has blood collection centers in California and Maine but provides blood products to hospitals throughout southern California and the East Coast. Medical evaluation for babesiosis in both febrile and afebrile transfusion patients should include a Giemsa-stained thin blood smear, an acute serologic evaluation by IFA testing and a convalescent serologic evaluation by IFA testing taken 4&#x2013;6 weeks apart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>), and PCR evaluation of whole blood.</p>
      <p>The varied clinical spectrum of babesiosis makes its detection in blood donors challenging. This case exemplifies the limitations in screening healthy asymptomatic donors for babesiosis. Available screening tests to detect <italic>Babesia</italic> spp. postdonation are not cost-effective and have inadequate sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref><italic>,</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). Nucleic acid testing and inactivation procedures may provide useful options for detecting <italic>Babesia</italic> spp. in the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref><italic>,</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>). Until effective screening procedures are available, however, diagnosis of babesiosis in blood donors will continue to be based primarily on clinical observation.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="citation">
        <p><italic>Suggested citation for this article:</italic> Ngo V, Civen R. Babesiosis acquired through blood transfusion, California. Emerg Infect Dis [serial on the Internet]. 2009 May [<italic>date cited</italic>]. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/EID/content/15/5/785.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/EID/content/15/5/785.htm</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Robert Hunter for coordinating the blood bank investigation, Anne Kjemtrump and Barbara Herwaldt for their expertise and advice in the clinical and epidemiological aspects of babesiosis, Marianna Wilson and David E. Dassey for their thoughtful review, and the laboratory staff at CDC for their assistance with testing and confirmation.</p>
    </ack>
    <bio>
      <p>Ms Ngo is an epidemiologist and Dr Civen is a medical epidemiologist. with the vector-borne disease unit of the Acute Communicable Disease Control program of the Los Angeles County Department of Public Health. Their research interests include the surveillance and epidemiology of vector-borne diseases affecting Los Angeles County.</p>
    </bio>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leiby</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Babesiosis and blood transfusion: flying under the radar.</article-title><source>Vox Sang</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>65</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1423-0410.2006.00740.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16507014</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Conrad</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kjemtrup</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carreno</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomford</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wainwright</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eberhard</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal/><article-title>Description of <italic>Babesia duncani</italic> n.sp. (Apicomplexa: Babesiidae) from humans and its differentiation from other piroplasms.</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>779</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>89</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2006.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16725142</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Herwaldt</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Bruyn</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pieniazek</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Homer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lofy</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Slemenda</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <etal/><article-title><italic>Babesia divergens</italic>&#x2013;like infection, Washington State.</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source> <year>2004</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>622</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15200851</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leiby</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houghton</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Persing</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Badon</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal/><article-title>Demonstrable parasitemia among Connecticut blood donors with antibodies to <italic>Babesia microti.</italic></article-title><source>Transfusion</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1804</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1537-2995.2005.00609.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16271108</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5. </label>
        <citation citation-type="web"><collab>Maine Center for Disease Control and Prevention</collab> Reportable infectious diseases in Maine, <year>2006</year> Summary [cited 2008 May 20]. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.maine.gov/dhhs/boh/newpubs.htm">http://www.maine.gov/dhhs/boh/newpubs.htm</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6. </label>
        <citation citation-type="web"><collab>Rhode Island Department of Health</collab> Health topics: babesiosis [cited 2008 May 20]. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health.state.ri.us/topics/babesiosis.php">http://www.health.state.ri.us/topics/babesiosis.php</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McQuiston</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Childs</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chamberland</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tabor</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Transmission of tick-borne agents of disease by blood transfusion: a review of known and potential risks in the United States.</article-title><source>Transfusion</source> <year>2000</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>274</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>84</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1537-2995.2000.40030274.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10738026</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Krause</surname> <given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spielman</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Telford</surname> <given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sikand</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKay</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christianson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal/><article-title>Persistent parasitemia after acute babesiosis.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source> <year>1998</year>;<volume>339</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199807163390304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9664092</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wormser</surname> <given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dattwyler</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shapiro</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halperin</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steere</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klempner</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <etal/><article-title>The clinical assessment, treatment, and prevention of Lyme disease, human granulocytic anaplasmosis, and babesiosis: clinical practice guidelines by the Infectious Diseases Society of America.</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1089</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>134</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/508667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17029130</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kjemtrup</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fritz</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chervenak</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conrad</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Investigation of transfusion transmission of a WA1-type babesial parasite to a premature infant in California.</article-title><source>Transfusion</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1482</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1537-2995.2002.00245.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12421222</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11. </label>
        <citation citation-type="confproc"><string-name><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name> Infections transmitted from use of blood products. Presented at: Infectious Diseases Society of America 45th Annual Meeting; October 5, <year>2007</year>; San Diego, CA, USA.</citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
