<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16100468</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2782172</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2005.20.4.687</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Extraskeletal Ewing's Sarcoma of the Hard Palate</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>Mi Seon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>Hye Kyoung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Jung Bae</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Eum</surname>
            <given-names>Jae Wook</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Pathology, Pusan Paik Hospital, College of Medicine, Inje University, Busan, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>*</label>Department of Otorhinolaryngology-Head &amp; Neck Surgery, Pusan Paik Hospital, College of Medicine, Inje University, Busan, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Address for correspondence: Mi Seon Kang, M.D. Department of Pathology, Pusan Paik Hospital, 633-165 Gaegum-dong, Busanjin-gu, Busan 614-735, Korea. Tel: +82.51-890-6043, Fax: +82.51-893-9322, <email>pathkang@inje.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>20</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>687</fpage>
      <lpage>690</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2005 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Extraskeletal Ewing's sarcoma (EES) is a rare soft tissue tumor morphologically indistinguishable from the more common Ewing's sarcoma of bone. We report a case of EES arising in the hard palate of 34-yr-old male patient. Microscopically, the monotonous small round cells without neuronal differentiation showed membranous positive immunoreactivity for MIC2/CD99 and vimentin. Ultrastructurally, the tumor cells showed a few intracytoplasmic organelles without evidence of neurosecretory granules or neurofilaments. The <italic>EWS-FLI1</italic> chimeric gene was identified using the nested reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Sarcoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Ewing's</kwd>
        <kwd>Palate, Hard</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Ewing's sarcoma (ES) is a small, round, blue cell malignancy that most commonly arises in the skeleton of adolescents and young adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). A rare subset of ES, known as extraskeletal Ewing's sarcoma (EES) arises in soft tissue rather than in relationship to bone. EES shares histologic, immunohistochemical, and molecular findings with bone ES. The principal sites of EES are the chest wall, lower extremities, and paravertebral region. The head and neck have seldom been involved as the primary site of EES (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Here we report a case of extraskeletal ES of the hard palate in a young man aged 34 yr. To our knowledge, there is no previously reported instance of this tumor at this site.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 34-yr-old male patient was admitted our hospital with a painless swelling of the left hard palate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). It was incidentally detected 4 months previously with a maximum diameter of 3 cm, and did not exhibit ulceration. A paranasal sinus CT-scan revealed a contrast-enhancing mass lesion in left side hard palate with focal bony destruction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>The patient underwent local excision of the mass lesion. The tissue specimen was fragmented containing several pieces of solid mass and the cut surface was pale tan without showing hemorrhage or necrosis.</p>
      <p>Histological examination of hematoxylin-eosin stained sections showed a homogeneous population of closely packed small neoplastic cells with abundant fibrovascular stroma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Remnant salivary gland tissue was observed at the tumor's periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Most of the individual cells had scanty cytoplasm, indistinct borders and round or oval nuclei with fine powdery chromatin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). The tumor cells were arranged haphazardly without neural or Homer-Wright rosettes. Mitosis was rare. Some of the tumor cells had a moderate amount of intracytoplasmic glycogen as demonstrated by PAS stain totally abolished after diastase pretreatment. A panel of immunohistochemical stains was performed. The tumor cells were positive for CD99/MIC2 and vimentin and negative for; the leukocyte common antigen, pancytokeratin, cytokeratin 7, neuron-specific enolase, chromogranin, synaptophysin, smooth muscle actin and S-100 protein. The CD99/MIC2 stain exhibited strong membranous staining (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). Histologic and immunohistochemical findings were compatible with ES. Ultrastructurally, the tumor cells showed a few intracytoplasmic organelles without evidence of neurosecretory granules or neurofilaments. The RT-PCR showed the presence of the <italic>EWS-FLI-1</italic> fusion transcript, which is of the t(11;22) translocation characteristic of ES and primitive neuroectodermal tumor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>).</p>
      <p>After resection, the patient was treated with multiagent chemotherapy with ifosfamide, cisplatin and etoposide combined with 6,800 cGy of radiotherapy. Eight months later, paranasal sinus CT scan reveals no evidence of recurrence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>ES is one of the most controversial tumors. Ever since its first description by James Ewing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) as a "diffuse endothelioma", remarkable evolution in the concepts regarding its histogenesis and relation with other small round cell tumors, including primitive neuroectodermal tumor (PNET). Recent immunoperoxidase and cytogenic studies indicate that PNET and ES are the same entity showing varying degrees of neuroectodermal differentiation and they are categorized into a group known as the Ewing family of tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>).</p>
      <p>Some studies require histologic evidence of rosette formation, others require immunohistochemical evidence of neural differentiation, with or without rosettes for a diagnosis of PNET. Schmidt et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) suggested that a tumor was designated a PNET if it had Homer-Wright rosettes on light microscopy or co-expressed two or more neural markers by immunohistochemistry. Using these criteria, they found that patients with PNET had a more aggressive clinical course than those with EES. In our case, tumor cells showed no rosette formation and were negative on immunohistochemical stains for neuron-specific enolase, S-100 protein, chromogranin, and synaptophysin. The tumor cells only showed positive staining for CD99/MIC and vimentin. The CD99/MIC2 identified by the 013 antibody, which is a useful immunohistochemical marker for ES (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). CD99/MIC2 is a cell surface glycoprotein found in virtually all ES and PNET, having been shown in up to 98% of ES and PNET. But it is also detected other small round cell tumors in the differential diagnosis such as T-lymphoblastic lymphoma, poorly differentiated synovial sarcoma, small cell osteosarcoma, rhabdomyosarcoma, desmoplastic small round cell tumor, small cell carcinoma, and Merkel cell carcinoma and it should be used as part of a panel of immunostains, given it's lack of complete specificity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). The current case could exclude the possibility of other small round cell tumors, such as lymphoma, rhabdomyosarcoma, poorly differentiated synovial sarcoma, by negative immunoreactivities for leukocyte common antigen, desmin, and cytokeratin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>).</p>
      <p>Although the exact etiology remains unknown, more than 95% of ES/PNET show the characteristic translocation t(11;22)(q24;q12) or the variant t(21;22)(q22;q12) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). These translocations fuse the 5'portion of the <italic>EWS</italic> gene on chromosome 22q12 to either <italic>FLI1</italic> on 11q24 or <italic>ERG</italic> on 21q22. The resultant fusion genes (<italic>EWS/FLI1</italic> or <italic>EWS/ERG</italic>) express chimeric proteins, which are capable of cell transformation and act as aberrant transcription factors. Identification of the fusion transcripts <italic>EWS/FLI1</italic> or <italic>EWS/ERG</italic> by RT-PCR or fluorescent in situ hybridization serves as a sensitive and specific diagnostic test for ES/PNET.</p>
      <p>Various therapeutic modalities have been developed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). Early and confident diagnosis coupled with modern chemoand radiotherapy has greatly improved the prognosis of ES/PNET. This approach has been successful in our patient: surgical excision followed by chemotherapy and radiotherapy resulted in no clinical evidence of recurrence by the nine-month follow-up examination.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dehner</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primitive neuroectodermal tumor and Ewing's sarcoma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8383465</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boor</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jurkovic</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friedmann</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plank</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kocan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extraskeletal Ewing's sarcoma of the nose</article-title>
          <source>J Laryngol Otol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>74</fpage>
          <lpage>76</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11233634</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>TK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>YL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheen</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extraskeletal Ewing's sarcoma of the scalp</article-title>
          <source>J Laryngol Otol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>73</fpage>
          <lpage>75</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10789420</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shon</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extraskeletal Ewing sarcoma of cervical epidural region: Cases Report</article-title>
          <source>J Korean Radiol Soc</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
          <lpage>89</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extraskeletal cervical epidural Ewing's Sarcoma-Case Report and Review of the Literature</article-title>
          <source>J Korean Neurosurg Soc</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>48</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ewing</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diffuse endothelioma of bone</article-title>
          <source>Proc NY Pathol Soc</source>
          <year>1921</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Delattre</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zucman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melot</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garau</surname>
              <given-names>XS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zucker</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenoir</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ambros</surname>
              <given-names>PF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheer</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turc-Carel</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Triche</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aurias</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Ewing's family of tumours-a subgroup of small-round-cell tumors defined by specific chimeric transcripts</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>331</volume>
          <fpage>294</fpage>
          <lpage>299</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8022439</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zucman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melot</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desmaze</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghysdael</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plougastel</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peter</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zucker</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Triche</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheer</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turc-Carel</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Combinatorial generation of variable fusion proteins in the Ewing family of tumours</article-title>
          <source>EMBO J</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>4481</fpage>
          <lpage>4487</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8223458</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herrmann</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jurgens</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harms</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant peripheral neuroectodermal tumor and its necessary distinction from Ewing's sarcoma: a report from the Kiel Pediatric Tumor Registry</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>2251</fpage>
          <lpage>2259</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1655208</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weidner</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tjoe</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immunohistochemical profile of monoclonal antibody 013: antibody that recognizes glycoprotein p30/32MIC2 and is useful in diagnosing Ewing's sarcoma and peripheral neuroepithelioma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>486</fpage>
          <lpage>494</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7513503</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldblum</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Enzinger and Weiss's soft tissue tumors</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <edition>4th edn</edition>
          <publisher-loc>St. Louis</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Mosby Inc</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1303</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wexler</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DeLaney</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsokos</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Avila</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steinberg</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weaver-McClure</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jarosinski</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hijazi</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balis</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horowitz</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ifosfamade and etoposide plus vincristin, doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide for newly diagnosed Ewing's sarcoma family of tumors</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>901</fpage>
          <lpage>911</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8756388</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A nodular submucosal tumor is noted on the left side of hard palate.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-687-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>The paranasal CT scan showing a contrast-enhancing mass lesion in left side hard palate with focal bony destruction (*).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-687-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Light microscopy of the tumor shows closely packed small round cells with abundant thin-walled vessels (H&amp;E, &#xD7;40).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-687-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Acini of minor salivary gland are seen at the periphery of tumor (arrow) (H&amp;E, &#xD7;10).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-687-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Most of the tumor cells have scanty cytoplasm and round or oval nuclei with fine powdery chromatin (H&amp;E, &#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-687-g005"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F6" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Strong membranous MIC2/CD99 immunoreactivity (LSAB, &#xD7;200).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-687-g006"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F7" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 7</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>EWS/FLI1</italic> chimeric gene of approximately 260 bp is identified by RT-PCR in this case (arrow) (M, size marker; lane 1, positive control; lane 2, negative control; lane 3, this case).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-687-g007"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
