<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18828905</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2566573</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-7819-6-106</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7819-6-106</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Adenocarcinoma of the third portion of the duodenum in a man with CREST syndrome</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anastasopoulos</surname>
            <given-names>Georgios</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>drmarinis@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A2" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marinis</surname>
            <given-names>Athanasios</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>sakisdoc@yahoo.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Konstantinidis</surname>
            <given-names>Christos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>drchriskons@yahoo.gr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Theodosopoulos</surname>
            <given-names>Theodosios</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>theodosios@vodafone.net.gr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fragulidis</surname>
            <given-names>Georgios</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>foreo@otenet.gr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vassiliou</surname>
            <given-names>Ioannis</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>ianvass@otenet.gr</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Second Department of Surgery, Areteion University Hospital, 76 Vassilisis Sofia's Ave, 11528, Athens, Greece</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <fpage>106</fpage>
      <lpage>106</lpage>
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wjso.com/content/6/1/106"/>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2008 Anastasopoulos et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Anastasopoulos et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p>
          <!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Anastasopoulos
               Georgios
               
               drmarinis@gmail.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Adenocarcinoma of the third portion of the duodenum in a man with CREST syndrome
         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>World Journal of Surgical Oncology 6(1): 106-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1477-7819(2008)6:1&#x0003c;106&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1477-7819</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>-->
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>CREST (Calcinosis, Raynaud's phenomenon, Esophageal dysmotility, Sclerodactyly and Telangiectasias) syndrome has been rarely associated with other malignancies (lung, esophagus).This is the first report of a primary adenocarcinoma of the third portion of the duodenum in a patient with CREST syndrome.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 54-year-old male patient with CREST syndrome presented with colicky postprandial pain of the upper abdomen, diminished food uptake and a 6-Kg-body weight loss during the previous 2 months. An ulcerative lesion in the third portion of the duodenum was revealed during duodenoscopy, with a diagnosis of adenocarcinoma on biopsy specimen histology. The patient underwent a partial pancreatoduodenectomy. No adjuvant therapy was instituted and follow-up is negative for local recurrence or metastases 21 months postoperatively.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>CREST syndrome has been associated with colon cancer, gastric polyps, familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP) syndrome and Crohn's disease; however, this is the first report of a primary adenocarcinoma of the duodenum in a patient with CREST syndrome. However, any etiologic relationship remains to be further investigated.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>CREST syndrome (Calcinosis, Raynaud's phenomenon, Esophageal dysmotility, Sclerodactyly and Telangiectasias) has been rarely associated with other malignancies (lung, esophagus), whereas duodenal adenocarcinoma has never been reported to be associated with this subtype of systemic sclerosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. This is the first report of a primary adenocarcinoma of the third portion of the duodenum in an adult male patient with CREST syndrome.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 54-year-old man was referred to our clinic because of colicky postprandial pain of the upper abdomen during the last month, with aggravation 5 days before admission. The patient had diminished the amount of food uptake and had also a 6-Kg-body weight loss during the previous 2 months. His past medical history included CREST syndrome under cortisone therapy during the last year and primary repair of the left ureter and the small intestine due to traumatic perforation in a car accident 17 years ago. Physical examination revealed a pale, malnourished patient and an unremarkable abdomen without tenderness or distension. Besides an anemia, the other blood investigations, as well as tumor markers, were within normal limits. Plain abdominal radiographs showed no pathological findings, while contrast-enhanced series demonstrated a stricture in the transition area from the second to the third portion of the duodenum (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Abdominal computed tomography showed a mass in the duodenum, without evidence of metastases (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Thorax computed tomography was negative for metastases as well. Gastroduodenoscopy revealed an ulcerated lesion between the second and third portion of the duodenum and the biopsies showed an adenocarcinoma. Colonoscopy was normal.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Barium upper GI series showing a stricture (arrow) in the transition of the second to the third portion of the duodenum.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-6-106-1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Computed tomography of the abdomen depicting a mass (arrows) in the duodenum.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-6-106-2"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Laparotomy, through a bilateral subcostal incision, revealed a large tumor locally invading the third portion of the duodenum and possibly the pancreas. Therefore, a partial pancreatoduodenectomy (Whipple's procedure) was carried out. Histological examination revealed a low-grade duodenal adenocarcinoma of maximal diameter 4 cm, which infiltrated the duodenal wall and the fibro-adipose tissue of the mesentery. Metastasis was found in one out of ten lymph nodes examined, while the surgical margins were negative for microscopic disease.</p>
      <p>The patient's postoperative course was complicated with a peripancreatic-remnant collection and a lower respiratory infection, which were treated conservatively.</p>
      <p>No additional therapy was instituted and 21 months after the operation the patient is alive, without any evidence of local recurrence or metastases.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Primary duodenal adenocarcinoma represents a relatively rare clinical entity. Duodenum constitutes the most predominant site (55%) of occurrence of adenocarcinoma throughout the small intestine, followed by the jejunum (18%) and ileum (13%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The distribution pattern of adenocarcinoma within the duodenum is reported to parallel the length of each portion. The first portion is affected in 15%, the second portion in 40% and the third and fourth portion in 45% of the cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>Most of these neoplasms are asymptomatic until they become large in size. Partial duodenal obstruction, with associated symptoms of crumpy postprandial pain of the upper abdomen, nausea and vomiting, is the most common mode of presentation. Hemorrhage, usually indolent, is the second most common mode of presentation. Due to their location these tumors cause non-specific and vague symptoms leading to a delay of diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Periampullary tumors may cause obstructive jaundice or pancreatitis.</p>
      <p>Barium upper GI series and endoscopy of the upper gastrointestinal (GI) tract establish the diagnosis with a sensitivity of 81,9% and 88%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], while colonoscopy and thoraco-abdominal computed tomography are carried out to exclude any synchronous or metastatic cancer.</p>
      <p>The only possibility of cure is obtained by a radical resection. The percentage of resectability with a curative intent is reported to range from 50% to 73% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. For the tumors located in the first and the second portion of the duodenum, a Whipple's procedure is considered necessary for the radical resection of the tumor and its lymphatic drainage. For tumors of the third and fourth portion, a segmental resection of the duodenum with the appropriate lymphadenectomy is performed with a curative intent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Chemotherapy and radiation are considered to have only a small contribution to the overall survival or the disease-free survival of these patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Primary duodenal adenocarcinoma is an aggressive tumor with an overall 5-year survival rate of about 25% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], which can be significantly improved up to 54% after curative resection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The most important prognostic factors are the stage of the disease and the location of the tumor. Tumors with negative margins in the surgical specimen, which are located in the first and second portions of the duodenum, are considered to have a better prognosis. Other series report that histologic grade, depth of invasion, tumor size and metastases to regional lymph nodes influence the survival rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p>
      <p>Primary duodenal adenocarcinoma has been associated with colon cancer, gastric polyps, especially villous and tubulovillous adenomas, familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP) and Crohn's disease. It has been stated that primary duodenal adenocarcinoma is one of the main causes of death in patients with FAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. A case of an early duodenal adenocarcinoma from a Brunner's gland has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Another case of primary duodenal adenocarcinoma in a patient with neurofibromatosis type 1 has also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>Limited cutaneous scleroderma or CREST syndrome consists one of the two main subsets of systemic sclerosis, which is a multisystemic disorder of unclear pathogenesis, characterized by inflammatory, vascular and fibrotic changes of the skin and various internal organ systems (GI tract, lungs, heart and kidneys) and involves immunologic mechanisms leading to vascular endothelial damage and fibroblast activation. CREST syndrome consists of calcinosis, Raynaud's phenomenon, esophageal dysmotility, sclerodactyly and telangiectasias and is associated with a better prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p>
      <p>The association of this syndrome with malignancies is extremely rare. A case of CREST syndrome and adenocarcinoma of the lung has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. It is also suggested that patients with scleroderma and Barrett's metaplasia have an increased risk of complications, such as strictures or adenocarcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Another case of progressive systemic sclerosis (CREST syndrome), sarcoidosis and esophageal adenocarcinoma in a 50-year-old Japanese female has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Finally, we report the first case of a male patient with CREST syndrome and duodenal adenocarcinoma.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>A relationship between duodenal adenocarcinoma and limited cutaneous scleroderma has not yet been described and in our case is considered a matter of coincidence. Whether underlying mechanisms exist (immunologic, genetic, etc) remains to be elucidated with further research.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contributions</title>
      <p>GA, IV and CK carried out the surgical procedure and contributed to the design of the study; GA and AM gathered the data, drafted the manuscript and critically revised it; IV, TT and GF revised and finally approved the manuscript for been published. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Salvant</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carter</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armstrong</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Polk</surname>
              <given-names>OD</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Austin</surname>
              <given-names>KI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CREST syndrome: a variant of progressive systemic sclerosis, associated with interstitial pulmonary fibrosis and malignancy</article-title>
          <source>South Med J</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>1185</fpage>
          <lpage>1187</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3420453</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katzka</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reynolds</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saul</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plotkin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lang</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ouyang</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jimenez</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Barrett's metaplasia and adenocarcinoma of the esophagus in scleroderma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>46</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3799692</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9343(87)90376-7</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maenawa</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nogami</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of progressive systemic sclerosis associated with sarcoidosis and esophageal adenocarcinoma</article-title>
          <source>J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8482751</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Howe</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamel</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menck</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scott-Conor</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adenocarcinoma of the small bowel. Review of the National Cancer Data Base, 1985&#x2013;1995</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>2593</fpage>
          <lpage>2706</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594853</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0142(19991215)86:12&lt;2693::AID-CNCR14&gt;3.0.CO;2-U</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coit</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>De Vita Jr VT, Hellman S Rosenberg SA</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cancer of the small intestine</article-title>
          <source>Cancer: Principles and Practice of Oncology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-name>Philadelphia: Lipincott, Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1204</fpage>
          <lpage>1206</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCarron</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibbs</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fakih</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nava</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajput</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Duodenal adenocarcinoma: vague complaints, delayed diagnosis and poor outcome</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings in the ASCO (Gastrointestinal Cancers Symposium)</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>171A</volume>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sohn</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lillemoe</surname>
              <given-names>KD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cameron</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pitt</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaufman</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hruban</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeo</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adenocarcinoma of the duodenum: factors influencing long-term survival</article-title>
          <source>J Gastrointest Surg</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>87</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9841972</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1091-255X(98)80107-8</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bakaeen</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murr</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarr</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farnell</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagorney</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farley</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Heerden</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiersema</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schleck</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donohue</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>What prognostic factors are important in duodenal adenocarcinoma?</article-title>
          <source>Arch Surg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <fpage>635</fpage>
          <lpage>642</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10843358</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archsurg.135.6.635</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tocchi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mazzoni</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puma</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mizzini</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cassini</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bettelli</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tagliacozzo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adenocarcinoma of the third and fourth portions of the duodenum: results of surgical treatment</article-title>
          <source>Arch Surg</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>80</fpage>
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12511157</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ryder</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ko</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hines</surname>
              <given-names>OS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gloor</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reber</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary duodenal adenocarcinoma: a 40-year experience</article-title>
          <source>Arch Surg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <fpage>1070</fpage>
          <lpage>1075</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10982512</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archsurg.135.9.1070</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Groves</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saunders</surname>
              <given-names>BP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spigelman</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names/>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Duodenal cancer in patients with familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP): results of a 10-year prospective study</article-title>
          <source>Gut</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>636</fpage>
          <lpage>641</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11950808</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.50.5.636</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akino</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kondo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ueno</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamazaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosokawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimozi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adachi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Honda</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ichiyanagi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akahonai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujisawa</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arimura</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Endo</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imai</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carcinoma of duodenum arising from Brunner's gland</article-title>
          <source>J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>296</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11993514</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s005350200038</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Joo</surname>
              <given-names>YE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rew</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary duodenal adenocarcinoma associated with neurofibromatosis type 1</article-title>
          <source>J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>215</fpage>
          <lpage>219</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11931536</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s005350200024</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fauci</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braunwald</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isselbacher</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kasper</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hauser</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Longo</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Systemic Sclerosis (Scleroderma)</article-title>
          <source>Harrison's Principles of Internal Medicine Companion Handbook</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill International Editions</publisher-name>
          <fpage>880</fpage>
          <lpage>882</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
