<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Orthop</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ORT</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Orthopaedica</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1745-3674</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1745-3682</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Informa Healthcare</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19968602</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2823314</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/17453670903413152</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SORT_A_441493_O</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Failed internal fixation due to osteonecrosis following traumatic periprosthetic fracture after hip resurfacing arthroplasty</article-title>
        <subtitle>A case report and review of the literature</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zustin</surname>
            <given-names>Jozef</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name>
            <surname>Winter</surname>
            <given-names>Eugen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AF0001"><sup>1</sup>Institute of Pathology, University Medical Centre Hamburg Eppendorf, Hamburg</aff>
        <aff id="AF0002"><sup>2</sup>Trauma Surgery, Orthopedics and Arthroplasty Clinic, Klinikum Friedrichshafen, Friedrichshafen, Germany</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email xlink:href="j.zustin@uke.uni-hamburg.de">j.zustin@uke.uni-hamburg.de</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>80</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>666</fpage>
      <lpage>669</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Nordic Orthopedic Federation</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the source is credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>A 55-year-old man had undergone a Birmingham Hip Resurfacing (Cup 56, Head 50; BHR; Smith and Nephew TLC, London, UK) for primary osteoarthritis. The index procedure and postoperative healing were uneventful and radiographs showed well-fixed femoral and acetabular components.</p>
      <p>18 weeks after surgery, the patient was involved in a motorcycle accident and fell on the operated hip. An undislocated vertical fracture of the femoral neck was treated surgically to preserve the prosthesis. As the centrally located implant stem might cause difficulty with the placing of typical implants (e.g. screw-plate device or a cephalomedullary nail), 3 parallel cannulated cancellous screws in a triangular configuration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1A</xref>) were used for fixation of the fracture. Care was taken to avoid contact between the implanted stainless steel screws and both the stem and lateral walls of the femoral component. The patient was operated on 14 h after the injury.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A. Traumatic periprosthetic femoral neck fracture 18 weeks after the index procedure treated with cannulated cancellous screws. B. Collapse of the femoral neck (short arrow) led to marked dislocation of both the proximal femoral remnant and all 3 screws (long arrow). C. After the revision surgery with conversion to a femoral stemmed total hip replacement with extra-large femoral head.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ORT-1745-3674-80-666-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>11 weeks later, the patient presented with hip pain. Radiographs showed 15-mm descent of the femoral component and a dislocation of all 3 screws (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1B</xref>). The arthroplasty was converted to a femoral stemmed total hip replacement with extra-large femoral head (cement-free BiCONTACT System, Aesculap AG, Tuttlingen, Germany) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1C</xref>) and retention of the well-fixed acetabular component. Follow-up at 8 months was uneventful.</p>
      <p>Retrieved femoral remnant tissue with the in situ femoral component and several bone tissue fragments from the neck obtained at revision surgery were immediately fixed in buffered formalin for further analysis. The specimen was cut with the femoral component in situ, by a diamond-coated band saw, into 4 quadrants and analyzed macroscopically and by contact radiography (Faxitron X-Ray LLC, Wheeling, IL). Both the medial and lateral sections of the central slice were completely embedded in plastic after cement dissolution with acetone and removal of the prosthesis. The specimens were processed undecalcified and embedded in methylmethacrylate. From each undecalcified processed plastic block, one 5-&#x3BC;m section was cut with a heavy-duty microtome. The sections were stained by the toluidine blue staining method.</p>
      <p>Macroscopically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2A</xref>), a well-fixed femoral component with minimal cement mantle and focal superficial cement penetration was found. Contact radiography of the specimen revealed no reaction to the intraosseously located screw (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2B</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A. Well-fixed femoral component, narrow superficial zone of cement penetration, and irregular fracture line were apparent macroscopically on the cut plane. B. Absence of vital reaction to the screw was evident by contact radiography several weeks after the procedure. C. Cement granulomas and fibrosis were found at the bone-cement interface. D. Bone trabeculae without stainable osteocytes and precipitations of calcium salts were found in the vicinity of the screw and of the fracture line. E. Bone tissue fragments from femoral neck distally to the fracture line revealed several fractured individual bone trabeculae (long arrow) with formation of microcallus and focal resorptive changes (short arrow). F. Broad fracture callus within the isolated bone fragments from femoral neck distal to the fracture line.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ORT-1745-3674-80-666-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Microscopically, foreign body granulomas and loose fibrosis were apparent at the bone-cement interface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2C</xref>). The remaining bone tissue showed a loss of stainable osteocytes and disorganized intertrabecular bone marrow. More distally, many dead, irregular bone fragments&#x2014;so-called &#x201C;bone chips&#x201D; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">Doorn et al. 1996</xref>)&#x2014;without resorptive reaction were found in the vicinity of both the intraosseous screw and the fracture line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2D</xref>). In contrast with the former, multifocal fracture of bone trabeculae associated with the formation of microcallus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2E</xref>) and broad areas of mineralized callus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2F</xref>) were present in the bone fragments removed from the rest of the femoral neck at the revision surgery. We found no fibrocartilaginous tissue, characteristic of pseudoarthrosis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0002">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Hip resurfacing arthroplasty is currently the fastest growing hip procedure worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">Amstutz and Le Duff 2008</xref>). One of the major complications associated with resurfacing is periprosthetic femoral neck fracture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0015">Shimmin and Back 2005</xref>). As this is not usually associated with trauma, change in biomechanical properties and/or pathological alterations within the femoral remnant bone tissue are believed to be causative. Typical non-traumatic periprosthetic fractures are usually treated with revision to a stemmed femoral component, although there have been several reports of successful nonoperative management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">Cumming and Fordyce 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0006">Cossey et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0013">Morgan et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
      <p>With wide use of the hip resurfacing procedure in young active patients, it is likely that the number of traumatic periprosthetic fractures will increase. Apart from revision surgery with conversion to total hip arthroplasty, several alternative operative and nonoperative therapeutic options might be considered. Recently, several reports of successful operative treatment of traumatic periprosthetic fractures after hip resurfacing have been published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">Aning et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0012">Mereddy et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0017">Weinrauch and Krikler 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0014">Orpen et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0018">Whittingham-Jones et al. 2008</xref>) (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <caption>
          <p>Overview of successful operative treatment of traumatic periprosthetic fracture after hip resurfacing arthroplasty</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" id="table1">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Preoperative diagnosis</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time to fracture</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trauma</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fracture type</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody valign="top">
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">posttraumatic arthritis</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 years</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">car accident</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">comminuted sub-trochanteric</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">contoured broad AO DCP</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 months</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whittingham-Jones (2008)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osteoarthritis</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 years</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">displaced inter-trochanteric</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">locking plate 3 screws</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orpen (2009)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osteoarthritis</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">fall from a ladder</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">multi-fragmented reverse oblique intertrochanteric</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">locking plate 3 screws</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orpen (2009)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osteoarthritis</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 months</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">fall on a hip</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">closed intertrochanteric</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130&#xB0;angled blade plate</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 months</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weinrauch (2008)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">osteoarthritis</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 months</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">fall</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">undisplaced basicervical</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 cannulated cancellous screws</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 years</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mereddy (2008)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2013;</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 years</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">traffic accident</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">complex multifragmentary</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 locking screws cerclage wires</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aning (2005)</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>As vital reaction to cement was apparent histologically at the bone-implant interface in our case, we believe that the femoral bone remnant was viable after implantation of the hip resurfacing arthroplasty. The absence of vital reactions to the screw used for the fracture fixation and resorptive as well as reparative changes proximal to the fracture line were, however, suggestive of osteonecrosis. The other 2 screws were implanted somewhat more distally, and ended within the collapsed necrotic bone tissue. Loss of stainable osteocytes in the bone trabeculae was apparent throughout the remnant of the femoral head. The remaining vital femoral neck fragments showed vital mineralized fracture callus formations.</p>
      <p>As trauma-induced avascular necrosis of the femoral head, either with or without fracture, represents the most common form of aseptic femoral head necrosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">Bachiller et al. 2002</xref>), we suggest that posttraumatic osteonecrosis of the femoral remnant caused the treatment failure of the periprosthetic fracture in our patient. This led to the collapse of necrotic bone tissue several weeks after the operative treatment, followed by descent of the prosthesis and the screws used for the fracture fixation.</p>
      <p>Periprosthetic fracture after hip resurfacing replacement is a well-documented early-onset complication of this modern arthroplasty method, with an incidence of 1&#x2013;3% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">Beaule et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0002">Amstutz et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">De Smet 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0015">Shimmin and Back 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0011">Marker et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">Amstutz and Le Duff 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0016">Steffen et al. 2008</xref>). Osteonecrosis in femoral remnants has been found in recent retrieval analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">Little et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0016">Steffen et al. 2008</xref>), and was considered causative for most typical periprosthetic fractures due to weakening of the bone structure in the absence of adequate trauma. In contrast to these fractures, analysis of our single case with periprosthetic fracture following adequate trauma revealed vital reactions at the bone-cement interface after the index procedure. However, the subsequent accident led to 2 additional important events (fracture and its operative therapy) that had an adverse influence on further viability of the bone remnant tissue, which led to its failure. Thus, we suggest that traumatic fractures can take place in the absence of osteonecrosis in femoral remnant&#x2014;even at later follow-up. Furthermore, we have demonstrated that osteonecrosis can appear in such cases secondary to attempts to treat the traumatic periprosthetic fracture operatively.</p>
      <p>We believe that the risk of secondary osteonecrosis is high after operative treatment of traumatic periprosthetic fracture after resurfacing replacement; thus, a revision to total hip arthroplasty is probably preferable in such cases.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>JZ: research, retrieval analysis, and writing of the manuscript. EW: surgery, and review of the manuscript.</p>
      <p>No competing interests declared.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amstutz</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le Duff</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Eleven years of experience with metal-on-metal hybrid hip resurfacing: a review of 1000 conserve plus</article-title>
          <source>J Arthroplasty (Suppl 1)</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>(6)</issue>
          <fpage>36</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
          <comment>Epub 2008 Jul 17.</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amstutz</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campbell</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le Duff</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fracture of the neck of the femur after surface arthroplasty of the hip</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg (Am)</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <issue>(9)</issue>
          <fpage>1874</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15342747</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aning</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aung</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackinnon</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fixation of a complex comminuted proximal femoral fracture in the presence of a Birmingham hip resurfacing prosthesis</article-title>
          <source>Injury</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>(9)</issue>
          <fpage>1127</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15979622</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bachiller</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caballer</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Portal</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Avascular necrosis of the femoral head after femoral neck fracture</article-title>
          <source>Clin Orthop</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <issue>(399)</issue>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>109</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011698</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beaule</surname>
              <given-names>PE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dorey</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le Duff</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gruen</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amstutz</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Risk factors affecting outcome of metal-on-metal surface arthroplasty of the hip</article-title>
          <source>Clin Orthop</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <issue>(418)</issue>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>93</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15043098</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cossey</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Back</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimmin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Young</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spriggins</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The non-operative management of periprosthetic fractures associated with the Birmingham hip resurfacing procedure</article-title>
          <source>J Arthroplasty</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>(3)</issue>
          <fpage>358</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809955</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cumming</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fordyce</surname>
              <given-names>MJF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Non-operative management of a peri-prosthetic subcapital fracture after metal-on-metal Birmingham hip resurfacing</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg (Br)</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <issue>(7)</issue>
          <fpage>1055</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14516046</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Smet</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Belgium experience with metal-on-metal surface arthroplasty</article-title>
          <source>Orthop Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>(2)</issue>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15833458</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Doorn</surname>
              <given-names>PF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirra</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campbell</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amstutz</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tissue reaction to metal on metal total hip prostheses</article-title>
          <source>Clin Orthop (Suppl)</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <issue>(329)</issue>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>205</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Little</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruiz</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harding</surname>
              <given-names>IJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLardy-Smith</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gundle</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Athanasou</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Osteonecrosis in retrieved femoral heads after failed resurfacing arthroplasty</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg (Br)</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>320</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15773638</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marker</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seyler</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jinnah</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delanois</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ulrich</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Momnt</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Femoral neck fractures after metal-on-metal total hip resurfacing: a prospective cohort study</article-title>
          <source>J Arthroplasty (Suppl 3)</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>(7)</issue>
          <fpage>66</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mereddy</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malik</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geary</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Peri-prosthetic fracture of femur following metal-on-metal Birmingham hip resurfacing treated by internal fixation</article-title>
          <source>Injury Extra</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <comment>In Press</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morgan</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Myers</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O'Dwyer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intertrochanteric fracture below Birmingham Hip Resurfacing: Successful non-operative management in two cases</article-title>
          <source>Injury Extra</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>(9)</issue>
          <fpage>313</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Orpen</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pearce</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deakin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keys</surname>
              <given-names>RI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Internal fixation of trohanteric fractures of the hip after surface replacements</article-title>
          <source>Injury Extra</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <issue>(2)</issue>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shimmin</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Back</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Femoral neck fractures following Birmingham hip resurfacing: a national review of 50 cases</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg (Br)</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>(45)</issue>
          <fpage>463</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15795193</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steffen</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foguet</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krickler</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gundle</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beard</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Femoral neck fractures after hip resurfacing</article-title>
          <source>J Arthroplasty</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <month>6</month>
          <day>13</day>
          <comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0017">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weinrauch</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krikler</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Proximal femoral fracture after hip resurfacing managed with blade-plate fixation</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg (Am)</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>1345</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18519330</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0018">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Whittingham-Jones</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charnley</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Annapureddy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Internal fixation after subtrochanteric femoral fracture after hip resurfacing arthroplasty</article-title>
          <source>J Arthroplasty</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
