<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yonsei Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Yonsei Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0513-5796</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1976-2437</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Yonsei University College of Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19881982</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2768253</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2009.50.5.729</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Isolated Petroclival Craniopharyngioma with Aggressive Skull Base Destruction</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Young-Hen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Sang-Dae</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lim</surname>
            <given-names>Dong-Jun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Jung-Yul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>Yong-Gu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Young-Sik</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Radiology, Korea University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Korea University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Pathology, Korea University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Corresponding author: Dr. Sang-Dae Kim, Department of Neurosurgery, Korea University College of Medicine, 516 Gojan 1-dong, Danwon-gu, Ansan 425-707, Korea. Tel: 82-31-412-5053, Fax: 82-31-412-5054, <email>neuron19@korea.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>50</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>729</fpage>
      <lpage>731</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Copyright: Yonsei University College of Medicine 2009</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We report a rare case of petroclival craniopharyngioma with no connection to the sellar or suprasellar region. MRI and CT images revealed a homogenously enhancing retroclival solid mass with aggressive skull base destruction, mimicking chordoma or aggressive sarcoma. However, there was no calcification or cystic change found in the mass. Here, we report the clinical features and radiographic investigation of this uncommon craniopharyngioma arising primarily in the petroclival region.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Craniopharyngioma</kwd>
        <kwd>skull base</kwd>
        <kwd>petroclival</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Craniopharyngiomas constitute approximately 2 to 4% of all primary intracranial tumors.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> These tumors characteristically arise in the sellar/suprasellar region, although there have been reports of tumor extension away from the sella or recurrences in distant sites after the removal of the primary lesions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> We describe an unusual case of aggressive craniopharyngioma primarily arising from clivus with extention to the posterior fossa that presented with multiple lower cranial nerve palsies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <sec>
        <title>History and examination</title>
        <p>A 55-year-old man with a previous diagnosis of chronic otomastoiditis in his left ear was admitted to our hospital with complaints of a 1-month history of progressive posterior cervicalgia. He also presented with dysphasia and repetitive aspirations three months before his admission. His neurologic examination revealed diffuse paravertebral tenderness, neck motion limitation to the left side, left facial nerve palsy (House-Brackmann grade 4) and severe ipsilateral hearing loss. The findings of a cerebellar function test were unremarkable. There was no previous history of surgical operation. Due to the progressive and severe nature of his symptoms, he underwent magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain with a 1.5T MR unit. MRI imaging disclosed a homogenously enhancing solid mass occupying the clivus, extending posterolaterally into the epidural space of posterior fossa beyond temporal bone, and anteriorly to prevertebral space at cervicomedullary junction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Its intracranial portion occupying the posterior fossa engulfed intraosseous segment of left intra cranial artery (ICA). There was no connection between the mass and the sellar or suprasellar regions. The size and location of the pituitary gland were unremarkable. It was mainly isointense to the brain cortex on both T1-weighted and T2-weighted images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). On high resolution bone algorithm CT images revealed that permeative bone destruction was excessively demonstrated in clivus, occipital condyle, petrous and mastoid portions of left temporal bone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). However, there was no calcification or cystic change observed within the lesion. Carotid and vertebral angiography revealed that the tumor was avascular and moved left vertebral artery toward the medial direction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The differential diagnosis included chordoma, sarcoma and metastasis of skull base.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Operative procedure and pathology</title>
        <p>The patient underwent resection of the mass via suboccipital craniectomy using the left transcondylar approach and C1 hemilaminectomy. The tumor mass began to bulge out when the occipital condyle was drilled. The intracranial segment of the vertebral artery was displaced posteriorly and medially by the tumor mass. The vertebral artery adhered to the surrounding soft tissue and tumor mass itself. The glossopharyngeal, vagal and hypoglossal nerves were intermingled with the tumor mass, which was rubbery and of hard consistency and moderate vascularity. A dural incision was made after the tumor mass was partially removed, but there were no signs of a definite tumor in the intracranial space. The pathological results demonstrated irregular nests of multistratified squamous cells with peripheral palisading of the nuclei and keratin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Postoperative course</title>
        <p>His symptoms, however, were not improved. Then, the patient was referred for radiotherapy at a dose of 72 Gy (40 fractions), however, the radiation therapy was stopped after the administration of the 36 Gy dose because of deterioration of his general condition. One 1 month later, he died of aggravation of aspiration pneumonia which did not respond to antibiotic treatment.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Craniopharyngiomas arise from squamous epithelial rests along the remnants of Rathke's pouch.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> Embryonic Rathke's pouch remnants are frequently observed in the pars tuberalis,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> the posterior wall of the pharynx,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> and the sphenoid bone.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> These patterns of localization explain the frequent occurrence of craniopharyngiomas in the suprasellar region<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> and the potential development of craniopharyngiomas in the sphenoid bone<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> or nasopharynx.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref> Other ectopic locations include the pineal gland,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref> third ventricle,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref> ethmoid sinus,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> and posterior fossa.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref></p>
      <p>Because craniopharyngiomas can extend to the anterior (2-5% of cases), middle (2%), or posterior (1-4%) cranial fossa and infrasellar extension is seen in about 5% of all cases,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref> a purely ectopic occurrence showing no sellar extension is very rare. Based on the radiological findings, we concluded that the patient's craniopharyngioma arose from the clivus and was entirely isolated from the sella or suprasellar regions, in agreement with previous reports of a few similar cases.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref> A possible explanation for the ectopic location of the tumor is the migration of squamous epithelial cell remnants of the obliterated craniopharyngeal canal.</p>
      <p>In contrast to the classic radiographic appearance of suprasellar craniopharyngiomas, which usually manifest as cystic or calcified tumors with a spectrum of presenting signs and symptoms, including visual changes, endocrine abnormalities and increased intracranial pressure,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref> neither calcification nor cystic components were found in this case. Moreover, the consideration of extensive bone destruction in the clivus, temporal petrous and occipital condyle resulted in the preoperative radiologic diagnosis of chordoma, aggressive sarcoma or metastasis instead of craniopharyngioma.</p>
      <p>In summary, although our case did not show any specific radiographic findings to allow for differential diagnosis of craniopharyngioma, the clinical manifestations and radiographic features of the mass suggest that craniopharyngioma should be included in the differential diagnosis of petroclival mass which causes aggressive skull base destruction.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have no financial conflicts of interest.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McLendon</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenblum</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bigner</surname>
              <given-names>DD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Russell and Rubinstein's pathology of tumors of the nervous system</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <edition>6th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>A Hodder Arnold Publication</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ragoowansi</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piepgras</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Postoperative ectopic craniopharyngioma. Case report</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>653</fpage>
          <lpage>655</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2002381</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tomita</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mendoza</surname>
              <given-names>ND</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Symon</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Recurrent craniopharyngioma in the posterior fossa</article-title>
          <source>Br J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>590</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1472325</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldberg</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eshbaugh</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Squamous cell nests of the pituitary gland as related to the origin of craniopharyngiomas. A study of their presence in the newborn and infants up to age four</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol</source>
          <year>1960</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>299</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13850582</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McGrath</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aspects of the human pharyngeal hypophysis in normal and anencephalic fetuses and neonates and their possible significance in the mechanism of its control</article-title>
          <source>J Anat</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>65</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">701197</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ransohoff</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Craniopharyngioma originating in the sphenoid bone. Case report</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1972</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>102</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5007266</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Benitez</surname>
              <given-names>WI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sartor</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Angtuaco</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Craniopharyngioma presenting as a nasopharyngeal mass: CT and MR findings</article-title>
          <source>J Comput Assist Tomogr</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1068</fpage>
          <lpage>1072</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3183117</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kanungo</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Just</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Black</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohr</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glikstein</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rochon</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasopharyngeal craniopharyngioma in an unusual location</article-title>
          <source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1372</fpage>
          <lpage>1374</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7677045</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Solarski</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panke</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panke</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Craniopharyngioma in the pineal gland</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>490</fpage>
          <lpage>491</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">581156</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Linden</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martinez</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalvo</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cahill</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intrinsic third ventricle craniopharyngioma: CT and MR findings</article-title>
          <source>J Comput Assist Tomogr</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>362</fpage>
          <lpage>363</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2925934</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jan</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsu</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary ethmoid sinus craniopharyngioma: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Laryngol Otol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <lpage>405</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9659511</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Altin&#xF6;rs</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Senveli</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erdo&#x11F;an</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arda</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pak</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Craniopharyngioma of the cerebellopontine angle. Case report</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>842</fpage>
          <lpage>844</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6608580</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bashir</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edwards</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Posterior fast craniopharyngioma</article-title>
          <source>Br J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>613</fpage>
          <lpage>615</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9115662</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xF6;kalp</surname>
              <given-names>HZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Egemen</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ildan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bacaci</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Craniopharyngioma of the posterior fossa</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>446</fpage>
          <lpage>448</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1922715</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Link</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Driscoll</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giannini</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolated, giant cerebellopontine angle craniopharyngioma in a patient with Gardner syndrome: case report</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>221</fpage>
          <lpage>225</lpage>
          <comment>discussion 225-6</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12182421</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sener</surname>
              <given-names>RN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Giant craniopharyngioma extending to the anterior cranial fossa and nasopharynx</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>162</volume>
          <fpage>441</fpage>
          <lpage>442</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8310943</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eldevik</surname>
              <given-names>OP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blaivas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gabrielsen</surname>
              <given-names>TO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hald</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chandler</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Craniopharyngioma: radiologic and histologic findings and recurrence</article-title>
          <source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>1427</fpage>
          <lpage>1439</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8883637</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Axial T2-weighted (upper left), T1-weighted (upper center), contrast-enhanced T1-weighted axial (Upper right), coronal (lower left), and sagittal (lower center, right) MR images show a large well-enhancing solid mass occupying the petroclival region with intracranial extension. It dose not show sellar or suprasellar extension. Compared with the brain cortex, it is isointense on both T1-weighted and T2-weighted images.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-50-725-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Bone-algorithm axial and coronal CT images reveal an extensive, permeative destruction, especially affecting temporal petromastoid and occipital condyle. Left carotid bony canal and jugular foramen were also destroyed. Sclerotic change of left temporal bone might be caused by chronic otomastoiditis. Left vertebral artery is medially displaced by the tumor (lower right) on angiogram.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-50-725-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Photomicrographs of tumor sections demonstrating irregular nests of multistratified squamous cells with peripheral palisading of nuclei (A), and expressing high- and low-molecular weight cytokeratin (B) (original magnifications, &#xD7;200).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-50-725-g003"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
