<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Gastroenterol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJG</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology : Official Journal of the Saudi Gastroenterology Association</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1319-3767</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-4049</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20871199</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2995103</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SJG-16-299</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1319-3767.70621</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Coincidence of Acute Brucella Hepatitis and Dengue Fever or Serologic Cross-reactivity?</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bzeizi</surname>
            <given-names>Khalid I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Benmousa</surname>
            <given-names>Ali</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sanai</surname>
            <given-names>Faisal M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Department of Medicine, Riyadh Military Hospital, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Ali Benmousa, Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Department of Medicine Riyadh Military Hospital, P.O. Box: 7897, Riyadh &#x2013; 111 59, Saudi Arabia. E-mail: <email xlink:href="alibenmousa@hotmail.com">alibenmousa@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>299</fpage>
      <lpage>301</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hepatic involvement in brucellosis is not uncommon since 10-20% of patient infected with brucella species can have abnormal liver function tests. The usual presentation of brucella hepatitis is in the form of chronic granulomatous hepatitis with mild to moderate elevation of liver enzymes, while acute hepatitis is rare. We report a young patient who presented with acute brucella-induced hepatitis and co-infection with dengue hemorrhagic virus resulting in severe elevation of liver enzymes and absence of granuloma on histology. His mother also simultaneously tested positive for both infections. The patient responded well to anti-brucella therapy with normalization of his liver profile. We discuss, herein, the hepatic involvement of these two infections and discuss the possible serological cross-reactivity between brucella and dengue fever virus.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Brucellosis</kwd>
        <kwd>cross-reactivity</kwd>
        <kwd>dengue fever</kwd>
        <kwd>hepatitis</kwd>
        <kwd>serum transaminase</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Brucellosis is a febrile zoonotic infectious disease with occasional hepatic involvement in 10&#x2013;20% of cases.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>] Hepatic involvement usually manifests as a non-specific liver enzyme elevation, while granuloma within the liver may commonly occur.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT3">3</xref>] Similarly, dengue fever is an acute febrile illness caused by a flavivirus and may in turn cause liver enzyme abnormalities. Co-infection of these two pathogens, while feasible, has not been previously described. We describe in this report the simultaneous serological documentation of these two pathogens suggesting an acute infection in two members of the family concomitantly.</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases" id="sec1-1">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 23-year-old Saudi male, previously fit and well, presented with 3 days of fever, chills, epigastric pain, jaundice, and anorexia. Three weeks prior to the onset of illness, he had returned to Saudi Arabia from Pakistan. He denied any history of blood transfusion, use of herbal medications, raw milk ingestion, and contact with animals or with any jaundiced patient. He also denied alcohol/drug abuse or extra-marital sexual relationship. His mother was diagnosed earlier with brucellosis and had just commenced treatment when he returned from Pakistan.</p>
      <p>On examination, he looked unwell, was jaundiced and febrile (39.7&#xB0;C). He had bilateral sub-conjunctival hemorrhages but no evidence of bleeding tendency elsewhere. The rest of his examination was unremarkable.</p>
      <p>The initial laboratory investigations showed a total bilirubin of 225 &#x3BC;mol/L (normal 2&#x2013;22), albumin 42 g/L (normal 36&#x2013;51), alkaline phosphatase (ALP) 146 U/L (normal 35&#x2013;129), alanine transaminase (ALT) 1587 U/L (normal 2&#x2013;40), aspartate transaminase (AST) 1438 U/L (normal 2&#x2013;37), and gamma glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT) 40 U/L (normal 11&#x2013;50). Full blood count and coagulation profile were normal. His viral screen was positive for anti-hepatitis A virus (HAV) IgG and anti-hepatitis E virus (HEV) IgG, while HAV and HEV IgM, HBsAg, anti-HBV IgM and hepatitis C virus serology as well as HCV RNA were all negative. Other viral screen including HIV, cytomegalovirus, and Epstein-Barr-Virus were negative as well. Blood film for malaria was negative several times and auto-antibodies (antinuclear and anti-smooth muscle antibodies) were not detected.</p>
      <p>An ultrasound of the abdomen with Doppler was completely normal. Blood culture was positive for <italic>Brucella melitensis</italic> and brucella serology was strongly positive and therefore he was started on doxycyclin and gentamycin. Screening test for viral hemorrhagic fever was done upon his arrival because of the presence of fever, subconjunctival hemorrhage, and living in two endemic areas. The test was strongly positive for dengue IgM with a titer of 1:2560. Liver histology showed intact architecture with heavy infiltration of the portal tracts by a mixture of mainly neutrophils and eosinophils. There was prominent canalicular cholestasis and Kupffer cell hyperplasia but no granulomas were seen.</p>
      <p>The patient showed significant improvement both clinically and biochemically after starting anti-brucella treatment. His liver profile returned to normal values within 6 weeks from the commencement of treatment.</p>
      <p>We opted to test the patient&#x2019;s mother for dengue fever in view of the above findings. Serological tests were done on a previously stored sample taken at the start of her illness which revealed strong dengue fever seropositivity (IgM) with a titer of 1:1280.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-2">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Brucellosis is a febrile zoonotic infectious disease that has a tendency toward chronicity and is capable of multisystem involvement.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT4">4</xref>] It is caused by facultative intracellular bacteria that can multiply within phagocytic cells in different tissues. In many developed countries, brucellosis is considered an endemic disease and although rarely fatal, it is associated with significant morbidity to the infected host.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT5">5</xref>] In Saudi Arabia, brucella is reported as endemic in many regions including the central, north, and south regions.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT7">7</xref>]</p>
      <p>Hepatic involvement in brucellosis is seen in 10 - 20% of patients.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>] Hepatomegaly is the most commonly reported hepatobiliary sign which occurs in up to one to two-thirds of patients,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT8">8</xref>] although not always associated with abnormality in liver function. Hepatic inflammation was described in 10% of a University of Minnesota brucella series of 244 patients.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref>] The level of ALT elevation in brucella hepatitis is described as modest and in majority of the patients is less than two to three times the upper limit of normal.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT9">9</xref>]</p>
      <p>Our patient has a definite active infection with <italic>Brucella melitensis</italic> as proven by positive blood culture and very high brucella titer and he had evidence of acute hepatitis clinically, biochemically, and histologically. Acute hepatitis, although a recognized feature of brucellosis, is however, very rare and only a few cases so far have been reported in the literature.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT10">10</xref>]</p>
      <p>Hepatic granuloma is relatively common in patients with chronic brucellosis,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref>] while not being universal.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT11">11</xref>] While our patient&#x2019;s hepatic histology did not reveal granuloma, his level of transaminase elevation was also much higher than what has been described in brucella hepatitis. Pakistan is endemic for dengue hemorrhagic fever, and an epidemic was reported in the Western region of Saudi Arabia during the period of the patient&#x2019;s illness. We performed dengue fever serology in our patient due to his atypical presentation for brucellosis and the presence of subconjunctival hemorrhages.</p>
      <p>Dengue is a febrile illness that is caused by flavivirus. Hepatic involvement in patients with dengue fever varies from mild elevation in one or more liver enzymes to acute hepatic failure which is rare.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT13">13</xref>] In a series of 1585 patients reported by the Dengue Reference Center (CRD) in Brazil, 44% had altered level of at least one of the enzymes (AST and/or ALT); 17% had at least one of the enzymes increased to three folds and 3.8% had acute hepatitis (ALT/AST level increased more than 10 folds).[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT14">14</xref>] The disease, however, is self-limiting and complete recovery is the rule.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT14">14</xref>]</p>
      <p>The presence of high titer of IgM antibodies against dengue in this patient makes it plausible to attribute his illness to this pathogen. However, we feel that the likely cause for hepatitis here is the brucellosis. His mother presented with the typical features of brucellosis and her diagnosis was confirmed both by culture and serology. She too had a high titer of IgM antibodies against dengue. She responded well to antibiotics with complete resolution of her symptoms in much the same way as her son.</p>
      <p>A recent study in 800 blood donors from Mexico reportedly found that 59% of donors were reactive for anti-dengue virus IgG, and 0.71% was reactive for anti-brucella serology, without mentioning whether any patient showed common sero-positivity.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT15">15</xref>] Moreover, none had clinical features of acute brucellosis or dengue fever, while only 2% of the overall samples were reactive for anti-dengue virus IgM antibodies. It is very unlikely that our patient and his mother both had brucellosis and dengue fever simultaneously. The positive culture for brucellosis in both patients would make brucella the more likely etiological agent rather than dengue fever. An explanation for this phenomenon is the possible cross-reactivity between brucella and dengue fever virus. While cross reactivity between brucella and other pathogens like Entameba histolotica had been suggested,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT16">16</xref>] and similarly sera from patients with positive brucella serology were found to exhibit positivity against <italic>E. coli</italic> O157 and <italic>Y. enterocolitica</italic> O9,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT17">17</xref>] there have been no reports of such cross-reactivity with viruses, and in particular with flaviviruses. On the other hand, antibodies from the sera of dengue fever patients can cross react with other flavivirus species including Japanese encephalitis and yellow fever viruses,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT18">18</xref>] although no prior reports exist of cross reactivity with brucella.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="CIT1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spink</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Spink</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Nature of Brucellosis</article-title>
          <source>Complications of Brucellosis</source>
          <year>1956</year>
          <edition>1st ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>185</fpage>
          <lpage>186</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boron</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jezna</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Korenkieciwz</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Musiatowicz</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Liver pathology in chronic brucellosis</article-title>
          <source>Acta Hepatogastroenterol</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>261</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sanai</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashraf</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdo</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Satti</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Batwa</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Husseini</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hepatic granuloma: Decreasing trend in a high-incidence area</article-title>
          <source>Liver Int</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>1402</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18694402</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pappas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akritidis</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bosilkovski</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsianos</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brucellosis</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>352</volume>
          <fpage>2325</fpage>
          <lpage>36</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15930423</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pappas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Papadimitriou</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akritidis</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christou</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsianos</surname>
              <given-names>EV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The new global map of human brucellosis</article-title>
          <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439329</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kiel</surname>
              <given-names>FW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>MY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of 506 consecutive positive serologic tests for brucellosis in Saudi Arabia</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>1384</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3624438</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fallatah</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oduloju</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Dusari</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fakunle</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human brucellosis in Northern Saudi Arabia</article-title>
          <source>Saudi Med J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1562</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16228056</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Namiduru</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gungor</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dikensoy</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baydar</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ekinci</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karaoglan</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiological, clinical and laboratory features of brucellosis: A prospective evaluation of 120 adult patients</article-title>
          <source>Int J Clin Pract</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>20</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12587937</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crossley</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute and chronic hepatic involvement of brucellosis</article-title>
          <source>Gastroenterology</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7084621</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Talley</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eckstein</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gattas</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stiel</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute hepatitis and <italic>Brucella melitensis</italic> infection: Clinicopathological findings</article-title>
          <source>Med J Aust</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>148</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3259669</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Young</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Brucella melitensis</italic> hepatitis: The absence of granulomas</article-title>
          <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>414</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">475172</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kuo</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tai</surname>
              <given-names>DI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang-Chien</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lan</surname>
              <given-names>CK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiou</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liaw</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Liver biochemical tests and dengue fever</article-title>
          <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>265</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1355950</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alvarez</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramirez-Rhonda</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dengue and hepatic failure</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>670</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4061482</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Souza</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alves</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nogueira</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gicovate Neto</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bastos</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siqueira</surname>
              <given-names>EW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aminotransferase changes and acute hepatitis in patients with dengue fever: Analysis of 1585 cases</article-title>
          <source>Braz J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>156</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15361994</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rodr&#xED;guez Rodr&#xED;guez</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garza Rodr&#xED;guez</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chavarria</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramos-Jim&#xE9;nez</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rivera</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tam&#xE9;z</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dengue virus antibodies in blood donors from an endemic area</article-title>
          <source>Transfus Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>125</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19566669</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chabasse</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moreau</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Achard</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robert</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hocquet</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Positive amebic immunofluorescence reaction during hepatic brucellosis</article-title>
          <source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot Filiales</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>150</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6780208</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chart</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okubadejo</surname>
              <given-names>OA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rowe</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The serological relationship between <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157 and <italic>Yersinia enterocolitica</italic> O9 using sera from patients with brucellosis</article-title>
          <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1547843</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Makino</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tadano</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saito</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maneekarn</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sittisombut</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sirisanthana</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Studies on serological cross-reaction in sequential flavivirus infections</article-title>
          <source>Microbiol Immunol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>951</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7723688</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
