<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJO</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Korean Journal of Ophthalmology : KJO</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8942</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2092-9382</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Ophthalmological Society</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21052515</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2955278</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3341/kjo.2010.24.5.318</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Case of <italic>Pantoea</italic> Endophthalmitis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Na Eun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>In Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Jong Moon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Gyeongsang National University School of Medicine, Jinju, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Institute of Health Science, Gyeongsang National University, Jinju, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Reprint requests to Jong Moon Park. Department of Ophthalmology, Gyeongsang National University School of Medicine, #90 Chiram-dong, Jinju 660-730, Korea. Tel: 82-55-750-8170, Fax: 82-55-758-4158, <email>parkjm@gnu.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>05</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>24</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>318</fpage>
      <lpage>321</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2010 The Korean Ophthalmological Society</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A previously healthy 50-year-old man was transferred to our hospital for evaluation of acute inflammation in his right eye after ocular trauma while using a grass mower. Slit lamp examination showed 1 mm-length full thickness corneal laceration without leakage, 4+ cells and inflammatory membrane in the anterior chamber, 10% hypopyon, posterior synechiae formation, and cataract change. Upon orbital computerized tomography, a metallic intraocular foreign body in the lens was indentified. Vitrectomy, phacoemulsification, foreign body removal, anterior chamber irrigation, and intravitreal antibiotics injections of vancomycin and ceftazidime were performed. In a culture of humor from the anterior chamber grew <italic>Pantoea</italic> species. More procedures were performed, including intravitreal antibiotics injection of ceftazidime. Upon administering a course of intravenous ceftazidime, fortified ceftazidime and moxifloxacin eye drops, and oral prednisolone, the patient improved.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Endophthalmitis</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>Pantoea</italic> species</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Endophthalmitis is an uncommon but potentially devastating complication of penetrating ocular injuries with retained intraocular foreign bodies (IOFBs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Retained IOFBs are associated with endophthalmitis in approximately 6.9 to 30% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p>
    <p><italic>Pantoea</italic> species is a Gram-negative aerobic <italic>bacillus</italic> in the family <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic>. All species of the genus <italic>Pantoea</italic> can be isolated from feculent material, plants, and soil, where they can be either pathogens or commensals. <italic>Pantoea agglomerans</italic> (<italic>P. agglomerans</italic> synonyms, <italic>Erwinia herbicola</italic>, <italic>Enterobacter agglomerans</italic>) and other <italic>Pantoea</italic> species cause infections in humans and are also pathogenic to plants. <italic>P. agglomerans</italic> was most associated with penetrating trauma by vegetative material and catheter-related bacteremia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p>
    <p>We report a case of a patient who had endophthalmitis caused by <italic>Pantoea</italic> species infection via a retained metallic IOFB, which has not been reported previously in Korea.</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 50-year-old healthy man was transferred to our hospital for evaluation of acute inflammation in the anterior chamber in his right eye. He experienced an ocular trauma while using a grass mower 7 days -prior. Oral cephalosporine and ofloxacin eye drops were prescribed in a private clinic after trauma. He felt severe ocular pain and deterioration of vision and accompanying aggravation of the inflammation as the result of having too much to drink the day before his visit. He had an unremarkable medical history and no underlying illness.</p>
      <p>At the time of the initial visit, the patient's visual acuity was at the level of hand motion in the right eye and 1.0 in the left eye. The intraocular pressure (IOP) was 16 mmHg in the right eye and 10 mmHg in the left eye. The conjunctiva of the right eye was intensely injected with chemosis. Slit lamp examination showed corneal edema, 1 mm-length full thickness corneal laceration without leakage, 4+ cells and an inflamed membrane in the anterior chamber, 10% hypopyon, a mid-dilated-irregular pupil, posterior synechiae formation, and cataract change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Fundus examination revealed a grade 4 vitreous opacity, and B-scan ultrasonography showed opacity in the anterior vitreous. An IOFB suspected as metallic material in the lens was identified upon orbital computerized tomography (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Initial laboratory analyses revealed a white blood cell count of 21,920 cells/mm<sup>3</sup> (neutrophil, 89.9%).</p>
      <p>We performed pars plana vitrectomy, phacoemulsification, foreign body removal, anterior chamber irrigation, suture of the corneal laceration, and intravitreal antibiotics injections of vancomycin (1 mg in 0.1 mL for Gram-positive coverage) and ceftazidime (2.25 mg in 0.1 mL for Gram-negative coverage). The foreign body in the lens was a piece of metal. During the operation, we aspirated some humor in the anterior chamber for identifying the causative bacterium and tests of antibiotic sensitivity.</p>
      <p>The day after operation, there were severe stromal edema and Descemet's membrand folds in the cornea and +3 to +4 cells, no hypopyon in the anterior chamber, and grade 3 vitreous opacity. The patient was treated with ciprofloxacin 200 mg (2 times/day) and tobramycin 80 mg (2 times/day) intravenously and fortified vancomycin (25 mg/mL), as well as moxifloxacin and tobramycin eye drops every 15 minutes. Three days postoperatively, no one was detected in Gram's staining, but <italic>Pantoea</italic> species grew in the culture of humor from the anterior chamber (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Using the VITEK 2 System (BioMerieux, Marcy l'Etoile, France) for antimicrobial susceptibility determination, the culture demonstrated susceptibility to ampicillin, aztreonam, cefotaxime, ceftazidime, ciprofloxacin, gentamicin, imipenem, peperacillin, and tobramycin, whereas resistance to ampicillin. Because the culture tested sensitive to antibiotics, the patient was given ceftazidime 1 g (2 times/day) intravenously, as well as fortified ceftazidime (50 mg/mL) and moxifloxacin eye drops every 15 minutes and oral prednisolone 45 mg daily with discontinuing vancomycin. Six days after operation, vitreous opacity and the red reflex degree worsened, so a repeat intravitreal antibiotics injection of ceftazidime (2 mg in 0.1 mL), as above, was performed.</p>
      <p>One week after last injection, the patient was noted to have +3 cells in the anterior chamber, grade +1 to +2 vitreous opacity, and IOP of 18 mmHg. Attempts at tapering oral corticosteroid and increasing the interval of eye drops progressed favorably without increasing inflammation. Two months after trauma, the best corrected visual acuity was 0.6, and no cells in the anterior chamber or vitreous opacity were detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). He subsequently underwent a secondary IOL placement 4 months after trauma.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Post-traumatic endophthalmitis with retained IOFBs should attract great attention because of its high incidence and poor prognosis. Neuroimaging, preferably with non-contrast computed tomography, provides excellent information about IOFB size, shape, and location. Vitrectomy, which may reduce the incidence and the severity of endophthalmitis is suggested for the treatment of IOFBs and its complications and should be performed as soon as possible. Routine intravenous administration of antibiotics, combined with periocular injection and postoperative topical antibiotics, are recommended. Intravitreal antibiotics warrant consideration in patients with a positive Gram stain in cases of suspected endophthalmitis. A recent study reveals that the only benefit of adding intravitreal antibiotics was in eyes with IOFBs and in high-risk settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. There was no significant difference in outcomes between Gram-positive, Gram-negative, and fungal infections in infectious endophthalmitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p>
      <p>Bacteria of the family <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> are important pathogens, causing intestinal and systemic illness of humans and other animals. <italic>Pantoea</italic> is a genus of Gram-negative aerobic bacteria of the family <italic>Enterobactoericeae</italic>, compromised of seven species and two subspecies. Within the genus, <italic>P. agglomerans</italic> is the most commonly isolated species in humans among not primary pathogens, but rather secondary opportunistic pathogens particularly in immunocompromised individuals. <italic>P. agglomerans</italic> is most associated with penetrating trauma by vegetative material, catheter-related bacteremia, and occupational exposure to airborne biological agents via the respiratory route when working with plants. <italic>P. agglomerans</italic> bacteremia has also been described in association with the contamination of intravenous fluid, total parenteral nutrition, the anesthetic agent propofol, and blood projects. There are reports of <italic>P. agglomerans</italic> infection, including arthritis or synovitis, osteromyelitis, ostitis, cholelithiasis, occupational respiratory infection, skin allergy, and peritonitis. In children, <italic>Pantoea</italic> species has a predilection for the lungs and infections may induce life-threatening conditions, such as septic shock and respiratory failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p>
      <p><italic>Pantoea ananatis</italic> causes disease symptoms in a wide range of economically important agricultural crops and forest tree species worldwide and could induce blood stream infection in elderly-human [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. <italic>Pantoea</italic> has become known to be susceptible to tetracycline, as well as broad-spectrum cephalosporins, aminoglycosides, semisynthetic penicillins, and quinolones in most cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p>
      <p>To date, there have been two reported cases of endophthalmitis caused by <italic>P. agglomerans</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. One case involved an ensuing perforated cornea and endophthalmitis caused by injury to the left eye while gardening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. The lens was opaque, and its anterior capsule was ruptured. A culture of fluid obtained by anterior chamber paracentesis yielded a species of the <italic>Erwinia herbicolalathyri</italic> group (<italic>Enterobacter agglomerans</italic>). After extracapsular cataract extraction was performed and a course of cefazolin administered, the patient showed improvement. Another case reported involved metastatic endophthalmitis caused by the Gram-negative organism <italic>Enterobacter agglomerans</italic> following internal hemorrhoidal ligation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. The patient developed anterior uveitis that progressed to panophthalmitis, with a lenticular abscess and a necrotic retina. Despite aggressive surgery and appropriate antibiotic therapy, the affected eye lost useful vision.</p>
      <p>A previously healthy 50-year-old man presented with endophthalmitis after ocular trauma. In response, vitrectomy, phacoemulsification, foreign body removal, anterior chamber irrigation, and intravitreal antibiotics injections of vancomycin and ceftazidime were performed. <italic>Pantoea</italic> species grew in a culture of humor from the anterior chamber. Antibiotic susceptibility revealed that there was no difference from established antibiotics sensitivity for <italic>Pantoea</italic> species. After proper antibiotics management, we achieved a favorable outcome.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Traumatic endophthalmitis following penetrating ocular injuries with retained intraocular foreign bodies</article-title>
          <source>Chin J Traumatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>167</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12749789</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mieler</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ellis</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Retained intraocular foreign bodies and endophthalmitis</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmology</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>1532</fpage>
          <lpage>1538</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2255525</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parver</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enger</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Infectious endophthalmitis after penetrating injuries with retained intraocular foreign bodies. National Eye Trauma System</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmology</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>1468</fpage>
          <lpage>1474</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8414406</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Imrie</surname>
              <given-names>FR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foot</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macewen</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surveillance of intraocular foreign bodies in the UK</article-title>
          <source>Eye (Lond)</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>1141</fpage>
          <lpage>1147</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17525772</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cebulla</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flynn</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endophthalmitis after open globe injuries</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>147</volume>
          <fpage>567</fpage>
          <lpage>568</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19327442</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cruz</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cazacu</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pantoea agglomerans, a plant pathogen causing human disease</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1989</fpage>
          <lpage>1992</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17442803</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deletoile</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Decre</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Courant</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phylogeny and identification of Pantoea species and typing of Pantoea agglomerans strains by multilocus gene sequencing</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>300</fpage>
          <lpage>310</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19052179</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brady</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cleenwerck</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Venter</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phylogeny and identification of Pantoea species associated with plants, humans and the natural environment based on multilocus sequence analysis (MLSA)</article-title>
          <source>Syst Appl Microbiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>447</fpage>
          <lpage>460</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19008066</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yeh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colyer</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weichel</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Current trends in the management of intraocular foreign bodies</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>225</fpage>
          <lpage>233</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18408498</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andreoli</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andreoli</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kloek</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low rate of endophthalmitis in a large series of open globe injuries</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>147</volume>
          <fpage>601</fpage>
          <lpage>608.e2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19181306</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niederer</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von Lany</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Polkinghorne</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Infectious endophthalmitis: clinical features, management and visual outcomes</article-title>
          <source>Clin Experiment Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>631</fpage>
          <lpage>636</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18983548</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chale-Matsau</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snyman</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The survival of pathogens in soil treated with wastewater sludge and in potatoes grown in such soil</article-title>
          <source>Water Sci Technol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>168</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17087382</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van Rostenberghe</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Noraida</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wan Pauzi</surname>
              <given-names>WI</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The clinical picture of neonatal infection with Pantoea species</article-title>
          <source>Jpn J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>120</fpage>
          <lpage>121</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16632913</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gora</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackiewicz</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krawczyk</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occupational exposure to organic dust, microorganisms, endotoxin and peptidoglycan among plants processing workers in Poland</article-title>
          <source>Ann Agric Environ Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>143</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19572487</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>WE</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Enterobacter spp.: pathogens poised to flourish at the turn of the century</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>220</fpage>
          <lpage>241</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9105752</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of peritonitis caused by Pantoea agglomerans in a patient undergoing continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Med</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>426</fpage>
          <lpage>429</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coutinho</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Venter</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pantoea ananatis: an unconventional plant pathogen</article-title>
          <source>Mol Plant Pathol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>325</fpage>
          <lpage>335</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19400836</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mason</surname>
              <given-names>GI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bottone</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Podos</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Traumatic endophthalmitis caused by an Erwinia species</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>709</fpage>
          <lpage>713</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1087119</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zeiter</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koch</surname>
              <given-names>DD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>ParkE</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
              <suffix>2nd</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Font</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endogenous endophthalmitis with lenticular abscess caused by Enterobacter agglomerans (Erwinia species)</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmic Surg</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2784556</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Slit lamp photography at initial presentation shows conjunctival injection, corneal edema, hypopyon, exudative membrane, and mid-dilated pupil.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-318-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Orbital computerized tomography shows a metallic intraocular foreign body in the lens.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-318-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A culture of aspirated aqueous humor from the anterior chamber shows growth of <italic>Pantoea</italic> species (culture media: McConkey agar).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-318-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Fundus photography at two months after trauma shows vitreous and retinal clarity.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-24-318-g004"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
