<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16361829</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2779316</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2005.20.6.1082</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>An Infantile Case of Sturge-Weber Syndrome in Association with Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber Syndrome and Phakomatosis Pigmentovascularis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Chang-Woo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Du-Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>Yeon-Geun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>Hyang-Suk</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jong-Duk</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Pediatrics, Wonkwang University School of Medicine, Iksan, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address for correspondence: Chang-Woo Lee, M.D. Department of Pediatrics, Wonkwang University College of Medicine, 344-2 Sinyoung-dong, Iksan 570-711, Korea. Tel: +82.63-850-1099, Fax: +82.63-853-3670, <email>chan33@wonkwang.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>20</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>1082</fpage>
      <lpage>1084</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2005 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sturge-Weber syndrome can be associated with facial port-wine stains and intracranial calcification, and concurrent Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome has been reported. Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome is a rare congenital mesodermal phakomatosis characterized by cutaneous hemangiomas, venous varicosities and soft tissue or bone hypertrophy of the affected extremities. This report is presented a rare case of the Sturge-Weber syndrome in combination with the Klippel-Trennaunay syndrome and phakomatosis pigmentovascularis in a 4-month-old infant. He showed nevus flameus on the right leg and both part of the face and back, leptomeningeal angiomatosis on right hemisphere, hypertrophy of the right leg, hemiconvulsion on the left and also evidences of congenital glaucoma and nevus of Ota. Very rare case combined with these three kinds of phakomatosis has been reported.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber Syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Sturge-Weber Syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Phakomatosis Pigmentovascularis</kwd>
        <kwd>Neurocutaneous Syndromes</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Sturge-Weber syndrome is a sporadic condition of mesodermal phakomatosis characterized by a portwine vascular nevus on the upper part of the face, leptomeningeal angiomatosis that involves one or both hemispheres, choroidal vascular lesions associated with glaucoma, seizures, neurologic deterioration, and eventual neurodevelopmental delay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>).</p>
      <p>Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome, also a mesodermal phakomatosis, is defined by a triad of cutaneous and visceral hemangiomas, which can appear at any site of the body, venous varicosities, and soft tissue or bone hypertrophy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Overlap between Sturge-Weber syndrome and Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome is recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome is a nonhereditary condition that shares clinical features with Sturge-Weber syndrome and over 40 cases of combined Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome and Sturge-Weber syndrome have now been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p>
      <p>Phakomatosis pigmentovascularis is a distinctive association of cutaneous hemangiomas and melanocytic nevi. The hemangiomas consist of extensive nevus flammeus, while the melanocytic lesions may be aberrant mongolian spots, nevus of Ota, and nevus of Ito. Nevus of Ota is a permanent, non-homogeneous bluish gray, black or brown lesion on the facial skin limited to the area innervated by the first and second divisions of the trigeminal nerve, with frequent association of the ipsilateral ocular pigmentation.</p>
      <p>We experienced an unusual case of male infant with features of both Sturge-Weber syndrome and Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome, who presented with nevus flammeus on the face, back and leg, leptomeningeal angiomatosis on right hemisphere, hypertrophy of the right leg, hemiconvulsion, congenital glaucoma and nevus of Ota.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 4-month-old male infant presented with nevus flammeus on the right leg and both part of the face and back, hypertrophy of the right leg and first attack of hemiconvulsion on the left. A diagnosis of Sturge-Weber syndrome was made during neonatal period on the basis of portwine vascular nevus on the upper part of the face, leptomeningeal angiomatosis that involves right hemisphere, choroidal vascular lesions associated with glaucoma. He had not taken any other form of medication in the previous 3 months.</p>
      <p>His physical examination showed nevus flammeus diffusely involving the both side of his face and extending to the both lower eyelids and cheeks. There were bilateral oculodermal melanosis and an area of bluish gray pigmentation of the episclera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Diffuse bluish discoloration or spots were present on the left side of his shoulder, arm, and wrist (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). His right lower limb showed a relative soft tissue hypertrophy and nevus flammeus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). There was no difference in length of both lower limb. But the circumference of his right thigh was 25 cm and that of his left thigh was 21.5 cm.</p>
      <p>The hematologic, biochemical, and urinary laboratory tests and the chest and skull radiographs were normal. Abdominal ultrasonography showed no pathologic findings of the visceral organs. On cranial computed tomography scan, there was hyper-dense appearance secondary to meningeal venous angiomatous change on the right cerebral hemisphere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). The patient was diagnosed to have Sturge-Weber syndrome in association with Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome, according to the results of physical examination and radiologic evaluation.</p>
      <p>Treatment with anticonvulsant was begun. But hemiseizures were recurred several times. His electroencephalography revealed low amplitude polyphasic spikes and waves activity, and voltage suppression in right hemisphere. The frequency of seizure was reduced probably due to anticonvulsants, excegran, acetazolamide and corticosteroid. At the time of discharge his medical regime included excegran and acetazoleamide.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome is present at birth and usually involves a lower extremity but may involve more than one and portions of trunk or face. Enlargement of the soft tissues may be gradual and may involve the entire extremity, a portion of it, or selected digits. Thick-walled venous varicosities typically become apparent ipsilateral to the vascular malformation after child begins to ambulate. Supportive care includes compression bandages for varicosities and surgical treatment may help selected patients. Associated complication include dislocation of joint, congestive heart failure, cerebral arteriovenous malformations, spinal arteriovenous malformations, macrocephaly, microcephaly, thombophlebitis, hematuria, rectal bleeding and orbitofrontal varices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>).</p>
      <p>Sturge-Weber syndrome is a rare, sporadic disease with a potentially progressive course. Facial and leptomeningeal angioma are usually, but not necessarily, on the same side (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). About 70% of patients with epilepsy have their first seizure within the first year of life. The initial seizures often involve the hemibody contralateral to the pial angioma and early seizures are triggered by fever in about one third of cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Almost all the early seizures qualify as status epilepticus. The outcome after the first seizures is variable, but long term follow-up have shown that the seizure are often well controlled. Interictal EEG in Sturge-Weber syndrome shows focal and unilateral depression of the background activity over the area of leptomeningeal agiomatosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Focal epileptiform abnormalities are infrequent in infants, even in those with frequent seizures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Surgery should be considered early when medical treatment fails. The earlier the surgery with respect to seizure onset, the less the chance of increased neurologic deterioration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>).</p>
      <p>Nevus of Ota is more common in females and in Asian and black patients, and differs from a Mongolian spots, not only by its distribution but also by having a speckled rather than a uniform appearance. Malignant change is rare and laser therapy may effectively decrease the pigmentation.</p>
      <p>Four types of phakomatosis pigmentovascularis have been recognized, each of which are subgrouped further by the abscence (type a) or presence (type b) of systemic organ involvement. All types of phakomatosis pigmentovascularis have nevus flammeus as a component. In addition to nevus flammeus, type I has an epidermal nevus, type II has blue spots with or without nevus anemicus, type III has nevus spilus, with or without nevus anemicus, type IV has blue spots and nevus spilus with or without nevus anemicus. Our case can be classified as type IIa, according to the classification of phakomatosis pigmentovascularis. Phakomatosis pigmentovascularis is a rare disorder characterized by the association of a nevus flammeus and melanocytic lesions. Phakomatosis pigmentovascularis was first described as association of cutaneous hemangioma and melanotic or epidermal nevi by Ota in 1939 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). Abnormalities in the neural regulations of blood vessels may be important in the development of the vascular component of phakomatosis pigmentovascularis. Anomaly in the migration of the neural crest-derived melanocytes would result in nevus of Ota, Mongolian spots and nevus spilus. There is double heterozygosity with the recessive vascular mutation on chromosome and the pigmentary mutation on the homologous chromosome. During embryogenesis, somatic recombination or crossing-over occurs between the homologous chromosomes, resulting in 2 different cell populations, each being homozygous for either allele. Associated clinical manifestation of the above-mentioned neurophacomatosis include scoliosis, renal angiomas, moyamoya disease, aplastic anemia, abdominal lymphangioma, chylothorax, deafness, chronic thyroiditis, pyogenic granuloma and mental retardation.</p>
      <p>There is no specific curative treatment for this combined disorder. Recognition of possible underlying systemic and local anomalies and complications dictates management.</p>
      <p>We present a 4-monthold baby boy who is considered as an interesting case of Sturge-Weber syndrome in association with Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome and phakomatosis pigmentovascularis. To the best of our knowledge, Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome has been reported many times, and the only one case of Sturge-Weber syndrome in association with Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome and phakomatosis pigmentovascularis has been reported in 13-yr-old girl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). But the infantile case of the above-mentioned combined neurophacomatosis has not been reported. In infantile case there were no venous varicosities and bony hypertrophy of the affected extremities.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>This paper was supported by the grant from <funding-source>Wonkwang University</funding-source> in 2004.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sturge</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of partial epilepsy apparently due to a lesion of one of the vasomotor centers of the brain</article-title>
          <source>Trans Clin Soc Lond</source>
          <year>1879</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>162</fpage>
          <lpage>167</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barek</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ledor</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ledor</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Klippel-Trenaunay syndrome: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Mt Sinai J Med</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>66</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6283338</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deutsch</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weissenbacher</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Widhalm</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolf</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barsegar</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Combination of the syndrome of the Sturge-Weber and the syndrome of Klippel-Trenaunay</article-title>
          <source>Klin Pediatr</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>188</volume>
          <fpage>464</fpage>
          <lpage>471</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Willliams</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
              <suffix>III</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elster</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cranial CT and MR in the Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Am J Neuroradiol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1317663</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stephan</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hall</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Macrocephaly in association with unusual cutaneous angiomatosis</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>353</fpage>
          <lpage>359</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">170387</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jaksch</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bewermeyer</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dreesbach</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heiss</surname>
              <given-names>WD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cerebral hemorrhage in arteriovenous malformation associated with Klippel-Trenaunay syndrome</article-title>
          <source>J Neurol</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>233</volume>
          <fpage>48</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3005520</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boltshauser</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoare</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sturge-Weber syndrome with bilateral intracranial calcification</article-title>
          <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>429</fpage>
          <lpage>435</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">932761</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Revol</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilly</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Challamel</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epilepsie et maladie de Sturge-Weber</article-title>
          <source>Boll Lega Ital Epil</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brenner</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharbrough</surname>
              <given-names>FW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Electroencephalographic evaluation in Sturge-Weber syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Neurology</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>629</fpage>
          <lpage>632</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">945510</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sassower</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duchowny</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jayakar</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>EEG evaluation in children with Sturge-Weber syndrome and epilepsy</article-title>
          <source>J Epilepsy</source>
          <year>1944</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>289</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ogunmekan</surname>
              <given-names>AO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hwang</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoffman</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sturge-Weber-Dimitri disease: role of hemispherectomy in prognosis</article-title>
          <source>Can J Neurol Sci</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>78</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2924212</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ota</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nevus fusco-caeruleus ophthalmo-maxillaris</article-title>
          <source>Jpn J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1939</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>369</fpage>
          <lpage>374</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Won</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of phakomatosis pigmentovascularis type IIb associated with perirenal lipomatosis</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>1069</fpage>
          <lpage>1073</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Bilateral facial nevus flammeus, oculodermal melanosis and an area of bluish gray pigmentation of the episclera.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-1082-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Diffuse bluish discoloration on the left side of his shoulder, arm, and wrist.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-1082-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>His right lower limb showed a relative soft tissue hypertrophy and nevus flammeus.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-1082-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Hyper-dense appearance secondary to meningeal venous angiomatous change at the right cerebral hemisphere on cranial computed tomography scan.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-20-1082-g004"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
