<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report" xml:lang="EN">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18507908</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2600287</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-0029</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1406.080029</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Dispatch</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Persistence of <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> in Soil Under Natural Conditions</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Persistence of <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> in Soil under Natural Conditions</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> Persistence in Soil</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Eisen</surname>
            <given-names>Rebecca J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Petersen</surname>
            <given-names>Jeannine M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Higgins</surname>
            <given-names>Charles L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wong</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Levy</surname>
            <given-names>Craig E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">&#x2021;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mead</surname>
            <given-names>Paul S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schriefer</surname>
            <given-names>Martin E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Griffith</surname>
            <given-names>Kevin S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gage</surname>
            <given-names>Kenneth L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ben Beard</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>*</label>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Fort Collins, Colorado, USA</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>&#x2020;</label>National Park Service, Washington, DC, USA</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>&#x2021;</label>Arizona Department of Health Services, Phoenix, Arizona, USA</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: Rebecca J. Eisen, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 3150 Rampart Rd, Fort Collins, CO 80521, USA; email: <email xlink:href="rjeisen@cdc.gov">rjeisen@cdc.gov</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>941</fpage>
      <lpage>943</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>As part of a fatal human plague case investigation, we showed that the plague bacterium, <italic>Yersinia pestis,</italic> can survive for at least 24 days in contaminated soil under natural conditions. These results have implications for defining plague foci, persistence, transmission, and bioremediation after a natural or intentional exposure to <italic>Y. pestis</italic>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author" xml:lang="EN">
        <title>Keywords: </title>
        <kwd>Yersinia pestis</kwd>
        <kwd>soil</kwd>
        <kwd>plague</kwd>
        <kwd>dispatch</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Plague is a rare, but highly virulent, zoonotic disease characterized by quiescent and epizootic periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Although the etiologic agent, <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic>, can be transmitted through direct contact with an infectious source or inhalation of infectious respiratory droplets, flea-borne transmission is the most common mechanism of exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Most human cases are believed to occur during epizootic periods when highly susceptible hosts die in large numbers and their fleas are forced to parasitize hosts upon which they would not ordinarily feed, including humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). Despite over a century of research, we lack a clear understanding of how <italic>Y. pestis</italic> is able to rapidly disseminate in host populations during epizootics or how it persists during interepizootic periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). What limits the geographic distribution of the organism is also unclear. For example, why is the plague bacterium endemic west of the 100th meridian in the United States, but not in eastern states despite several known introductions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>)?</p>
    <p>Persistence of <italic>Y. pestis</italic> in soil has been suggested as a possible mechanism of interepizootic persistence, epizootic spread, and as a factor defining plague foci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>). Although <italic>Y. pestis</italic> recently evolved from an enteric bacterium, <italic>Y. pseudotuberuclosis</italic>, that can survive for long periods in soil and water, studies have shown that selection for vector-borne transmission has resulted in the loss of many of these survival mechanisms. This suggests that long-term persistence outside of the host or vector is unlikely (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><italic>11</italic></xref>). Previous studies have demonstrated survival of <italic>Y. pestis</italic> in soil under artificial conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><italic>12</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><italic>14</italic></xref>). However, survival of <italic>Y. pestis</italic> in soil under natural exposure conditions has not been examined in North America.</p>
    <sec sec-type="other1">
      <title>The Study</title>
      <p>As part of an environmental investigation of a fatal human plague case in Grand Canyon National Park, Arizona, in 2007, we tested the viability of <italic>Y. pestis</italic> in naturally contaminated soil. The case-patient, a wildlife biologist, was infected through direct contact with a mountain lion carcass, which was subsequently confirmed to be positive for <italic>Y. pestis</italic> based on direct fluorescent antibody (DFA) testing (which targets the <italic>Y. pestis</italic>&#x2013;specific F1 antigen), culture isolation, and lysis with a <italic>Y. pestis</italic> temperature-specific bacteriophage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>). The animal was wearing a radio collar, and we determined the date of its death (October 26, 2007) on the basis of its lack of movement. The case-patient had recorded the location at which he encountered the carcass and had taken photographs of the remains, which showed a large pool of blood in the soil under the animal&#x2019;s mouth and nose. During our field investigation, &#x2248;3 weeks after the mountain lion&#x2019;s death, we used global positioning satellite coordinates and photographs to identify the exact location of the blood-contaminated soil. We collected &#x2248;200 mL of soil from this location at depths of up to &#x2248;15 cm from the surface.</p>
      <p>After collection, the soil was shipped for analysis to the Bacterial Diseases Branch of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Fort Collins, Colorado. Four soil samples of &#x2248;5 mL each were suspended in a total volume of 20 mL of sterile physiologic saline (0.85% NaCl). Samples were vortexed briefly and allowed to settle for &#x2248;2 min before aliquots of 0.5 mL were drawn into individual syringes and injected subcutaneously into 4 Swiss-Webster strain mice (ACUC Protocol 00&#x2013;06&#x2013;018-MUS). Within 12 hours of inoculation, 1 mouse became moribund, and liver and spleen samples were cultured on cefsulodin-Irgasan-novobiocin agar. Colonies consistent with <italic>Y. pestis</italic> morphology were subcultured on sheep blood agar. A DFA test of this isolate was positive, demonstrating the presence of F1 antigen, which is unique to <italic>Y. pestis.</italic> The isolate was confirmed as <italic>Y. pestis</italic> by lysis with a <italic>Y. pestis</italic> temperature&#x2013;specific bacteriophage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15"><italic>15</italic></xref>). Additionally, the isolate was urease negative. Biotyping (glycerol fermentation and nitrate reduction) of the soil and mountain lion isolates indicated biovar <italic>orientalis</italic>.</p>
      <p>Of the 3 remaining mice, 1 became moribund after 7 days and was euthanized; 2 did not become moribund and were euthanized 21 days postexposure. Culture of the necropsied tissues yielded no additional isolates of <italic>Y. pestis</italic>. Pulsed-field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) typing with <italic>Asc</italic>I was performed with the soil isolate, the isolate recovered from the mountain lion, and the isolate obtained from the case-patient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16"><italic>16</italic></xref>). The PFGE patterns were indistinguishable, showing that the <italic>Y. pestis</italic> in the soil originated through contamination by this animal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>). Although direct plating of the soil followed by quantification of CFU would have been useful for assessing the abundance of <italic>Y. pestis</italic> in the soil, this was not possible because numerous contaminants were present in the soil.</p>
      <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
        <label>Figure</label>
        <caption>
          <p><italic>Asc</italic>I pulsed-field gel electrophoresis patterns for the <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> isolates recovered from soil (lane 3) and the mountain lion (lane 2). Lane 1, <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serotype Braenderup standard.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="08-0029-F"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>It is unclear by what mechanism <italic>Y. pestis</italic> was able to persist in the soil. Perhaps the infected animal&#x2019;s blood created a nutrient-enriched environment in which the bacteria could survive. Alternatively, adherence to soil invertebrates may have prolonged bacterial viability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17"><italic>17</italic></xref>). The contamination occurred within a protected rock outcrop that had limited exposure to UV light and during late October, when ambient temperatures were low. These microclimatic conditions, which are similar to those of burrows used by epizootic hosts such as prairie dogs, could have contributed to survival of the bacteria.</p>
      <p>These results are preliminary and do not address 1) the maximum time that plague bacteria can persist in soil under natural conditions, 2) possible mechanisms by which the bacteria are able to persist in the soil, or 3) whether the contaminated soil is infectious to susceptible hosts that might come into contact with the soil. Answers to these questions might shed light on the intriguing, long-standing mysteries of how <italic>Y. pestis</italic> persists during interepizootic periods and whether soil type could limit its geographic distribution. From a public health or bioterrorism preparedness perspective, answers to these questions are necessary for evidence-based recommendations on bioremediation after natural or intentional contamination of soil by <italic>Y. pestis</italic>. Previous studies evaluating viability of <italic>Y. pestis</italic> on manufactured surfaces (e.g., steel, glass) have shown that survival is typically &lt;72 hours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18"><italic>18</italic></xref>). Our data emphasize the need to reevaluate the duration of persistence in soil and other natural media.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="citation">
        <p><italic>Suggested citation for this article</italic>: Eisen RJ, Petersen JM, Higgins MS, Wong D, Levy CE, Mead PS, et al. Persistence of <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> in soil under natural conditions. Emerg Infect Dis [serial on the Internet]. 2008 Jun [<italic>date cited</italic>]. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/EID/content/14/6/941.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/EID/content/14/6/941.htm</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank L. Chalcraft, A. Janusz, R. Palarino, S. Urich, and J. Young for technical and logistic support.</p>
    </ack>
    <bio>
      <p>Dr Eisen is a service fellow in the Division of Vector-Borne Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Fort Collins. Her primary interest is in the ecology of vector-borne diseases.</p>
    </bio>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1. </label>
        <citation citation-type="confproc"><string-name><surname>Barnes</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name> Conference proceedings: surveillance and control of bubonic plague in the United States. Symposium of the Zoological Society of London. <year>1982</year>;50:237&#x2013;70.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gage</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kosoy</surname> <given-names>MY</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Natural history of plague: perspectives from more than a century of research.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>505</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>28</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ento.50.071803.130337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15471529</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Drancourt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houhamdi</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raoult</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name> <article-title><italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> as a telluric, human ectoparasite-borne organism.</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>234</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(06)70438-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16554248</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eisen</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bearden</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilder</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montenieri</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antolin</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gage</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Early-phase transmission of <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> by unblocked fleas as a mechanism explaining rapidly spreading plague epizootics.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>15380</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0606831103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032761</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Webb</surname> <given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gage</surname> <given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antolin</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Classic flea-borne transmission does not drive plague epizootics in prairie dogs.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <year>2006</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>6236</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0510090103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16603630</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cherchenko</surname> <given-names>II</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dyatlov</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Broader investigation into the external environment of the specific antigen of the infectious agent in epizootiological observation and study of the structure of natural foci of plague.</article-title><source>J Hyg Epidemiol Microbiol Immunol</source> <year>1976</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">135026</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7. </label>
        <citation citation-type="book"><string-name><surname>Pollitzer</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name> Plague. World Health Organization Monograph Series No. 22. Geneva: The Organization; <year>1954</year></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bazanova</surname> <given-names>LP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maevskii</surname> <given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khabarov</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></string-name> <comment>An experimental study of the possibility for the preservation of the causative agent of plague in the nest substrate of the long-tailed suslik</comment> <source>Med Parazitol (Mosk)</source> <year>1997</year>; (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9445996</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Achtman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zurth</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morelli</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Torrea</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guiyoule</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carniel</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name> <article-title><italic>Yersinia pestis</italic>, the cause of plague, is a recently emerged clone of <italic>Yersinia pseudotuberculosis</italic>.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <year>1999</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>14043</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.24.14043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10570195</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brubaker</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Factors promoting acute and chronic diseases caused by yersiniae.</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source> <year>1991</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1889045</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perry</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fetherston</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></string-name> <article-title><italic>Yersinia pestis</italic>&#x2014;etiologic agent of plague.</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source> <year>1997</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8993858</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baltazard</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karimi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eftekhari</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chamsa</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mollaret</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></string-name> <article-title>La conservation interepizootique de la peste en foyer invetere hypotheses de travail.</article-title><source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot</source> <year>1963</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1230</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>41</lpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mollaret</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Conservation du bacille de la peste durant 28 mois en terrier artificiel: demonstration experimentale de la conservation interepizootique de las peste dans ses foyers inveteres.</article-title><source>CR Acad Sci Paris.</source><year>1968</year>;<volume>267</volume>:<fpage>972</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3</lpage></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mollaret</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></string-name> <comment>Experimental preservation of plague in soil</comment> [in French]. <source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot Filiales</source> <year>1963</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1168</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14156818</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15. </label>
        <citation citation-type="book"><string-name><surname>Chu</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></string-name> Laboratory manual of plague diagnostics. Geneva: US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and World Health Organization; <year>2000</year></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab> <article-title>Imported plague&#x2014;New York City, 2002.</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12904738</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Darby</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghori</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falkow</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name> <article-title><italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>: plague bacteria biofilm blocks food intake.</article-title><source>Nature</source> <year>2002</year>;<volume>417</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/417243a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015591</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18. </label>
        <citation citation-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rose</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Donlan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banerjee</surname> <given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arduino</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Survival of <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> on environmental surfaces.</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source> <year>2003</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>2166</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>71</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.4.2166-2171.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676697</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
