<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18437025</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2526419</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2008.23.2.347</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Case of Occupational Rhinitis Caused by Porcine Pancreatic Extract Developing into Occupational Asthma</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Seung Youp</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hur</surname>
            <given-names>Gyu Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ye</surname>
            <given-names>Young Min</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Hae Sim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Otolaryngology, Kyung Hee University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>*</label>Department of Allergy and Rheumatology, Ajou University School of Medicine, Suwon, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Address for correspondence: Hae-Sim Park, M.D. Department of Allergy and Rheumatology, Ajou University School of Medicine, San-5 Wonchon-dong, Yeongtong-gu, Suwon 442-749, Korea. Tel: +82.31-219-5150, Fax: +82.31-219-5154, <email>hspark@ajou.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>23</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>347</fpage>
      <lpage>349</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2008 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Porcine pancreatic extracts (PPE), which are widely used as a digestive drug in Korea, are composed of &#x3B1;-amylase and lipase. Such enzymes are commonly described as occupational allergens. This is the first report of occupational rhinitis caused by PPE developing into occupational asthma in a hospital nurse. She showed strong positive response in the skin prick test (SPT) (5+, wheal ratio of allergen to histamine) and had a high serum-specific IgE level to PPE, but showed a negative response in the methacholine bronchial challenge test (MBT). She had been exposed to PPE intermittently with intermittent medications for rhinitis. Two years later, she presented with rhinitis and additional asthmatic symptoms. In contrast to her first visit, she showed a positive response in the MBT, and developed bronchoconstriction in the PPE-bronchial provocation test (BPT). These findings suggest that inhalation of PPE powder can induce IgE-mediated occupational rhinitis in a hospital setting, which will develop into occupational asthma if avoidance is not complete.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Pancreatic Extracts</kwd>
        <kwd>Occupational Rhinitis</kwd>
        <kwd>Occupational Asthma, Specific IgE</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Porcine pancreatic extracts (PPE), composed of &#x3B1;-amylase and lipase, are widely used as a digestive drug in this country; however, they can induce IgE-mediated occupational rhinitis or asthma in bakery workers or those involved in the pharmaceutical industry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Although it is widely accepted that allergic rhinitis may precede asthma, few studies have reported about occupational rhinitis developing into occupational asthma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). This is the first case of occupational rhinitis progressing into occupational asthma during a 2-yr follow-up period with chronic exposure to digestive enzymes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 31-yr-old female who had dispensed digestive drugs to admitted patients during 6 yr of employment as a university hospital nurse presented to allergy clinic 2 yr ago and complained of rhinorrhea and sneezing, but no asthmatic symptoms, when handling PPE powders. The patient was non-atopic and had no history of medical illness or family history of allergic disease. To evaluate her IgE responses, a skin prick test (SPT) was performed, and strongly positive responses were generated to PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase (5+ and 3+ wheal ratios of allergen to histamine, respectively). PPE and other medicinal extracts collected from her workplace were prepared according to the previously described method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) and used to detect serum-specific IgE by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). The positive cutoff value for a high level of serum-specific IgE antibody was defined as the mean&#xB1;3 SD (standard deviations) of the absorbance value from unexposed healthy controls. The patient showed high levels of specific IgE to PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase by ELISA (1041 and 1003 absorbance value, respectively). To confirm bronchial sensitization, a methacholine bronchial challenge test (MBT) and a specific bronchial provocation test (BPT) were performed with PPE, and both generated negative responses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The patient was thus diagnosed with occupational rhinitis to PPE. Antihistamine and a topical steroid were recommended to control her rhinitis symptoms, and she continued working in the same environment. Two years later, she revisited our allergy clinic complaining of rhinitis and additional asthmatic symptoms. A second SPT showed increased responses to PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase (6+ and 6+ wheal ratios of allergen to histamine, respectively), and her serum-specific IgE level was found to be highly elevated by ELISA (720 and 718 absorbance values and respectively). A second MBT demonstrated positive responses at 1.36 mg/mL, and the BPT showed an early asthmatic response after inhalation of PPE (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>); both tests were performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Negative responses were recorded for the other drug powders tested.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>This case demonstrates that PPE powder inhalation can induce occupational rhinitis, and furthermore develop into  occupational asthma when the causative allergen is not avoided in an exposed nurse working in a hospital. It is commonly accepted that allergic rhinitis precedes the development of asthma, although reports on allergic rhinitis turning into asthma are few, especially in a hospital nurse by drug powder. The patient had been diagnosed as having occupational rhinitis, due to the work-related rhinitis symptoms, strongly positive responses in the SPT, and high serum-specific IgE levels to PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase, but not in the MBT and specific BPT. After 2 yr, she developed occupational asthma, showing the additional symptoms of lower respiratory tract and a positive response on the MBT and specific BPT.</p>
      <p>PPE are composed of &#x3B1;-amylase and lipase, which are common components of digestive enzymes. Enzyme allergy has been recognized since the late 1960s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). It may cause asthma, rhino-conjunctivitis, allergic contact dermatitis, and contact urticaria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). A community-based study recently reported that enzymes could be a specific occupational risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). There have been some reports of occupational asthma induced by these enzymes inhaled during the course of work, predominantly among pharmaceutical industry workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). In our preceding reports, we detected occupational allergy to enzymes, such as &#x3B1;-amylase and Empynase&#xAE; among hospital personnel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>).</p>
      <p>The major pathogenic mechanism of occupational allergies induced by high-molecular-weight drugs is an IgE-mediated response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). The subject of this case had strongly positive responses in the SPT and a high serum level of specific IgE by ELISA to both PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase. In addition, the BPT with PPE produced immediate bronchoconstriction. These findings suggest that the pathogenic mechanism of occupational rhinitis is an IgE-mediated response, and chronic exposure to PPE can result in occupational asthma via an IgE-mediated reaction. In this study, the patient showed positive responses to both PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase by SPT and ELISA, which may indicate that &#x3B1;-amylase is the major allergenic component within the PPE. In our preceding study, it had been demonstrated that PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase had extensive cross-allergenicity by PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase ELISA inhibition test, and shared one strong IgE binding component by IgE immunoblot study. However, lipase showed minimal inhibition for both PPE and &#x3B1;-amylase ELISA inhibition tests, and a lesser degree of inhibition on lipase ELISA inhibition test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>).</p>
      <p>In conclusion, it is important to carefully examine, treat, and follow patients with occupational allergic rhinitis, and remove them early enough from allergen exposure, in order to prevent the disease progressing to asthma.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Losada</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hinojosa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quirce</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>S&#xE1;nchez-Cano</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moneo</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occupational asthma caused by alpha-amylase inhalation: clinical and immunologic findings and bronchial response patterns</article-title>
          <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>118</fpage>
          <lpage>125</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1730831</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zentner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeep</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wahl</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kunkel</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kiethe-Tebbe</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiple IgE-mediated sensitizations to enzymes after occupational exposure: evaluation by skin pricks test, RAST, and immunoblot</article-title>
          <source>Allergy</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>928</fpage>
          <lpage>934</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9298178</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brisman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belin</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical and immunological responses to occupational exposure to alpha-amylase in the baking industry</article-title>
          <source>Br J Ind Med</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>604</fpage>
          <lpage>608</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1832939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Piirila</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Estlander</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hytonen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keskinen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tupasela</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuppurainen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rhinitis caused by ninhydrin develops into occupational asthma</article-title>
          <source>Eur Respir J</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>1918</fpage>
          <lpage>1921</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9272939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suh</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nahm</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alpha amylase is a major allergenic component in occupational asthma patients caused by porcine pancreatic extract</article-title>
          <source>J Asthma</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>511</fpage>
          <lpage>516</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12375710</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pepys</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Longbottom</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hargreave</surname>
              <given-names>FE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Faux</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Allergic reactions of the lungs to enzymes of Bacillus subtilis</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1969</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>1181</fpage>
          <lpage>1184</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4181839</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flindt</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary disease due to inhalation of derivatives of Bacillus subtilis containing proteolytic enzyme</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1969</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>1177</fpage>
          <lpage>1181</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4181838</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Laraqui</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harourate</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belamallem</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benhaymoud</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verger</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occupational respiratory risks in workers exposed to enzymes in detergents</article-title>
          <source>Rev Mal Respir</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>485</fpage>
          <lpage>492</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8999475</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zock</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cavalle</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kromhout</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kennedy</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sunyer</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muniozguren</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Payo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almar</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anto</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kogevinas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of specific occupational asthma risks in a community-based study with special reference to single and multiple exposures</article-title>
          <source>J Expo Anal Environ Epidemiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>397</fpage>
          <lpage>403</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15361899</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dolan</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyers</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bronchial asthma and allergic rhinitis associated with inhalation of pancreatic extracts</article-title>
          <source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>812</fpage>
          <lpage>813</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4429276</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cartier</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malo</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pineau</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolovich</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occupational asthma due to pepsin</article-title>
          <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>574</fpage>
          <lpage>577</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6425388</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aiken</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peel</surname>
              <given-names>ET</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hendrick</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occupational asthma due to porcine pancreatic amylase</article-title>
          <source>Occup Environ Med</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>762</fpage>
          <lpage>764</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9404326</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nahm</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>New occupational allergen in a pharmaceutical industry: serratial peptidase and lysozyme chloride</article-title>
          <source>Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>225</fpage>
          <lpage>229</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9048533</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bahn</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sensitization to Empynase&#xAE; (pronase B) in exposed hospital personnel and identification of the Empynase&#xAE; allergen</article-title>
          <source>Clin Exp Allergy</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>352</fpage>
          <lpage>358</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16499647</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Petrick</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salvin</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occupational rhinitis</article-title>
          <source>Immunol Allergy Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          <lpage>203</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12803358</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>This study was supported by the Korea Health 21 R&amp;D Project, <funding-source>Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare</funding-source>, Republic of Korea (<award-id>A050571</award-id>).</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Clinical features of the patient</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-23-347-i001"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>SPT, skin prick test; A/H, the ratio of the size of the wheal caused by the allergen and histamine (1 mg/mL); PPE-BPT, bronchial provocation test to porcine pancreatic extract.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
