<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728526</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2693836</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2007.22.4.762</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Syringocystadenocarcinoma Papilliferum: A Case Report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>So Hyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Young Min</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Dong Hoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Jong Soo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Ki Hong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Dermatology, College of Medicine, Yeungnam University, Daegu, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Address for correspondence: Dong Hoon Shin, M.D. Department of Dermatology, College of Medicine, Yeungnam University, 317-1 Daemyung-dong, Nam-gu, Daegu 705-717, Korea. Tel: +82.53-620-3160, Fax: +82.53-622-2216, <email>dhshin@med.yu.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>22</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>762</fpage>
      <lpage>765</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2007 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Syringocystadenocarcinoma papilliferum (SCACP) is a rare form of adenocarcinoma of the skin. This is the malignant counterpart of syringocystadenoma papilliferum (SCAP) and usually develops on the scalp in a long-standing lesion identified clinically as SCAP. We describe a 65-yr-old Korean man with a nodule on the right supra-pubic area with a 2-yr duration. Histologically this tumor had a similar overall configuration as in SCAP, but the tumor was asymmetric and poorly circumscribed, extending into the deep dermis and showed cytologic atypia. The tumor cells showed positive reaction to GCDFP-15, but negative reaction to CEA and HMFG-1. We established the diagnosis of SCACP in the patient, and a wide excision was performed to remove the tumor. The patient has been well without relapse or metastasis for 2 yr.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Sweat Gland Neoplasm</kwd>
        <kwd>Apocrine Gland</kwd>
        <kwd>Carcinoma</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Syringocystadenocarcinoma papilliferum (SCACP) is listed in the WHO classification of skin tumor as the malignant form of syringocystadenoma papilliferum (SCAP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). Most lesions seem to have arisen from long-standing SCAP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Histopathologically, SCACP has many structural similarities with SCAP, but it can be differentiated from SCAP in that it has an asymmetric and poorly circumscribed structure of tumor, often extending deep into the subcutaneous fat, and atypical cells, many of which are in mitosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>).</p>
      <p>To our knowledge, no case of SCACP have been reported in the Korean medical literature. Herein we report a case of SCACP occurring on the right supra-pubic area of a 65-yr-old Korean male patient.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 65-yr-old Korean man presented with a single nodule on the right supra-pubic area. He had had the lesion for 2 yr. The patient stated that the lesion began as a bean-sized papule and had increased gradually in size with time. It also become painful and hemorrhagic. He had suffered from limitation of motion of both legs because of osteomyelitis. His personal medical history included hypertension with regular medication. Physical examination revealed a single, 3.4&#xD7;3.5 cm, erythematous, dome-shaped, and firm tumor surrounded by bloody crust on the right supra-pubic area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Regional lymph nodes were not palpable, and the physical examination did not reveal any remarkable findings except for the mass.</p>
      <p>Histopathologic examination revealed a tumor with a solid and cystic pattern in the upper dermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) and a tumor of numerous irregular shaped structures in the deep dermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Cystic invagination that connected to the skin surface through infundibular structures was extending to the dermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). The lower portion of cystic invagination was composed of multiple layered epithelium with decapitation on the luminal surface of the cells. There was a dense infiltration of numerous plasma cells and lymphocytes in the stroma of tumor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Variable degrees of nuclear atypia with large and hyperchromatic nuclei and mitotic figures were observed in these tumor cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). Based on these histopathological findings, the diagnosis of SCACP was made. Immunohistochemically the tumor cells showed positive reaction to gross cystic disease fluid protein (GCDFP)-15, but negative reaction to carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) or human milk fat globules (HMFG)-1.</p>
      <p>Laboratory tests including complete blood count and urinalysis were within normal limits or negative. Liver function tests and hepatitis B serologic tests revealed chronic hepatitis B. Tumor markers (CEA, &#x3B1;-fetoprotein, prostate specific antigen, and CA19-9), chest radiography, hepatobiliary sonography and gastrocolonoscopy did not show any internal malignancy or metastasis. A computed tomography (CT) of abdomen and pelvis could not be checked because of the patient's lower leg deformity.</p>
      <p>Wide excisional surgery was performed to remove the tumor. There has not been any signs of recurrence or metastasis for 2 yr after the opertaion.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>SCACP is one of the sweat gland carcinomas and is regarded as the malignant counterpart of SCAP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). Although SCAP is frequently encountered clinically, SCACP is rarely observed and its clinical and histologic characteristics are not well known. Only eight cases of SCACP have been reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The male (n=4)-to-female (n=4) ratio was 1:1. The patients' age ranged from 47 to 74 yr, having SCACP in their scalp. Clinically, the lesion shows skin-colored or yellowish papules or nodules that remain unchanged for many years but then begin to enlarge suddenly with bleeding or ulceration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Usually the lesion is covered with crusts as a consequence of secretion of apocrine epithelial cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Its size varies from 2.5 to 13 cm. The duration of disease progression from the lesion to SCACP has been more than scores of years, but in cases of Arai et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>) and our case rapid development for two years was observed. Only surgical excision was performed in all reported cases.</p>
      <p>Histopathologically, as in SCAP, tumor shows deep epidermal cystic invaginations containing numerous papillae. Neoplastic cells lining the cystic cavities are connected to the skin surface through funnel-shaped structures lined by infundibular epithelium. The upper part of invaginations is made up of keratinizing squamous epithelium, whereas the lower part and papillae are composed of two- or multi-layered epithelium. Cells of the inner layer have columnar with oval nuclei and abundant eosinophilic cytoplasm and decapitation on the luminal surface, while the cells of the outer layer are small, cuboidal of flattened and have scanty cytoplasm and oval nuclei. Stroma of the tumor contains a dense inflammatory infiltrate, composed of numerous plasma cells and lymphoid cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Occasionally, numerous normal apocrine glands can be found. However, SCACP can be different from SCAP in that it has an asymmetric structure of tumor and the boundary is not clear; often tumor cells infiltrate the deep dermis or subcutaneous fat in tubular, cystic or solid types; neoplastic cells exhibit crowed nuclei, variable degrees of nuclear atypia, and numerous mitotic figures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). From the above figdings, SCACP can be considered malignant. Our case could be diagnosed as SCACP since it was shown that tumor cells were infiltrating into the deep dermis and atypical cells were observed along with the characteristics of SCAP.</p>
      <p>Uncommonly, SCAP had a tubular dermal component or tubular apocrine adenoma. However, in contrast with the dermal component of SCACP, dermal tumor cells in our case were arranged with varying sizes and shapes such as strand, cord, or angular shapes. Also, dermal component was horizontally oriented as was the case for most malignant neoplasms.</p>
      <p>In three previous cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), since the basement membrane of these papillations was intact and there was no involvement of the dermis, the specimens were diagnosed as SCACP in situ.</p>
      <p>Cuataneous metastases from breast or gastrointestinal cancers should be differentiated from SCACP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). They lack papillary structures containing deep invaginations as seen in SCACP. Metastatic thyroid carcinoma and hidradenoma papilliferum should also be included in the differential diagnosis due to their papillary structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>).</p>
      <p>Immunohistochemical and histochemical features of SCACP have been reported in 3 cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). Positive reactions to diastase-resistance periodic acid-Schiff (PAS) and cytokeratin were observed in all 3 cases and immunoreactivities to CEA showed positive reactions in 2 cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). Ishida et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) reported negativity to GCDFP-15 and CEA, and loss of immunoreactivities to CEA and GCDFP-15 in SCACP might be associated with its malignant de-differentiation in comparision with SCAP; however, Arai et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>) observed immunoreactivities to CEA and GCDFP-15 and stated that the loss of immunoreactivities to CEA and GCDFP-15 were not associated with the malignant de-differentiation. GCDFP-15 may be positive in both apocrine and eccrine units (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). HMFG-1 is positive in normal apocrine gland and tumors with apocrine differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Therefore, HMFG-1 is thought to be a marker for apocrine differentiation in skin neoplasms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Positivity for GCDFP-15 and negativity for CEA and HMFG-1 were observed in our case.</p>
      <p>The histogenesis of SCAP and SCACP is controversial. However, the differentiaton of apocrine glands is recently supported by following findings: decapitation is shown on the luminal surface of inner layer cells; the tumor is connected to folliculosebaceous structures; and there is apocrine glands in the underlying tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). In our case, decapitation and cystic invagination from the infundibular structure support the hypothesis that SCACP originates from apocrine glands.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Numata</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosoe</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Itoh</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Munakata</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayashi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maruyama</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Syringoadenocarcinoma papilliferum</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Pathol</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2982933</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Requena</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kiryu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ackerman</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Ackerman's Histologic Diagnosis of Neoplastic Skin Disease: A Method by Pattern Analysis. Neoplasms with Apocrine Differentiation</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lippincott-Raven</publisher-name>
          <fpage>665</fpage>
          <lpage>675</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dissanayake</surname>
              <given-names>RV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salm</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sweat-gland carcinomas. Prognosis related to histological type</article-title>
          <source>Histopathology</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>445</fpage>
          <lpage>466</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6253380</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seco Navedo</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fresno Forcelledo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orduna Domingo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Junco Petrement</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soler Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Syringocystadenoma papilliferum with malignant evolution: presentation of a case</article-title>
          <source>Ann Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>685</fpage>
          <lpage>689</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7187194</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bonadi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Urso</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Syringocystadenocarcinoma papilliferum</article-title>
          <source>Histopathology</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>475</fpage>
          <lpage>477</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8735727</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ishida-Yamamoto</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wada</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lizuka</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Syringocystadenocarcinoma papilliferum: case report and immunohistochemical comparison with its benign counterpart</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>755</fpage>
          <lpage>759</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606929</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kusakabe</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kiyokane</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of syringocystadenocarcinoma papilliferum in situ occurring partially in syringocystadenoma papilliferum</article-title>
          <source>J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>146</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12692383</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chi</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsai</surname>
              <given-names>RY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Syringocystadenocarcinoma papilleferum: successfully treated with Mohs micrographic surgery</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>468</fpage>
          <lpage>471</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15008887</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jeong</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choe</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The utility of HMFG-1 and GCDFP-15 to discriminate the differentiation of eccrine and apocrine neoplasms</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>1583</fpage>
          <lpage>1591</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ohnishi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immunohistochemical analysis of human milk fat globulin expression in extramammary Paget's disease</article-title>
          <source>Clin Exp Dermatol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298114</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A single 3.4&#xD7;3.5 cm-sized erythematous dome-shaped nodule covered with bloody crust on the right suprapubic area.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-22-762-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A low-power view of the lesion shows a tumor with a solid and cystic pattern in the upper dermis and diffusely infiltrating the lower dermis (H&amp;E, &#xD7;1).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-22-762-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tumor cells of strand or cord structures in the deep reticular dermis with desmoplastic stroma (H&amp;E, &#xD7;40).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-22-762-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cystic invagination connected to the infundibular portion extends downward (H&amp;E, &#xD7;40). (<bold>B</bold>) Inferior portion of cystic invagination lined by multiple layered epithelium with decapitation on the luminal surface of the cells, numerous plasma cells and lymphocytes in the stroma (H&amp;E, &#xD7;100).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-22-762-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Tumor cells having large and hyperchromatic nuclei (H&amp;E, &#xD7;200). (<bold>B</bold>) Hyperchromatic nuclei and mitotic figures were observed in these tumor cells (H&amp;E, &#xD7;200).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-22-762-g005"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Cases of syringocystdenocarcinoma papilliferum in the literature</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-22-762-i001"/>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
