<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1097-6647</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1532-429X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19671181</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2734562</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1532-429X-11-28</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1532-429X-11-28</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cardiovascular magnetic resonance of quinticuspid aortic valve with aortic regurgitation and dilated ascending aorta</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meng</surname>
            <given-names>Yanfeng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>meng.yanfeng@yahoo.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A2" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Lijun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>lijunzhang016@yahoo.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A3" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Zhaoqi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>zhaoqi5000@vip.sohu.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Yongmei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>wangyongmei523283@yahoo.com.cn</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaoming</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>xmyang@u.washington.edu</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Radiology, Beijing Anzhen Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing 100029, PR China </aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Image-Guided Bio-Molecular Interventions Research, Radiology, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98109, USA</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>28</fpage>
      <lpage>28</lpage>
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcmr-online.com/content/11/1/28"/>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2009 Meng et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Meng et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p>
          <!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Meng
               Yanfeng
               
               
               meng.yanfeng@yahoo.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Cardiovascular magnetic resonance of quinticuspid aortic valve with aortic regurgitation and dilated ascending aorta
         </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance 11(1): 28-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1532-429X(2009)11:1&#x0003c;28&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1532-429X</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>-->
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We report a rare case of a quinticuspid aortic valve associated with regurgitation and dilation of the ascending aorta, which was diagnosed and post-surgically followed up by cardiovascular magnetic resonance and dual source computed tomography.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Aortic valve malformation is a common congenital cardiac anomaly in the adult population. Dysfunction of the malformed aortic valve has been shown to cause significant morbidity and mortality. Among the malformations, bicuspid is the most common form, which has been identified in 1&#x2013;2% of population with male predominance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. To our knowledge, an aortic valve containing 5 leaflets (quinticuspid) is very rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Here we report a case of quinticuspid aortic valve associated with aortic regurgitation and dilation of the ascending aorta.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 24-year-old Chinese man presented with worsening symptoms of palpitation, chest discomfort and shortness of breath over a two-year period. There was no prior history of rheumatic fever or endocarditis. On physical examination, his pulse was 68 per minute with a blood pressure of 145/41 mmHg. Subsequently, the patient underwent a series of imaging studies including echocardiography, chest X-ray, dual source x-ray computed tomography (CT) and cardiovascular magnetic resonance (CMR) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), which showed a quinticuspid aortic valve. The CT scan demonstrated an aortic valve with 5 valve cusps and slightly thickened leaflet edges. In the systolic phase, the valve orifice measures 6.3 cm<sup>2 </sup>in area and opened like a pentagon, while in the diastolic phase, the valve orifice measured 1.2 cm<sup>2 </sup>in area and closed like pentagram (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1a, b, d, e</xref>). Five sinuses of valsalva were identified with variable sizes, of which the posterior sinus was notably smaller than all other sinuses. CMR SSFP for the cine sequence demonstrated incomplete closure of the five aortic valve cusps, in which a small orifice was found in diastolic phase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1d</xref>, Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). In addition, aortic regurgitation was noted as blood back-flow was demonstrated from aorta to left ventricle at diastolic phase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1f</xref>). Phase contrast images demonstrated the peak flow velocity of regurgitation at 480 cm/s. Furthermore, the patient was found to have an enlarged left ventricle chamber (484 ml for the end diastolic volume with a normal range of 77&#x2013;195 ml, and 270 ml for the end systolic volume with a normal range of 19&#x2013;72 ml), and a dilated ascending aorta (49 mm in diameter; normal range: &lt; 40 mm) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1c, f</xref>).</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>CT and CMR of quinticuspid aortic valve pre- and post-operative examination</bold>. (a) Dual source CT revealed malformed aortic valve in diastolic phase. (b) Dual-source CT showed malformed aortic valve in systolic phase. (c) Dilated ascending aorta. (d) CMR revealed malformed aortic valve in diastolic phase. (e) CMR showed malformed aortic valve in systolic phase. (f) Regurgitation in diastolic phase revealed as signal void (arrow). (g) Dual source CT showed mechanical valve in systolic phase. (h) Dual source CT showed mechanical valve in diastolic phase. (i) There is no regurgitation in diastolic phase.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1532-429X-11-28-1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Given the aggravating symptoms of aortic insufficiency and imaging finding of aortic valve anomaly, the patient proceeded to receive an aortic valve replacement with a concurrent Robicsek procedure, a surgery of reinforced aortoplasty. The aortic root was transected and the malformed aortic valve was replaced with an ON-X25 mechanical valve (ON-X technologies, Inc., Austin, Texas, USA). A 32 mm artificial vessel was used to enwrap the aortic root with Robicsek procedure. Postoperative CT and CMR scans were performed and showed functional artificial aortic valve with no regurgitations detected (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1g&#x2013;i</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In congenital aortic anomalies, the number of aortic leaflets can deviate from the normal three leaflets. Bicuspid is the most common form. Uni- and quadricuspids are seen much less frequently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. To our knowledge, this is the first reported case of quinticuspid aortic valve accompanied with detailed imaging studies.</p>
      <p>The cause of this type of aortic valve anomaly is unknown. During embryologic development, the aortic valve normally develops into three commissures and three leaflets. If this process fails, the valve may be less than three cusps. If more than three commissures develop, it would cause a valve with four or more cusps. Valves with abnormal numbers may open improperly to cause stenosis, or may close incompletely resulting in regurgitation. Patients with these abnormalities may expect to develop hemodynamically significant complications at some point in their lifetime. In our case, the patient developed left ventricular chamber dilation and ascending aorta dilation at a relatively young age of 24 years.</p>
      <p>CT and CMR have been demonstrated to be effective imaging methods for accurate diagnosis of aortic valve malformation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. In this case, accurate preoperative diagnosis of aortic valve abnormality was made easier with dual source CT and CMR. CT yielded images with higher spatial and temporal resolution than CMR. We were able to demonstrate detailed anatomy of the quinticuspid aortic valve and size of each sinus of valsalva. However, CMR yielded hemodynamic data in addition, including a detailed assessment of aortic regurgitation with signal changes from the abnormal blood flow. Both CT and MR are useful in postoperative follow-up of the morphology and function of the artificial valve. Although echocardiography is both sensitive and specific in detecting bicuspid aortic valves, it proved to be less useful in this case due to poor echocardiographic windows, and did not identify the 5 closely related leaflets.</p>
      <p>In general, patients with known aortic valve anomaly are closely followed up to monitor the symptoms and signs relating to aortic stenosis or insufficiency. The goal is to prevent permanent damage to the left ventricle, or excessive dilation of the ascending aorta leading to aortic dissection and aneurysm. Same cases may necessitate surgical intervention, which commonly include aortic valve replacement with procedures to manage dilated ascending aorta. Given the fact that the currently available valve substitutes are not ideal for young patients, some choose valve repair instead. Tricuspidization is suitable for bicuspid and quadricuspid valves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], and bicuspidization, for unicuspid aortic valves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Our patient was successfully managed with aortic valve replacement with a Robicsek procedure for aortic root narrowing.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In summary, we have illustrated an unusual case of quinticuspid aortic valve in a young adult presented with aortic regurgitation, left ventricular enlargement, and dilation of the ascending aorta. This case also demonstrates the value of CT and CMR in the diagnosis of this condition.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contributions</title>
      <p>YM was responsible for the analysis and interpretation of the images, drafting of the manuscript. LZ was responsible for the generation of images, analysis and reconstruction of images. ZZ was responsible for the revision of the manuscript. YW was responsible for acquirement of images and provision of clinical information. XY was responsible for the revision and editing of the manuscript</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' information</title>
      <p>YM, MD, Fellow of Radiology. LZ, MD, Resident of Radiology. ZZ, MD, Professor and Chairman of Radiology. YW, MD, Associated professor of Radiology. XY, MD, PhD, Professor and Director of Image-Guided Bio-Molecular Interventions Research, Radiology</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 1</title>
          <p><bold>CMR cine of aortic valve movement</bold>. the CMR movie showed the movement of the quinticuspid aortic valve in a cardiac cycle.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1532-429X-11-28-S1.avi" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="x-msvideo">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <sec>
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <p>Authors want to thank Hongxiu Ji, MD, PhD for her editorial assistance.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cannata</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lanfranconi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vitali</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garatti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonacina</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Is aortic wall degeneration related to bicuspid aortic valve anatomy in patients with valvular disease?</article-title>
          <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <fpage>937</fpage>
          <lpage>942</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18954633</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcvs.2007.11.072</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bogers</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aytug</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hendriks</surname>
              <given-names>FF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huysmans</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Quinticuspid aortic valve causing aortic valve incompetence and stenosis</article-title>
          <source>Thorax</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>542</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7135297</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thx.37.7.542</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bansal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arora</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Traub</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haybron</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Univuspid aorta valve and aortic arch aneurysm in a patient with Turner syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Asian Cardiovasc Thorac Ann</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>266</fpage>
          <lpage>267</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18515684</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hor</surname>
              <given-names>KN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Border</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cripe</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benson</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hinton</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The presence of bicuspid aortic valve does not predict ventricular septal defect type</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>146A</volume>
          <fpage>3202</fpage>
          <lpage>3205</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19012349</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajmg.a.32609</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yildirim</surname>
              <given-names>SV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xFC;m&#xFC;&#x15F;</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Co&#x15F;kun</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>T&#xFC;rk&#xF6;z</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Quadricuspid aortic valve: a rare cause of aortic regurgitation and stenosis</article-title>
          <source>Turk J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>500</fpage>
          <lpage>502</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19102060</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Feldman</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khandheria</surname>
              <given-names>BK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warnes</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seward</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tajik</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Incidence, description and functional assessment of isolated quadricuspid aortic valves</article-title>
          <source>Am J Cardiol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>937</fpage>
          <lpage>938</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2181849</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9149(90)91446-D</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Debl</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Djavidani</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buchner</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poschenrieder</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heinicke</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmid</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobuch</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feuerbach</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riegger</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luchner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unicuspid aortic valve disease: a magnetic resonance imaging study</article-title>
          <source>Rofo</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>180</volume>
          <fpage>983</fpage>
          <lpage>987</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18814102</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ucar</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vural</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cicekcioglu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasaoglu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aydogdu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koparal</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case report: Multidetector CT presentation of a parachute-like asymmetric mitral valve</article-title>
          <source>Br J Radiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>e266</fpage>
          <lpage>e268</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18941039</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1259/bjr/20218809</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gleeson</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mwangi</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horgan</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cradock</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Steady-state free-precession (SSFP) cine MRI in distinguishing normal and bicuspid aortic valves</article-title>
          <source>J Magn Reson Imaging</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>873</fpage>
          <lpage>878</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18821622</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmri.21547</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kawazoe</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Izumoto</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuboi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koizumi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tricuspidization of incompetent bicuspid aortic valve</article-title>
          <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>126</volume>
          <fpage>908</fpage>
          <lpage>910</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14502193</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5223(03)00391-X</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McMullan</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oppido</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davies</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawahira</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cochrane</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>d'Udekem d'Acoz</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Penny</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brizard</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical strategy for the bicuspid aortic valve: tricuspidization with cusp extension versus pulmonary autograft</article-title>
          <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>134</volume>
          <fpage>90</fpage>
          <lpage>98</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17599491</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcvs.2007.01.054</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>KI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeserich</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aicher</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sch&#xE4;fers</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tricuspidization of the quadricuspid aortic valve</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>1087</fpage>
          <lpage>1089</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18291208</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2007.09.016</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sch&#xE4;fers</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aicher</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riodionycheva</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindinger</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xE4;dle-Hurst</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langer</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdul-Khaliq</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bicuspidization of the unicuspid aortic valve: a new reconstructive approach</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>2012</fpage>
          <lpage>2018</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18498811</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2008.02.081</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
