<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Saudi Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ASM</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Annals of Saudi Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0256-4947</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0975-4466</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19448375</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2813643</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ASM-29-240</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0256-4947.51776</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letters</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Extended-spectrum &#x3B2;-lactamase <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> meningitis treated with tigecycline</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wadi</surname>
            <given-names>Jamal Ahmad</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Selawi</surname>
            <given-names>Fadi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">b</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>a</label>From the Jordan Hospital &amp; Medical Center, Amman, Jordan</aff>
      <aff id="AF0002"><label>b</label>From The Specialty Hospital, Amman, Jordan</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Correspondence: Jamal Ahmad Wadi MD Third Floor, Office 11, Jordan Hospital &amp; Medical Center, Queen Noor Street P.O. Box 143589 Amman, Jordan 11814 T: +962 6 568 6551 F: +962 6 568 6551 <email xlink:href="jamalwadimd@yahoo.com">jamalwadimd@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>29</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>240</fpage>
      <lpage>241</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Annals of Saudi Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><bold>To the Editor:</bold> Multidrug-resistant bacteria are increasing in prevalence, causing sporadic outbreaks of difficult-to-treat infections. <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> is a gram-negative pathogen that is known to cause both community and nosocomial infections. Infections caused by <italic>Klebsiella</italic> that express extended-spectrum &#x3B2;-lactamases (ESBLs) pose a serious challenge to clinicians as they are resistant to a broad range of &#x3B2;-lactams, including third-generation cephalosporins, thus complicating therapy and limiting treatment options. Furthermore, patients infected with these strains may have higher mortality rates and may require a longer hospital stay. Patients are generally sicker and have received more antibiotics than patients who are not infected with ESBL-producing strains.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref></p>
    <p>We treated a case of ESBL-positive <italic>Klebsiella meningitis</italic> induced by gunshot trauma, with difficult to remove shrapnel. The patient improved with 2 weeks of tigecycline treatment. Earlier we reported a case of multidrug resistant <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> nosocomial meningitis treated successfully with tigecycline.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT3">3</xref></p>
    <p>A 32-year-old male patient not known to have any chronic illnesses, admitted on 31 August 2008 with a history of a gunshot injury to his lumbar area with opened and shredded meninges. The large bowel was also injured; he underwent laparotomy and bowel resection with primary anastomosis with successful outcome. Many pieces of shrapnel could not be surgically removed and were left in the meninges and spinal canal. He presented with fever and leaking infected cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) from an open lumbar wound, and was taking several different antimicrobial agents (ceftriaxone, metronidazole and ciprofloxacin for a week) without good response. He suffered from bilateral lower limb paraplegia and sensory loss below the umbilical level. Several debridement surgeries and meningeal repairs were attempted, but he continued to suffer from an infected CSF leak. Surface swabs grew ESBL-positive <italic>Klebsiella pneumonia</italic> and <italic>Enterococcus fecalis.</italic> Serial CSF sampling from the upper thoracic spine showed repeated growth of <italic>K pneumoniae</italic> with a similar antibiogram, i.e., sensitive to imipenem, ertapenem, levofloxacin, and ciprofloxacin (tigecycline sensitivity was not available either by disk diffusion or Vitek in the specialty hospital laboratory) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>). Blood cultures taken twice one week apart showed no growth. The patient was initially started on ceftriaxone, ciprofloxacine, teichoplanin, and pipracillin/tazobactam at different intervals during his admission, and then on imipenem plus teichoplanin, but the latter was discontinued as soon as ESBL-<italic>Klebsiella</italic> was identified from CSF. The patient had seizures that were not controlled. Six days later imipenem was discontinued and tigecycline 100 mg loading dose and 50 mg every 12 hours was prescribed for a total duration of 14 days. A week later, parenteral ciprofloxacin was added for 3 days for systemic sepsis. In the meantime he was receiving tigecycline. Two days later, the CSF culture was sterile. The patient was continued on tigecycline and showed remarkable clinical improvement. A CSF culture follow up showed progressive improvement (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>). He was discharged home afebrile and in relatively good condition. He was well for 2 weeks and then was readmitted with chest pain and shortness of breath, and diagnosed with pulmonary embolism to which he succumbed in 3 days.</p>
    <table-wrap id="T0001" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Results of cerebrospinal fluid sampling.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 Aug</th>
            <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 Sep</th>
            <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 Sep</th>
            <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 Sep</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose (mg/dL)</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein (mg/dL)</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White blood cells (per mm<sup>3</sup>)</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5200</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">550</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Differential</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P95%, L5%</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P33%, L63%</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P77%, L23%</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Red blood cells (per mm<sup>3</sup>)</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1152</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culture</td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESBL-producing <italic>Klebsiella</italic></td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESBL-producing <italic>Klebsiella</italic></td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESBL-producing <italic>Klebsiella</italic></td>
            <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No growth</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>Shading represents dates when patient received tigecycline, which was continued for 2 additional weeks. ESBL: extended-spectrum &#x3B2;-lactamase. P: polymorphonuclear leukocytes, L: lymphocytes.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
    <p>Tigecycline is relatively a novel glycylcycline molecule that escapes the classic resistance mechanisms that bacteria harbor against tetracyclines, i.e. drug efflux pumps and protection of ribosomes. Thus, it has expanded antimicrobial coverage and potent in vitro antibacterial activity against a wide range of clinically important gram-positive and gram-negative aerobic bacteria and anaerobes, including <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Enterococcus</italic> species, <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae, Moraxella catarrhalis, Neisseria gonorrhoeae,</italic> most Enterobacteriaceae, and <italic>Bacteroides fragilis,</italic> but it has limited or no activity against <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and reduced activity against <italic>Proteus mirabilis.</italic> Its licensed indications so far are skin and soft tissue infections and complicated intra-abdominal infections. Studies are currently ongoing for diabetic foot infection, community-acquired pneumonia and nosocomially acquired pneumionia (Wyeth communication). Thus far no controlled studies are available on treating CNS infections with tigecycline in humans.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT3">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT6">6</xref> This is our second case of multidrug-resistant gram-negative meningitis in which tigecycline was used with a successful outcome.</p>
    <p>Jamal Wadi serves as a consultant for Al Hikma Pharmaceuticals and receives an honorarium from Wyeth, Aventis, MSD, Al Hikma Pharmaceuticals and Abbot for lectures, meetings and consultations. He is also on an advisory board for Wyeth and Aventis.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>Jamal Wadi serves as a consultant for Al Hikma Pharmaceuticals and receives an honorarium from Wyeth, Aventis, MSD, Al Hikma Pharmaceuticals and Abbot for lectures, meetings and consultations. He is also on an advisory board for Wyeth and Aventis.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="CIT1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reuben</surname>
              <given-names>Ramphal</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paul G</surname>
              <given-names>Ambrose</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extended-spectrum &#xDF;-lactamases and clinical outcomes: current data</article-title>
          <source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>S164</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16544267</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gerardo</surname>
              <given-names>Mart&#xED;nez-Aguilar</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Outbreak of nosocomial sepsis and pneumonia in a newborn intensive care unit by multiresistant extended spectrum lactamase producing Klebsiella pneumoniae: High Impact on Mortality</article-title>
          <source>Infection Control and Hospital Epidemiology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <month>11</month>
          <fpage>725</fpage>
          <lpage>728</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11842997</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jamal Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>Wadi</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohammad Abu Al</surname>
              <given-names>Rub</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multidrug resistant Acinetobacter nosocomial meningitis treated successfully with parenteral tigecycline: case report</article-title>
          <source>Ann Saudi Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <season>Nov-Dec</season>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gary A</surname>
              <given-names>Noskin</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tigecycline: A new glycylcycline for treatment of serious infections</article-title>
          <source>Clinical Infecttious Diseases</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>S303</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Timothy</surname>
              <given-names>Babinchak</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The efficacy and safety of tigecycline for the treatment of complicated intra-abdominal infections: Analysis of Pooled Clinical Trial Data</article-title>
          <source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>S354</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16080073</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ellis-Grosse</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The efficacy and safety of tigecycline in the treatment of skin and skin-structure infections: results of 2 double-blind phase 3 comparison studies with vancomycin-aztreonam</article-title>
          <source>Clinical Infectious Diseases</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>S341</fpage>
          <lpage>53</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16080072</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
