<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Veterinary Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1229-845X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1976-555X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19255531</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2801107</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4142/jvs.2009.10.1.89</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A suspected case of Lyme borreliosis in a hunting dog in Korea</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Ul Soo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Hyun Wook</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>You</surname>
            <given-names>Sung Eun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Youn</surname>
            <given-names>Hee Jeong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Veterinary Clinical Pathology, College of Veterinary Medicine, Chonbuk National University, Jeonju 561-756, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Haemaru Referral Animal Hospital, Sung Nam 463-050, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>KRF Priority Zoonotic Disease Research Institute, College of Veterinary Medicine, Seoul National University, Seoul 151-742, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Corresponding author: Tel: +82-2-880-1267; Fax: +82-2-888-0659, <email>younhj@snu.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>89</fpage>
      <lpage>91</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2009 The Korean Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A two-year-old male Pointer had been presented with anorexia, cachexia, and weight loss of 10-day duration. Upon physical examination, fever, lethargy, superficial lymph node enlargement, and tick infestation were noted. The only abnormality in CBC and serum chemistry analyses was mild hyperglobulinemia. Spleen was enlarged by radiography, and the lymph nodes showed neutrophilic lymphadenitis by cytological examination. A polymerase chain reaction test for babesiosis and commercial ELISA tests for <italic>Ehrlichia canis</italic>, heartworm, and Lyme disease was negative except for Lyme disease, which was verified by both an IFA-IgG test and a quantitative C<sub>6</sub> assay. Doxycycline was administered for 2 weeks and the recovery was uneventful. Post-treatment C<sub>6</sub> titer decreased to within normal limits.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>dog</kwd>
        <kwd>fever</kwd>
        <kwd>hyperglobulinemia</kwd>
        <kwd>Lyme disease</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Lyme disease is a tick-borne disease caused by <italic>Borrelia</italic> (<italic>B.</italic>) <italic>burgdorferi</italic> sensu lato. It affects humans and dogs worldwide, and has been reported in North America, Europe, Asia, Australia, South America, and Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Vectors of <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic> sensu lato include various species of hard ticks of the <italic>Ixodes</italic> spp..</p>
    <p>In Korea, <italic>B. afzelii</italic>, <italic>B. garinii</italic>, and <italic>B. valaisiana</italic> have been identified in ticks and several clinical cases of Lyme disease in humans have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. However, there are no known occurrences in dogs. We report a possible case of Lyme borreliosis in a hunting dog evaluated by a commercial C<sub>6</sub> ELISA kit, IFA, and a laboratory quantitative C<sub>6</sub> assay.</p>
    <p>A 2-year-old male Pointer dog was presented to Haemaru Referral Animal Hospital with signs of anorexia, cachexia, and weight loss of a 10-day duration. The body condition score decreased from 3/5 to 1/5 at presentation. The dog was born and raised in Kwangju, Kyonggi-do. It had been used in hunting, and was exposed to ticks. The hunting area covered Bongwha and Youngju, Kyongsangnam-do. Upon physical examination, a mild fever (39.7&#x2103;), lethargy, and enlargement of both superficial cervical lymph nodes were noted. Initial screening tests include CBC, serum chemistry, cytology of fine needle aspirates of enlarged lymph nodes, and abdominal radiography. Blood works and serum chemistry results were all within normal limits, except for mild hyperglobulinemia (4.6 g/dl, reference range 2.5-4.5 g/dl) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The radiography showed that the spleen was enlarged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Smears of lymph node aspirates revealed a predominant population of small lymphocytes with a lesser number of medium to large lymphocytes, plasma cells, neutrophils, and macrophages, consistent with neutrophilic lymphadenitis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Based on this finding, increased serum globulin was considered to be associated with chronic inflammation, and lymphoproliferative neoplasia was ruled out. On the day of the first visit, infectious diseases were screened using a commercial ELISA kit (SNAP 3Dx; IDEXX, USA) for a heartworm (<italic>Ehrlichia canis</italic>) antigen, and a Lyme antibody (C<sub>6</sub> antibody). All the tests were negative except for Lyme disease. On the same day, EDTA whole blood was also submitted to the College of Veterinary Medicine, Chonbuk National University, for PCR testing for <italic>E. canis</italic> and <italic>Babesia</italic> (the results were negative for both). To confirm the positive results of the ELISA kit for Lyme disease, the rest of the patient's serum was submitted to an IDEXX Reference Laboratory (USA) for a C<sub>6</sub> titer assay and to Antech Diagnostics (USA) for a Lyme IgG assay. The C<sub>6</sub> serum titer was 30 U/ml (positive &#x2265; 30), and the IgG titer was 1 : 256 (negative &lt; 1 : 64). These results were highly suggestive of active borreliosis.</p>
    <p>Treatment with doxycycline (10 mg/kg s.i.d, PO; Myung In Pharm, Korea) and supportive drugs (vitamin C, thiamine, serratiopeptidase and famotidine) was administered for 2 weeks. The dog responded well to treatment and the clinical signs disappeared. 3 weeks after the initiation of treatment, the lymph nodes had returned to normal size and serum globulin levels had decreased to 2.7 g/dl. Post-treatment C<sub>6</sub> level was 10 U/ml.</p>
    <p>C<sub>6</sub> peptide is derived from the VlsE antigen, <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic> surface protein expressed when <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic> is transmitted to the dog but not expressed in the tick, in tissue culture, or in Lyme vaccines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The sensitivities and specificities of this peptide-based ELISA are reportedly equivalent or superior to those of western blot assays alone or a combination of whole-cell based ELISA and western blot analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The C<sub>6</sub> antibody titer has been found to decrease post-treatment because production of the antibody to the C<sub>6</sub> peptide may depend on the presence of a viable organism. For this reason, post treatment C<sub>6</sub> levels may be used as an indicator of therapy outcome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p>
    <p>The patient in this report was presumptively diagnosed with Lyme borreliosis based on an increased C<sub>6</sub> antibody titer. This diagnosis was confirmed by both a commercial Lyme antibody test kit and a laboratory quantitative C<sub>6</sub> assay (IDEXX Reference Laboratory, USA) along with an increased IgG titer by IFA. Normal lymph nodes, resolution of the anorexia and fever, and decreased C<sub>6</sub> antibody titer post treatment also supported our diagnosis. In a previous report, the median percent decline in C<sub>6</sub> level relative to pretreatment values at 6 and 12 months were found to be 68.0% and 83.3%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. However, in this case, a PCR test using peripheral blood was unsuccessful. The negative PCR test may be attributed to the fact that it was done using a peripheral blood sample. Connective tissue, synovia, or skin samples near the tick bite are preferred for PCR because <italic>Borrelia</italic> organisms rarely spread hematogenously. The organism can also be isolated from the skin area for an extended period. In this case, there was tick infestation when it came to the animal hospital, so if a skin sample from near the tick bite site was used for PCR, positive results would have been possible. A skin biopsy sample from as close as possible to the tick-bite should be submitted for a reliable PCR test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p>
    <p>To the best of our knowledge, canine Lyme borreliosis has never been reported in Korea. This disease might be underestimated in dogs because <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic> sensu lato has been isolated in ticks and wild rodents in Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Patients could also easily be overlooked due to good responses to therapy without a proper diagnosis. If a symptomatic dog has outdoor activity and a history of tick infestation, Lyme disease should be included in the differential diagnosis.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p>This work was supported by <funding-source>Korean Research Foundation</funding-source> grant (<award-id>KRF-005-E00078</award-id>).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chae</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu do</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shringi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klein</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chong</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>IY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foley</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Microbial pathogens in ticks, rodents and a shrew in northern Gyeonggi-do near the DMZ, Korea</article-title>
          <source>J Vet Sci</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>293</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18716449</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koh</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>KW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>First molecular detection of <italic>Borrelia afzelii</italic> in clinical samples in Korea</article-title>
          <source>Microbiol Immunol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>1201</fpage>
          <lpage>1207</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094538</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hartmann</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greene</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Ettinger</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feldman</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diseases caused by systemic bacterial infections</article-title>
          <source>Textbook of Veterinary Internal Medicine: Diseases of the Dog and Cat</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <edition>6th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>St. Louis</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
          <fpage>619</fpage>
          <lpage>625</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kook</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differentiation of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> sensu lato on the basis of RNA polymerase gene (rpoB) sequences</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>2557</fpage>
          <lpage>2562</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10878043</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O'Connor</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanscom</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Utility of an in-office C<sub>6</sub> ELISA test kit for determination of infection status of dogs naturally exposed to <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic></article-title>
          <source>Vet Ther</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>308</fpage>
          <lpage>315</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12447839</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levy</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O'Connor</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanscom</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lorentzen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dimarco</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Quantitative measurement of C<sub>6</sub> antibody following antibiotic treatment of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> antibody-positive nonclinical dogs</article-title>
          <source>Clin Vaccine Immunol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>119</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18003819</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>FT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobson</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Straubinger</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grooters</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Philipp</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of a <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> VlsE invariable region useful in canine Lyme disease serodiagnosis by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>4160</fpage>
          <lpage>4166</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11060084</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Littman</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldstein</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Labato</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lappin</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ACVIM small animal consensus statement on Lyme disease in dogs: diagnosis, treatment, and prevention</article-title>
          <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>422</fpage>
          <lpage>434</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16594606</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mogilyansky</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loa</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adelson</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mordechai</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tilton</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison of Western immunoblotting and the C<sub>6</sub> Lyme antibody test for laboratory detection of Lyme disease</article-title>
          <source>Clin Diagn Lab Immunol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>924</fpage>
          <lpage>929</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15358654</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O'Connor</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Esty</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanscom</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Philipp</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dogs vaccinated with common Lyme disease vaccines do not respond to IR6, the conserved immunodominant region of the VlsE surface protein of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic></article-title>
          <source>Clin Diagn Lab Immunol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>458</fpage>
          <lpage>462</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15138170</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwan</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification and characterization of Lyme disease spirochetes, <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> sensu lato, isolated in Korea</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>1831</fpage>
          <lpage>1837</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8349761</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Speck</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reiner</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Streich</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reusch</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wittenbrink</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Canine borreliosis: a laboratory diagnostic trial</article-title>
          <source>Vet Microbiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>132</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17101241</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Radiograph of the spleen. The abdomen was decreased by lack of fat. In the lateral view, soft tissue density structure (arrows) was identified in the ventral region of the middle abdomen, and this structure was considered to be splenomegaly based on the position and shape.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jvs-10-89-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Microphotograph of the enlarged superficial cervical lymph node. Note the mixed population of lymphocytes, neutrophils, and plasma cells with a predominance of small lymphocytes. Some of the cells were lysed in the background. Wright stain, &#xD7;400.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jvs-10-89-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>CBC and serum chemistry results</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jvs-10-89-i001"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>WBC: white blood cell, RBC: red blood cell, HGB: hemoglobin, HCT: hematocrit, MCV: mean corpuscular volume, MCHC: mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration, MCH: mean corpuscular hemoglobin, PLT: platelet, BUN: blood urea nitrogen, ALT: alanine transaminase, ALP: alkaline phosphatase.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
