<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yonsei Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Yonsei Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0513-5796</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1976-2437</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Yonsei University College of Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16385662</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2810600</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2005.46.6.843</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Case of Intolerance to Warfarin Dosing in an Intermediate Metabolizer of CYP2C9</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Soo-Youn</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>June Soo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jong-Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Reprint address: requests to Dr. Jong-Won Kim, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Samsung Medical Center, #50, Ilwon-dong, Kangnam-gu, Seoul 135-710, Korea. Tel: 82-2-3410-2705, Fax: 82-2-3410-2719, <email>jwonk@smc.samsung.co.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>46</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>843</fpage>
      <lpage>846</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2005 The Yonsei University College of Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We report a case of intolerance to warfarin dosing due to impaired drug metabolism in a patient heterozygous for the <italic>CYP2C9*3</italic> allele. A 30-year-old woman with an artificial cardiac pacemaker was taking warfarin to prevent thromboembolism. This patient had an extremely elevated international normalized ratio (INR) of prothrombin time (PT) following standard doses of warfarin and experienced difficulties during the induction of anticoagulation. Genotyping for <italic>CYP2C9</italic> revealed that this patient was an intermediate metabolizer with genotype <italic>CYP2C9*1/*3</italic>. This case suggests the clinical usefulness of pharmacogenetic testing for individualized dosage adjustments of warfarin.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Warfarin</kwd>
        <kwd>cytochrome P-450 CYP2C9</kwd>
        <kwd>polymorphism</kwd>
        <kwd>prothrombin time</kwd>
        <kwd>pharmacogenetics</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Warfarin, a widely used anticoagulant, may increase the risk of bleeding complications with narrow therapeutic index.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> The prolongation of the prothrombin time (PT) remains the primary way to measure the anticoagulant effect of warfarin. Because warfarin is subject to great variability between individuals in its pharmacokinetics with effective daily doses ranging from 0.5 mg to 60 mg,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> therapy should be individualized by monitoring patient's international normalized ratio (INR) of PT.</p>
      <p>Warfarin metabolism is catalyzed by CYP2C9, which metabolizes S-wafarin to inactive S-7-hydroxywarfarin.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> A genetic polymorphism of <italic>CYP2C9</italic> contributes to variability among patients for required maintenance doses of warfarin. Multiple studies have clearly demonstrated an increased frequency of <italic>CYP2C9</italic> allelic variants such as <italic>CYP2C9*2</italic> and <italic>CYP2C9*3</italic> in patients stabilized on low-dose warfarin therapy and have established relations between genetic deficiency in <italic>CYP2C9</italic> enzyme activity with increased likelihood of extremely elevated INRs and major bleeding events, compared with the general population.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></p>
      <p>In this report, we present a case of warfarin therapy in a patient with the variant <italic>CYP2C9*1/*3</italic>, which resulted in decreased activity of CYP2C9. Extremely prolonged PT during the induction phase of standard warfarin therapy was found and a reduction of warfarin dosage was required to get the target INR in this case.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 30-year-old woman with an artificial cardiac pacemaker presented to the clinic complaining of dizziness and dyspnea. The patient had a history of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy with complete atrioventricular block and the pacemaker had been implanted in her 13 years before presentation. Her prescription medication for the previous 2 years included lasix 20 mg, spironolactone 12.5 mg, imidapril 2.5 mg, and teprenone 50 mg twice a day.</p>
      <p>She had suffered from dizziness and dyspnea for the last 2 months and visited the outpatient clinic. Physical examination of this woman showed a blood pressure of 110/68 mmHg, a heart rate of 76 beats/min, and normal body temperature. Her body weight was 45.2 kg and she was 156 cm in height. Initial laboratory results were unremarkable with a normal PT of 13.5 sec (INR 1.03). Cardiomegaly was found on chest X-ray. Echocardiogram indicated atrial fibrillation. Echocardiogram also revealed decreased systolic function and hypertrophy of the left ventricle. The patient was started on 4 mg of warfarin daily to prevent thromboembolism.</p>
      <p>When she revisited the outpatient clinic after 1 week, her PT was found to be 88.2 sec (INR 6.36) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). On admission to the ward, 10 mg of Vitamin K was injected with warfarin withdrawal. After normalization of the patient's PT, 2 mg/day of warfarin was initially prescribed and the dose was then increased to 3 mg/day, which resulted in a PT of 36.3 - 47.0 sec (INR 2.69 - 3.45). Administration of warfarin doses was reduced even further (1 - 2 mg/day) to achieve the target therapeutic INR of 2.0 to 3.0 and she was discharged after 16 days of hospitalization. She continues to receive warfarin therapy at the outpatient clinic monthly and her PT remains stable, even though her warfarin dose has been reduced to 2 mg/day.</p>
      <p>This patient was genotyped for <italic>CYP2C9</italic>. DNA was isolated from peripheral blood and all 9 exons of <italic>CYP2C9</italic> gene were amplified by PCR.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref> The PCR products were sequenced using ABI PRISIM BigDye terminator Cycle sequencing kit (Perkin-Elmer, USA) and an ABI Prism 3100 Genetic Analyzer (Perkin-Elmer, USA). The patient was an intermediate metabolizer with the genotype of <italic>CYP2C9*1/*3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>CYP2C9, one of the major isoforms of the CYP2C subfamily, is involved in the metabolism of many clinically important therapeutic agents such as warfarin, phenytoin, sulfonylurea and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> Genetic polymorphisms of <italic>CYP2C9</italic> bring about significant variability among individuals in drug response.</p>
      <p>At the time of this report,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref> variant alleles of <italic>CYP2C9</italic> had been reported.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref> Previous studies have demonstrated that 2 common variants <italic>CYP2C9*2</italic> and <italic>CYP2C9*3</italic> are associated with reduced catalytic activity of CYP2C9.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> Therefore, subjects who are homo- or heterozygous for these variant alleles require reduced maintenance doses for CYP2C9 substrates including warfarin. The <italic>CYP2C9*3</italic> variant would have a greater impact than the <italic>CYP2C9*2</italic> variant on the dose requirements of warfarin.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> Intermediate metabolizers with heterozygous <italic>CYP2C9*2</italic> and <italic>CYP2C9*3</italic> would require on average 21% and 34% lower maintenance doses of warfarin, as compared with extensive metabolizers (<italic>CYP2C9*1/*1</italic>).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref> Poor metabolizers with 2 variant alleles (<italic>CYP2C9*2/*2</italic>, <italic>CYP2C9*2/*3</italic> and <italic>CYP2C9*3/*3</italic>) would require 60 - 90% lower doses of warfarin than extensive metabolizers.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></p>
      <p>Allele frequencies of <italic>CYP2C9</italic> variants have been shown to be markedly different among populations. Caucasians possess higher frequencies of <italic>CYP2C9*3</italic> than Asians (6-10% vs 2-5%).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> There have been no documented Asian carriers of the <italic>CYP2C9*2</italic> variant, while 8-20% of Caucasians appear to have the <italic>CYP2C9*2</italic> allele.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> Yoon et al reported that from a pool of 574 Koreans 2.3% were heterozygous for <italic>CYP2C9*3</italic> and none were found to be carriers of <italic>CYP2C9*2</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref> Interethnic difference in the prevalence of CYP2C9 variants causes an apparent need for an interethnic difference in the maintenance dose of warfarin.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref></p>
      <p>There are several Korean reports<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref> regarding warfarin dosing and its toxicity based on clinical assessment and PT monitoring. This case study is the first clinical report of a Korean patient with the <italic>CYP2C9*1/*3</italic> genotype as the major determinant of warfarin intolerance. She attained an extremely high INR at the standard doses and might be at a higher risk for developing severe complications. In this patient, we could not identify any specific pharmacokinetic or pharmacodynamic factors associated with warfarin response, such as drug interactions or disease conditions. Therefore, a pharmacogenetic test was performed to explore the possible genetic factors contributing to the unusual drug response. This patient could have taken appropriate therapeutic changes earlier and been maintained on a safer regimen with lower doses, if she had been genotyped at the beginning of warfarin therapy.</p>
      <p>The <italic>CYP2C9</italic> genotype is associated with a risk of over-anticoagulation and bleeding complications. Previous studies have suggested that the variant group, compared with patients with the wild-type genotype, required a higher rate of above-range INR, more time to therapeutic INR, larger maintenance doses, more time to stable warfarin dosing, longer hospitalization, and a higher risk of serious bleeding events.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></p>
      <p>At present, clinicians are used to adjusting the warfarin dose based on PT and clinical response. Additional <italic>CYP2C9</italic> genotyping can serve as an important guide for more rapid dosage adjustment and prediction of drug response in each individual. <italic>CYP2C9</italic> genotyping is recommended to complement PT monitoring especially when the unusual metabolic capacity of warfarin is suspected. Characterization of <italic>CYP2C9</italic> polymorphic alleles may identify patients at risk, so that warfarin can be given more cautiously, especially during the induction phase of anticoagulation.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>This study was supported by a grant of the Korea Health 21 R &amp; D Project, Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare, R. O. K (03-PJ10-PG13-GD01-0002)</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miners</surname>
              <given-names>JO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birkett</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cytochrome P450C9: an enzyme of major importance in human drug metabolism</article-title>
          <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>525</fpage>
          <lpage>538</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9663807</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Echizen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pharmacogenetics of CYP2C9 and interindividual variability in anticoagulant response to warfarin</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacogenomics J</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>202</fpage>
          <lpage>214</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12931134</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Echizen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pharmacogenetics of warfarin elimination and its clinical implications</article-title>
          <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>603</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11523725</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aithal</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Day</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kesteven</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daly</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Association of polymorphisms in the cytochrome P450 CYP2C9 with warfarin dose requirement and risk of bleeding complications</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>353</volume>
          <fpage>717</fpage>
          <lpage>719</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10073515</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kaminsky</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human P450 metabolism of warfarin</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacol Ther</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9014207</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Daly</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>BP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pharmacogenetics of oral anticoagulants</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacogenetics</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>247</fpage>
          <lpage>252</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724615</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Higahi</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veenstra</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kondo</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wittkowsky</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srinouanprachanh</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farin</surname>
              <given-names>FL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Association between CYP2C9 genetic variants and anticoagulation-related outcomes during warfarin therapy</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>287</volume>
          <fpage>1690</fpage>
          <lpage>1698</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11926893</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tabrizi</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zehnbauer</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borecki</surname>
              <given-names>IB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McGrath</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buchman</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freeman</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The frequency and effects of cytochrome P450 (CYP) 2C9 polymorphisms in patients receiving warfarin</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>194</volume>
          <fpage>267</fpage>
          <lpage>273</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11893129</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kashima</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nomizo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muramoto</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimizu</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nasu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metabolism of warfarin enantiomers in Japanese patients with heart disease having different CYP2C9 and CYP2C19 genotypes</article-title>
          <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>519</fpage>
          <lpage>528</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9630825</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scordo</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pengo</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spina</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dahl</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gusella</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Padrini</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Influence of CYP2C9 and CYP2C19 genetic polymorphisms on warfarin maintenance dose and metabolic clearance</article-title>
          <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>702</fpage>
          <lpage>710</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12496751</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldstein</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pieper</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cytochrome P450 2C9 polymorphisms: a comprehensive review of the in-vitro and human data</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacogenetics</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>251</fpage>
          <lpage>263</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11927841</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stubbins</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harries</surname>
              <given-names>LW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tarbit</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolf</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic analysis of the human cytochrome P450 CYP2C9 locus</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacogenetics</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>429</fpage>
          <lpage>439</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8946475</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhasker</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miners</surname>
              <given-names>JO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coulter</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birkett</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Allelic and functional variability of cytochrome P4502C9</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacogenetics</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9110362</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ingelman-Sunberg</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nebert</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daly</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Human cytochrome P450 (CYP) genes</source>
          <comment>Available from: URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.imm.ki.se/CYPalleles/cyp2c9.htm">http://www.imm.ki.se/CYPalleles/cyp2c9.htm</ext-link></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
              <given-names>YR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shon</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Frequency of cytochrome P450 2C9 mutant alleles in a Korean population</article-title>
          <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>280</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298075</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chi</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Warfarin-associated fetal intracranial hemorrhage: a Case Report</article-title>
          <source>J Korean Med Sci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>764</fpage>
          <lpage>767</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555837</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huh</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>DI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>BB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moon</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joh</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical and functional assessment after anticoagulant therapy of acute deep vein thrombosis involving the lower limb</article-title>
          <source>Yonsei Med J</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>686</fpage>
          <lpage>693</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12950126</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sohn</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Warfarin toxicity patients in the emergency department</article-title>
          <source>J Korean Soc Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>145</fpage>
          <lpage>149</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Time course of warfarin therapy and international normalization ratio of prothrombin time.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-843-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Detection of nucleotide changes by sequencing analysis of CYP2C9 gene in the individual heterozygous for the <italic>CYP2C9*3</italic> allele with A1075C (Ile359Leu) substitution.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-46-843-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
