<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cardiothorac Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of Cardiothoracic Surgery</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1749-8090</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19368736</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2672084</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1749-8090-4-16</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1749-8090-4-16</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Torsion of right middle lobe after a right upper lobectomy</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Chih-Hao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>musclenet2003@yahoo.com.tw</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hung</surname>
            <given-names>Tzu-Ti</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>tzdi0921731610@yahoo.com.tw</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Tung-Ying</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>wax921@yahoo.com.tw</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A4" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Hung-Chang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>cs520915@yahoo.com.tw</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Thoracic Surgery, Mackay Memorial Hospital, Taipei City, Taiwan</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Mackay Memorial Hospital, Taipei City, Taiwan</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <fpage>16</fpage>
      <lpage>16</lpage>
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cardiothoracicsurgery.org/content/4/1/16"/>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2009 Chen et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Chen et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p>
          <!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Chen
               Chih-Hao
               
               musclenet2003@yahoo.com.tw
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Torsion of right middle lobe after a right upper lobectomy
         </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Cardiothoracic Surgery 4(1): 16-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1749-8090(2009)4:1&#x0003c;16&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1749-8090</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>-->
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lobar torsion after lung resection is a quite rare complication. A 50-year-old woman presented typical features on chest radiographs and CT(computed tomography) scan of lobar torsion after a right upper lobectomy. After emergency lobectomy of right middle lobe, the patient recovered well and discharged 10 days after the second operation.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Resection of right upper lobe is a common procedure in patients with lung cancer. Infrequently, the fissure between the middle lobe and lower lobe is well developed so that torsion of the middle lobe might occur during or after an operation, especially when pneumopexy is not performed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 50-year-old woman presented 2-month cough and mild symptoms of hemoptysis. On routine chest radiograph of regular health examination, the patient was found to have a mass measuring around 3.5 cm in greatest diameterin right upper lung field (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Subsequent bronchoscopic brushing cytology confirmed the mass to be malignant. 7 days after admission, the patient underwent lobectomy and radical lymph node dissection through a standard right posterolateral thoracotomy. The chest radiograph on postoperative day 1 and 2 showed adequate lung expansion with no obvious abnormality. 5 days after operation, the patient presented fever and mild dyspnea. Follow-up chest radiograph showed a wedge-shaped opacity of large area in the middle lung field (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). Bedside bronchoscopy showed tight orifice of right middle lobe. CT scan showed collapse and hemorrhagic consolidation in right middle lobe (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Under the impression of torsion, the patient underwent explorative thoracotomy. Under direct visualization, the right middle lobe was found to have a 720-degree counterclockwise torsion along the pedicle axis. An emergency lobectomy was performed. The patient was discharged 10 days after operation.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A. mass measuring around 3.5 cm in greatest diameterin right upper lung field</bold>. B. Follow-up chest radiograph showed a wedge-shaped opacity of large area in the middle lung field.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1749-8090-4-16-1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>CT scan showed collapse and hemorrhagic consolidation in right middle lobe</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1749-8090-4-16-2"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Lobar torsion can occurred in traumatic, spontaneous and postoperative conditions. Its occurrence is quite rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Prompt diagnosis of the torsion is quite difficult and must be differentiated from sputum impaction and lobar pneumonia. Because of the other 2 conditions may response well to chest physical therapy and effective antibiotic therapy respectively. The physical findings, including fever, tachycardia, dyspnea and decreased breath sounds, are not specific to make a diagnosis. The key steps are radiographic and bronchoscopic. Typical radiographic findings include homogenous consolidation in plain film and absence of contrast enhancement in the affected lobe on CT scan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. A careful bronchoscopic examination may reveal abnormally tight and obstructed orifice of the affected lobe. Right middle lobe is by far the most common afftected lobe. Pneumopexy is a key procedure to prevent such complication.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Pneumopexy with the use of sutures to anchor the middle lobe to the lower lobe after a right upper lobectomy must be practiced in all cases to reduce the risk of lobar torsion, especially if the fissure is well developed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contributions</title>
      <p>CHC: the main author to write the article. TTH: collection of data and help us to revise the manuscript. TYC: help us for clinical pathological interpretation. HCL: final approval of the manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cable</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deschamps</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nichols</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trastek</surname>
              <given-names>VF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pairolero</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lobar torsion after pulmonary resection: presentation and outcome</article-title>
          <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>1091</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11726883</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mtc.2001.117839</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Felson</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lung torsion: radiographic findings in nine cases</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>162</volume>
          <fpage>631</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3809475</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
