<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Trop Med Hyg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0002-9637</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1476-1645</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348490</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2844546</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2010.09-0658</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Images in Clinical Tropical Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><italic>Angiostrongylus cantonensis</italic>: Lesions in Brain and Spinal Cord</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Diao</surname>
            <given-names>Zongli</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>Erhu</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yin</surname>
            <given-names>Chenghong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AFF1">Beijing Tropical Medicine Research Institute, and Department of Radiology, Beijing Friendship Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">*Address correspondence to Chenghong Yin, Beijing Tropical Medicine Research Institute, Beijing Friendship Hospital, Capital Medical University, 95 Yong-An Road, Beijing 100050, China. E-mail: <email>modscn@yahoo.com.cn</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <volume>82</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>519</fpage>
      <lpage>519</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene's Re-use License which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A 13-year-old boy had a one-month history of left upper limb numbness and headache, and a 20-day history of intermittent fever. He had eaten an inadequately cooked <italic>Pomacea canaliculata,</italic> an intermediate host of <italic>Angiostrongylus cantonensis</italic>, 35 days earlier. Blood count analysis showed 7.52 &#xD7; 10<sup>9</sup> leukocytes/L with 18.3% eosinophils (0.5&#x2013;5%). A lumbar puncture showed clear cerebrospinal fluid without erythrocytes (80 &#xD7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells/L), 45% lymphocytes and 54% eosinophils; the opening pressure was 150 mm of H<sub>2</sub>O. Results of tests for circulating antigens of <italic>Angiostrongylus cantonensis</italic> were positive. Magnetic resonance imaging of the brain showed an enhancement in sagittal T1-weighted images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Magnetic resonance imaging of the spine showed a contrast-enhanced nodule in sagittal T1-weighted images after administration of gadolinilum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Consequently, a diagnosis of angiostrongyliasis was made, and the patient was treated with albendazole and dexamethasone. Symptoms of headache and intermittent fever resolved within 20 days, but left upper limb numbness remained. This symptom disappeared with time. Brain and spinal cord lesions were completely resolved at a one-year follow-up.</p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Magnetic resonance imaging of the brain of the patient, showing multiple lesions in sagittal T1-weighted images after administration of gadolinilum.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="tropmed-82-519-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Spinal magnetic resonance imaging of the spine of the patient, showing a contrast-enhanced nodule in sagittal T1-weighted images after administration of gadolinilum.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="tropmed-82-519-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </body>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
