<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Cancer Imaging</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>e-Med</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19933019</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2792083</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2009.0011</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ci090011</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans with contiguous infiltration of the underlying bone</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Garg</surname>
            <given-names>Mandeep Kumar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yadav</surname>
            <given-names>Mukesh Kumar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gupta</surname>
            <given-names>Suruchi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>Narender</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Khandelwal</surname>
            <given-names>Niranjan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AFF1"><sup>a</sup>Department of Radiodiagnosis and Imaging, <sup>b</sup>Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Leprology, and <sup>c</sup>Department of Cytology and Gynaecological Pathology, Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh -160 012, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Corresponding address: Dr Mandeep Kumar Garg, Department of Radiodiagnosis and Imaging, Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh 160012, India. E-mail: <monospace><email>gargmandeep@hotmail.com</email></monospace></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>63</fpage>
      <lpage>66</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2009 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans (DFSP) is a rare, low-grade, cutaneous neoplasm with pronounced tendency for local recurrence. A case of DFSP that showed direct infiltration into the underlying bone marrow is described. To the best of our knowledge, such direct bony involvement by dermatofibrosarcoma has not been reported in the English literature to date. The role of imaging is also discussed for planning adequate initial treatment, which will result in a lower recurrence rate and improved clinical outcome.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords:</title>
        <kwd>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberance</kwd>
        <kwd>bone infiltration</kwd>
        <kwd>recurrence</kwd>
        <kwd>imaging</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans (DFSP) is an uncommon, low-grade cutaneous malignancy that originates from the dermis<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. It can occur in any part of the body, but has predilection for the trunk, head and neck region, and the proximal extremities <sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. The tumor begins as a small bump on the skin surface and then grows in the dermis to form a larger mass that swells and bulges outwards, hence the name &#x2018;protuberans&#x2019;. Distant metastasis of DFSP is extremely rare; however, it is a locally aggressive tumor and shows marked tendency to recur even after wide local excision.<sup>3,4</sup> We emphasize the role of imaging in the preoperative evaluation of these tumors so that more accurate treatment plans can be instituted, leading to decreased recurrence rates.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 20-year-old male presented to our hospital with a progressively increasing swelling on the right leg for the previous 9 months. It was painless and non-tender to start with, but showed rapid growth over the last few weeks with onset of pain that was continuous and mild to moderate in intensity. There was no history of any fever, loss of weight or any trauma to the local site. Complete blood cell counts and biochemical laboratory parameters were within normal limits. The physical examination revealed an irregular, protuberant swelling with a large indurated, non-ulcerated plaque on the right leg. The swelling appeared to be fixed to the underlying bone. No regional lymphadenopathy was noted.</p>
      <p>Radiography of the right leg revealed a rounded soft tissue mass approximately 5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;3&#x2009;cm in size along the anteromedial aspect of the right tibia with associated cortical erosions in the tibia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>A,B). No soft tissue calcification or periosteal reaction was noted. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) was performed to further characterize the mass and delineate the extent of bone marrow involvement. The bone marrow of proximal metadiaphysis of the right tibia over a segment of approximately 7&#x2009;cm revealed an abnormal hypointense signal on T1-weighted images and hyperintense signal on inversion recovery and T2-weighted images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>A,B). There was evidence of cortical breach along the anterior aspect of the tibia with a large associated soft tissue mass that was infiltrating the subcutaneous tissues and bulging anteriorly. The soft tissue was predominantly hypointense on T1-weighted images and hyperintense on T2-weighted images depicting florid enhancement after contrast administration. The underlying bone marrow also showed heterogenous post-contrast enhancement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>A,B). These findings were suggestive of an unresectable malignant sarcomatous tumor.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Radiographs of the right leg, anteroposterior (A) and lateral projection (B) showing a well-defined soft tissue mass along the anteromedial aspect of the right tibia (arrowhead, A) with suggestion of cortical breach (arrow, B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci09001101"/></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>MRI sagittal T1-weighted (A) and fat suppressed coronal T2-weighted images (B) demonstrating abnormal marrow signal of the proximal metadiaphysis of the right tibia with sharp zone of transition. Also note the large soft tissue seen anteriorly (arrowhead, A).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci09001102"/></fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>MRI axial T1-weighted pre-contrast (A) and post-contrast (B) images depicting large soft tissue bulging anteromedial to the right tibia and showing florid enhancement after contrast administration. Mild heterogeneous enhancement is also noted in the underlying bone marrow. The soft tissue is seen to infiltrate the subcutaneous planes associated with cortical breach in the tibia anteriorly (arrow, B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci09001103"/></fig></p>
      <p>The patient underwent core-needle biopsy under local anaesthesia from swelling on the right leg which showed highly cellular smears with clusters of spindle-shaped cells in a fibromyxoid background. The cells showed moderate pleomorphism and storiform pattern in places (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>A). These features were suggestive of DFSP. The stains for CD34 were positive on immunohistochemistry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>B). The patient is scheduled for neoadjuvant therapy with imatinib mesylate to be followed by surgical excision of the tumor.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Biopsy smear showing highly cellular tumor with fibroblastic spindle cells producing storiform pattern (A) and immunohistochemical stain for CD34 (B) showing strong membranous positivity around the tumor cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci09001104"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans is a rare, painless, monoclonal, cutaneous soft tissue sarcoma of unknown cause that was first described by Taylor in 1890<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. It constitutes approximately 1% of all soft tissue sarcomas, shows slight male preponderance and generally presents in the third and fourth decades of life<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]</sup>. Its clinical manifestations are non-specific. It often masquerades as a benign, indolent tumor on the trunk and proximal extremities. The surface of the tumor is characterized by irregular protuberant swellings, and a hard indurated plaque of irregular outline forms the base. It is a slow-growing neoplasm; however in the later stages, it may show rapid growth and the lesion may become painful, ulcerated and can discharge.</p>
      <p>Surgery with wide local excision or Mohs micrographic surgery remains the treatment of choice in these patients<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Radiation therapy, hitherto with a limited role, is recently being used as an adjunct to surgical excision, primarily in cases in which the tumor is unresectable, there are positive resection margins on histology and when the surgery is going to leave major cosmetic or functional deficits. Chemotherapy has rarely been used in the treatment of DFSP. Recently, a very promising neoadjuvant molecular therapy with imatinib mesylate, a potent and selective inhibitor of several protein-tyrosine kinases, is advocated in adult patients with unresectable, recurrent or metastatic DFSP<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>.</p>
      <p>DFSP is a locally invasive fibrohistiocytic tumor with a recurrence rate of up to 25% even after wide local excision with a safety margin of 3&#x2013;5 cm<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. This is attributed to the fact that DFSP extends far beyond the assessed clinical margins, spreading locally in the dermis, subcutaneous tissues and muscles. Our index case illustrates that it can extend even deeper to directly involve the bone with cortical erosions and bone marrow infiltration. To the best of our knowledge such deep invasion of the tumor with infiltration into the underlying bone has not been described in the literature to date except in one case of DFSP of the scalp where the calvarium was also infiltrated<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. This could partly be due to the fact that imaging is rarely a part of the preoperative workup in these patients.</p>
      <p>DFSP is a low-grade malignancy with only a few sporadic cases of distant metastases<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11 B12 B13"><sup>11&#x2013;13</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. The diagnosis of DFSP generally comes from core-needle or incisional biopsy. Histologically, it consists of uniform but atypical spindle cells placed in a fibrotic stroma in the dermis and subcutaneous tissues exhibiting characteristic &#x2018;cartwheel&#x2019; or &#x2018;storiform&#x2019; appearance<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Immunohistochemistry studies have shown that DFSP stains positive for CD34 and negative for factor XIIIa, which are very useful markers to differentiate DFSP from dermatofibroma.<sup>9</sup> The poor prognostic indicators of DFSP include advanced age, high mitotic index, increased cellularity, DNA aneuploidy and fibrosarcomatous changes within the tumor<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Multiple local recurrences can also predispose to distant metastasis, thus highlighting the significance of adequate initial treatment.</p>
      <p>The extent of the tumor and the degree of invasion of underlying tissues is usually assessed by physical examination and not much importance has been given to the role of imaging except to rule out metastasis. Mendenhall et al.<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>]</sup> and McArthur<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>]</sup> discussed the role of MRI in determining deep tumor invasion. Because DFSP is a locally invasive tumor with a high rate of post-operative recurrence, we advocate that imaging (preferably MRI) should be done in all such cases especially those involving the extremities. MRI will ascertain the exact depth of invasion by showing the tumor margins, and will guide the clinician to institute an adequate initial treatment by choosing an appropriate surgical plan with or without adjunctive chemo-/radiotherapy. This in turn will lead to a reduced rate of local recurrence and improved clinical outcome. However, the cost/benefit ratio needs to be further substantiated by larger prospective studies.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <notes>
      <fn-group>
        <fn>
          <p>This paper is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancerimaging.org">http://www.cancerimaging.org</ext-link>. In the event of a change in the URL address, please use the DOI provided to locate the paper.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Snow</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gordon</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Larson</surname>
              <given-names>PO</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans: a report on 29 patients treated by Mohs micrographic surgery with long-term follow-up and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/cncr.20316">doi:10.1002/cncr.20316</ext-link>. PMid:15221986</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15221986</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ballo</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zagars</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pisters</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pollack</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of radiation therapy in the management of dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans</article-title>
          <source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>823</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0360-3016(97)00895-X">doi:10.1016/S0360-3016(97)00895-X</ext-link>. PMid:  </comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9531366</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nouri</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lodha</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jimenez</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robins</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mohs micrographic surgery for dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans: University of Miami and NYU experience</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>1060</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1524-4725.2002.02084.x">doi:10.1046/j.1524-4725.2002.02084.x</ext-link>. PMid:12460303</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12460303</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maggoudi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vahtsevanos</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Psomaderis</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans of the face: report of 2 cases and an overview of the recent literature</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>140</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.joms.2005.02.030">doi:10.1016/j.joms.2005.02.030</ext-link>. PMid:16360873</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16360873</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mendenhall</surname>
              <given-names>WM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zlotecki</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scarborough</surname>
              <given-names>MT:</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>2503</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/cncr.20678">doi:10.1002/cncr.20678</ext-link>. PMid:15503305</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15503305</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans: treatment results of 35 cases</article-title>
          <source>Radiother Oncol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>175</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0167-8140(00)00228-0">doi:10.1016/S0167-8140(00)00228-0</ext-link>. PMid:11054521</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11054521</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Monnier</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vidal</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans: a population based cancer registry descriptive study of 66 consecutive cases diagnosed between 1982 and 2002</article-title>
          <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1237</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-3083.2006.01780.x">doi:10.1111/j.1468-3083.2006.01780.x</ext-link>. PMid:17062038</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17062038</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Asuquo</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Umoh</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebughe</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberance: case reports</article-title>
          <source>Ann Afr Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>80</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18240709</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McArthur</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans: recent clinical progress</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>2876</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17647063</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Uematsu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fukai</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamura</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Distant metastasis of dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans of the scalp &#x2013; case report</article-title>
          <source>Neurol Med Chir</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>493</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2176/nmc.43.493">doi:10.2176/nmc.43.493</ext-link>. PMid:14620201</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Auer</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Auer</surname>
              <given-names>RN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metastatic dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans mimicking meningioma</article-title>
          <source>Clin Neuropathol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>190</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9707332</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ko&#x15F;ar</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ergeneci</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case report. Dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans metastatic to lung without local recurrence</article-title>
          <source>Tani Girisim Radyol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>195</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14661489</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suehara</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yazawa</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hitachi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metastatic Bednar tumor (pigmented dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans) with fibrosarcomatous change: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Orthop Sci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>662</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00776-004-0831-2">doi:10.1007/s00776-004-0831-2</ext-link>. PMid:16228691</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16228691</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
