<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xml:lang="EN" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Intern Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJIM</journal-id>
      <journal-title>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1226-3303</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2005-6648</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Association of Internal Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18646514</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2686979</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3904/kjim.2008.23.2.103</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Renal infarction resulting from traumatic renal artery dissection</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>Kyung Pyo</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Sik</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>Gong Yong</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Na</surname>
            <given-names>Ki Ryang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yun</surname>
            <given-names>Il Yong</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Sung Kwang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Renal Regeneration Laboratory, Chonbuk National University Medical School, Jeonju, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Diagnostic Radiology, Research Institute of Clinical Medicine, Chonbuk National University Medical School, Jeonju, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Chungnam National University Medical School, Daejeon, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Correspondence to: Sung Kwang Park, M.D., Department of Internal Medicine, Renal Regeneration Laboratory, Chonbuk National University Medical School, 634-18, Keum-Am dong, Jeonju 561-712, Korea. Tel: 82-63-250-1683, Fax: 82-63-254-1609, <email>parksk@chonbuk.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>23</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>103</fpage>
      <lpage>105</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2008 The Korean Association of Internal Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Renal artery dissection may be caused by iatrogenic injury, trauma, underlying arterial diseases such as fibromuscular disease, atherosclerotic disease, or connective tissue disease. Radiological imaging may be helpful in detecting renal artery pathology, such as renal artery dissection. For patients with acute, isolated renal artery dissection, surgical treatment, endovascular management, or medical treatment have been considered effective measures to preserve renal function. We report a case of renal infarction that came about as a consequence of renal artery dissection.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Kidney</kwd>
        <kwd>Infarction</kwd>
        <kwd>Trauma</kwd>
        <kwd>Dissection</kwd>
        <kwd>Renal artery</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Renal artery dissection may be caused by iatrogenic injury, trauma, underlying arterial diseases such as fibromuscular disease, atherosclerotic disease, or connective tissue disease. Often, renal artery dissection is detected during diagnostic work-up for malignant hypertension, acute flank pain, or renovascular hypertension in the chronic stage<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1)</xref>. Some patients do well with conservative treatment, while others need emergent or urgent surgery<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3)</xref>. Treatment is chosen based on the patient's hemodynamic status, renal function, and the feasibility of treatment modality<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2)</xref>. Here we report a case of renal infarction that came about as a consequence of renal artery dissection and also discuss the proper treatment modality.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 38-year-old male presented to our clinic with a history of persistent left flank pain. Three days before admission, while intoxicated with alcohol, he slipped on the bathroom floor. Other than that, there was no unusual medical history. His blood pressure was 128/72 mmHg. Physical examination revealed severe tenderness at the left costovertebral angle. Laboratory indices were as follows: hemoglobin 15.6 g/dL, white blood cell count 12.08x10<sup>3</sup>/&#xB5;L, platelet count 24.1&#xD7;10<sup>4</sup>/&#xB5;L, blood urea nitrogen 17 mg/dL, creatinine 0.97 mg/dL, and LDH 980 IU/L (normal, 218-472 IU/L). Urinalysis showed negative dip stick for protein and blood, with normal urine sediment. Electrocardiography showed normal sinus rhythm. Contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) scan showed a small aneurysm (arrow) in the distal portion of the left renal artery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). In addition, a well-demarcated, non-enhanced left kidney parenchyma (arrow) was demonstrated, suggesting infarction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). Renal angiography demonstrated a dissecting aneurysm of the left renal artery (arrow) and multiple filling defects along the peripheral portion of left kidney (arrowhead) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). Since the patient was hemodynamically stable, and his pain was gradually subsiding, we treated him conservatively. Two months later, on follow-up CT, a focal pseudoaneurysm was still present at the same site on the left renal artery (arrow), while the previously infarcted region of the left kidney had resolved completely, leaving only some parenchymal scarring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Renal artery injury is a rare complication of blunt abdominal trauma. However, exercise and sports activities have been associated with renal artery dissection in cases where the dissection was considered secondary to anatomical variation or acceleration/deceleration injury to the renal artery and subsequent intimal tearing<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5)</xref>. In the presented case, there was no anatomic variation of the renal artery on radiologic studies, so we hypothesized that the dissection was related to acceleration/deceleration injury to a normal renal artery.</p>
      <p>An isolated renal artery dissection may be suspected in patients complaining of severe flank pain after blunt abdominal trauma<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6)</xref>. Radiological imaging may be helpful in detecting renal artery pathology, such as renal artery dissection. For patients with acute, isolated renal artery dissection, surgical treatment, endovascular management, or medical treatment have been considered as measures to preserve renal function<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7)</xref>. M&#xFC;ller et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1)</xref> reported that renal artery dissection can be treated with surgical revascularization. Their indications for surgical intervention were organ preservation and the treatment or improvement of a patient's renovascular hypertension<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1)</xref>. Recently, Lee et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2)</xref> reported the case of a patient who had renal artery dissection complicated by renal infarction, that was successfully treated using endovascular management for salvaging the renal parenchyma. The patient's lesion was easily accessible using percutaneous angioplasty and stent.</p>
      <p>Management of renal artery dissection remains controversial. Surgical revascularization after renal artery dissection requires skillful expertise because of perivascular inflammation and scarring potentially present in the diseased renal artery segment. Before planning surgical revascularization, careful preoperative examination may be necessary to evaluate the precise pathologic status of the diseased renal artery segment<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1)</xref>. Endovascular intervention of the renal artery has largely been used to treat renal artery stenosis in renovascular hypertension. Recently, its use in cases of arterial dissection has increased. However, the feasibility and effectiveness of this modality in treating renal artery dissection has not been confirmed<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2)</xref>. Moreover, if renal function and vital signs are normal, invasive treatment such as surgical or endovascular revascularization may not be necessary, because medical treatment alone with strict blood pressure control is as effective as surgical management<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8)</xref>. Beroniade et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9)</xref> also suggested that surgery should be reserved as a second-line modality. In our case, renal angiography was performed for diagnosis of renal infarction, but no revascularization of renal artery dissection was performed. Because of the patient's stable vital signs and normal renal function, we elected to manage him conservatively. Follow-up CT showed that the infarcted area of the left kidney was recovering with small cortical scarring, while the patient's blood pressure remained normal.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, physician should take the patient's medical status into consideration when deciding treatment modality for renal artery dissection. When renal function is normal, medical treatment rather than surgical or endovascular revascularization may be sufficient.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>This paper was supported by research funds of <grant-sponsor>Chonbuk National University</grant-sponsor> in 2007.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xFC;ller</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reiher</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pfeiffer</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xFC;llser</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hort</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voiculscue</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grabensee</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>F&#xFC;rst</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sandmann</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical treatment of renal artery dissection in 25 patients: indications and results</article-title>
          <source>J Vasc Surg</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>761</fpage>
          <lpage>768</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12663975</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moon</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Min</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hwang</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baek</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jo</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>GI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Percutaneous intervention of spontaneous renal artery dissection complicated with renal infarction: a case report and literature review</article-title>
          <source>Catheter Cardiovasc Interv</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>335</fpage>
          <lpage>338</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14571483</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bae</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Earm</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hae</surname>
              <given-names>IH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of spontaneous renal artery dissection causing renal infarction in a previous healthy man</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Nephrol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>831</fpage>
          <lpage>836</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walker</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Packer</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Running repairs: renal artery dissection following extreme exertion</article-title>
          <source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1258</fpage>
          <lpage>1259</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10344373</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Borrero</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Left renal artery dissection caused by a football injury</article-title>
          <source>N Y State J Med</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>550</fpage>
          <lpage>552</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1798627</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharples</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sobeh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yaqoob</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Renal artery dissection after blunt abdominal trauma: a rare cause of acute cortical necrosis</article-title>
          <source>Am J Kidney Dis</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>E11</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12200828</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ando</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohno</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirata</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Emoto</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogata</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mimata</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous recovery from renal infarction resulting from renal artery dissection</article-title>
          <source>Int J Urol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>405</fpage>
          <lpage>408</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15948731</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Edwards</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stanson</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holley</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shepes</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolated renal artery dissection: presentation, evaluation, management and pathology</article-title>
          <source>Mayo Clin Proc</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>564</fpage>
          <lpage>571</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7109685</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beroniade</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Froment</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pison</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary renal artery dissection: presentation of two cases and brief review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Am J Nephrol</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>382</fpage>
          <lpage>389</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3324764</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-wrap>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Contrast-enhanced abdominal CT scan showed small aneurysm (arrow) in the distal portion of the left renal artery (A) and Well-demarcated, non-enhanced parenchyma (arrow) of the left kidney, which suggested left renal infarction (B). Renal angiography demonstrated dissecting aneurysm of the left renal artery (arrows) and multiple filling defects along the peripheral portion of the left kidney (arrowheads) (C). Follow-up CT findings. show focal pseudoaneurysm was still present at the same site in the left renal artery (arrow) after two months. The previously infarcted region of the left kidney resolved, leaving some renal scarring (D).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjim-23-103-g001"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-wrap>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
