<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Gastroenterol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJG</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology : Official Journal of the Saudi Gastroenterology Association</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1319-3767</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-4049</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20871200</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2995104</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SJG-16-302</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1319-3767.70622</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Intraoperative Localization of Vascular Malformation of Small Bowel by Selective Intra-arterial Dye Injection</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Eshpuniyani</surname>
            <given-names>Priya B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kantharia</surname>
            <given-names>Chetan V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Prabhu</surname>
            <given-names>RamKrishna Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Supe</surname>
            <given-names>Avinash N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001">Department of Surgical Gastroenterology, KEM Hospital, Parel, Mumbai, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Avinash N. Supe, Department of Surgical Gastroenterology, KEM Hospital, Parel, Mumbai &#x2013; 400 012, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="avisupe@gmail.com">avisupe@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>302</fpage>
      <lpage>304</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Angiomatous malformation is the most common vascular abnormality, accounting for 30-40% cases of obscure GI bleeding from small bowel. Surgical resection is the treatment of choice in severe or recurrent hemorrhage requiring multiple blood transfusions. However, the diffuse nature of the lesions poses a challenge to localize them accurately preoperatively, for exact resection. We present a case in which we have used selective mesenteric angiography with selective cannulation and exact localization of the lesion by injecting dye such as methylene blue, indigo carmine, and fluorescein, to localize the angiomatous malformation before surgical resection and also to determine the exact resection to be done.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Diffuse lesions</kwd>
        <kwd>exact localization</kwd>
        <kwd>methylene blue</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Angiomatous malformation is the most common vascular abnormality of the GI tract. Small bowel lesions account for 30-40% cases of obscure GI[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>] bleeding. These lesions are suspected in patients with a negative upper endoscopy and colonoscopy. In such patients, angiography with selective cannulation with injection of dye is a useful mode of localization of the lesion.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT5">5</xref>] We report a case of angiomatous malformation in the jejunum in which this method of diagnosis and localization proved to be useful in surgical management.</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases" id="sec1-1">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A sixty year old man presented with malena since 3 months. He had H/O multiple blood transfusions prior to referral. On admission, his vital parameters were stable. Per-abdomen examination, rectal examination, and proctoscopy were normal. His hemoglobin (Hb) was 9 g/dl with rest of the blood investigations being normal. Ultrasonography of the abdomen, upper GI endoscopy, push enteroscopy 1 m from duodeno-jejunal flexure, and colonoscopy were normal. Capsule endoscopy (using M2A capsule) was also normal. Meckel&#x2019;s scan using 99m-Tc pertechnetate radioisotope and Nuclear Scan using technetium Tc 99m&#x2013;labeled red blood cells showed abnormal uptake of tracer in the left hypochondrium, extending into the left iliac fossa with the suspicion of active bleeding in the small bowel. The focal nature of the pooling suggested possibility of a vascular anomaly in the proximal jejunum. Triple vessel angiography confirmed angiomatous malformation in the jejunum with the presence of a large jejunal branch arising from the superior mesenteric artery (SMA) [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>] with multiple small micro aneurysms.
<fig id="F0001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Superior mesenteric angiography with super-selective cannulation into the feeding vessel-showing the diffuse vascular lesion</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-16-302-g001"/></fig></p>
      <p>In view of the persistent bleeding, surgery was planned. On the morning of the surgery, triple vessel angiography was done with a 4Fr catheter (Cordis, Florida, USA) placed at origin of SMA and selective canulation of the feeding vessel with a 2.7Fr Prograde microcathether (Teremo, Japan) placed in the feeding vessel. The catheters were secured to the thigh to prevent displacement and the patient was shifted to the operation theatre. On exploration, 1.5 feet of jejunum showed dilated submucosal vessels and increased vascularity. Rest of the bowel appeared normal. Methylene blue was injected into the feeding vessel via the microcatheter following which, more than 1.5 feet was found to be discoloured with a clear demarcation, around 2 cm beyond the abnormal looking bowel on either side [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>]. Resection of the demarcated segment of jejunum was done. The patient did not require any blood transfusion during surgery and postoperatively.
<fig id="F0002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Intraoperative picture showing demarcation of small bowel after injection of methylene blue into the microcathether placed in the feeding vessel</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="SJG-16-302-g002"/></fig></p>
      <p>On histopathologic examination, submucosa showed thickened, congested, focally tortuous vascular channels, some being extremely thin walled blood vessels. Findings were consistent with angiomatous malformation.</p>
      <p>Post-operative course was uneventful and the patient was asymptomatic at follow up, 4 months postoperatively. His postoperative Hb was 10 mg/dl at last visit.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-2">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Angiomatous malformation is the most common vascular abnormality, accounting for 30-40% cases of obscure GI bleeding from small bowel. 15% of lesions are located in jejunum and ileum. Common presentation is malena or hematochezia as bleeding is usually low grade. However, it can be massive in approximately 15% of patients, as seen in our patient.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>]</p>
      <p>Surgical resection is the treatment of choice in severe or recurrent hemorrhage requiring multiple blood transfusions.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>] However, exact preoperative localization of the lesion poses a challenge. Various methods such as push enteroscopy, colonoscopy, RBC scan, and selective mesenteric angiography have been used for diagnosis and exact localization of the lesions. Infrequently angiomatous malformations can be detected by visual inspection of the serosal side of the bowel during Laparotomy.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>]</p>
      <p>Radionuclide scanning, Tc 99m&#x2013;labeled red blood cells or <sup>99m</sup>Tc sulfur colloid, is helpful for detecting and better localization of active bleeding from angiomatous malformation as in our case. Though it detects bleeding with rates as low as 0.1 mL/min, the intermittent nature of bleeding limits the utility of radionuclide studies in angiomatous malformation.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>] Hence, lesions may be missed in patients who are not actively bleeding at the time of presentation, leading to inadequate resection.</p>
      <p>Selective mesenteric angiography is a useful diagnostic technique, with its sensitivity ranging from 58 to 86%. The rate of bleeding (0.5 mL/min), technique, and timing in relation to period of bleeding[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>] are its limiting factors. Thus, there is the possibility of missing out small lesions bleeding slowly or delayed presentation.</p>
      <p>In diffuse angiomatous malformation as in our patient, where a single bleeding vessel cannot be identified, routinely used methods such as intraoperative palpation, endoscopy, and visual inspection through multiple enterotomies are of little value, as it does not help to determine the exact extent of the bowel to be resected.</p>
      <p>Hence, in such patients, selective mesenteric angiography with selective cannulation and exact localization of the lesion by injecting dye such as methylene blue, indigo carmine, and fluorescein is an excellent modality of investigation and treatment as it assists not only in exact localization of angiomatous malformation before surgical resection,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT5">5</xref>] but also in determining the extent of resection to be done, by accurate demarcation as in our case. This helps to avoid missing out on lesions which are either diffuse or are not actively bleeding and thus recurrence of the lesion.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="CIT1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karnam</surname>
              <given-names>US</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barkin</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vascular malformations of small intestine</article-title>
          <source>Curr Treat Options Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>173</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11469975</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duchini</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Godino</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Talavera</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Achord</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Angiodysplasia of colon</article-title>
          <comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.emedicine.com/med/topic134.htm">http://www.emedicine.com/med/topic134.htm</ext-link> [last accessed on 2008 Jul 17]</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hussain</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Selective angiographic catheterisation for jejunal angiodysplasia</article-title>
          <source>Postgrad Med J</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222835</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koga</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iida</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagai</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aoyagi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takesue</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Jejunal angiodysplasia confirmed by intravascular injection technique <italic>in vitro</italic>: Report of a case and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8877645</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mika</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Masataka</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasuhiro</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shigeyoshi</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kazuhiko</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasushi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of jejunal angiodysplasia with repeating melena</article-title>
          <source>J Japan Surg Assoc</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>861</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
