<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Orthop Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CIOS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2005-291X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2005-4408</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Orthopaedic Association</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21119945</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2981785</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4055/cios.2010.2.4.260</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Intradural Extramedullary Tuberculoma Mimicking En Plaque Meningioma</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shim</surname>
            <given-names>Dae Moo</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>Sung Kyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Tae Kyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chae</surname>
            <given-names>Soo Uk</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wonkwang University Hospital, Iksan, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>*</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wonkwang University Sanbon Hospital, Gunpo, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Correspondence to: Sung Kyun Oh, MD. Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wonkwang University Sanbon Hospital, 1142 Sangbon-dong, Gunpo 435-040, Korea. Tel: +82-31-390-2224, Fax: +82-31-398-2223, <email>niceo@daum.net</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>05</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>260</fpage>
      <lpage>263</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2010 by The Korean Orthopaedic Association</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 24-year-old man with tuberculosis meningitis developed acute paraplegia and sensory disturbances 5 weeks after receiving conventional antituberculous therapy. Magnetic resonance imaging revealed an intradural extramedullary long segmental mass mimicking en plaque meningioma at the T2-T6 vertebrae levels. Prompt surgical decompression was performed. A histology examination of the mass revealed a tuberculoma. After surgery, the patient showed improved motor power and a normal bladder function. Intradural extramedullary tuberculoma of the spinal cord is rare complication of tuberculosis meningitis, which can occur as a response to conventional antituberculous therapy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Tuberculoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Spinal cord</kwd>
        <kwd>En plaque meningioma</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Tuberculosis is still an important pathological entity in developed and developing countries. Central nervous system involvement in patients with tuberculosis is estimated to be approximately 10% with tuberculous meningitis being the most common manifestation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3)</xref> Spinal tuberculoma is also an extrapulmonary manifestation of tuberculosis involving the central nervous system, and are characterized as extradural, intradural extramedullary, or intradural according to their location. In particular, an intradural extramedullary tuberculoma is extremely rare. Only 30 cases reports have been found in the literature.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9)</xref></p>
    <p>We describe an unusual case of intradural, extramedullary tuberculoma mimicking en plaque meningioma as a complication of tuberculous meningitis in a previously healthy human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-negative young male.</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 24-year-old male was admitted to our hospital with a 1 week history of progressive headache and fever. His previous medical history was clear. On the neurologic examination, his mental status was normal without focal neurological deficits. The laboratory examination revealed nonspecific findings. HIV antibodies were negative. Lumbar cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) analysis showed pleocytosis, increased total protein level (167 mg/dL) and decreased glucose (32 mg/dL). Tubercle bacillus was detected in the CSF and the adenosine deaminase (ADA) level was elevated (12 IU/L). Brain MRI revealed small, multiple high signal intensity lesions on the diffusion weighted image. His chest X-ray showed diffuse ill-defined patches and nodules with increased density in both apical lungs. Tuberculosis meningitis and pulmonary tuberculosis were suspected and antituberculous treatment with rifampicin, isoniazid, ethambutol and pyrazinamide was started. Nine days after the antituberculous treatment, his general condition and headache had improved significantly. However, four weeks after antituberculous treatment, he developed acute sensory disturbance below T10 dermatome as well as urination disturbances. A neurological examination revealed grade 3/3 paraparesis and hyporeflexia. Spinal MRI showed a long segmentally located soft tissue mass mimicking a meningioma in the intradural, extramedullary space of the posterior spinal canal from T2 to T6 with severe cord compression and displacement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Surgical decompression and a biopsy were performed. During the operation, a T3, T4, T5 and T6 laminectomy was performed. The dura was thickened and the cord was infiltrated with an adhesive mass. The dura was opened and closed in the normal manner after removing the mass under microscope guidance. Grossly, the mass was very soft with a dark green color. Optical microscopy of the mass revealed chronic granulomatous inflammation with neutrophil infiltration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The cultures were negative for Mycobacterium tuberculosis, and the stains for fungi and acid-fast micro organisms were negative. Twelve weeks after surgery, the patients reported low back discomfort. MRI of the thoracic and lumbar areas showed lumbosacral tuberculosis spondylitis with multiple abscesses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Anti-tuberculous medication was continued for 18 months. At the one year follow-up, the patient could walk without assistance and urinate normally.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Spinal involvement in tuberculosis is classified into four categories: Potts spine, nonosseous spinal tuberculoma, tuberculous arachnoiditis and tuberculous meningitis. Intradural spinal tuberculomas are estimated to be composed of only 2% to 5% of central nervous system tuberculomas.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5)</xref></p>
      <p>Compton and Dorsch<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8)</xref> reported 11 cases of intratudral extramedullary tuberculoma in 1984. Since then, there have been 19 more cases reported in the English literature.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9)</xref> All cases, except for 4 initially presented with tubculous meningitis. Most case reviews involved the thoracic spine.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10)</xref> The diagnostic method is generally histopathology, even though AFB cultures from the granulomas were positive in only one of the reported cases.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7)</xref> A myelogram can be helpful but MRI is the diagnostic procedure of choice.</p>
      <p>Interestingly, most intradural extramedullary tuberculoma cases were detected after antibuberculous therapy had been initiated, which is known as paradoxical response.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7)</xref></p>
      <p>Tuberculoma can occur at any time but most reported cases showed a paradoxical response during the early course of chemotherapy, which ranged from 3 weeks to 1 year.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7)</xref> The mechanism for the paradoxical response is unclear. However, is is believed to be the result of an interaction between the host's immune response and the direct effects of mycobacterial products.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10)</xref> This condition has been recognized more frequently. Narita et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10)</xref> reported paradoxical worsening in up to 36% of patients with tuberculosis and AIDS after antiretroviral therapy. Hydrocephalus and new granuloma can appear despite regular chemotherapy. Therefore, mental or focal neurological changes during the follow-up must be checked in patients with tubeculous meningitis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10)</xref></p>
      <p>The prognosis for neurological improvement is good with a prompt surgical excison and appropriate antituberculous medication.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6)</xref> Although intramedullary tuberculoma can be treated with medication alone, an intradural extramedullary tuberculoma is essential for surgery when compression of spinal cord occurs.</p>
      <p>En plaque meningioma can present with thoracic spinal cord and nerve root compression.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1)</xref> The case presented herein was initially diagnosed with en plaque meningioma based on the radiological findings. The differential diagnosis between tuberculous patchy meningitis and meningioma in the form of plaque is difficult without obtaining a biopsy specimen.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, intradural extramedullary tuberculoma can occur in tuberculous meningitis patients as a paradoxical response to antituberculous chemotherapy. Although quite rare, intradural extramedullary tuberculomas should be considered in a differential diagnosis of an en plaque meningioma of the spinal cord.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mirzai</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tuberculoma of the cervical spinal canal mimicking en plaque meningioma</article-title>
          <source>J Spinal Disord Tech</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>197</fpage>
          <lpage>199</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15800442</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prakash</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jha</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paradoxical response to chemotherapy in neurotuberculosis</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>214</fpage>
          <lpage>222</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16714861</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pino</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An intradural extramedullary tuberculoma of the spinal cord in a non-HIV-infected patient: case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Lung</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>184</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>193</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16902844</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Skendros</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamaria</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kontopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsitouridis</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sidiropoulos</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intradural, eextramedullary tuberculoma of the spinal cord as a complication of tuberculous meningitis</article-title>
          <source>Infection</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>117</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12682818</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roca</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intradural extramedullary tuberculoma of the spinal cord: a review of reported cases</article-title>
          <source>J Infect</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>425</fpage>
          <lpage>431</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15907551</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kasliwal</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srivastava</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tuberculoma presenting as an intradural extramedullary lesion</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>541</fpage>
          <lpage>543</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17992050</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kojima</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanno</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hattori</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intradural extramedullary tuberculoma of the thoracic spine: paradoxical response to antituberculous therapy</article-title>
          <source>Intern Med</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>797</fpage>
          <lpage>798</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18421202</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Compton</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dorsch</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intradural extramedullary tuberculoma of the cervical spine: case report</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>200</fpage>
          <lpage>203</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6689720</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muthukumar</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sureshkumar</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Concurrent syringomyelia and intradural extramedullary tuberculoma as late complications of tuberculous meningitis</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Neurosci</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1225</fpage>
          <lpage>1230</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18029276</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Narita</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashkin</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hollender</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pitchenik</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paradoxical worsening of tuberculosis following antiretroviral therapy in patients with AIDS</article-title>
          <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>158</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <lpage>161</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9655723</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T2-weighted sagittal (A) and enhanced T1-weighted sagittal (B) section of magnetic resonance imaging scan of a thoracic spine,showing an intradural extramedullary mass extending from T2 through T6 and compressing the spinal cord.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-2-260-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Photomicrograph shows chronic granulomatous inflammation with neutrophil infiltrate under low and high magnification (A, H&amp;E &#xD7; 200; B, H&amp;E &#xD7; 400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-2-260-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Postoperative 3 month follow-up magnetic resonance imaging scan of the thoracic and lumbar regions. Laminectomy state of thoracic spine (A). Typical finding of tuberculosis spondylitis L5-S1 with multiple abscess (B).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-2-260-g003"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
