<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yonsei Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Yonsei Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0513-5796</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1976-2437</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Yonsei University College of Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17963351</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2628159</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2007.48.5.883</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Acute Myocardial Infarction Due to an Unruptured Sinus of Valsalva Aneurysm in a Patient with Beh&#xE7;et's Syndrome</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Sak</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Chang-Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoo</surname>
            <given-names>Kyung-Jong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="A1">Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, Yonsei Cardiovascular Center, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Reprint address: requests to Dr. Kyung-Jong Yoo, Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, Yonsei Cardiovascular Center, Yonsei University College of Medicine, 250 Seongsanno, Seodaemun-gu, Seoul 120-752, Korea. Tel: 82-2-2228-8485, Fax: 82-2-313-2992, <email>kjy@yuhs.ac</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>48</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>883</fpage>
      <lpage>885</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2007 The Yonsei University College of Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>This report describes the case of a 45-year-old Korean female who had suffered from Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome for two years with a huge, unruptured aneurysm originating from the left coronary sinus. The aneurysm had caused myocardial and aortic insufficiency by compressing the proximal left anterior descending coronary artery. The orifice of the aneurysm was at the left coronary sinus, about 5mm from the left main coronary ostium, and it was filled with organized thrombi. Surgical repair was performed by closing the entrance of the aneurysm with a Dacron patch and by implementing aortic valve repair and coronary artery bypass grafting. The patient's coronary flow was restored postoperatively, and all anginal symptoms disappeared.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Aneurysm</kwd>
        <kwd>coronary sinus</kwd>
        <kwd>myocardial infarction</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Aneurysm of the sinus of Valsalva (SVA) is a rare clinical manifestation of Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome. Only a few cases of SVA accompanying Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome have been reported.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> Since the SVAs caused by an active inflammatory disease, such as Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome, tend to enlarge progressively and have a high risk of rupture, early diagnosis and surgical management is critical for the patient survival.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 45-year-old female was admitted to the emergency department for intermittent chest pain, which had been aggravated 30 minutes before admission. She had been suffering from recurrent oral and genital ulcers and had been diagnosed with Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome for two years. She was taking oral medications, including Colchicine. Upon physical examination, her blood pressure was 118/70mmHg, and her pulse rate was 71 beats/min. A 12-lead EKG revealed a normal sinus rhythm with nonspecific ST &amp; T-wave abnormalities. Initial laboratory findings showed increased total creatinine phosphokinase (CPK) of 94IU/L and an MB fraction of 8.7ng/mL (0.0-5.0ng/mL). C-reactive protein (CRP), one of the acute phase reactants, was also elevated to 53mg/L (reference range 0.0-8.0mg/L). A transesophageal echocardiogram (TEE) revealed mild aortic regurgitation and normal ventricular wall motion. A coronary angiogram showed an 80% luminal narrowing of the proximal to middle left anterior descending artery and a 70% stenosis of the first diagonal branch. Since coronary artery disease subsequent from Beh&#xE7;et's disease was suspected, we planned elective coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) and started medical treatment with intravenous heparin and isosorbide dinitrate, along with corticosteroids, to control Beh&#xE7;et's disease activity while also monitoring the patient's CRP. After two weeks of medication with steroids, the CRP was normalized, but the patient complained of more frequent chest pain. Suspecting the progression of coronary artery disease, we performed a non-invasive, multi-dimensional computed tomogram (MD-CT). MD-CT revealed a dilated left SVA with a huge aneurysm compressing the proximal left anterior descending artery and the left circumflex artery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Since the aneurysm was huge and the patient complained of severe chest pain, an emergent operation was performed. Intraoperative TEE showed regional wall motion abnormality of the anterolateral segment, and EKG monitoring showed ST elevation. The operation was performed through a median sternotomy with mild hypothermic cardiopulmonary bypass. The aorta was cross-clamped and opened transversely. The orifice of the aneurysm was observed at the left SVA. The size of the orifice was about 2cm in diameter, and it originated about 5mm from the left main coronary ostium. The orifice, filled with organized mural thrombi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>), was closed with a two-layered autologous pericardium and a Dacron patch, and the CABG was performed between the left anterior descending and the obtuse marginal coronary arteries, using left internal mammary and radial artery composite Y-grafts. Since the left coronary cusp of the aortic valve was fibrotic and retracted into the left ventricular outflow tract, aortic valvuloplasty was performed concomitantly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). The patient was weaned from cardiopulmonary bypass uneventfully, and intraoperative TEE revealed improved anterolateral wall motion and trivial aortic regurgitation. A postoperative MD-CT, performed one month after surgery, showed patent bypass grafts with a regressed aneurysm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The patient was followed-up for nine months, and recovery has been uneventful.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>An SVA is a rare cardiac anomaly that is observed in only 0.14-0.96% of open-heart surgeries.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> Most SVAs are congenital, and acquired SVAs are rare. Acquired SVAs can be caused by a deficiency of the aortic media, which may result from trauma, endocarditis, syphilis, connective tissue diseases, such as Marfan's syndrome or  Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome, or a senile type of dilation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
      <p>Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome is a systemic inflammatory disease with rare cardiac and vascular manifestations, such as pericarditis, aortic or mitral regurgitation, endomyocardial fibrosis, arterial or venous occlusion, and varices and aneurysms of the sinus of Valsalva, which can occur in about five percent of patients.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> Both SVAs and Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome occur more frequently in Asian patient populations.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref></p>
      <p>In our case, although Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome is diagnosed only with clinical manifestations, SVA was considered to be caused by Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome since the disease progression was too rapid and initial laboratory findings revealed an elevated CRP which was normalized with steroid treatment. Before surgery, our patient showed compromised cardiac function, caused by aneurysmal compression of the left coronary system. Since the huge SVA was filled with organized thrombi and it was not feasible to resect and remove the SVA completely, we closed the orifice with a patch and reestablished coronary circulation with bypass grafts; cardiac function improved, and the patient became symptom-free after surgery. Although advances in echocardiography have reduced the need for other diagnostic procedures, we could not detect the SVA in the initial TTE since it was too small at that time. The MD-CT taken after two weeks showed a huge SVA, which suggested a rapid progression of the disease.</p>
      <p>Although unruptured SVAs are mostly asymptomatic, fatal complications, such as infection, systemic embolism, right ventricular outflow tract obstruction, malignant arrhythmias, and acute coronary syndrome, can occur.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref> In addition, SVAs caused by active inflammatory disease, such as Beh&#xE7;et's syndrome, tend to enlarge progressively and have a high risk of rupture, early surgical repair may reduce mortality and morbidity.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kusuyama</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamagishi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimada</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muro</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unruptured aneurysm of the sinus of valsalva with Be&#xE7;het's disease</article-title>
          <source>Circ J</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>108</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11999657</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Okada</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eishi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kitoh</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kosakai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isobe</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakano</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Huge aneurysm of the sinus of Valsalva following infective endocarditis in Be&#xE7;het's disease</article-title>
          <source>J Heart Valve Dis</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>179</fpage>
          <lpage>180</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9130128</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wakabayashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tawarahara</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurata</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aneurysms of all sinuses of Valsalva and aortic valve prolapse secondary to Be&#xE7;het's disease</article-title>
          <source>Eur Heart J</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>1766</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8922939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takach</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reul</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duncan</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooley</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Livesay</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ott</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sinus of Valsalva aneurysm or fistula: management and outcome</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>1573</fpage>
          <lpage>1577</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10585023</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kutay</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ekim</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yakut</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical repair of postoperative left sinus of Valsalva aneurysm dissecting into the interventricular septum</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>341</fpage>
          <lpage>343</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15620978</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goo</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bang</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Be&#xE7;het's disease combined with various types of fistula</article-title>
          <source>Yonsei Med J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>625</fpage>
          <lpage>628</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16259058</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harkness</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitton</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barreiro</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alejo</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gott</surname>
              <given-names>VL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baumgartner</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A 32-year experience with surgical repair of sinus of Valsalva aneurysms</article-title>
          <source>J Card Surg</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>198</fpage>
          <lpage>204</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15725151</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vural</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sener</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tasdemir</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bayazit</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Approach to sinus of Valsalva aneurysms: a review of 53 cases</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>71</fpage>
          <lpage>76</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11423277</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) Preoperative MD-CT showed a dilated left SVA with a huge aneurysm (An) compressing the left coronary artery. (B) Postoperative MD-CT showed patent left internal mammary (LIMA) and radial artery (RA) bypass grafts, with a regressed aneurysm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-48-883-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) The orifice of the aneurysm (Or) was observed at the left SVA, originating about 5mm from the left main coronary ostium, and was filled with organized mural thrombi. (B) The orifice of the aneurysm was closed with a patch (P), and then aortic valvuloplasty was performed.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-48-883-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
