<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vasc Health Risk Manag</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Vascular Health and Risk Management</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Vascular Health and Risk Management</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1176-6344</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1178-2048</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove Medical Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20531949</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2879292</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">vhrm-6-317</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Volumetric capnography: In the diagnostic work-up of chronic thromboembolic disease</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Moreira</surname>
            <given-names>Marcos Mello</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-vhrm-6-317">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-vhrm-6-317"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Terzi</surname>
            <given-names>Renato Giuseppe Giovanni</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-vhrm-6-317">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cortellazzi</surname>
            <given-names>Laura</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-vhrm-6-317">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Falc&#xE3;o</surname>
            <given-names>Antonio Luis Eiras</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-vhrm-6-317">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Junior</surname>
            <given-names>Heitor Moreno</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-vhrm-6-317">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Martins</surname>
            <given-names>Luiz Cl&#xE1;udio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-vhrm-6-317">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Coelho</surname>
            <given-names>Otavio Rizzi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-vhrm-6-317">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1-vhrm-6-317"><label>1</label>Department of Surgery</aff>
      <aff id="af2-vhrm-6-317"><label>2</label>Department of Internal Medicine, State University of Campinas, School of Medical Sciences, Campinas, Sao Paulo, Brazil</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1-vhrm-6-317">Correspondence: Marcos Mello Moreira, Rua Celso Eg&#xED;dio de Souza Santos, 181, Jardim Chapad&#xE3;o, CEP: 13070-057, Campinas, S&#xE3;o Paulo, Brazil, Tel +55 19 3241 9872, Fax +55 19 3521 7830, Email 
<email>tucammm@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Dove Press titles changed from ppub to collections in 2009.
								Fake ppub written to satisfy Coll Date Type=ppub-->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <fpage>317</fpage>
      <lpage>319</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2010 Moreira et al, publisher and licensee Dove Medical Press Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The morbidity and mortality of pulmonary embolism (PE) have been found to be related to early diagnosis and appropriate treatment. The examinations used to diagnose PE are expensive and not always easily accessible. These options include noninvasive examinations, such as clinical pretests, ELISA D-dimer (DD) tests, and volumetric capnography (VCap). We report the case of a patient whose diagnosis of PE was made via pulmonary arteriography. The clinical pretest revealed a moderate probability of the patient having PE, and the DD result was negative; however, the VCap associated with arterial blood gases result was positive. The patient underwent all noninvasive exams following admission to hospital and again eight months after discharge. Results gained from invasive tests were similar to those produced by image exams, highlighting the importance of VCap as an important noninvasive tool.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>pulmonary embolism</kwd>
        <kwd>pulmonary hypertension</kwd>
        <kwd>volumetric capnography</kwd>
        <kwd>d-dimers</kwd>
        <kwd>pretest probability</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Pulmonary embolism (PE) is the third most common cause of death in the United States, with an estimated 100,000 deaths and over 780,000 clinically apparent cases diagnosed annually.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-vhrm-6-317">1</xref> Results of autopsy studies have indicated that most cases of venous thromboembolism (VTE) go undiagnosed, even when they are the immediate cause of death. When PE is missed on initial presentation, a delay of 24 hours, during which anticoagulation occurs, increases the risk of recurrent embolism from 4% to 23%, and leads to a fivefold increase in the likelihood of death within a year.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-vhrm-6-317">2</xref> Traditional examinations used to detect PE are generally expensive and are not able to be carried out in all hospitals, which increases difficulty of access.</p>
    <p>In the search for a cost-effective screening approach to PE, ELISA D-dimer (DD) testing shows promise, often sparing patients unnecessary radiation and expense. However, DD has limitations, and gaining an understanding of these limitations in practice is vital. Additionally, measuring the volumetric capnography (VCap) associated with arterial blood gas analysis (ABGA), is an alternative to traditional examinations.</p>
    <p>In this case report we present the results of clinical score (Wells), DD (Vidas<sup>&#xAE;</sup>), and the VCap variables of a patient diagnosed with PE who was submitted for clinical treatment (dicoumarin). The DD, VCap, and image exams were conducted following admission to the hospital and again eight months after discharge (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1-vhrm-6-317">Table 1</xref>).</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>Our case study was a 25-year-old male smoker, who had symptoms of medium level dyspnea for one year. He was sent to a referral center for further investigation and underwent a transthoracic echocardiogram, which revealed &#x201C;straddling thrombus&#x201D;, or a moderate dilation of the chambers on the right side of the heart; additionally, his pulmonary artery systolic pressure was estimated at 78 mmHg and pulmonary artery diastolic pressure was estimated at 22 mmHg. Following the transthoracic echocardiogram, he was admitted to hospital based on a preliminary diagnosis of PE and treatment of anticoagulation with heparin was started.</p>
      <p>In the physical examination the patients was found to be in generally good health. He was conscious, alert, dyspneic (22 bpm), had cyanosis of the extremities, a heart rate 88, arterial pressure of 150/110 mmHg, and did not have edema or tightening of the lower limbs. A pretest (Wells&#x2019; score) revealed there was a moderate probability that the patient had PE. ABGA in room air revealed PaO<sub>2</sub> = 66.2; PaCO<sub>2</sub> = 28.9 mmHg; and SpO<sub>2</sub> = 98%.</p>
      <p>Pulmonary scintigraphy showed heterogeneous distribution of perfusion in both lungs.</p>
      <p>The ELISA DD levels were determined (VIDAS<sup>&#xAE;</sup> D-dimer; bioM&#xE9;rieux, France); this test has a cutoff of &lt;500 ng/mL. The sample taken on admission to the hospital was negative for PE (339.54 ng/mL; false-negative). The Doppler echocardiogram of the lower limbs showed no thrombi.</p>
      <p>Respiratory dead space and functional space were determined through VCap (CO<sub>2</sub>SMO PLUS 8100<sup>&#xAE;</sup>; Dixtal/Novametrix, Brazil) associated with ABGA (Radiometer ABL<sup>&#xAE;</sup> 700 Series; Radiometer Medical ApS, Denmark). The indices derived from these values were the end-tidal alveolar dead space fraction (AVDSf), the late dead space fraction (fDlate), and arterial-end-tidal CO<sub>2</sub> gradient [P(a-et)CO<sub>2</sub>] (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1-vhrm-6-317">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <p>After a history of more than two weeks of development and maintaining clinical and hemodynamic stability, we suspected repeated and extensive PE, but chemical thrombolysis did not show improvement. A pulmonary arteriogram revealed the patient had normal coronary arteries; ventriculography showed an ejection fraction of LV of 69%; important bulging in the abdominal region; amputation was present in peripheral branches, suggestive of multiple chronic emboli; and thrombus was located in the inferior lobe of the left lung, along with hypoperfusion of the middle segment in the lung right.</p>
      <p>Eight months after the patient was discharged, a new lung scintigraphy (control), ELISA DD, and VCap were carried out. In comparison with the first round of tests, this scintigraphy revealed a discreet improvement in the perfusion pattern in the apical, anterior, posterior, and superior segments of the patient&#x2019;s right lung. The DD result was 157.96 ng/mL. The ABGA in room air revealed PaO<sub>2</sub> = 70.0 mmHg, PaCO<sub>2</sub> = 30.0 mmHg, and SpO<sub>2</sub> = 99%.</p>
      <p>The association of VCap variables with ABGA allows for the calculation of several indices, the variations of which can infer the presence of occlusion or improve after treatment of pulmonary vessels.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-vhrm-6-317">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-vhrm-6-317">5</xref></p>
      <p>We determined the following parameters:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>AVDSf: PaCO<sub>2</sub> &#x2013; PetCO2/PaCO<sub>2</sub>;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-vhrm-6-317">6</xref></p></list-item><list-item><p>fDlate = PaCO<sub>2</sub> &#x2013; Pet(15% CPT)CO<sub>2</sub>/PaCO<sub>2</sub>;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-vhrm-6-317">7</xref></p></list-item><list-item><p>P(a-et)CO<sub>2</sub>: PaCO<sub>2</sub> &#x2013; PetCO<sub>2</sub>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-vhrm-6-317">8</xref></p></list-item></list></p>
      <p>The calculation of fDlate attempts to avoid differences introduced in the functional dead space value by height, gender, and age. The use of an estimated tidal volume also eliminates the effect of the respiratory rate on tidal volume. In addition, the mathematical extrapolation of phase III of the CO<sub>2</sub> expirogram at 15% of the total lung capacity (TLC) is aimed at bringing PetCO<sub>2</sub> and PaCO<sub>2</sub> into closer proximity. The TLC was obtained using the method devised by Grimby et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-vhrm-6-317">9</xref></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>When an episode of PE occurs, the imbalance in the ventilation/perfusion ratio is increased, and, consequently, the variables which form the functional dead space are altered. In the literature, we observe the following higher cut-off values for the studied variables: 0.15 for AVDSf,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-vhrm-6-317">6</xref> 0.12 for fDlate,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-vhrm-6-317">7</xref> and 5 mmHg for P(a-et)CO<sub>2</sub>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-vhrm-6-317">8</xref> Considering the fact that a higher calculated value indicates greater obstruction of the vascular system (and a larger alveolar dead space), we infer that there is a correlation between the extent of the area without perfusion and the value obtained.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-vhrm-6-317">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-vhrm-6-317">5</xref> In this patient, the result of VCap variations were displayed in imaging results.</p>
      <p>Breen et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-vhrm-6-317">10</xref> in a similar case report, albeit without follow-up and VCap, described a patient with acute PE with a similarly negative ELISA DD result (495.1 ng/mL). Ray et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-vhrm-6-317">11</xref> using the same methodology ELISA (VIDAS<sup>&#xAE;</sup>), obtained 12 false-negative results for patients with DVT or PE interned in emergency services. So, in rare cases where the symptoms are present over a long period of time, D-dimers might have become negative. However, results of our study show that there is an attenuate for this situation: the association of a clinical pre-test + DD with VCap. Again, it should be emphasized that the association of noninvasive exams is essential (enhance sensibility).</p>
      <p>It is known that when dealing with PE, anticoagulation is aimed at reducing the possibility of a new embolic phenomenon, as well as reducing the mortality risk. Therefore, imaging tests are requested whenever there is clinical suspicion of PE. In spite of the fact that the diagnostic work-up for chronic PE is not the same as that for acute PE, noninvasive methods that rule out the possibility of PE would reduce the number of patients unnecessarily undergoing imaging tests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>In summary, we have presented the case of a patient with diagnosis of PE, which was confirmed through imaging tests and with altered pulmonary functional variables obtained through VCap tests. These variables followed the results of image exams throughout clinical intervention, highlighting the importance of VCap as a potential noninvasive tool when used in association with measures of DD levels and clinical pretests. In rare situations, in patients with clinical pretest result suggesting moderate or high probability for PE, but with a negative DD result, an alternative test could be the VCap. Our results indicate it must be performed twice because in our case study the first time it paralleled the important vascular obstruction, and the second time it showed the absence of improvement. In this way we have demonstrated that VCap is a very interesting noninvasive tool to appreciate the vascular obstruction of a chronic thromboembolic disease.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This study received part of its funding in the form of a grant from the Funda&#xE7;&#xE3;o de Amparo a Pesquisa do Estado de S&#xE3;o Paulo (FAPESP, Foundation for the Support of Research in the State of S&#xE3;o Paulo; Grant no. 02/05252-3).</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Disclosures</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="b1-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Horlander</surname>
              <given-names>KT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mannino</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leeper</surname>
              <given-names>KV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary embolism mortality in the United States, 1979&#x2013;1998: an analysis using multiple-cause mortality data</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>163</volume>
          <fpage>1711</fpage>
          <lpage>1717</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12885687</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kline</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Runyon</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary embolism and deep venous hrombosis</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Marx</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hockberger</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walls</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Rosen&#x2019;s emergency medicine</source>
          <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>CV Mosby, Inc</publisher-name>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>1210</fpage>
          <lpage>1234</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moreira</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terzi</surname>
              <given-names>RGG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vieira</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pre and post-pulmonary thromboendarterectomies capnographic variables</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras Cir Cardiovasc</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>509</fpage>
          <lpage>512</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18488123</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moreira</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terzi</surname>
              <given-names>RGG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grangeia</surname>
              <given-names>TAG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paschoal</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Volumetric capnography as a noninvasive diagnostic procedure in acute pulmonary thromboembolism</article-title>
          <source>J Bras Pneumol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>328</fpage>
          <lpage>332</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18545830</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moreira</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terzi</surname>
              <given-names>RGG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carvalho</surname>
              <given-names>CHN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oliveira Neto</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paschoal</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alveolar dead space and capnographic variables before and after thrombolysis in patients with acute pulmonary embolism</article-title>
          <source>Vasc Health Risk Manag</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19436653</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rodger</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bredeson</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The bedside investigation of pulmonary embolism diagnosis study</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>166</volume>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16432086</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eriksson</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wollmer</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olsson</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis of pulmonary embolism based upon alveolar dead space analysis</article-title>
          <source>Chest</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <fpage>357</fpage>
          <lpage>362</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2752819</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fletcher</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jonson</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cumming</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brew</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The concept of deadspace with special reference to the single breath test for carbon dioxide</article-title>
          <source>Br J Anaesth</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6779846</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grimby</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>S&#xF6;derholm</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spirometric studies in normal subjects. III. Static lung volumes and maximum voluntary ventilation in adults with a note on physical fitness</article-title>
          <source>Acta Med Scand</source>
          <year>1963</year>
          <volume>173</volume>
          <fpage>199</fpage>
          <lpage>206</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Breen</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dorfman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary embolism despite negative ELISA D-Dimer: A case report</article-title>
          <source>J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>290</fpage>
          <lpage>292</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18468832</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11-vhrm-6-317">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ray</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bellick</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birolleau</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marx</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arock</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riou</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Referent D-dimer enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay testing is of limited value in the exclusion of thromboembolic disease: result of a practical study in an ED</article-title>
          <source>Am J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>313</fpage>
          <lpage>318</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16635704</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <table-wrap id="t1-vhrm-6-317" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>VCap variables in admission and follow-up</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>D-Dimer</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>AVDSf</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>fDLate</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
              <bold>P(a-et)CO</bold>
              <sub>
                <bold>2</bold>
              </sub>
              <bold>(mmHg)</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut-off</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;500 ng/mL</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Admission</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">339.54 ng/mL</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-8 months</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.96 ng/mL</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>
            <bold>Abbreviations:</bold>
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="tfn1-vhrm-6-317">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>AVDSf, (end-tidal) alveolar dead space fraction;</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="tfn2-vhrm-6-317">
          <label>&#x2020;</label>
          <p>Fdlate, late dead space fraction;</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="tfn3-vhrm-6-317">
          <label>&#x2021;</label>
          <p>P(a-et)CO<sub>2</sub>, arterial-end-tidal gradient of CO<sub>2.</sub></p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
