<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16479087</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2733970</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2006.21.1.172</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Giant Vascular Eccrine Spiradenoma: Report of a Case with Immunohistochemical Study</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ko</surname>
            <given-names>Joo Youn</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Chang Woo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Moon</surname>
            <given-names>Sang Ho</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Kang Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Chan Kum</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Dermatology, Hanyang University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>*</label>Department of Pathology, Hanyang University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address for correspondence: Chan Kum Park, M.D. Department of Pathology, Hanyang University Hospital, 17 Haengdang-dong, Sungdong-gu, Seoul 133-792, Korea. Tel: +82.2-2290-8250, Fax: +82.2-2296-7502, <email>parkcg@hanyang.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>21</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>172</fpage>
      <lpage>176</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2006 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We report a rare case of giant vascular eccrine spiradenoma (GVES) which developed in 56-yr-old Korean woman. It is a rare variant of eccrine spiradenoma (ES), which might be mistaken for angiomatous lesions in view of its florid vascularity and hemorrhagic features. Histogenesis of GVES is not clearly elucidated although it is known that ES presumably originates in the eccrine glands. To clarify the histogenesis of GVES, immunohistochemical stainings using various monoclonal antibodies were also performed. The tumor was composed of three types of cells, namely pale epithelial cells, small basal cells, and myoepithelial cells. Therefore, we conclude that GVES originated from eccrine gland and mainly differentiates toward secretory portion of secretory coil.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Giant Vascular Eccrine Spiradenoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Myoepithelial Cell</kwd>
        <kwd>Immunohistochemistry</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Giant vascular eccrine spiradenoma (GVES) is a rare highly vascular variant of eccrine spiradenoma (ES), as only four cases are reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Clinically, it might be mistaken for angiomatous lesions in view of its florid vascularity and hemorrhagic features. It is well known that tumor lobules are composed of two types of epithelial cells, namely small, dark staining basaloid cells located at the periphery and larger cells with a pale nucleus situated mostly in the center. However, cellular differentiation of GVES remains under discussion and the cells of which is composed are not clearly described. This tumor is considered to differentiate toward both the dermal duct and the secretory segment of the eccrine sweat gland like ES (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). This has been substantiated by the identification of occasional myoepithelial cells at the periphery of tubular structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). However, other authors have not found myoepithelial cells by ultrastuctural and histochemical studies. Furthermore, immunohistochemistry has failed to demonstrate myoepithelial differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). To clarify the nature of the cells of which is composed, we performed immunohistochemical stainings using various monoclonal antibodies for cytokeratins (CKs: CK, CK7, CK20, Cam5.2), epithelial membrane antigen (EMA), and carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA). Double-marker analysis was performed using p63 and smooth muscle actin (SMA) and triple-marker analysis was also performed using p63, SMA, and CK7.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 56-yr-old healthy woman had a solitary violaceous protruding mass on her lower back. The tumor had begun as a small soft nodule approximately 3 yr before, and had grown slowly. The patient had no other complaint except paroxysmal pain. Physical examination showed a 2 cm sized, erythematous to violaceous hemispheric firm nodule on the left side of the lower back (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). All laboratory findings were within normal limits. An excisional biopsy was performed with the clinical impression of a painful tumor of the skin such as angiolipoma or neuroma. There was no recurrence at the 12 months follow-up.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Methods</title>
        <p>The resected tumor was routinely processed for light microscopy. For immunohistochemistry, formalin-fixed paraffin embedded tissue sections (4 to 5 m thick) were used. The antibody panel for epithelial cells included CK (Immunotech, Marseille, France), CK7 (ScyTec, Logan, UT, U.S.A.), CK20 (Biomeda, Foster City, CA, U.S.A.), Cam5.2 (Becton-Dickinson, San Jose, CA, U.S.A.), EMA (Signet Laboratories, Dedham, MA, U.S.A.), and CEA (Immunotech). The antibody panel for nerve fibers included neurofilament (Signet), and S-100 protein (Signet). For characterize myoepithelial cells, we used monoclonal antibodies for SMA (Immunotech) and p63 (clone 4A4, Oncogene Research Products, Boston, MA, U.S.A.). Recently, p63 has been proposed as a specific marker of precursor/stem cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>) and &#x394;N-p63 is the predominant p63 isoform preferrentially expressed in the epithelial basal cells of organs such as the skin, breast, prostate and uterine cervix. It is also expressed in ductal structures of skin appendages and is also used as a marker of myoepithelial cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Clone 4A4 is a mouse monoclonal antibody obtained from mice hyperimmunized with an aminoterminal fragment of the &#x394;N-p63 isoform expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> as a GST fusion protein. Clone 4A4 also stained basal cells as well as myoepithelial cells.</p>
        <p>Double marker analysis was performed using monoclonal antibody for p63 and SMA to differentiate basal cells and myoepithelial cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Triple marker analysis using monoclonal antibody for p63, SMA, and CK7 was also performed to clarify three type of the cells ES is composed of, namely pale epithelial cells, small basal cells, and myoepithelial cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Histopathology</title>
        <p>The cut surface of the gross specimen showed hemorrhagic nature in some parts. Microscopic examination revealed one large well-circumscribed encapsulated lobule and a small satellite lobule involving the dermis and subcutis. Unlike usual ES, a lobule consisted of peculiarly abundant stroma and compressed cellular cords or sheets that were composed of two types of cells: cells with large pale nuclei in the center and basaloid cells with small, dark nuclei at the periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The stroma showed greatly dilated vascular spaces containing pale pinkish lymph fluid and red blood cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Marked edematous or hyalinized perivascular stroma and a sprinkling of lymphocytes among tumor cells were characteristic histologic findings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
        <p>The luminal large, pale epithelial cells were strongly positive for CK, CK7, Cam5.2, and EMA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>) and negative for CK20. The outer layer of small basaloid cells were strongly positive for p63 and negative for SMA, CK, CK7, Cam5.2, and EMA. In addition, many p63+/SMA+ myoepithelial cells were present among tubules and sometimes around tubules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). Compressed cords of tumor cells were mostly composed of myoepithelial cells although there were scattered abortive tubules which were clearly recognized on CK, CK7, Cam5.2, and EMA immunostaining. CEA was only positive in luminal borders, luminal secretions, and intercellular canaliculi.</p>
        <p>Based on the results of immunohistochemical findings, we concluded that the tumor was composed of pale epithelial cells, small basal cells, and myoepithelial cells. The tubules were composed of pale epithelial cells and small basal cells which were surrounded by the basement membrane with or without myoepithelial cells. These were clearly recognized on double- and triple-marker analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p>
        <p>S-100+/neurofilament+ compressed nerve fibers were present in the vicinity of the tumor lobules but not in the tumor lobules. Nerve fibers did not appear to be increased in number.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>GVES, first described by Cotton et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) in 1986, is a rare variant of ES. They report two cases of unusually large ES with marked degree of vascularity. Both were above 2 cm in size and histologically showed prominent blood-filled vascular spaces. This marked vascularity is an uncommon feature in sweat gland tumors and might suggest that this type of ES arise from a highly vascular region of the normal sweat gland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). As far as we know, this is the fifth case of GVES in the literature. The clinical features of the previously reported cases of GVES are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). All cases of GVES, including our case, had made a faulty clinical diagnosis of angiolipoma, angiosarcoma, malignant melanoma, neuroma, sebaceous cyst, or venous thrombosis. It is emphasized that this rare type of ES may result in the erroneous diagnosis of angiomatous lesions by both clinicians and pathologists because of the florid vascularity and hemorrhagic features.</p>
      <p>To clarify the histogenesis of GVES, we performed double- and triple-marker analysis. We found numerous p63+/SMA+ myoepithelial cells that were mostly arranged as compressing cellular cords or strands around edematous or hyalinized perivascular spaces or among tubules or ducts. Tubular structures were mostly composed of two types of epithelial cells, namely inner luminal (CK+/CK7+/Cam5.2+) and outer basal cells (p63+/SMA-) and had basement membrane. Some of the tubules were lined by myoepithelial cells. Normal intradermal and intraepidermal eccrine duct and ductal portion of eccrine secretory coil are lined by two types of epithelial cells, inner luminal cells (CK+/CK7-/Cam5.2-) and basal cells (p63+/SMA-) without myoepithelial cells and basement membrane. But secretory portion of eccrine secretory coil is composed of inner luminal cells (CK+/CK7+/Cam5.2+) and outer myoepithelial cells (p63+/SMA+) with basement membrane. Therefore, tubule or ducts seen in GVES did not strictly correspond to intradermal eccrine duct and ductal portion of secretory coil. Furthermore, findings of numerous myoepithelial cells and CEA+/EMA+ intercellular canaliculi support that GVES differentiates toward secretory portion of eccrine secretory coil (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p>
      <p>Therefore, we conclude that GVES is a rare benign tumor originated from eccrine gland and mainly differentiates toward secretory portion of secretory coil.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cotton</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slater</surname>
              <given-names>DN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rooney</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goepel</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mills</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Giant vascular eccrine spiradenomas: a report of two cases with histology, immunohistology and electron microscopy</article-title>
          <source>Histopathology</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>1093</fpage>
          <lpage>1099</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3023231</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hey</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grouls</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rockelein</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vascular eccrine giant spiradenoma-a case report with histology and immunohistology of a rare variant of benign sweat gland tumors</article-title>
          <source>Z Hautkr</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>444</fpage>
          <lpage>447</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2841813</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Senol</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozcan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sasmaz</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ciralik</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Giant vascular eccrine spiradenoma</article-title>
          <source>Int J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>221</fpage>
          <lpage>223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9556114</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirose</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immunohistochemical analysis of cytokeratin expression in eccrine spiradenoma: similarities to the transitional portions between secretory segments and coiled ducts of eccrine glands</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>131</volume>
          <fpage>799</fpage>
          <lpage>807</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7532000</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eckert</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Betke</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmoeckel</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neuweiler</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmid</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myoepithelial differentiation in benign sweat gland tumors. Demonstrated by a monoclonal antibody to alpha-smooth muscle actin</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Pathol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>294</fpage>
          <lpage>301</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1331211</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maiorana</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nigrisoli</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Papotti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immunohistochemical markers of sweat gland tumors</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Pathol</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>196</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3525625</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsujita-Kyutoku</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kiuchi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danbara</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuri</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Senzaki</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsubura</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>p63 expression in normal human epidermis and epidermal appendages and their tumors</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Pathol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>17</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12534798</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chilosi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zamo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brighenti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malpeli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Montagna</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piccoli</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pedron</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lestani</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inghirami</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scarpa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doglioni</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menestrina</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Constitutive expression of DeltaN-p63alpha isoform in human thymus and thymic epithelial tumours</article-title>
          <source>Virchows Arch</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>443</volume>
          <fpage>175</fpage>
          <lpage>183</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12851817</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krenacs</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laszik</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dobo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Application of immunogold-silver staining and immunoenzymatic methods in multiple labelling of human pancreatic Langerhans islet cells</article-title>
          <source>Acta Histochem</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2565643</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A 2 cm sized, erythematous to violaceous hemispheric nodule on the left side of lower back.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A large well-circumscribed encapsulated lobule in the dermis. The abundant stroma shows greatly dilated vascular spaces containing pale pinkish lymph fluid and red blood cells (H&amp;E, &#xD7;20).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tubules are lined by two types of cells: cells with large pale nuclei and basaloid cells with small, dark nuclei. A sprinkling of lymphocytes among tumor cells are found (H&amp;E, &#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Immunohistochemical staining for CK (<bold>A</bold>), CK7 (<bold>B</bold>), Cam5.2 (<bold>C</bold>), and EMA (<bold>D</bold>). The luminal large, pale epithelial cells are strongly positive and the outer layer of small basaloid cells are negative (&#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Double marker analysis shows that nuclei of outer basal cells (arrow-head) of tubules are positive for p63 (brown color), and spindle shaped myoepithelial cells (arrow) are both positive for p63 (nucleus, brown color) and SMA (cytoplasm, reddish brown color) (&#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-g005"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F6" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Triple marker analysis shows that tubules are lined by CK7+ inner luminal cells (arrow-head, reddish brown color) and p63+ basal cells (small-arrow, dark brown color), and there are many p63+/SMA+ myoepithelial cells (large-arrow, central nucleus is dark brown color and peripheral cytoplasm is blue color) (&#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-g006"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Clinical features of patients with giant vascular eccrine spiradenoma</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-i001"/>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
      <label>Table 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Results of immunohistochemical stainings in normal skin</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-i002"/>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="T3" position="float">
      <label>Table 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Results of immunohistochemical stainings in this tumor</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-21-172-i003"/>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
