<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Heart J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eurheartj</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">ehj</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>European Heart Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0195-668X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1522-9645</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18390871</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2519250</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehn089</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ehn089</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinical Vignettes</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Sudden cardiac death due to acute right heart failure in a patient with arrhythmogenic right ventricular dysplasia and acute myocardial infarction</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gattenl&#xF6;hner</surname>
            <given-names>Stefan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Demmer</surname>
            <given-names>Philipp</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Geissinger</surname>
            <given-names>Eva</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>M&#xFC;ller-Hermelink</surname>
            <given-names>Hans-Konrad</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff><institution>Institute of Pathology, University of W&#xFC;rzburg</institution>, <addr-line>Josef-Schneiderstr.2, W&#xFC;rzburg D-97080</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Tel: <phone>+49 931 201 47420</phone>, Fax: <fax>+49 931 201 47440</fax>, Email: <email>stefan.gattenloehner@mail.uni-wuerzburg.de</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>29</volume>
      <issue>17</issue>
      <fpage>2063</fpage>
      <lpage>2063</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Published on behalf of the European Society of Cardiology. All rights reserved. &#xA9; The Author 2008. For permissions please email: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">
          <license-p>The online version of this article has been published under an open access model. Users are entitled to use, reproduce, disseminate, or display the open access version of this article for non-commercial purposes provided that the original authorship is properly and fully attributed; the Journal, Learned Society and Oxford University Press are attributed as the original place of publication with correct citation details given; if an article is subsequently reproduced or disseminated not in its entirety but only in part or as a derivative work this must be clearly indicated. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A 40-year-old patient with toothache and shoulder pain for 10 days died without former known history of cardiac arrhythmias or myocardial infarction (MI) on sleep-related sudden cardiac death (SCD). The autopsy did not reveal signs for traumatic violence or intoxications nor for acute/chronic infections particularly of the upper aerodigestive tract. Furthermore, no aspects of endo-/myocarditis including negative results for cardiotropic virus were evident.</p>
    <p>In contrast, the right ventricular (RV) myocardium showed a diffuse replacement by fatty tissue (&gt;70%) and dystrophy of cardiomyocytes (Panel A, arrows indicate endocardium), corresponding to an arrhythmogenic RV dysplasia (ARVD) with immunohistochemical up-regulation of the cytoskeleton protein desmin (Panel A, inset) and electronmicroscopic detection of abnormal desmosomes (Panel B, arrowheads and inset). Moreover, the proximal right coronary arteria showed an isolated high-grade stenosis (&#x223C;80%) with acute subtotal thrombotic obliteration (Panel C, inset histological image) resulting in acute MIs of subendocardial RV myocardium (Panel D, hypereosinophilic cardiomyocytes without nuclei). Since any signs of backward failure of the left ventricle such as lung oedema were lacking, we diagnosed an SCD due to acute RV failure in a patient with ARVD and acute MI.</p>
    <p>ARVD is behind hypertrophic concentric cardiomyopathy the major non-ischaemic cause for SCD in association with sports activity in young patients (age &lt;40 years). Here, we describe, to our knowledge, the first case of an ARVD in combination with coronary heart disease/MIs, which might have triggered acute ventricular arrhythmias/failure independently from physical exertion and should be therefore considered for <italic>in vivo</italic>/autopsy investigations in family members of ARVD patients.</p>
    <p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by the Wilhelm-Sander-Stiftung and the foundation Fight against Cancer.</p>
    <p>
      <inline-graphic xlink:href="ehn08901.jpg"/>
    </p>
  </body>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
