<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yonsei Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Yonsei Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0513-5796</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1976-2437</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Yonsei University College of Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19718411</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2730625</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2009.50.4.585</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cholesterol Granuloma of the Tympanic Membrane Presenting as a Blue Eardrum</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Jang</surname>
            <given-names>Chul Ho</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jun Sung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>Yong Bum</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Otolaryngology, Chonnam National University Medical School, Gwangju, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Research Center for Resistant Cells, Chosun Medical School, Gwangju, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Corresponding author: Dr. Chul Ho Jang, Department of Otolaryngology, Chonnam National University Medical School, 8 Hak-dong, Gwangju 501-757, Korea. Tel: 82-62-220-6774, Fax: 82-62-220-6776, <email>chulsavio@hanmail.net</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>50</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>585</fpage>
      <lpage>587</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Copyright: Yonsei University College of Medicine 2009</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Intramembranous tympanic membrane cholesterol granuloma (CG) occurs infrequently. Here, the authors report a case of CG in the tympanic membrane presenting as a blue eardrum in the right ear. In addition, a pinhole perforation noted in the anterosuperior area revealed a brown discharge. High-resolution temporal bone CT showed a bulging mass shadow in the middle ear and a soft tissue dense lesion that filled both the epitympanum and mastoid cavity. Tympanomastoidectomy was performed under general anesthesia. New bone formation was confirmed in the mastoid antrum and epitympanum, and the epitympanum was blocked by new bone. The tympanic membrane revealed a round, brownish mass with a glistening surface and a severely thickened pars tensa. We herein report this case and review pertinent medical literature.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Cholesterol granuloma</kwd>
        <kwd>tympanic membrane</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Cholesterol granuloma (CG) of the middle ear typically presents as a conductive hearing loss and a blue eardrum, whereas those at the petrous apex either manifest as the side effects of bony erosion (with sensorineural hearing loss, tinnitus, vertigo, or cranial nerve impairment), or are incidentally identified.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> CG can be a perfectly localized and isolated mass in any pneumatized area in temporal bone, the middle ear cavity,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> mastoid antrum,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> external auditory canal,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> or the petrous apex,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> as has been found in as many as 12 - 20% of temporal bones with chronic otitis media.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> According to a histopathologic study, CG may be present in 12% of patients with chronic otitis media with an intact tympanic membranes, and in 21% of those with a perforated tympanic membrane.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> However, intramembranous tympanic membrane CG occurs less frequently, and only one case has so far been reported in the English literature.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref> Here, we report our experiences with a case of CG in the tympanic membrane and review relevant medical literature.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 42-year-old man presented with a history of childhood coalescent otitis media and, as consequent, hearing loss in the right ear. He complained of middle ear fullness without otalgia. A blue eardrum was identified at the local clinic. The patient was referred to our department. Otomicroscopic findings of the right tympanic membrane demonstrated a bulging blue eardrum. Two weeks after presentation, otomicroscopic findings showed a pinhole perforation in the anterior area with a brown discharge. A pure tone audiogram showed a dead ear on the right side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). High resolution temporal bone CT showed a bulging mass shadow in the middle ear and a dense soft tissue lesion, which filled both the epitympanum and mastoid cavity. New bone formation was noted between the epitympanum and middle ear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>), and bulging soft tissue in the middle ear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). No definite ossicular shadow was identified. Tympanomastoidectomy was performed under general anesthesia, and new bone formation was confirmed in the mastoid antrum and epitympanum, the latter of which was blocked by the new bone. No ossicular structure was identified in the epitympanum. The dead ear finding is believed to have been caused by a complication of childhood coalescent otitis media. After elevation of the tympanomeatal flap, the tympanic membrane revealed a round, brownish mass with a glistening surface and a severely thickened pars tensa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The incus and stapes were not identified. After removing the mass from the tympanic membrane, it was sent for pathological examination, which confirmed CG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Postoperatively, the patient had an uneventful course without any sign of blue eardrum recurrence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Three factors are considered to play an important role in the development of CGs: interference with drainage, hemorrhage, and ventilation obstruction,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref> although remaining mesenchyme<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref> and hematopoietic bone marrow<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> have also been suggested to be associated with CG formation.</p>
      <p>Clinically, CG of the temporal bone appears in three forms:<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref> in association with chronic otitis media (especially cholesteatoma), idiopathic hemotympanum, or a localized lesion in the middle ear, mastoid antrum, external auditory canal, and petrous apex. CG can also occur without any previous history of infection.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></p>
      <p>In the present case, the patient had a history of otitis media from childhood. Moreover, the bulging tympanic membrane had a pinhole perforation with brown discharge in the anterior pars tensa. CGs contain hemosiderin, lipids, and cholesterol crystals. Microscopically, these crystals are surrounded by foreign body giant cells in fibrous connective tissue, which is infiltrated by round cells.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></p>
      <p>Jaisinghani et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref> correlated pathologic findings of the tympanic membrane with pathologic changes in the middle ear cleft in cases with chronic otitis media in 150 temporal bones. They found a significant correlation between CG and tympanic membrane retraction and a mild additive effect when retraction was associated with perforation, however, the described case showed no tympanic membrane retraction. CG in the tympanic membrane has been rarely reported. In a recently published case, Haginomori et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref> reported histopathological characteristics of CG in the tympanic membrane, and speculated that, when hemorrhage occurs in the tympanic membrane, it is likely due to the absence of drainage or air exchange systems. On the other hand, when a CG develops in the tympanic membrane, it may promote its own growth in a vicious circle, by becoming another source of hemorrhage from small vessels whose numbers continue to increase.</p>
      <p>Park<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref> suggested that blue eardrum is an independent clinical entity, and found no bone changes with temporal bone CT or surgical findings. In the present case, however, temporal bone CT showed new bone formation in the epitympanum. Moreover, intraoperative findings indicated a complete attic block by new bone formation.</p>
      <p>This finding together with the resolution of blue eardrum indicate that the main reason for blue eardrum in the present case was CG at the tympanic membrane.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, we report a case of CG of the tympanic membrane, which presented as blue eardrum.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <p>This work was supported by the National Research Foundation (NRF) grant funded by the <funding-source>Korea government (MEST)</funding-source> through the <funding-source>Research Center for Resistant Cells</funding-source> (<award-id>R13-2003-009</award-id>).</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have no financial conflicts of interest.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brackmann</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toh</surname>
              <given-names>EH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical management of petrous apex cholesterol granulomas</article-title>
          <source>Otol Neurotol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>529</fpage>
          <lpage>533</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12170157</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miglets</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Booth</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholesterol granuloma presenting as an isolated middle ear tumor</article-title>
          <source>Laryngoscope</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>410</fpage>
          <lpage>415</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6257993</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoffman</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholesterol cyst manifesting a middle ear vascular tumor</article-title>
          <source>Am J Otolaryngol</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>68</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6534196</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Palva</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lehto</surname>
              <given-names>VP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnsson</surname>
              <given-names>LG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Virtanen</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xE4;kinen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large cholesterol granuloma cysts in the mastoid. Clinical and histopathologic findings</article-title>
          <source>Arch Otolaryngol</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>786</fpage>
          <lpage>791</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2415096</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Matt</surname>
              <given-names>BH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Myer</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
              <suffix>3rd</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bellet</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholesterol granuloma presenting the ear canal</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>672</fpage>
          <lpage>673</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2382940</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>da Costa</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paparella</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schachern</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kimberley</surname>
              <given-names>BP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Temporal bone histopathology in chronically infected ears with intact and perforated tympanic membranes</article-title>
          <source>Laryngoscope</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>1229</fpage>
          <lpage>1236</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1405982</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haginomori</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takamaki</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takenaka</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurisu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuji</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholesterol granuloma in the tympanic membrane</article-title>
          <source>Otol Neurotol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>1201</fpage>
          <lpage>1202</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16788430</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nager</surname>
              <given-names>GT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderveen</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholesterol granuloma involving the temporal bone</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>204</fpage>
          <lpage>209</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">773243</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nager</surname>
              <given-names>GT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Nager</surname>
              <given-names>GT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hyams</surname>
              <given-names>VJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholesterol granuloma</article-title>
          <source>Pathology of the ear and temporal bone</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
          <fpage>914</fpage>
          <lpage>939</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jackler</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A new theory to explain the genesis of petrous apex cholesterol granuloma</article-title>
          <source>Otol Neurotol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>96</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12544037</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miura</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sando</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orita</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirsch</surname>
              <given-names>BE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Histopathologic study of the temporal bones and Eustachian tubes of children with cholesterol granuloma</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>609</fpage>
          <lpage>615</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12126017</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alaminos</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gamboa</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prades</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Sade</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholesterol granuloma in the middle ear</article-title>
          <source>Basic aspects of the Eustachian tube and middle ear disease</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <conf-name>Conference on the Eustachian tube and middle ear disease</conf-name>
          <publisher-loc>Genova</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Kugler and Ghedini Publications</publisher-name>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>109</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leonetti</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shownkeen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marzo</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Incidental petrous apex findings on magnetic resonance imaging</article-title>
          <source>Ear Nose Throat J</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>200</fpage>
          <lpage>202</lpage>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>206</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11338643</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jaisinghani</surname>
              <given-names>VJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paparella</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schachern</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tympanic membrane/middle ear pathologic correlates in chronic otitis media</article-title>
          <source>Laryngoscope</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>712</fpage>
          <lpage>716</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10334219</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholesterol granuloma of the middle ear</article-title>
          <source>Middle ear diseases</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <publisher-loc>Seoul</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Academy'A</publisher-name>
          <fpage>53</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>The pure tone audiogram showing that the hearing level in the right ear had scaled out at all frequencies.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-50-585-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>High-resolution temporal bone CT findings of the middle ear and mastoid. (A) Temporal bone CT showing a dense soft tissue lesion filling both the epitympanum and mastoid cavity on the right side. New bone formation as a complication of childhood coalescent mastoiditis was noted. (B) Shows the bulging soft tissue in the middle ear.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-50-585-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>After elevation of the tympanomeatal flap, the inner surface of the tympanic membrane showed this round, brownish mass which had a glistening surface (arrow indicates) with severely thickened pars tensa at the posteroinferior quadrant.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-50-585-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Microscopic examination showing typical foreign body giant cells (arrows indicate) surrounding cholesterol crystals (Hematoxylin &amp; Eosin stain, &#xD7;100)</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-50-585-g004"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
