<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yonsei Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Yonsei Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0513-5796</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1976-2437</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Yonsei University College of Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19108030</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2628035</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2008.49.6.1036</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pleural Epithelioid Hemangioendothelioma</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Young Joo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>Moon Jae</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeong</surname>
            <given-names>Ki Cheon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hahn</surname>
            <given-names>Chang Hoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hong</surname>
            <given-names>Ki Pyo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Yee-Jeong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Yong Tai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Internal Medicine, National Health Insurance Cooperation Ilsan Hospital, Goyang, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Chest Surgery, National Health Insurance Cooperation Ilsan Hospital, Goyang, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Pathology, National Health Insurance Cooperation Ilsan Hospital, Goyang, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Reprint address: requests to Dr. Yong Tai Kim, Department of Internal Medicine, National Health Insurance Cooperation Ilsan Hospital, 1232 Baekseok-dong, Ilsandong-gu, Goyang 410-719, Korea. Tel: 82-31-900-0238, Fax: 82-31-900-0049, <email>ytkim@nhimc.or.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>49</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>1036</fpage>
      <lpage>1040</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2008 The Yonsei University College of Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Epithelioid hemangioendothelioma (EHE) is a rare tumor of vascular origin. While it can be found in any tissue, it is most often found in lung and liver and usually has an intermediate behavior. EHEs originating from pleural tissue have been less frequently described than those from other sites. Furthermore, to date, all of the cited pleural EHEs were described as highly aggressive. In the present report, we describe a rare case of pleural EHE extending to lung and bone in a 31-year-old woman. The histological diagnosis was confirmed by both conventional examination and immunohistochemistry. Her disease stabilized during the 4th course of adriamycin (45 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1-3), dacarbazine (300 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1-3) and ifosfamide (2,500 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1-3) with mesna, and she survived for 10 months after the diagnosis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Pleura</kwd>
        <kwd>epithelioid hemangioendothelioma</kwd>
        <kwd>immunohistochemistry</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Epithelioid hemangioendothelioma (EHE) is a rare tumor of vascular origin. Pulmonary epithelioid hemangioendothelioma (PEH) was first described in 1975 by Dail and Leibow and was originally termed "intravascular bronchioloalveolar tumor (IVBAT)".<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> Dail confirmed the vascular nature of the tumor and thus, in recent literature, the term PEH has been used in lieu of IVBAT. PEH has subsequently been recognized as the pulmonary counterpart of EHE occurring in other sites. EHE typically arises in variable locations such as the lung, liver, bone, soft tissue, skin, gastrointestinal tract, brain, mediastinum, spleen, breast, testis, thyroid, and heart.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> The tumor has a clinical course intermediate between benign hemangioma and angiosarcoma.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref> Its etiology is still unknown.</p>
      <p>EHEs originating from pleura have been less frequently described than those from other sites. The pleural EHE is more aggressive than others.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref> Here we describe an uncommon case of pleural EHE extending to the lungs and bone in a 31-year-old woman. To our knowledge, this is the first case of an EHE originating from pleura in Korea.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 31-year old woman was admitted to the hospital for upper back and radiating, bilateral shoulder pain of 5 months duration. She was a non-smoker and had no history of asbestos exposure. She complained of dull pain around the 5th vertebral body that was exacerbated in the upright position and relieved when supine. Physical examination and laboratory findings were unremarkable. A chest computerized tomography (CT) showed a nodular pleural thickening on the right side of the chest including a 1.5 cm-sized extrapleural tumorous lesion on the apicoposterior segment, several foci of subpleural nodular lesions on the right middle and lower lobes, and bone metastases affecting the 5th and 12th thoracic vertebral bodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). A bone scan showed a focally increased uptake at the level of the 5th thoracic spine, suggesting bone metastasis, and a linear uptake at the 7th left anterior rib that could not be ruled out as a possible bone metastasis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). A thoracoscopic wedge resection of the right lower lobe of the lung was performed. Grossly, the specimen consisted of a wedge of resected lung tissue measuring 5.0 &#xD7; 3.0 &#xD7; 2.5 cm with multiple scattered and variably sized subpleural whitish-tan plaques, at the largest diameter measuring 1.2 &#xD7; 1.0 &#xD7; 0.2 cm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Histologically, the tumor showed pleura-based intraparenchymal growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Microscopically, a hyalinized stroma surrounded the tumor cells. The epithelioid cells contained slightly pleiomorphic, rounded nuclei and scanty cytoplasm with prominent intracytoplasmic vacuoles. Few mitotic figures were observed. Hemorrhagic necrosis was evident and surgical margins were clear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Immunohistologically, the tumor cells were negative for cytokeratin, calretinin, desmin, and S-100 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>). However, the tumor cells showed diffuse strong positivity for &#x3B1;-SMA and vimentin, diffuse weak positivity for factor VIII and CD31 and focally weak positivity for CD34 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>). As a result of examination and laboratory findings, the patient was diagnosed with pleural epithelioid hemangioendothelioma with peripheral lung parenchymal invasion and multiple bone metastases to the spine. Palliative radiotherapy on the spine and chemotherapy with adriamycin (45 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1, every 3 weeks) were started as soon as the diagnosis was confirmed. When the progression of the disease was confirmed on the chest CT after the 3rd round of adriamycin chemotherapy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>), the regimen was switched to Mesna-Doxorubicin-Ifosfamide-Dacarbazine (MAID) to be administered every 4 weeks as an injection of adriamycin (45 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1 - 3), dacarbazine (300 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1 - 3) and ifosfamide (2,500 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1 - 3) with mesna. After the 2nd course of the MAID regimen, the chest CT showed stable disease, and patient's symptoms improved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). She continued to receive MAID chemotherapy and survived for 10 months after her diagnosis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The pleura is one of many anatomical sites of origin for EHE. EHE originating from the pleura is an extremely rare. To date, only 13 cases of pleural EHE have been reported in the English literature (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></p>
      <p>In many respects, pleural EHE differs from its pulmonary counterpart (PEH). According to the literature, pleural EHE affects symptomatic, older adult males, while PEH usually affects asymptomatic, young to middle-aged females.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref> All reported cases of diffuse pleural EHE were highly malignant and widely metastatic regardless of the fact that they took the form of an EHE tumor.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> Whereas PEH usually progresses slowly with intermediate behavior, pleural EHE has an aggressive clinical course and a poor prognosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></p>
      <p>The poor prognostic factors of PEH include the presence of respiratory symptoms or pleural effusion on chest radiography at presentation, extensive intravascular, endobronchial, or interstitial tumor spread, hepatic metastases, peripheral lymphadenopathy and the presence of spindle cells in the tumor.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref> Variable chemotherapeutic agents and radiotherapy regimens have been used in affected patients but showed no demonstrable therapeutic benefit. As the treatment of choice for PEH, a surgical excision of the nodules seems to be appropriate, although in asymptomatic patients no therapy can be considered.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref> However, in pleural EHE, a complete surgical resection is usually impossible. An effective treatment has not yet been established, although Pinet et al. reported a case of an aggressive form of pleural EHE with complete remission after treatment with carboplatine plus etoposide.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></p>
      <p>Differentiation of pleural EHE from PEH is important because prognosis and treatment depend on the tumor's location. A differential diagnosis can be made by a gross or radiologic examination on the presence or absence of a discrete nodular mass formation in subpleural lung parenchyma and a histological examination on an intravascular, intraalveolar, and intrabronchial growth pattern.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref></p>
      <p>In addition, the differential diagnosis of pleural EHE from a diffuse pleural carcinomatosis or mesothelioma should be given careful consideration due to their similar radiologic appearance. The diagnosis of EHE is suspected based on histological features and confirmed by immunohistochemistry. Positive staining with an anti-vimentin antibody and anti-factor VIII, BNH9, or anti-CD 31 antibodies confirms the diagnosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref> Anti-factor VIII and BNH 9 stain can highly distinguish endothelial cells from others. The negativity of anti-cytokeratin staining excludes tumors of an epithelial origin. This is imperative for pleural primitive tumors in order to exclude mesothelioma or carcinoma.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></p>
      <p>In this report we describe a patient who was diagnosed with pleural EHE confirmed by immunohistochemistry in the differential diagnosis of a unilateral pleural effusion. The patient sustained stable disease long-term and her symptoms improved after systemic chemotherapy with adriamycin, dacarbazine, and ifosfamide with mesna.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dail</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liebow</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gmelich</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friedman</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyai</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Myer</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intravascular, bronchiolar, and alveolar tumor of the lung (IVBAT). An analysis of twenty cases of a peculiar sclerosing endothelial tumor</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>452</fpage>
          <lpage>464</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6295602</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colby</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gown</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hammar</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mertens</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant vascular tumors of the serous membranes mimicking mesothelioma. A report of 14 cases</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1431</fpage>
          <lpage>1439</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8944035</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yousem</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hochholzer</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unusual thoracic manifestations of epithelioid hemangioendothelioma</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>463</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3105516</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pinet</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magnan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garbe</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Payan</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vervloet</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aggressive form of pleural epithelioid haemangioendothelioma: complete response after chemotherapy</article-title>
          <source>Eur Respir J</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>237</fpage>
          <lpage>238</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10489858</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crotty</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McAdams</surname>
              <given-names>HP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erasmus</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sporn</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roggli</surname>
              <given-names>VL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epithelioid hemangioendothelioma of the pleura: clinical and radiologic features</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>175</volume>
          <fpage>1545</fpage>
          <lpage>1549</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11090371</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Shraim</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahboub</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neligan</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chamberlain</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghazarian</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary pleural epithelioid haemangioendothelioma with metastases to the skin. A case report and literature review</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Pathol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>109</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15623498</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Livolsi</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brooks</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant epithelioid vascular tumors of the pleura: report of a series and literature review</article-title>
          <source>Hum Pathol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          <lpage>34</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10665909</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kitaichi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagai</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishimura</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Itoh</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asamoto</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Izumi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary epithelioid haemangioendothelioma in 21 patients, including three with partial spontaneous regression</article-title>
          <source>Eur Respir J</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>89</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9701420</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishak</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dail</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sweet</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enzinger</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epithelioid hemangioendothelioma and related lesions</article-title>
          <source>Semin Diagn Pathol</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <lpage>287</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3303234</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miettinen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindemayer</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaubal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endothelial cells markers CD31, C34 and BNH9 antibody to H and Y-antigens. Evaluation of their specificity and sensitivity in the diagnosis of vascular tumors and comparison with Von Willebrand factor</article-title>
          <source>Mod Pathol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>141</fpage>
          <lpage>149</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>On chest CT scan, the largest diameter of the extrapleural tumorous lesion on the apicoposterior segment is (A) 15 mm at initial diagnosis, (B) 30.7 mm after the 3rd adriamycin (45 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1, every 3 wks), and (C) 30.8 mm after the 2nd MAID regimen, administered every 4 wks as an injection of adriamycin (45 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1 - 3), dacarbazine (300 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1 - 3) and ifosfamide (2,500 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, day 1 - 3) with mesna.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-49-1036-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A bone scan at diagnosis shows a focally increased uptake (A) at the level of the 5th thoracic spine suggesting bone metastasis and (B) a linear uptake at the 7th left anterior rib that could not be ruled out as a potential metastasis.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-49-1036-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Photograph of a specimen of thoracoscopic wedge resection of the right lower lobe shows multiple scattered and variably sized subpleural whitish-tan plaques.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-49-1036-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Histological photographs of a lung specimen show (A) pleura-based intraparenchymal tumor growth (H &amp; E &#xD7;40) and (B) tumor cells surrounded by a hyalinized stroma with intracytoplasimic vacuolization (H &amp; E &#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-49-1036-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) Immunohistostaining shows diffuse negative reactivity with cytokeratin (&#xD7;200). (B) Immunohistostaining shows diffuse positive reactivity with factor VIII (&#xD7;200).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-49-1036-g005"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Case Reports of Pleural Epithelioid Hemangioendotheliomas Cited in the English Literature</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-49-1036-i001"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>M, male; F, female; NA, not available; LN, lymph node; CR, complete remission.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
