<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20409393</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2954527</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-1917</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1605.091917</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letters to the Editor</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Fluoroquinolone-Resistant Typhoid, South Africa</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Keddy</surname>
            <given-names>Karen H.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>Anthony M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sooka</surname>
            <given-names>Arvinda</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ismail</surname>
            <given-names>Husna</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oliver</surname>
            <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">National Institute of Communicable Diseases, Johannesburg, South Africa (K.H. Keddy, A.M. Smith, A. Sooka, H. Ismail)</aff>
        <aff id="aff2">University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg (K.H. Keddy, A.M. Smith, H. Ismail)</aff>
        <aff id="aff3">National Health Laboratory Service, Groote Schuur, Cape Town, South Africa (S. Oliver)</aff>
        <aff id="aff4">University of Cape Town, Cape Town (S. Oliver)</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: Karen H. Keddy, National Institute for Communicable Diseases, Enteric Diseases Reference Unit, Private Bag X4, Sandringham, Johannesburg 2131, South Africa; email: <email xlink:href="karenk@nicd.ac.za">karenk@nicd.ac.za</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>879</fpage>
      <lpage>880</lpage>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords: </title>
        <kwd>Bacteria</kwd>
        <kwd>Salmonella enterica Typhi</kwd>
        <kwd>fluoroquinolone resistance</kwd>
        <kwd>qnr genes</kwd>
        <kwd>typhoid</kwd>
        <kwd>South Africa</kwd>
        <kwd>letter</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><bold>To the Editor</bold>: <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serotype Typhi, the causal pathogen for typhoid, is a major public health hazard in many parts of the world, with an estimated 21.6 million cases of typhoid and 217,000 deaths occurring each year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Most isolates in South Africa are susceptible to quinolones, and fluoroquinolones remain the treatment of choice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>). The disease is primarily water or foodborne, but person-to-person spread is well recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Travelers to disease-endemic regions may be at risk for typhoid, which may result in the importation of strains of <italic>S.</italic> Typhi with unfamiliar or unusual resistance patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). Such infections present a challenge to local clinicians on optimal patient management.</p>
    <p><italic>S.</italic> Typhi was isolated from the blood culture of a woman 65 years of age from Cape Town; she had been in contact with a traveler to Bangladesh. The patient was treated first with ciprofloxacin, but this medication was changed to high-dose ceftriaxone combined with doxycycline for 8 days; she recovered well. Contact tracing indicated no family members had typhoid fever or carried the organism. The person who had traveled to Bangladesh was unavailable to provide further history or a stool specimen. No other potential source of infection could be elucidated: the patient lived in an urban area with safe water sources and shared meals with her family.</p>
    <p>The isolate was referred to the Enteric Diseases Reference Unit for confirmation of identification, serotyping (Kauffman-White scheme), and antimicrobial drug susceptibility testing using the Etest (bioM&#xE9;rieux, Marcy l&#x2019;&#xC9;toile, France) and agar dilution methods, according to criteria of the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (Wayne, PA, USA) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clsi.org">www.clsi.org</ext-link>). The isolate was resistant to ampicillin, chloramphenicol, sulfamethoxazole, nalidixic acid, and ciprofloxacin, but susceptible to ceftriaxone and tetracycline.</p>
    <p>Pulsed-field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) analysis was performed on the isolate, following the standard PulseNet protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). The PFGE pattern was compared with a database of <italic>S.</italic> Typhi PFGE patterns from South Africa by using BioNumerics version 6.01 software (Applied Maths, Sint-Martens-Latem, Belgium). The PFGE pattern of this isolate was 100% identical to pattern JPPX01.0026 in the Global PulseNet <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi Database. This pattern, which has been reported to PulseNet from India, Kenya, Tanzania, and Taiwan, is the most common pattern in the database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pulsenetinternational.org/projects/styphidatabase.asp">www.pulsenetinternational.org/projects/styphidatabase.asp</ext-link>); it is rarely seen in South Africa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>).</p>
    <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
      <label>Figure</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Dendrogram of pulsed-field gel electrophoresis patterns representative of the 15 largest clusters of <italic>Salmonella</italic> <italic>enterica</italic> serotype Typhi isolates identified in South Africa during 2005&#x2013;2009. The pattern of isolate 372460 is indicated. Scale bar represents percentage similarity of pathogens.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="09-1917-F"/>
    </fig>
    <p>PCR was used to isolate the quinolone resistance-determining region (QRDR) of <italic>gyrA</italic>, <italic>gyrB</italic>, <italic>parC,</italic> and <italic>parE</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). Genes were sequenced by using the BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) and an Applied Biosystems 3130 genetic analyzer. The QRDR DNA sequences were compared with those of <italic>S.</italic> Typhi strain Ty2 (GenBank accession no. AE014613). PCR also used to confirm the presence of <italic>qnrA</italic>, <italic>qnrB,</italic> and <italic>qnrS</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). Analysis for mutations in the QRDR of <italic>gyrA</italic>, <italic>gyrB</italic>, <italic>parC,</italic> and <italic>par</italic> found a single amino-acid mutation (Ser83 to Tyr) in g<italic>yrA</italic>. No amino acid mutations were identified in g<italic>yrB</italic>, <italic>parC</italic>, and <italic>parE</italic>. PCR for detection of <italic>qnr</italic> genes confirmed the presence of a <italic>qnrS</italic> gene, which was identified as the <italic>qnrS1</italic> variant by nucleotide sequence analysis.</p>
    <p>The efflux of quinolones from bacterial cells was investigated in the following manner. For nalidixic acid and ciprofloxacin, agar dilution MIC testing was performed in the absence and presence of 40 &#xB5;g/mL of the efflux pump inhibitor, Phe-Arg-&#x3B2;-naphthylamide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). In the presence of efflux pump inhibitor, the MIC to ciprofloxacin decreased from 4 &#xB5;g/mL to 1 &#xB5;g/mL, and the MIC to nalidixic acid decreased from &gt;512 &#xB5;g/mL to 32 &#xB5;g/mL, establishing the involvement of an efflux pump in conferring quinolone resistance.</p>
    <p>The mutation in g<italic>yrA</italic> (Ser83 to Tyr) confers reduced susceptibility to ciprofloxacin to a maximum MIC &#x2248;0.5 &#xB5;g/mL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>) and the QnrS1 protein confers reduced susceptibility to ciprofloxacin to a maximum MIC &#x2248;0.5 &#xB5;g/mL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>). We showed that a single amino acid mutation in <italic>gyrA</italic> (Ser83 to Tyr) with the QnrS1 protein and active efflux, conferred ciprofloxacin resistance, at least to an MIC level of 4 &#xB5;g/mL. Previously, Smith et al. reported quinolone resistance in South African isolates of <italic>S.</italic> Typhi mediated by mutations in <italic>gyrA</italic> and <italic>parC</italic> in combination with active efflux (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). We report <italic>qnrS1</italic> from <italic>S.</italic> Typhi, confirming the role of plasmid-mediated fluoroquinolone resistance in <italic>S.</italic> Typhi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>) and a fluoroquinolone- resistant strain in South Africa. Fluoroquinolone resistance is well recognized in Bangladesh; other researchers have described multidrug-resistant <italic>S.</italic> Typhi isolates imported from that country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>). Molecular epidemiology supports the conclusion that this strain likely originated in Bangladesh (L. Theobald, pers.comm.).</p>
    <p>In conclusion, fluoroquinolone-resistant typhoid fever is a reality in South Africa in patients who have a history of travel or contact with travelers. Blood cultures are mandatory to guide antimicrobial drug management. Plasmid-mediated fluoroquinolone resistance has implications for cotransference of resistance to the major antimicrobial agents used to treat typhoid fever and for the potential for rapid spread of fluoroquinolone resistance through <italic>S.</italic> Typhi strains in South Africa. The presence of fluoroquinolone-resistant typhoid fever could force a change in current treatment guidelines for this disease.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="citation">
        <p><italic>Suggested citation for this article</italic>: Keddy KH, Smith AM, Sooka A, Ismail H, Oliver S. Fluoroquinolone-resistant typhoid, South Africa [letter]. Emerg Infect Dis [serial on the Internet] 2010 May [<italic>date cited</italic>]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/EID/content/16/5/879.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/EID/content/16/5/879.htm</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Lisa Theobald and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, USA, for information on comparative PFGE patterns in the Global PulseNet <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi Database. We also thank George Jacoby for providing control strains for <italic>qnr</italic> PCR and Malcolm Cupido for providing information on tracing of the patient and of the patient&#x2019;s contacts.</p>
      <p>The following institutions have contributed PFGE patterns to the Global PulseNet <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi Database, with which our strain was compared: National Institute of Cholera and Enteric Diseases, Kolkata, India; Central Laboratories, Ministry of Health, Jerusalem, Israel; Taiwan Centers for Disease Control, Taipei, Taiwan; Research Institute for Tropical Medicine, Department of Health, Manila, the Philippines; China Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, China; Duke University&#x2013;Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Centre Collaboration, Moshi, Tanzania; University College Hospital, Galway, Ireland. This study was undertaken as part of the mandated responsibility of the Enteric Diseases Reference Unit of the National Institute for Communicable Diseases.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Crump</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luby</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mintz</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></string-name> <article-title>The global burden of typhoid fever.</article-title><source>Bull World Health Organ</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>346</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15298225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Group for Enteric Respiratory and Meningeal Disease Surveillance in South Africa</collab> GERMS-SA Annual Report 2008. <year>2009</year> [cited 2010 Mar 9]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nicd.ac.za/units/germs/annual/germssa_ann_report_2008.pdf">http://www.nicd.ac.za/units/germs/annual/germssa_ann_report_2008.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab> Background document: the diagnosis, treatment and prevention of typhoid fever. Geneva: The Organization, <year>2003</year></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kubota</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ackers</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brachman</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mintz</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Analysis of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serotype Typhi pulsed-field gel electrophoresis patterns associated with international travel.</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1205</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.43.3.1205-1209.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15750084</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ribot</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fair</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gautom</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cameron</surname> <given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hunter</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Swaminathan</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal/><article-title>Standardization of pulsed-field gel electrophoresis protocols for the subtyping of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7, <italic>Salmonella</italic>, and <italic>Shigella</italic> for PulseNet.</article-title><source>Foodborne Pathog Dis</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>67</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/fpd.2006.3.59</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16602980</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Govender</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keddy</surname> <given-names>KH</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Quinolone-resistant <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi in South Africa, 2003&#x2013;2007.</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>138</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>90</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268809990331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19563699</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hirose</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashimoto</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tamura</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kawamura</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ezaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sagara</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal/><article-title>DNA sequence analysis of DNA gyrase and DNA topoisomerase IV quinolone resistance&#x2013;determining regions of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar typhi and serovar paratyphi A.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>3249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.46.10.3249-3252.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12234852</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gunell</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webber</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kotilainen</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lilly</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caddick</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jalava</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/><article-title>Mechanisms of resistance in nontyphoidal <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> strains exhibiting a nonclassical quinolone resistance phenotype.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>3832</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00121-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19596880</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pfeifer</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matten</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rabsch</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></string-name> <article-title><italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhi with CTX-M beta-lactamase, Germany.</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1533</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1509.090567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19788837</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ackers</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Puhr</surname> <given-names>ND</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tauxe</surname> <given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mintz</surname> <given-names>ED</given-names></string-name> <article-title>Laboratory-based surveillance of <italic>Salmonella</italic> serotype Typhi infections in the United States: antimicrobial resistance on the rise.</article-title><source>JAMA</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>283</volume>:<fpage>2668</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>73</lpage> <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.283.20.2668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10819949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
