<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clinics (Sao Paulo)</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1807-5932</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1980-5322</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Hospital das Cl&#xED;nicas da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de S&#xE3;o Paulo</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20613943</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2898544</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1807-59322010000600014</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">cln_65p647</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letter to the Editor</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Distinctive Tomographic Abnormalities of the Craniocervical Region in a Patient with Osteogensis Imperfecta Type IV B</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kaissi</surname>
            <given-names>Ali Al</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cln_65p647">I</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-cln_65p647">II</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-cln_65p647"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Klaushofer</surname>
            <given-names>Klaus</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cln_65p647">I</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grill</surname>
            <given-names>Franz</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-cln_65p647">II</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="af1-cln_65p647"><label>I</label> Ludwig Boltzmann Institute of Osteology, Hanusch Hospital of WGKK and AUVA Trauma Centre Meidling, 4th Medical Department, Hanusch Hospital - Vienna, Austria</aff>
        <aff id="af2-cln_65p647"><label>II</label> Orthopaedic Hospital of Speising, Paediatric Department - Vienna, Austria</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1-cln_65p647">Tel.: 00 43 1 91021 86924, Email: <email>ali.alkaissi@osteologie.at</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>65</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>647</fpage>
      <lpage>649</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2010 Hospital das Cl&#xED;nicas da FMUSP</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Osteogenesis imperfecta is a clinically and genetically heterogeneous group of heritable disorders of connective tissue characterized by reduced bone mass (osteopenia) with associated bone fragility. The resulting skeletal manifestations are due to a generalized deficiency in the development of both membranous and endochondral bone and include markedly thin calvarium with delayed closure of the fontanelles and the sutures and excessive Wormian bone formation. Sillence et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cln_65p647">1</xref> developed a classification system of OI subtypes: OI type I, which is characterised by blue sclerae; perinatal lethal OI type II, also known as congenital OI ; OI type III, a progressively deforming subtype with normal sclera; and OI type IV, which is characterized by a normal sclera. Levin et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-cln_65p647">2</xref> have suggested that OI subtypes could be further divided into type A and B based on the absence or presence of dentinogenesis imperfecta. Basilar impression involves the upward (vertical) migration of the odontoid process into the foramen magnum with a depression in the cranium. Basilar impression is a developmental defect and refers to the infolding of the occipital condyles, an elevation of the clivus, and the posterior cranial fossa of the skull.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-cln_65p647">3</xref> The soft bones of the skull base allow for progressive infolding of the dysplastic clivus and translocation of the odontoid into the posterior fossa. The combination of platybasia and basilar impression can lead to severe distortion of the spinal cord and the anterior brain stem.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cln_65p647">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-cln_65p647">6</xref> The specific structures that can be involved include the upper cervical cord, medulla, pons, mid-brain, cerebellum, as well as the vertebrobasilar system.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CLINICAL REPORT</title>
      <p>Lateral skull radiographs showed significant frontal and occipital bossing, multiple wormian bones in the lambdoid suture associated with ill-defined skull base deformity and total loss of teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-cln_65p647">Figure 1</xref>). Anteroposterior skull radiograph showed excessive aeration of the frontal sinuses, osteopenia and total loss of teeth because of dentinogenesis imperfecta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-cln_65p647">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>Strikingly, 3D sagittal CT scan showed assimilation of the entire anterior arch of the atlas with the foramen magnum. The odontoid process was greater than 7.8 mm above Chamberlain's line* (a) associated with thinned and dysplastic clivus. Note the Wachenheim-Clivus line** (b) in our patient the line does not intersect and is not tangential to the odontoid process (this confirms the existence of marked craniocervical abnormalities). Severe platybasia associated with significant distortion of the anatomical relations of the posterior fossa. Note the persistence of dentocentral synchondrosis (arrow) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-cln_65p647">Figure 3</xref>). An Axial reformatted CT scan revealed clefting of the anterior arch of the atlas and dysplasia of the posterior arch (arrows). The odontoid was impacted between the synchondrosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-cln_65p647">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The modified Sillence system of classification differentiates OI into four types. Type I is marked by minor bone fragility and blue sclera, while type II is a lethal disorder. Type III consists of a group of sporadic cases that are mostly clinically and genetically heterogenous, and type IV has varying degrees of bone fragility with normal sclera. In general, OI type I is a purely qualitative collagen defect, whereas OI of type II, III, and IV are qualitative and quantitative alterations in collagen synthesis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cln_65p647">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-cln_65p647">3</xref> Levin et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-cln_65p647">2</xref> have proposed the addition of subtypes A and B to the modified Sillence classification system based on the absence or presence of dentinogenesis imperfecta, respectively. There have been a number of reports that have described the malformation complex in patients with OI type IVB. Engelbert et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-cln_65p647">7</xref> performed a questionnaire study to determine the prognosis of walking in patients with different types of OI. Interestingly, of 18 patients with OI type IV, 4 used wheelchairs. The mean age of the entire group was 11 years old. It should be noted, however, that basilar impression was neither screened for nor investigated in that study. Charnas and Marini<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-cln_65p647">9</xref> reported their experience neuroimaging in 31 cases of OI type IV. Two of these cases were characterized by basilar invagination, three cases had macrocephaly, and two cases involved ventricular enlargement. Sillence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cln_65p647">4</xref> recommended screening all patients with OI and particularly those with OI type IVB. He believes that basilar impression occurs with the highest frequency in patients with OI type IVB (patients with mild or moderate risk of fractures and normal scleras, but with dentinogenesis imperfecta). Most cases of basilar impression in patients with OI and or other forms of osteochondrodysplasias are probably due to the congenital bone malformation of the posterior fossa (primary basilar impression/invagination).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-cln_65p647">10</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-cln_65p647">13</xref> MacKenzie et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14-cln_65p647">14</xref> reported the sudden death of a patient with Marfan syndrome that was attributable to a primary type of basilar invagination. Secondary basilar impression, as seen in OI, results from abnormally soft bone that, in effect, slowly melts over the upright cervical spine, which progressively protrudes through the foramen magnum.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-cln_65p647">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cln_65p647">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-cln_65p647">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-cln_65p647">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-cln_65p647">13</xref></p>
      <p>Odontoid abnormalities have a reputation for being overlooked, resulting in a situation involving future instability and a potential risk for neurologic injury. Our present patient was characterized by a long odontoid/basilar impression associated with the persistence of axial synchondrosis. The localization and level of the axial synchondrosis is not only important as an anatomical detail but it is also extremely important from a clinical perspective due to odontoid fractures.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-cln_65p647">15</xref> The severe defective mineralization of the calvarium and its relevant osseous structures correlates directly with the development of basilar impression/basilar invagination and can cause serious distortion of the brainstem. Finally, we need to stress that the sagittal reconstruction image of a multidetector CT scan is a useful investigative modality for assessing the extent of osseous malformation in asymptomatic patients with OI who are at a high risk of progression. MRI images, however, serve as a reference to predict possible neurological symptoms and signs. Therefore, the optimal imaging strategy for a particular patient will depend on the accurate clinico- radiographic assessment of the individual&#x2019;s underlying pathology.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="b1-cln_65p647">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sillence</surname>
              <given-names>DO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Senn</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danks</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic heterogeneity in osteogenesis imperfects</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>110</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2-cln_65p647">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levin</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salinas</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jorgenson</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Classification of dentinogenesis imperfecta by dental characteristics</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>332</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">75372</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3-cln_65p647">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chamberlain</surname>
              <given-names>WE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Basilar impression/platybasia: Bizarre developmental anomaly of occipital bone and upper cervical spine with striking and misleading neurologic manifestations</article-title>
          <source>Yale J Biol Med</source>
          <year>1939</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>478</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4-cln_65p647">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sillence</surname>
              <given-names>DO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Craniocervical abnormalities in osteogenesis imperfecta. Genetic and molecular correlation</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Radiol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>427</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          <comment>Review</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7700720</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5-cln_65p647">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parker</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ell</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sillence</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Basilar impression complicating osteogenesis imperfecta type IV: the clinical and neurological findings in four cases</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>357</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6-cln_65p647">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Janus</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Engelbert</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beek</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goosken</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pruijs</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta in childhood. MR imaging of basilar impression</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Radiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12810217</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7-cln_65p647">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Engelbert</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uiterwaal</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gulmans</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pruijs</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Helders</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Osteogenesis imperfecta in childhood: prognosis for walking</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>397</fpage>
          <lpage>402</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10969267</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8-cln_65p647">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carson</surname>
              <given-names>GC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>LK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Radiologic diagnosis of traumatic occipitovertebral dissociation 2. Comparison of three methods</article-title>
          <source>AJR</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>162</volume>
          <fpage>887</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8141013</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9-cln_65p647">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Charnas</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marini</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Communicating hydrocephalus, basilar invagination, and other neurologic features in osteogenesis imperfecta</article-title>
          <source>Neurology</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>2603</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8255464</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10-cln_65p647">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al Kaissi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chehida</surname>
              <given-names>FB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghachem</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klaushofer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grill</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A hypoplastic atlas and long odontoid process in a girl manifesting phenotypic features resembling spondyloepimetaphyseal dysplasia joint laxity syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Skeletal Radiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>469</fpage>
          <lpage>73</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18256824</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11-cln_65p647">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al Kaissi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chehida</surname>
              <given-names>FB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gharbi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghachem</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varga</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klaushofer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Persistent torticollis, facial asymmetry, grooved tongue, and dolicho-odontoid process in connection with atlas malformation complex in three family subjects</article-title>
          <source>Eur Spine J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <issue>Supp 3</issue>
          <fpage>265</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17245565</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12-cln_65p647">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Menzes</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Specific entities affecting the craniocervical region: osteogenesis imperfecta and related osteochondrodysplasias: Medical and surgical management of basilar impression</article-title>
          <source>Childs Nerv Syst</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1169</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18401562</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13-cln_65p647">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crockard</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Basilar impression and osteogenesis imperfecta</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg Spine</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>594</fpage>
          <lpage>600</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18074683</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14-cln_65p647">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MacKenzie</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rankin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sudden death due to atlantoaxial subluxation in Marfan syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Am J Forensic Med Pathol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>369</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14634478</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15-cln_65p647">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garton</surname>
              <given-names>HJL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park Papadopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fracture dislocation of the neurocentral synchondrosis of the axis. Case illustration</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg Spine</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <fpage>350</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1-cln_65p647" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Lateral skull radiographs showed significant frontal and occipital bossing, multiple wormian bones in the lambdoid suture associated with ill-defined skull base deformity and total loss of teeth.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cln_65p647f1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2-cln_65p647" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Anteroposterior skull radiograph showed excessive aeration of the frontal sinuses, osteopenia and total loss of teeth because of dentinogenesis imperfecta.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cln_65p647f2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3-cln_65p647" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A sagittal CT scan showed assimilation of the entire anterior arch of the atlas with the foramen magnum. The odontoid process was greater than 7.8 mm above Chamberlain's line* (a) associated with thinned and dysplastic clivus. Note the Wachenheim-Clivus line** (b) in our patient the line does not intersect and is not tangential to the odontoid process (this confirms the existence of marked craniocervical abnormalities). Severe platybasia associated with significant distortion of the anatomical relations of the posterior fossa. Note the persistence of dentocentral synchondrosis (arrow). At this stage we planned for transoral odontoidectomy and posterior fixation of the occiput with the spinous processes of C2 &#x2013;C3. *Chamberlain's line joins the hard palate to the posterior lip of the foramen magnum. Basilar impression is defined as being present when the tip of the dens projects more than 5 mm above Chamberlain's line.3 **Wachenheim clivus line (a method to evaluate and assess craniocervical junction abnormality/injury), a line drawn along the posterior aspect of the clivus toward the odontoid process. An abnormality is suspected when this line does not intersect and or / not tangential to the odontoid process.8</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cln_65p647f3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4-cln_65p647" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>An axial reformatted CT scan revealed clefting of the anterior arch of the atlas and dysplasia of the posterior arch (arrows). The odontoid has been impacted between the synchondrosis</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cln_65p647f4"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
