<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id>
      <journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">1908508</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2118944</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">91341413</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The role of clonal selection in the pathogenesis of an autoreactive human B cell lymphoma</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>1991</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>174</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>525</fpage>
      <lpage>537</lpage>
      <permissions/>
      <abstract>
        <p>To study the association of autoimmunity and human B cell neoplasia, we have established a model of a B cell lymphoma which expresses a pathogenic autoantibody of defined specificity. The Ig VH gene expressed in this neoplasm was analyzed longitudinally using clinical specimens taken from the splenic lymphoma (S) at diagnosis and from lymph node relapses 3 and 4 yr later (N3 and N4). Southern analysis and oligonucleotide hybridization experiments demonstrated that clonally related predominant and minor tumor cell populations were present in S at diagnosis, and that the minor population became the predominant population in the relapse specimens, N3 and N4. Although the Ig specificity and idiotype were the same at diagnosis and at both relapses, analysis of the expressed VH gene sequences showed 14 base changes between S and N3, and 2 further changes at N4. Little sequence heterogeneity was observed at each sampling time, indicating that the ongoing mutation frequency was low. The relevant germline precursor VH gene was determined from autologous germline DNA and compared to the expressed genes. Based on the pattern of shared and unshared mutations, we were able to establish the genealogic relationship of the germline VH gene and the expressed clonotypes of S, N3 and N4. Taken together, the findings from Southern blotting, oligonucleotide hybridization, and sequence analysis permit us to describe a molecular aspect of tumor progression, "clonotypic shift", wherein subpopulations of the malignant clone, marked by different V gene clonotypes, emerge and predominate at different time points in the evolution of the lymphoma. Furthermore, the sequential and nonrandom pattern of the VH mutations, correlated with the observed conservation of autospecificity and idiotype, implies that clonal selection may have influenced the pathogenesis of the lymphoma.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
