<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Hepatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJHEP</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Korean Journal of Hepatology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1738-222X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2093-8047</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Association for the Study of the Liver</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21757989</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3304640</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3350/kjhep.2011.17.2.161</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Liver Pathology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cholangiocarcinoma arising in von Meyenburg complexes</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Hee Kyung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Jin</surname>
            <given-names>So-Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology, Soon Chun Hyang University Bucheon Hospital, Soon Chun Hyang University College of Medicine, Bucheon, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Soon Chun Hyang University Seoul Hospital, Soon Chun Hyang University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Corresponding author: So-Young Jin. Department of Pathology, Soon Chun Hyang University Seoul Hospital, 22 Daesagwan-gil, Yongsan-gu, Seoul 140-743, Korea. Tel. +82-2-709-9424, Fax. +82-2-790-5820, <email>jin0924@schmc.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>161</fpage>
      <lpage>164</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2011 by The Korean Association for the Study of the Liver</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>von Meyenburg complexes</kwd>
        <kwd>Cholangiocarcinoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Liver</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Von Meyenburg complexes (VMCs) are a rare incidental premortem finding. They are developmental defects, rather than a true neoplasm, that are found relatively frequently at laparotomy and necropsy. Although VMCs were originally reported to occur in only 0.6-0.7% of surgical and autopsy specimens,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref> a recent study of consecutive autopsies found that the incidence was approximately 5.6% in adults and 0.9% in children.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> The question of malignant transformation of hepatic VMCs is controversial.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> Malignant transformation of VMCs to intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma (CC) is very rare, with only 35 cases (including 5 Korean cases) described in the English literature to date.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref> Herein we report a case of intrahepatic CC arising from VMCs in an elderly man and a brief review of the pathologic findings is presented.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE SUMMARY</title>
      <p>A 66-year-old male was transferred to our hospital for the evaluation and treatment of a hepatic mass that was found during the preoperative workup for knee replacement surgery. This patient had been diagnosed with hypertension 20 years previously. The results of a physical examination were unremarkable, and those of liver function tests were normal with the exception of a high serum gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase level (307 IU/L). Serum alpha-fetoprotein and carcinoembryonic antigen levels were 6.5 ng/mL and 1.54 ng/mL, respectively, and he was negative for both hepatitis B surface antigen and antibody to hepatitis C virus. An abdominal computed tomography scan revealed two lobulated masses with a bulging contour on the right lobe that were distinct from each other. Given a suspicion of hepatocellular carcinoma, the patient submitted to a right liver lobectomy. At 10 months after the operation he was well, with no evidence of a tumor.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>PATHOLOGIC FINDINGS</title>
      <p>The resected portion of the right liver had dimensions of 16&#xD7;14&#xD7;7 cm and weighed 480 g. Centrally there was an ill-demarcated subcapsular mass intermingled with cystic and solid areas, measuring 7.0&#xD7;6.5&#xD7;5.0 cm; a surgical margin of at least 1.0 cm around the mass had been ensured. The cut surface of the solid part was pinkish-white and granular, without hemorrhage or necrosis. The cystic portion had spongiotic cut surfaces and ranged from 0.1 to 0.3 cm in diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Another lobulated subcapsular mass, measuring 1.5&#xD7;1.5&#xD7;1.0 cm, was circumscribed, yellow-tan, and firm. The remaining hepatic parenchyma was cirrhotic. Microscopically, most of the main tumor comprised multiple irregularly shaped and slightly dilated ducts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). These bile ducts were surrounded by dense fibrous connective tissue and occasional lymphocytes, typical of VMCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). The lining epithelium was a single layer of flattened cuboidal-to-columnar cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). The surrounding liver was affected by sweeping fibrosis, resulting in jigsaw-like micronodules, consistent with biliary cirrhosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). The epithelial cells possessed amphophilic cytoplasm and a basal round-to-ovoid nucleus.</p>
      <p>Multiple foci of dysplastic epithelium were found among the dilated bile ducts. These contained multiple regions of pseudostratified cells with enlarged nuclei and some apical snouts. Individual sections of dysplastic epithelia were hyperchromatic and had nuclei of various sizes with loss of polarity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Well to moderately differentiated infiltrative glandular or solid structures with desmoplastic stromal reactions were also evident (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Perineural invasion was present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Mitotic figures were seen occasionally, but no necrosis was observed. The characteristics of another mass was microscopically consistent with those of VMCs. The remaining liver parenchyma exhibited micro-/macronodular cirrhosis. Immunohistochemically, the VMCs, dysplastic foci, and carcinoma were positive for cytokeratin (CK)7 and CK19. The tumor cells were negative for hepatocyte antigen and CK20 staining. The carcinomatous area was focally positive and the VMCs were negative for p53. The Ki-67 labeling index was higher in solid areas of the CC exhibited than in the VMC and transitional areas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>VMCs were first described by von Meyenburg in 1918 as benign malformations of the hepatobiliary system. They may be found as isolated or multiple lesions. The nodular lesions vary in size from 0.1 to 1.5 cm in diameter, but lesions with diameters larger than 3 cm have also been described.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref> It can be argued that patients who have a large VMC or multiple VMCs and who are without life-threatening sequelae will have a correspondingly higher chance of developing hepatic carcinoma. However, few studies have found an association between the size or number of VMCs and the development of hepatic malignancy. Song et al suggest that the size of VMCs is a major factor in malignant transformation, and thus recommend regular follow-up to monitor any size increases in cases of large VMCs.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref> The present case presented with a 7.0-cm-sized solid, cystic mass, and the VMCs were larger than typical VMCs. Preoperatively, it was necessary to distinguish VMCs from other hepatic lesions such as metastatic liver tumor, true cysts, Caroli's disease, cystadenoma, cystadenocarcinoma, and liver abscess using radiologic techniques. However, the definitive diagnosis of VMCs can be made only after histological examination.</p>
      <p>The theory regarding the pathogenesis of VMCs postulates the presence of an arrest or disruption of hepatic ductal plate remodeling during the late phase of development of the intrahepatic biliary tree.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref> A malignant tumor arising from a preneoplastic lesion can be defined by observing a transition from the preneoplastic lesion to malignancy. For example, severe epithelial dysplasia frequently antedates the appearance of cancer in long-term cigarette smokers and patients with Barrett's esophagus. In the present case, transitional foci showing varying degrees of dysplasia and representing the progression from VMCs to malignant tumor were observed adjacent to CC foci. These observations indicate that VMCs may be a premalignant lesion of CC.</p>
      <p>The malignant transformation of VMCs to intrahepatic CC remains controversial.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref> Burns et al reported that long-standing cholestasis, dilatation, and hepatotoxin might play a role in bile duct carcinogenesis in patients with VMCs,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> and Jain et al provided evidence of the neoplastic transformation of VMCs.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> Since there are only a few reports in the literature documenting the existence of an association between VMCs and hepatic malignancy, further examination is needed to prove bile duct carcinogenesis in VMCs.</p>
      <p>The significant increase in the Ki-67 labeling index from benign VMCs through to hyperplasia or dysplasia and adenocarcinoma indicates that this index represents a useful adjunct for detecting preneoplastic lesions and malignant transition in VMCs.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref> In the present case, the Ki-67 labeling index was higher in solid areas of the CC than in the VMC and transitional areas.</p>
      <p>In summary, our case showed that intrahepatic CC occurring in association with VMCs develops either via an architectural transition of benign to dysplasia or carcinoma in situ, then to malignant glands of the biliary epithelium. This suggests that VMCs are associated with an increased risk of CC of the liver. However, confirmation that VMCs are precancerous lesions of intrahepatic CC requires the careful evaluation of a large number of patients.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thommesen</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biliary hamartomas (von Meyenburg complexes) in liver needle biopsies</article-title>
          <source>Acta Pathol Microbiol Scand A</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>93</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">696321</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karhunen</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Penttil&#xE4;</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liesto</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xE4;nnikk&#xF6;</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xF6;tt&#xF6;nen</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occurrence of benign hepatocellular tumors in alcoholic men</article-title>
          <source>Acta Pathol Microbiol Immunol Scand A</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>141</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3716801</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Redston</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wanless</surname>
              <given-names>IR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The hepatic von Meyenburg complex: prevalence and association with hepatic and renal cysts among 2843 autopsies [corrected]</article-title>
          <source>Mod Pathol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>237</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8685220</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarode</surname>
              <given-names>VR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdul-Karim</surname>
              <given-names>FW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Homer</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robert</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evidence for the neoplastic transformation of Von-Meyenburg complexes</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1131</fpage>
          <lpage>1139</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10935654</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burns</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuhns</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wieman</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholangiocarcinoma in association with multiple biliary microhamartomas</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>1287</fpage>
          <lpage>1299</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2174673</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>YW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>YK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case with intrahepatic double cancer: hepatocellular carcinoma and cholangiocarcinoma associated with multiple von Meyenburg complexes</article-title>
          <source>Yonsei Med J</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>506</fpage>
          <lpage>509</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10565264</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huh</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cholangiocarcinoma arising in von Meyenburg complexes: report of four cases</article-title>
          <source>Pathol Int</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>503</fpage>
          <lpage>512</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18705771</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xian</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma arising in multiple bile duct hamartomas: report of two cases and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>580</fpage>
          <lpage>584</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19282767</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Slone</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bova</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MR findings of multiple biliary hamartomas</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>161</volume>
          <fpage>581</fpage>
          <lpage>583</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8352110</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desmet</surname>
              <given-names>VJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Congenital diseases of intrahepatic bile ducts: variations on the theme "ductal plate malformation"</article-title>
          <source>Hepatology</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1069</fpage>
          <lpage>1083</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1398487</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Macroscopic findings of the right lobe of the liver. The cut surface exhibits an ill-defined mass intermingled with cystic and solid areas and measuring 7.0&#xD7;6.5&#xD7;5.0 cm, and another white nodule, located in the subcapsular region, measuring 1.5&#xD7;1.5&#xD7;1.0 cm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjhep-17-161-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Microscopic findings of von Meyenburg complexes (VMCs) and nonneoplastic liver tissue. Microscopically, the main tumor consists of a solid part (bottom right) and multiple irregularly shaped and slightly dilated ducts (A). These bile ducts are surrounded by dense fibrous connective tissue and occasional lymphocytes, typical of VMCs (B). The lining epithelium of the cysts is a single layer of multifocally flattened cuboidal-to-columnar cells (C). The nonneoplastic liver contains jigsaw-like micronodules separated by sweeping fibrosis, comparable to biliary cirrhosis (D) (A: hematoxylin and eosin (H-E), &#xD7;20; B: H-E, &#xD7;40; C: H-E, &#xD7;200, D: Masson's trichrome, &#xD7;40).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjhep-17-161-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Microscopic findings of cholangiocarcinoma. In the transitional area, pseudostratification, epithelial tufting with mild-to-moderate nuclear pleomorphism, and hyperchromasia are observed in the cysts (A). Well-to moderately differentiated cholangiocarcinoma with desmoplastic stromal reactions is evident in the solid area (B). Perineural invasion is present (C). The Ki-67 labeling index is higher in the solid cholangiocarcinoma area than in the VMC and transitional areas (D) (A: H-E, &#xD7;100; B: H-E, &#xD7;200; C: H-E, &#xD7;100, D: Ki-67, &#xD7;40).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjhep-17-161-g003"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
