<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Radiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J Radiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJR</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Korean Journal of Radiology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1229-6929</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2005-8330</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Society of Radiology</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24043981</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3772267</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3348/kjr.2013.14.5.829</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Neuroimaging and Head &amp; Neck</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Case Report</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Arachnoid Cyst in Oculomotor Cistern</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Min-Kyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Hyun Seok</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeun</surname>
            <given-names>Sin-Soo</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jung</surname>
            <given-names>So-Lyung</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ahn</surname>
            <given-names>Kook-Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Bum-soo</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Radiology, Seoul St. Mary's Hospital, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul 137-701, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Seoul St. Mary's Hospital, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul 137-701, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Corresponding author: Hyun Seok Choi, MD, Department of Radiology, Seoul St. Mary's Hospital, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, 222 Banpo-daero, Seocho-gu, Seoul 137-701, Korea. Tel: (822) 2258-1439, Fax: (822) 599-6771, <email>hschoi@catholic.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>829</fpage>
      <lpage>831</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 The Korean Society of Radiology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oculomotor cistern is normal anatomic structure that is like an arachnoid-lined cerebrospinal fluid-filled sleeve, containing oculomotor nerve. We report a case of arachnoid cyst in oculomotor cistern, manifesting as oculomotor nerve palsy. The oblique sagittal MRI, parallel to the oculomotor nerve, showed well-defined and enlarged subarachnoid spaces along the course of oculomotor nerve. Simple fenestration was done with immediate regression of symptom. When a disease develops in oculomotor cistern, precise evaluation with proper MRI sequence should be performed to rule out tumorous condition and prevent injury of the oculomotor nerve.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Arachnoid cyst</kwd>
        <kwd>Oculomotor nerve cistern</kwd>
        <kwd>Oculomotor nerve</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Oculomotor cistern is normal anatomic structure encasing oculomotor nerve in the cavernous sinus. Various diseases can develop in the oculomotor cistern and usually cause third nerve palsy. It is important to make precise preoperative diagnosis of the disease involving the oculomotor cistern by MR imaging with proper sequences to avoid injury of the oculomotor nerve. We report the first case, to the best of our knowledge, of a patient with an arachnoid cyst from the oculomotor cisterns treated with simple fenestration and drainage.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 29-year-old woman with progressive blurred vision and diplopia for 7 years was admitted for further evaluation. Ophthalmological examination revealed right oculomotor nerve palsy as ptosis and downward deviations in the right eye. In room light, pupils measured 6 mm in the right eye and 3 mm in the left eye.</p>
      <p>Orbit MRI was performed using 3.0T system (Magnetom Verio; Siemens Medical Solutions, Erlangen, Germany). T2-weighted axial MR images with heavily T2-weighted 3D turbo spin-echo sequence revealed a hyperintense lesion with an internal hypointense linear structure in the right orbital apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). No enhancement was noted on gadolinium enhanced T1 weighted axial image (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The internal structure revealed right oculomotor nerve within the cystic lesion, which continued into oculomotor cistern on oblique sagittal images with heavily T2-weighted 3D turbo spin-echo sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>).</p>
      <p>The patient underwent right sub-frontal craniotomy and the cystic lesion on prior MR images was shown after unroofing the optic canal. The cystic wall was fenestrated and high pressure cerebrospinal fluid -like fluid was drained. Microscopically, the cystic wall was lined by normal arachnoid membrane, representing arachnoid cyst (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). After the operation, she felt immediate regression of symptoms on the third nerve palsy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The oculomotor cistern (OMC) is arachnoid-lined dural cuff which contains the oculomotor nerve as it enters the cavernous sinus roof. After the oculomotor nerve enters the cavernous sinus, the OMC is gradually tapered and eventually terminates below the tip of the anterior clinoid process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Oculomotor nerve penetrates the orbital apex through the cavernous sinus and the superior orbital fissure.</p>
      <p>Various pathologic conditions such as schwannoma, cavernous hemangioma, lymphoma, lymphangioma, metastasis, dermoid and epidermoid rarely develop in the OMC. Tanriover et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>) reported a case of the schwannoma in the OMC, causing the oculomotor nerve palsy. Itshayek et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) reported another case of cavernous hemangioma of the oculomotor nerve, manifesting facial neuralgia. Diseases involving OMC usually manifest oculomotor nerve palsy due to their anatomic location as in reports previously mentioned.</p>
      <p>In general, OMC do not extend into orbital apex because the OMC terminates before reaching the superior orbital fissure. Conditionally, the OMC is able to extend to the orbital apex when the orbital apex syndrome occurs. Orbital apex syndrome is a disease from the orbital apex causing dysfunctions in the optic nerve (II), oculomotor nerve (III), trochlear nerve (IV), abducens nerve (VI), and ophthalmic branch of the trigeminal nerve (V1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Meningocele is one of pathologies involved in this area and have been reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>) which were usually meningoceles from optic nerve sheath.</p>
      <p>Here, we reported a case of arachnoid cyst arising from oculomotor cistern. Oculomotor cistern is covered by the arachnoid membrane within the dural cuff. Thus, the expansion of oculomotor cistern is able to manifest as dural ectasia or dilation of arachnoid space. In our case, the only arachnoid membrane lined OMC, seemed to be protruding into orbital apex while the dural cuff was terminated at intracranium proximal to orbital apex. It is also observed in type II extradural meningeal cyst with neural tissue at spine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). To the best of our knowledge, there were no reports about arachnoid cyst of oculomotor cistern at orbital apex.</p>
      <p>Arachnoid cysts are fluid-filled cavities within the arachnoid membrane. The symptoms of arachnoid cysts can vary depending on the location and the pressure on surrounding neural structures. So, the oculomotor nerve can be compressed by the arachnoid cyst along any location in its course. Ashker et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) reported a case of an arachnoid cyst compressing the oculomotor nerve in the right interpeduncular cistern. Also, Cheng et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) reported a case of the arachnoid cyst in cavernous sinus, causing deterioration of visual acuity. In most cases, it is sufficient that simple fenestration decompresses arachnoid cyst with decreasing pressure effects.</p>
      <p>When a disease occurs in the OMC, precise preoperative evaluation must be performed to prevent injury of the oculomotor nerve. MR with heavily T2-weighted 3D turbo spin-echo sequence can be useful to differentiate various pathologies in the OMC. And, if there is a cystic lesion with signal null on FLAIR image, arachnoid cyst must be included as differential diagnosis.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Everton</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rassner</surname>
              <given-names>UA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osborn</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harnsberger</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The oculomotor cistern: anatomy and high-resolution imaging</article-title>
          <source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>1344</fpage>
          <lpage>1348</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18417604</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martins</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasuda</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campero</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rhoton</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Microsurgical anatomy of the oculomotor cistern</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <issue>4 Suppl 2</issue>
          <fpage>ONS-220</fpage>
          <lpage>ONS-227</lpage>
          <comment>discussion ONS-227-228</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tanriover</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kemerdere</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kafadar</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muhammedrezai</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akar</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Oculomotor nerve schwannoma located in the oculomotor cistern</article-title>
          <source>Surg Neurol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
          <comment>discussion 88</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17210311</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Itshayek</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perez-Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Umansky</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spektor</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cavernous hemangioma of the third cranial nerve: case report</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>E653</fpage>
          <comment>discussion E653</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17881939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yeh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foroozan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Orbital apex syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>490</fpage>
          <lpage>498</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15523194</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>US</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unilateral optic nerve sheath meningocele presented with amblyopia</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr Ophthalmol Strabismus</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>48 Online</volume>
          <fpage>e65</fpage>
          <lpage>e66</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21800781</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lunardi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farah</surname>
              <given-names>JO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruggeri</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nardacci</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrante</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puzzilli</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgically verified case of optic sheath nerve meningocele: case report with review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurg Rev</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>201</fpage>
          <lpage>205</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9297723</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mesa-Guti&#xE9;rrez</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qui&#xF1;ones</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ginebreda</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Optic nerve sheath meningocele</article-title>
          <source>Clin Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>661</fpage>
          <lpage>668</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19668771</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shanmuganathan</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leatherbarrow</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ansons</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laitt</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bilateral idopathic optic nerve sheath meningocele associated with unilateral transient cystoid macular oedema</article-title>
          <source>Eye (Lond)</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>800</fpage>
          <lpage>880</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12439687</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khosla</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wippold</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
              <suffix>2nd</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CT myelography and MR imaging of extramedullary cysts of the spinal canal in adult and pediatric patients</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>178</volume>
          <fpage>201</fpage>
          <lpage>207</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11756120</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ashker</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weinstein</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dias</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanev</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonsall</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arachnoid cyst causing third cranial nerve palsy manifesting as isolated internal ophthalmoplegia and iris cholinergic supersensitivity</article-title>
          <source>J Neuroophthalmol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>197</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18769282</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>DY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiou</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intracavernous sinus arachnoid cyst with optic neuropathy</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Neurosci</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>267</fpage>
          <lpage>269</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20036550</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Findings of arachnoid cyst in oculomotor cistern on MR images and immunohistochemistry.</p>
        <p><bold>A.</bold> Axial MR image with heavily T2-weighted 3D turbo spin-echo sequence shows hyperintense lesion as arachnoid cyst (straight arrow) with internal oculomotor nerve (curved arrow) in right orbital apex. <bold>B.</bold> Gadolinum-enhanced T1-weighted MR image in axial plane reveals no enhancement of lesion (arrow). <bold>C.</bold> Oblique sagittal MR image with heavily T2-weighted 3D turbo spin-echo sequence reveals oculomotor nerve within lesion (curved arrow) which comes from interpeduncular cistern, passes through oculomotor cistern (between arrowheads), and continued with cystic lesion (straight arrow) in orbital apex. <bold>D.</bold> Immunohistochemical staining of surgical specimen with 400 high-power fields showed positive for epithelial membrane antigen, which is suggestive of arachnoid cyst.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjr-14-829-g001"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
