<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Korean Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23772166</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3678018</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2013.28.6.959</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Respiratory Diseases</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Case of Acute Pulmonary Embolism Associated with Dysplasminogenemia</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoo</surname>
            <given-names>Hongseok</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Hee-Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yi</surname>
            <given-names>Chin A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>Yoon Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Joung</surname>
            <given-names>Ji Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeong</surname>
            <given-names>Hyemin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>Kyeongman</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Medicine, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine and Genetics, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Radiology, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Address for Correspondence: Kyeongman Jeon, MD. Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Medicine, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, 81 Irwon-ro, Gangnam-gu, Seoul 135-710, Korea. Tel: +82.2-3410-3429, Fax: +82.2-3410-3849, <email>kjeon@skku.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>03</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>28</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>959</fpage>
      <lpage>961</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2013 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The incidence of pulmonary embolism (PE) rises markedly with age, and only a few cases have been reported in younger adults. Thrombophilia has been reported as one of the predisposing factors for PE in younger adults. Here we report an extraordinary case of PE complicated with dysplasminogenemia, a rare genetic disorder resulting in hypercoagulability, in a young male. An 18-yr-old male visited an emergency room in the United States complaining chest discomfort. He was diagnosed as PE with deep vein thrombosis without apparent risk factors. Anticoagulation therapy with warfarin had been initiated and discontinued after 6 months of treatment. After returning to Korea he was tested for thrombophilia which revealed decreased activity of plasminogen and subsequent analysis of PLG gene showed heterozygous Ala620Thr mutation. He was diagnosed with PE complicated with dysplasminogenemia. Life-long anticoagulation therapy was initiated. He is currently under follow-up without clinical events for 2 yr.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Deficiency</kwd>
        <kwd>Diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Plasminogen</kwd>
        <kwd>Pulmonary Embolism</kwd>
        <kwd>Venous Thromboembolism</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Acute pulmonary embolism (PE) is a common clinical problem, often with fatal consequences. The clinical presentation of PE is diverse, ranging from asymptomatic to hemodynamic deterioration. Most cases of PE arise from deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in the calf and about 80% of patients with PE have DVT at the time of presentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>).</p>
      <p>The incidence of PE increases significantly with age. However, it seldom occurs in patients younger than 20 yr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Various factors associated with PE such as smoking, immobilization, and malignancy have been identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). However, predisposing factors vary somewhat across age groups. Malignancy is rare in younger patients whereas they have a higher incidence of trauma compared to older patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p>
      <p>Plasminogen is a precursor of plasmin, which plays an important role in fibrinolysis by degrading fibrin clots. Few cases of plasminogen deficiency associated with DVT and PE have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>), and the association of plasminogen deficiency with thrombosis is controversial. Here we report an extraordinary case of PE complicated with dysplasminogenemia, a rare genetic disorder resulting in hypercoagulability, in a young male.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE DESCRIPTION</title>
      <p>An 18-yr-old Korean male high school student studying abroad visited an emergency department on 28 April 2009 in the United States complaining of sudden onset chest pain. The chest pain developed one hour before his visit to the emergency room and was localized to the anterior chest area. His vital signs included a blood pressure of 130/85 mmHg, pulse rate of 96 beats/min, respiratory rate of 20 breaths/min, and body temperature of 36.8&#x2103;. His hemoglobin was 16.3 g/dL, WBC count was 6,450/&#xB5;L (57.3% segmented neutrophils), and platelet count was 175,000/&#xB5;L. His prothrombin time and activated partial thromboplastin time were 0.98 (INR) (reference range 0.9-1.1) and 32.6 sec (reference range 29.1-41.9 sec), respectively. Electrocardiography showed a normal sinus rhythm without abnormal ST segment change. Chest radiography revealed no abnormality. However, the D-dimer level was elevated to 2.56 &#xB5;g/mL (reference range &lt; 0.5 &#xB5;g/mL).</p>
      <p>Suspicious of PE, the attending physician ordered a chest computed tomography (CT) scan and duplex ultrasonography of the lower extremity veins. The chest CT scan showed PE in left main pulmonary artery with parenchymal infarction and reactive effusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Deep vein thrombus was not visible on duplex ultrasound of the lower extremity veins. As he spent a considerable amount of time studying at a desk, the physician diagnosed him with PE associated with reduced mobility despite the lack of evidence for DVT. Anticoagulation therapy with warfarin was started. After six months of treatment, the anticoagulation treatment was discontinued as he had no risk factors for recurrent PE.</p>
      <p>Two months later, the patient returned to Korea and visited the outpatient clinic of Samsung Medical Center on 2 December 2009. Considering the patient's young age, the physician evaluated other risk factors for venous thromboembolism including genetic risk factors for thrombophilia. Protein C and S activity were normal. Anti-phospholipid antibody was absent. However, plasminogen activity was decreased to 59% (reference range 75%-112%). Under suspicion for plasminogen deficiency, a plasminogen gene (PLG) mutation test was performed. The test revealed a PLG mutation of heterozygous Ala620Thr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The patient's farther and mother were also screened for the PLG mutation and the mother was also positive for PLG mutation of Ala620Thr (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The patient was diagnosed with dysplasminogenemia with PLG mutation Ala620Thr heterozygosity causing venous thromboembolism. Life-long anticoagulation therapy was initiated, and the patient was followed up for 24 months without any clinical events before he returned to the U.S.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Most patients with acute PE have identifiable risk factors at the time of presentation. Common risk factors include immobilization, recent surgery, malignancy, and heart disease. Genetic disorders such as deficiencies in protein C, protein S, and homozygous factor V Leiden are also known to cause thromboembolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). However, in some cases, predisposing factors for PE and DVT cannot be identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Identifying predisposing factors for PE is important in deciding the treatment duration and modality and in implementing preventive strategies for recurrence.</p>
      <p>Plasminogen deficiency is a rare genetic disorder associated with thrombophilia. In dysplasminogenemia, despite a normal immunoreactive plasminogen level, functional activity is markedly decreased due to abnormalities in the variant PLG molecule (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). Dysplasminogenemia seems to be more prevalent in Asia. Estimated overall incidence of dysplasminogenemia in Korea and Japan is around 1.6%-3.87%, compared to 0.03% in Scotland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>). However, few cases of thrombosis related to dysplasminogenemia in relatively young patients have been reported in Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). In Korea, Song et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) reported that 8.3% of patients with DVT had dysplasminogenemia, suggesting it as a risk factor for thrombosis in the Korean population. However, in heterozygous dysplasminogenemia patients whose plasminogen activity is relatively higher than that of homozygous patients, no increase in risk of thrombosis was revealed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). In a subsequent population-based study from Japan, isolated dysplasminogenemia, whether heterozygous or homozygous, was not found to be a risk factor for thrombosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Therefore, routine screening for thrombophilia including plasminogen deficiency is not recommended in venous thromboembolism patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>).</p>
      <p>In this case, it was suspected that venous stasis due to a long period of sitting caused DVT and PE. Therefore, anticoagulation was halted after six months of treatment. However, anticoagulation treatment should be maintained throughout life in patients with a thrombophilic tendency. The appropriate diagnosis resulted in modification of the treatment and preventive strategy. Although the benefit of routine screening for dysplasminogenemia in patients with thromboembolism is still debatable, it may be reasonable to check for genetic disorders resulting in hypercoagulability as well as other known risk factors when assessing young patients with PE with or without DVT.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sandler</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Autopsy proven pulmonary embolism in hospital patients: are we detecting enough deep vein thrombosis?</article-title>
          <source>J R Soc Med</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>205</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2716016</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silverstein</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heit</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohr</surname>
              <given-names>DN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petterson</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O'Fallon</surname>
              <given-names>WM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melton</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
              <suffix>3rd</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trends in the incidence of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism: a 25-year population-based study</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>158</volume>
          <fpage>585</fpage>
          <lpage>593</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521222</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldhaber</surname>
              <given-names>SZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bounameaux</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary embolism and deep vein thrombosis</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>379</volume>
          <fpage>1835</fpage>
          <lpage>1846</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22494827</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dunn</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glassroth</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary embolism in younger adults</article-title>
          <source>Chest</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>1507</fpage>
          <lpage>1511</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1600765</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aoki</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moroi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakata</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoshida</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Abnormal plasminogen: a hereditary molecular abnormality found in a patient with recurrent thrombosis</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>1186</fpage>
          <lpage>1195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">659588</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tapson</surname>
              <given-names>VF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute pulmonary embolism</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>358</volume>
          <fpage>1037</fpage>
          <lpage>1052</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322285</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robbins</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Classification of abnormal plasminogens: dysplasminogenemias</article-title>
          <source>Semin Thromb Hemost</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>220</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2146745</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Okamoto</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakata</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mannami</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baba</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katayama</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuo</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasaka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minematsu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomoike</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyata</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Population-based distribution of plasminogen activity and estimated prevalence and relevance to thrombotic diseases of plasminogen deficiency in the Japanese: the Suita Study</article-title>
          <source>J Thromb Haemost</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>2397</fpage>
          <lpage>2403</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14629475</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schuster</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>H&#xFC;gle</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tefs</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plasminogen deficiency</article-title>
          <source>J Thromb Haemost</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>2315</fpage>
          <lpage>2322</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17900274</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of an Ala601Thr mutation of plasminogen gene in 3 out of 36 Korean patients with deep vein thrombosis</article-title>
          <source>J Korean Med Sci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>167</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12692411</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shigekiyo</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanazuka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aihara</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azuma</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohshima</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horie</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakahira</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takeichi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>No increased risk of thrombosis in heterozygous congenital dysplasminogenemia</article-title>
          <source>Int J Hematol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>247</fpage>
          <lpage>252</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11039677</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dalen</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Should patients with venous thromboembolism be screened for thrombophilia?</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>121</volume>
          <fpage>458</fpage>
          <lpage>463</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18501222</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Chest computed tomography of the patient. (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>) CT scan demonstrates acute pulmonary embolism of the left main pulmonary artery (arrow). (<bold>C</bold>) CT scan reveals parenchymal infarction (arrow) with reactive effusion (arrow head).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-28-959-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>The results of nucleotide sequencing analysis showing Ala620Thr mutation (red arrow) in the patient and his mother.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-28-959-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
