<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasitol Res</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Parasitology Research</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0932-0113</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-1955</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20922417</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3024497</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2093</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-010-2093-6</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Short Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cutaneus myxosporidiasis in the Australian green tree frog (<italic>Litoria caerulea)</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Szczepaniak</surname>
            <given-names>Klaudiusz</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>k.o.szczepaniak@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tomczuk</surname>
            <given-names>Krzysztof</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Studzi&#x144;ska</surname>
            <given-names>Maria</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Sub-Department of Parasitology and Invasive Diseases, Institute of Biological Bases of Animal Diseases, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Life Sciences, Akademicka 12, 20-033 Lublin, Poland </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>108</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>489</fpage>
      <lpage>492</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2010</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>This case is reported with the intention of highlighting the presentation of cutaneous myxosporidiasis in Australian tree frog (<italic>Litoria caerulea</italic>) caused by genus <italic>Myxobolus</italic>. The morphology and morphometric characteristic of the spores were determined using light microscopy and differential interference contrast microscopy. Spores were pyriform in shape in frontal view and oval in lateral view, and the average size was respectively 11.4 &#xD7; 6.0 &#xD7; 4.5 &#x3BC;m (12.1 &#x2212; 9.5 &#xD7; 6.3 &#x2212; 5.4 &#xD7; 5.0 &#x2212; 4.1 &#x3BC;m). To the best of our knowledge, this is the second case of skin invasion caused by myxosporeans in amphibians.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2011</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Myxosporidiasis are invasions caused by parasites <italic>Myxosporea</italic>. According to National Center for Biotechnology Information, they are currently classified as the <italic>Myxozoa</italic> and are closely related with phylum Cnidaria. These are intracellular organisms, which may be localized in the internal organs or on surface of the body. Over 2,180 species of <italic>Myxosporea</italic> belonging to approximately 60 genera have been described. Myxosporeans are common parasites of cold-blooded vertebrates, particularly fishes. Thus far, only 15 species were found in 83 representatives of the class amphibians, most of them in frogs and toads (Eiras <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2005</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Material and methods</title>
      <p>A single adult <italic>Litoria caerulea</italic> was delivered to Sub-Department of Parasitology and Invasive Diseases, University of Life Sciences in Lublin in order to diagnose skin lesions observed by the owner. The animal was bought about 2&#xA0;weeks earlier, in good condition, and without noticeable dermatological problems. According to medical history, the frog was in good condition all the time from purchase. It was the only animal in owner&#x2019;s collection. Detailed husbandry information such as cage temperature, humidity, water quality, and eating habits has been established. All these environmental parameters were generally appropriate for this species.</p>
      <p>Microscopic examination material from the lesions revealed a myxosporidian plasmodium containing numerous mature spores. Morphometric characteristics of the spores (based on 30 mature spores from the skin lesions of the examined frog) were determined with the aid of a light microscope with Screen Measurement package. The morphological details were established using a differential interference contrast microscopy (DIC).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p>The physical examination of the frog skin showed two types of lesions: a several-millimeter-sized, polymorphic, gray-white cyst with partially liquid-filled content and ulcers which, according to the owner, were the consequence of rupture of the primary cyst (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The lesions were located on the head, back, and legs of the frog. During routine examinations, other signs of the disease were not observed.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Photgraph showing the macroscopically visible lesions in the skin of <italic>Litoria caerulea</italic>. <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Primary lesions (<italic>black arrowhead</italic>). <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Ulcers on the skin (<italic>black arrowhead</italic>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="436_2010_2093_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>Spores were pyriform in shape in frontal view, and oval in lateral view, and the average size was respectively 11.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;6.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;4.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;m (12.1&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;9.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;6.3&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;5.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;5.0&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;4,1&#xA0;&#x3BC;m). Each spore contains two unequal polar capsule. The average size of the large polar capsule was 6.04&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.05&#xA0;&#x3BC;m (6.8&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;5.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.5&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;1.6&#xA0;&#x3BC;m), while the smaller one was 4.66&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.04&#xA0;&#x3BC;m (5.4&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;4.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.7&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;1.4&#xA0;&#x3BC;m). Inside the spore body, a sporoplasm with two nuclei and vacuoles were seen (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Based on the morphology of spores isolated from the examined <italic>L. caerulea</italic>, the lesions on the skin were the consequence of myxosporean invasion from the genus <italic>Myxobolus</italic>.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>The spores of <italic>Myxobolu</italic>s sp. isolated from the skin of <italic>Litoria caerulea</italic>. <bold>a</bold> Differential interference contrast microscopy (DIC). <bold>b</bold> Fresh isolated spores from skin lesions in light microscope</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="436_2010_2093_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Line diagram of <italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp. spores isolated from <italic>Litoria caerulea</italic> skin according to a differential interference contrast microscopy (DIC). <bold>a</bold> Frontal view, <bold>b</bold> lateral view</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="436_2010_2093_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>Six genera of <italic>Myxosporea</italic> have been described from amphibians (<italic>Myxobolus, Myxidium, Hoferellus, Chloromyxum, Caudomyxum,</italic> and <italic>Spherospora</italic>) which were mainly observed in the gonads, deferent ducts, oviducts, kidneys, urinary bladder, ureter, gallbladder, and liver. Only two genera have been described in genus <italic>Litoria. Myxidium</italic> and <italic>Myxobolus</italic> species cause many pathological changes in the liver, gallbladder, bile ducts, and in the gonads (Eiras <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2005</xref>). There are three reports on the occurrence of <italic>Myxosporea</italic> in the Australian tree frog (<italic>L. caerulea</italic>). Delvinquier et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1992</xref>) described <italic>Myxidium immersum</italic> in the gallbladder in 32 species of tree frogs belonging to genus <italic>Litoria</italic> including <italic>L. caerulea</italic>. Hill et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1997</xref>) found trophozoites of <italic>Myxidium</italic> sp. in the bile ducts of several farmed Australian tree frogs with associated hepatitis. According to these authors, pathological changes in the liver and bile ducts could lead to the death of the host. Zwart has observed pathological effects of <italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp. in <italic>L. caerulea</italic> ovary (Sitj&#xE0;-Bobadilla <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2009</xref>). So far, only one report has described cutaneus myxosporidiasis in amphibians. Guy&#xE9;not and Naville (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1922</xref>) described species of <italic>Myxobolus ranae</italic> infecting the skin of the anuran <italic>Rana temporaria</italic> in Switzerland. Skin diseases caused by <italic>Myxosporea</italic> are common in fish. Cutaneus myxosporidiasis in fish are usually caused by species belonging to genera <italic>Myxobolus</italic> (<italic>Myxobolus squamae, Myxobolus ellipsoides, Myxobolus sandrae,</italic>and <italic>Myxobolus cotlani</italic>), <italic>Spherospora (Spherospora carassii</italic> and <italic>Spherospora molnari</italic>), <italic>Thelohanellus</italic> (<italic>Thelohanellus dogieli</italic>), and <italic>Henneguya</italic> (<italic>Henneguya wolinensis).</italic> It seems that most myxosporeans occurring in amphibians are characterized by little host specificity. Several species of <italic>Myxosporea</italic> were observed infecting several host species often living in separate geographical land (Eiras <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2005</xref>; Sitj&#xE0;-Bobadilla <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2009</xref>). However, there are no reports about the presence in amphibian species of myxosporeans occurring in fish or reptiles.</p>
      <p>To the best of our knowledge, this case is only the second reported case of cutaneus myxosporidiasis in amphibians. Location and morphometric characteristics of the spores isolated from the skin lesions of described Australian tree frog do not fit into any of the known species of the genus <italic>Myxobolus</italic> found so far in amphibians (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). We can conclude that the present material represents a species not yet described.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Members of the genus <italic>Myxobolus</italic> isolated from amphibians (Eiras <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2005</xref>; Sitj&#xE0;-Bobadilla <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2009</xref>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Species</th><th>Host</th><th>Geographic location</th><th>Parasite location</th><th>The shape of the spores</th><th>The size of the spores (&#x3BC;m) length, width, and thickness</th><th>The size of polar capsule (&#x3BC;m)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Myxobolus bufonis</italic></td><td><italic>Bufo regularis</italic></td><td>Egypt</td><td rowspan="2">Testes, kidneys liver, gallbladder</td><td rowspan="2">Disk-shaped</td><td rowspan="2">9.2&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;8.9&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;4.0</td><td rowspan="2">4.1&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;3.2</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bufo maculatus</italic></td><td>Cameron</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Myxobolus chimbuensis</italic></td><td><italic>Litoria darlington</italic></td><td rowspan="2">New Guinea</td><td rowspan="2">Testes</td><td rowspan="2">Ovoid</td><td rowspan="2">11.9&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;8.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;6.2</td><td rowspan="2">4.7&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.2</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Litoria thesaurensis</italic></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myxobolus fallax</italic></td><td><italic>Litoria fallax</italic></td><td>Australia</td><td>Testes</td><td>Ovoid</td><td>13.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;9.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;6.8</td><td>4.2&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.4</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myxobolus hylae</italic></td><td><italic>Hyla aurea</italic></td><td>Australia</td><td>Testes, oviduct, kidneys</td><td>Oval, egg-shaped</td><td>13.9&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;9.1&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;7.2</td><td>4.2&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.6</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp.</td><td><italic>Bufo regularis</italic></td><td>Togo</td><td>Testes</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp.</td><td><italic>Ptychadena maccarthyensis</italic></td><td>Togo</td><td>Testes</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp.</td><td><italic>Litoria caerulea</italic></td><td>Australia</td><td>Ovaries</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp.</td><td><italic>Litoria infrafrenata</italic></td><td>Indonesia</td><td>Testes, ovaries</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp.</td><td><italic>Litoria leuseri</italic></td><td>Indonesia</td><td>Ovaries</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myxobolus ranae</italic></td><td><italic>Rana temporaria</italic></td><td>Switzerland</td><td>Skin</td><td>Ovoid</td><td>11.1&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;8.1</td><td>4.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp.</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Litoria caerulea</italic></td><td rowspan="2">Poland</td><td rowspan="2">Skin</td><td rowspan="2">Pyriform</td><td rowspan="2">11.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;6.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;4.5</td><td>4.66&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.04</td></tr><tr><td>6.04&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.05</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>We do not know what really had happened to the invasion in the described Australian tree frog because little is known about the life cycles of myxosporeans in amphibians. Most of the available knowledge about the details of the development of these parasites is based on the disease caused in fishes. It is possible that anurans may become infected in aquatic environment (as tadpoles or as adults) in a similar way as the fishes, either by oral route or through the skin. This mode of infection by <italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp. in the Australian tree frog seems to be possible because this species spends most of its adult life in the treetops outside the water environment.</p>
      <p>There are various reports on the pathology of myxosporean invasions in amphibians. Some species seem to be not pathogenic like <italic>Chloromyxum salamandrae</italic> which has been isolated from the gallbladder from healthy salamanders (<italic>Eurycea multiplicata griseogaster</italic>, <italic>Eurycea multiplicata</italic> and <italic>Eurycea neotenes</italic>) (Upton et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1995</xref>). Myxozoan infection associated with host reproductive system and gonads reduce fertility (Browne et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2002</xref>; Mubarak and Abed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2001</xref>; Upton et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">1992</xref>). The most serious symptoms and pathological changes, which could lead to the death of the host, were associated with hepatic and renal myxosporidiasis (Duncan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2004</xref>; Mutschmann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1999</xref>). Lesions of the skin caused by myxospreans seem to have relatively the lowest health consequences for amphibians. During this invasion, we have observed only the skin lesions with no clear impact on the general condition of the animal.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Browne</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scheltinga</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pomering</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahony</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testicular myxosporidiasis in anurans, with a description of Myxobolus fallax n. sp</article-title>
          <source>Syst Parasitol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>110</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1015609513809</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12075129</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Delvinquier</surname>
              <given-names>BLJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Markus</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Passmore</surname>
              <given-names>NI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Myxidium lesminteri</italic> n. sp. (Myxosporea: Myxidiidae) from the gall-bladder of three southern African Anura</article-title>
          <source>Syst Parasitol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>25</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00008005</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duncan</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garner</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bartholomew</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reichard</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nordhausen</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Renal myxosporidiasis in Asian horned frogs (<italic>Megophrys nasuta</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>J Zoo Wildl Med</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>381</fpage>
          <lpage>386</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1638/03-048</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15526894</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eiras</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An overview on the myxosporean parasites in amphibians and reptiles</article-title>
          <source>Acta Parasitol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>267</fpage>
          <lpage>275</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guy&#xE9;not</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naville</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sur une myxosporidie (<italic>Myxobolus ranae</italic> n. sp.) et une microsporidie parasites de <italic>Rana temporaria</italic></article-title>
          <source>Rev Suisse Zool</source>
          <year>1922</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>425</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hill</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grenn</surname>
              <given-names>PE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lucke</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hepatitis in the green tree frog (<italic>Litoria caerulea</italic>) associated with infection by a species of <italic>Myxidium</italic></article-title>
          <source>Aust Vet J</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>910</fpage>
          <lpage>911</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.1997.tb11266.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9469229</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mubarak</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abed</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Morphopathological changes of the testicular tissue of Egyptian toad, <italic>Bufo regularis</italic> (Amphibia, Bufonidae) infected with <italic>Myxobolus</italic> sp. (Myxozoa, Myxobolidae)</article-title>
          <source>Acta Parasitol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          <lpage>118</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mutschmann</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A new myxozoan, <italic>Chloromyxum careni</italic> sp. n. (Myxosporea: Chloromyxidae) from the kidney of <italic>Megophrys nasuta</italic> Schlegel, 1858 (Anura: Pelobatidae) from Indonesia</article-title>
          <source>Acta Protozool</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sitj&#xE0;-Bobadilla</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Can myxosporean parasites compromise fish and amphibian reproduction?</article-title>
          <source>Proc R Soc B</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>276</volume>
          <fpage>2861</fpage>
          <lpage>2870</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2009.0368</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474043</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Upton</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freed</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freed</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McAllister</surname>
              <given-names>ChT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldberg</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testicular myxosporidiasis in the flat-backed toad, <italic>Bufo maculatus</italic> (Amphibia: Bufonidae), from Cameroon, Africa</article-title>
          <source>J Wildl Dis</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>326</fpage>
          <lpage>329</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1602591</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Upton</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McAllister</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trauth</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A new species of <italic>Chloromyxum</italic> (Myxozoa: Chloromyxidae) from the gall bladder of <italic>Eurycea</italic> spp. (Caudata: Plethodontidae) in North America</article-title>
          <source>J Wildl Dis</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>394</fpage>
          <lpage>396</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8592363</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
