<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15119664</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3015526</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Appendiceal Enterobius Vermicularis Infestation Associated With Right-Sided Chronic Pelvic Pain</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nackley</surname>
            <given-names>Anna C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>University of South Florida College of Medicine, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Division of Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, Tampa, Florida, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nackley</surname>
            <given-names>James J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>II, MD</degrees>
          <aff>University of South Florida College of Medicine, Division of Digestive Diseases and Nutrition, Tampa, Florida, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Yeko</surname>
            <given-names>Timothy R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>University of South Florida College of Medicine, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Division of Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, Tampa, Florida, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gunasekaran</surname>
            <given-names>Sivaselvi</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Tampa General Hospital, Department of Pathology, Tampa, Florida, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address reprint requests to: Timothy R. Yeko, MD, <addr-line>University of South Florida College of Medicine, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Division of Reproductive Endocrinology and Infertility, 4 Columbia Dr, Ste 529, Tampa, FL 33606, USA</addr-line>. Fax: <fax>813 259 8593</fax>, E-mail: <email>tyeko@hsc.usf.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Apr-Jun</season>
        <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>171</fpage>
      <lpage>173</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2004 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jsls-8-2-171.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Parasitic infestation is an uncommon cause of chronic pelvic pain among women of reproductive age. A case of chronic right-sided pelvic pain associated with appendiceal <italic>Enterobius vermicularis</italic> infestation was managed with appendectomy and antiparasitic therapy resulting in a complete resolution of symptoms.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Appendiceal <italic>Enterobius vermicularis</italic> infestation</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Chronic pelvic pain is a common complaint among women of reproductive age often due to infection, endometriosis, or adhesive disease. However, parasitic infection with resultant pain is usually not considered in the differential diagnosis. We report a case of chronic right lower quadrant abdominal and pelvic pain associated with appendiceal <italic>Enterobius vermicularis</italic> infestation that resolved after appendectomy and antiparasitic therapy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>METHODS AND RESULTS</title>
      <p>A 35 year-old, white, nulligravid female presented to the University of South Florida complaining of 2-years duration of chronic pelvic pain, particularly on the right side. The pain was not associated with her menses and was said to be intermittent in nature. She also complained of right-sided pain with intercourse. She denied any weight loss, gastrointestinal complaints, or irritation of the vulva, vagina, or anus. She reported no recent travel outside of the country and had no pets at home. Her gynecologic history was significant for laparoscopy 2 years prior for a left ovarian cyst.</p>
      <p>A left salpingo-oophorectomy was performed at that time, and there was no note of endometriosis. She reported regular menses and normal pap smears. Prior treatment with oral contraceptive pills and nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs provided no relief. On physical examination, her abdomen was soft and nontender. Her pelvic examination revealed normal external genitalia with tenderness in the right adnexa, but no appreciable masses or nodularity. A laparoscopy was then performed and right pelvic side wall adhesions involving the appendix were discovered <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>)</bold>. The adhesions were thin and filmy and easily lysed. A normal right tube and ovary were appreciated, and there was still no evidence of endometriosis. The appendix was noted to be full and a laparoscopic appendectomy was performed.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Appearance of appendix during laparoscopy.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-8-2-171-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Pathology reported a specimen measuring 6 cm long with a diameter of 0.5 cm. Fibrous adhesions were noted near the distal end. A nematode was discovered in the appendiceal lumen consistent with <italic>E. vermicularis</italic>
<bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>)</bold>. The patient was treated with a single tablet of mebendazole (Vermox) 100 mg orally, with a second dose given 2 weeks later. Postoperative follow-up at 2 weeks and at 4 months posttreatment revealed complete resolution of her pain.</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histologic slide of nematode in appendiceal lumen.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-8-2-171-g02"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p><italic>E. vermicularis</italic> or pinworm is a common parasitic infection that is found mostly in the pediatric population. The life cycle of this parasite starts with the ingestion of the eggs, which then hatch in the small intestine where the adult worm resides and mates. The female <italic>E. vermicularis</italic> then migrates down to and out of the rectum and deposits her eggs on the perianal skin. The majority of adult patients are asymptomatic; however, symptoms of <italic>E. vermicularis</italic> infestation can include perineal puritis, weight loss, vulvovaginitis, and chronic salpingitis. <italic>E. vermicularis</italic> has been documented on pap smears and throughout the genital tract including endometrium, fallopian tube, as well as in granulomas involving the ovary and pelvic peritoneum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> Presumably, in these uncommon circumstances, the female worm travels from the anus to the vagina and ascends the genital tract all the way into the pelvic cavity.</p>
      <p>In 1939, Botsford<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> reported a small series of patients presenting with complaints of chronic right lower quadrant abdominal pain, similar to our case, who were found to have appendiceal <italic>Enterobius</italic> infestation on pathological examination of the appendix. In 2 more recent surgical series,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref></sup> performed outside of the United States, the incidence of Enterobius infestation was low and commonly associated with an appendix that appeared normal. Less commonly, the appendix specimen showed acute and chronic inflammatory changes and peritoneal granulomas and periappendiceal adhesive disease, as in our case. Although these studies demonstrated the importance of pathological identification of nematodes and their oocytes, to make a specific diagnosis, they did not emphasize the need for any systemic therapy, as they considered appendectomy as curative.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> In a recent report from the gynecological literature,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> the pathological specimen from a hysterectomy case for chronic pelvic pain demonstrated the surprise finding of acute and chronic salpingitis due to <italic>E. vermicularis</italic> infestation of the fallopian tube. This same patient had an appendectomy 5 years earlier for <italic>E. vermicularis</italic>-related appendicitis. It was not clear in this case whether the tubal infestation was caused by local spread from the infested appendiceal stump at the time of surgery or had later spread via a transperineal route to her upper genital tract. This case clearly demonstrates the importance of eradicating the entire reservoir of <italic>E. vermicularis</italic> from the gastrointestinal tract, even after appendectomy.</p>
      <p>The treatment of <italic>E. vermicularis</italic> infection involves one dose of pyrantel pamoate 11 mg/kg, or mebendazole 100 mg orally with a second dose in 2 weeks to treat possible reinfection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></sup> It is also recommended that family members be treated to eliminate asymptomatic reservoirs.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>The differential diagnosis for chronic pelvic pain includes pelvic infection, endometriosis, adhesive disease, or gastrointestinal pathology. Nematode infestation of the appendix as a cause of chronic right-sided pelvic pain is an uncommon diagnosis, which should be considered when the more common etiologies have been ruled out. This particular patient had no identifiable risk factors for parasitic infection, the diagnosis being made only after microscopic examination of the appendix. Appendiceal nematode infestation manifested by gynecologic complaints, although rare, can occur and can be easily treated.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Meehan</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Enterobius granulomas of the uterus, ovary and pelvic peritoneum. Two case reports</article-title>. <source>Br J Obstet Gynaecol</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6704354</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botsford</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>HW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pinworm and appendicitis</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1939</year>;<volume>221</volume>:<fpage>933</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>936</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Appendicitis and Enterobius vermicularis</article-title>. <source>Scand J Gastroenterol</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1853157</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herd</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Histological audit of acute appendicitis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pathol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>456</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1597528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yandell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Zandt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Enterobius vermicularis salpingitis: a distant episode from precipitating appendicitis</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>553</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1495735</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Riper</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pyrantel pamoate for pinworm infestation</article-title>. <source>Am Pharm</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8456745</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
