<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24068139</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3760943</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20131958</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Circumscribed palmoplantar hypokeratosis: report of two Brazilian
cases<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Hipoqueratose circunscrita palmoplantar: relato de 2 casos
brasileiros</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rocha</surname>
            <given-names>Lilian Kelly</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nico</surname>
            <given-names>Marcello Menta Simonsen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> MD; Department of Dermatology, Medical School, University of S&#xE3;o Paulo,
S&#xE3;o Paulo, Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> MD, PhD; Department of Dermatology, Medical School, University of S&#xE3;o
Paulo, S&#xE3;o Paulo, Brazil.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">MAILING ADDRESS: Lilian Kelly F L Rocha, Av. Dr. En&#xE9;as de Carvalho
Aguiar, 510 - Pinheiros, 05403-000 - S&#xE3;o Paulo - SP, Brazil. E-mail:
<email>lilianrocha@me.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Aug</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>623</fpage>
      <lpage>626</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Circumscribed palmoplantar hypokeratosis is a recently recognized dermatosis and
rarely reported. It was first described in 2002 and is characterized by localized
loss of the horny layer in the palmoplantar area. This dermatosis is clinically
presented with a sharply circumscribed, reddish and asymptomatic plaque with slightly
depressed surface localized on the palms or the soles. The clinical differential
diagnosis includes mainly porokeratosis and Bowen's disease. Its pathogenesis remains
unknown, but studies have proposed a human papillomavirus induced disease or a
localized keratinization disorder in the palmoplantar area. We report herein two
cases of patients with lesions clinically and microscopically compatible with the
diagnosis of circumscribed palmoplantar hypokeratosis. We also present a brief
literature review of the etiopathogenic hyphoteses of this dermatosis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>A hipoqueratose palmar circunscrita &#xE9; uma condi&#xE7;&#xE3;o rara e pouco conhecida que foi
caracterizada apenas em 2002. Caracteriza-se por uma perda circunscrita e focal da
camada c&#xF3;rnea das regi&#xF5;es palmares ou plantares. Clinicamente, observam-se les&#xF5;es
avermelhadas, circunscritas, arredondadas, discretamente deprimidas e assintom&#xE1;ticas,
nas palmas ou, mais raramente, nas plantas. A diagnose diferencial cl&#xED;nica &#xE9; feita
principalmente com a poroqueratose palmoplantar e com a disqueratose de Bowen. Sua
patog&#xEA;nese &#xE9; desconhecida, havendo especula&#xE7;&#xF5;es sobre poss&#xED;vel origem viral ou de
altera&#xE7;&#xE3;o localizada da express&#xE3;o de citoqueratinas das regi&#xF5;es palmoplantares.
Relatamos os casos cl&#xED;nicos de duas doentes femininas com les&#xF5;es cl&#xED;nicas e
altera&#xE7;&#xF5;es histopatol&#xF3;gicas caracter&#xED;sticas de hipoqueratose palmar circunscrita de
evolu&#xE7;&#xE3;o cr&#xF4;nica, al&#xE9;m de uma breve revis&#xE3;o da literatura sobre as hip&#xF3;teses
etiopatog&#xEA;nicas desta dermatose.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Bowen's disease</kwd>
        <kwd>Keratins</kwd>
        <kwd>Porokeratosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Circunscribed circumscribed palmoplantar hypokeratosis was initially described by Perez
et al in 2002 and is characterized by a nummular, circumscribed, depressed, reddish and
asymptomatic plaque, commonly located over the thenar and hypothenar eminences of the
palm.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref></sup>It rarely occurs in the
plantar region. It affects adults or elderly patients, with higher prevalence in
females. Histopathology shows sharp decrease in the stratum corneum without changing the
dermis or the surrounding tissue and the absence of local inflammation. While analyzed
by electronic microscopy, it typically presents vacuolization of corneocytes.</p>
      <p>There are some etiopathogenic hypotheses for the appearance of the lesions, as trauma,
papilloma virus infection types 4 and 6, keratinizing disorder localized to the granular
and horny layers, reduction of keratin 9 and connexin 26 expression at the lesional
epidermis and increase of keratin 16 expression associated with reduction of keratin 2e
expression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B06">6</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Palmoplantar hypokeratosis can clinically mimic palmoplantar psoriasis, porokeratosis
and Bowen's disease, but there's no report of malignant lesions.</p>
      <p>The disease course is chronic and there is no need for treatment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Case 1: Female patient, 68 years old, white, had had lesions on the palms for 30 years.
There was no history of trauma or local infection. The dermatological exam showed two
reddish plaques of approximately 5x5mm on the right palm and 5x10mm on the left palm.
The lesions were circumscribed, nummular, depressed and located symmetrically over the
thenar regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). Her soles were not involved. The general clinical examination
was not significant. Direct mycological examination was performed with negative results,
and histopathological aspects of skin biopsy showed a focus of sharp decrease in the
stratum corneum thickness, mild acanthosis and no change in the basal layer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f01" fig-type="other" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Circumscribed and reddish plaque located on the thenar eminences (Case1)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0623-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" fig-type="other" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Detail of the right palm lesion (Case 1)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0623-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" fig-type="other" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histopathological aspects (Case 1) - Focus of sharp decrease in the stratum
corneum thickness - HE</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0623-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The one year follow-up showed no change of clinical lesions.</p>
      <p>Case 2: Female patient, 84 years old, white, had had a single lesion on the left palm
for over 24 years. The patient had no history of trauma or local infection. The physical
examination revealed a reddish, nummular, depressed and circumscribed patch, about 5 mm
in diameter, located over the thenar eminence of the left palm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">5</xref>). There were
no lesions on contralateral palm or on soles.</p>
      <fig id="f04" fig-type="other" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Reddish, nummular and depressed lesion, located on the thenar eminence of the left
palm (Case 2)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0623-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f05" fig-type="other" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Detail of the lesion (Case 2)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0623-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Direct mycological examination was performed with negative results. Histologically, it
showed an abrupt, well-demarcated decrease in the thickness of the stratum corneum and a
diminished granular layer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f06" fig-type="other" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histopathological aspects (Case 2) - Abrupt decrease in the stratum corneum
thickness &#x2013; HE</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0623-g06"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The circumscribed palmoplantar hypokeratosis is a benign dermatosis first described by
Perez et al. Thus far, little more than 50 cases have been reported in the
literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref></sup>The cases reported
in this study are probably the first reports of this disease in Brazil.</p>
      <p>There is a predominance of cases among women (4:1), mean age 65 years. Clinically,
lesions are typically nummular, circumscribed, reddish and asymptomatic plaques,
commonly located over the thenar and hypothenar eminences of the palms and the medial
portion of the plantar region.</p>
      <p>The main disorders considered in clinical differential diagnosis are palmoplantar
psoriasis, Bowen's disease and palmoplantar porokeratosis. We must also remember
dermatophytoses and palmoplantar syphilids. Histopathologically, the palmar
hypokeratosis focus is characterized by abrupt reduction of the stratum corneum, forming
a "step" between the lesion and the perilesional normal skin. The decrease of the focal
stratum corneum is responsible for the clinical aspect of the depressed lesion; the
reddish color is caused by visualization of dermal blood circulation in the area of
injury due to corneal thinning. For this reason erythema shall not be considered true,
since there is no vasodilatation.</p>
      <p>The pathogenesis of palmoplantar hypokeratosis is unknown. Some authors argue that the
disease is caused by local trauma, being a "forme fruste" of epidermolysis bullosa, due
to an alteration in keratinocytes maturation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref></sup>However, only a minority of the previously reported cases had a
history of local trauma.</p>
      <p>Some authors have detected within palmoplantar hypokeratosis lesions the presence of the
human papillomavirus (HPV) 4 and 6, arguing that the infection with these viruses may be
a (co) factor in the pathogenesis of this dermatosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref></sup>However, in some other reports where immunohistochemical
techniques and polymerase chain reaction were used, there was no evidence of the
presence of HPV in lesions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B08">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Urbina et al showed a reduction of hyaline granules and decrease in number of these
keratinocyte cells by electron microscopy, suggesting a primary disturbance of
keratinization.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Ishiko et al immunohistochemically demonstrated, in 2007, increased expression of
keratin 16 and Ki-67 in skin lesions, speculating that the circumscribed hypokeratosis
may be a consequence of epidermal hyperproliferation associated with fragility of
keratinocytes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B06">6</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In 2009, Tanioka M et al proposed the existence of two subtypes of the disease. In the
first subtype, the most common lesion is characterized by palmar "erythema", with
immunohistochemical reduction of keratin 6 and 16 and normal expression of keratin
9.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B05">5</xref></sup>The second subtype is
typically found in the plantar region with little or no "erythema". In this subtype the
expression of keratin 26 and connexin 9 was reduced. There were also non-significant
changes of keratins 6 and 16.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B05">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Recently, Kanitakis et al showed abnormal expression of some antigens associated with
epidermal differentiation and proliferation of keratinocytes, as corneodesmosin, LEKTI
(Lymphoepithelial Kazal type inhibitor) and kallikrein 5, concluding that in this
dermatosis there is an alteration of the regulation of the cutaneous desquamation
process.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The circumscribed palmoplantar hypokeratosis does not require treatment and there is no
description of malignancy in the literature. Only one case was reported with the
presence of alterations such as actinic keratosis limited to hypokeratosis lesions and
that may be a consequence of relevant sun exposure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Attempts to treat this disease were made with surgery, cryotherapy, photodynamic therapy
and topical therapy with calcipotriol, corticosteroids and retinoids, with poor
results<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The two cases presented here are fairly typical of circumscribed palmar hypokeratosis.
They constitute the first report of this rare condition in Brazil. Familiarity with this
illness is relevant for dermatologists in order to properly distinguish it from other
palmoplantar dermatosis avoiding unnecessary treatment.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Study carried out on the Department of Dermatology- University of S&#xE3;o Paulo- S&#xE3;o
Paulo- Brasil.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial funding: None</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>P&#xE9;rez</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xFC;tten</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gold</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Urbina</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Misad</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Izquierdo</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Circumscribed palmar or plantar hypokeratosis: a distinctive epidermal
malformation of the palms or soles</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12077576</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Resnik</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DiLeonardo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Circumscribed palmar hypokeratosis: new observations</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermatopathol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>112</fpage>
          <lpage>116</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16625071</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xF6;er</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falk</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Circumscribed palmar hypokeratosis induced by papilloma virus type
4</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>908</fpage>
          <lpage>909</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16635682</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berk</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bauschard</surname>
              <given-names>FD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hurt</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santa-Cruz</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eisen</surname>
              <given-names>AZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Circumscribed acral hypokeratosis</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>292</fpage>
          <lpage>296</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17412452</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tanioka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyagawa-Hayashino</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manabe</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toichi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyachi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Circumscribed Palmo-Plantar Hypokeratosis: A Disease With Two
Subtypes</article-title>
          <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>129</volume>
          <fpage>1045</fpage>
          <lpage>1047</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18818675</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ishiko</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dekio</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujimoto</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kameyama</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakamoto</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benno</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Abnormal keratin expression in circumscribed palmar
hypokeratosis</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>291</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17553594</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cribier</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fabre</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Merlio</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antoni-Bach</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acral circumscribed hypokeratosis of plantar and dorsum of the finger
localization: two cases</article-title>
          <source>Ann Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>36</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171227</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barry</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glusac</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kashgarian</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gwin</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McNiff</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Circumscribed palmar hypokeratosis: two cases and a review of the
literature</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Pathol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>484</fpage>
          <lpage>487</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18399810</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Urbina</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Misad</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Circumscribed palmar hypokeratosis: clinical evolution and
ultrastructural study after prolonged treatment with topical
calcipotriol</article-title>
          <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>491</fpage>
          <lpage>494</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987302</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kanitakis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lora</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balme</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roby</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Premalignant circumscribed palmar hypokeratosis: a new form of
circumscribed palmar hypokeratosis?</article-title>
          <source>Dermatology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>220</volume>
          <fpage>143</fpage>
          <lpage>146</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19955702</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
