<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24009804</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3758851</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-15-28</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2013.15.28.2251</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Imperforate Hymen - a rare cause of acute abdominal pain and tenesmus: case report and review of the literature</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mwenda</surname>
            <given-names>Aruyaru Stanley</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Transmara District Hospital-Kilgoris, Kenya</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Aruyaru Stanley Mwenda, Transmara District Hospital-Kilgoris, Kenya</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <elocation-id>28</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Aruyaru Stanley Mwenda et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Imperforate hymen is a rare condition that presents with amenorrhea, cyclical abdominal pains and urine retention among pubertal girls. A 14 year old girl with imperforate hymen underwent hymenotomy for hematocolpometra, having presented with abdominal pains and tenesmus.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Imperforate hymen</kwd>
        <kwd>amenorrhea</kwd>
        <kwd>pubertal girls</kwd>
        <kwd>urine retention</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="S0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Imperforate hymen, despite being the commonest female genital tract malformation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref>], is a rare occurrence with a prevalence of 0.014-0.1% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>]. It mostly presents during puberty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref>] although diagnoses in utero [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0006">6</xref>] and during the new born period and childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref>] are also documented.</p>
      <p>There are few cases of Imperforate hymen reported in Africa. A case of unique presentation with tenesmus besides other documented symptoms was managed at a rural Kenyan hospital. There is no recorded case of imperforate hymen presenting with tenesmus according to literature search. In this article, a review of the literature concerning the symptomatology of imperforate hymen among pubertal girls is also presented.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Patient and observation</title>
      <p>14 year old Kenyan girl of African descent presented to hospital with a weeklong complaint of lower abdominal pains associated with tenesmus. She had reduced appetite and poor intake of food due to the colicky pains. There was no abdominal distension but she had observed some suprapubic fullness. She did not have constipation, diarrhoea, vomiting or fevers. Her urinary habits were normal. She had never had her menstrual periods but she had developed secondary sexual characteristics.</p>
      <p>On examination, she was in severe pain, walking stooped over and had moderately tender suprapubic mass corresponding to a uterus at 16 weeks. Rectal examination revealed an anterior mass. Perineal examination revealed a bulging imperforate hymen exaggerated on valsava manoeuvre. Pelvic ultrasound done revealed distended uterus and vagina all filled up with homogenous thick fluid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>). A diagnosis of hematocolpometra was made.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Distended uterus</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-15-28-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Bladder compression by the distended uterus</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-15-28-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In theatre, an X-shaped incision of the hymen was made under anaesthesia and approximately 600mls of thick chocolate coloured blood evacuated. The edges of the hymen were everted and anchored by Vicryl 2/0 sutures. Analgesic cream and prophylactic oral antibiotics were prescribed. She made uneventful recovery and was doing well at 1 month. She was however lost to follow-up after that.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0003">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Imperforate hymen is a layer of connective tissue that forms a transverse septum and obstructs the vaginal opening at the level of the introitus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>]. Usually, the hymen is a membrane that embryologically develops through the fusion of the caudal end of the paramesonephric ducts and the urogenital sinus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>]. The central portion of this membrane perforates through the degeneration of its epithelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>]. Failure of the degeneration of the epithelial cells and subsequent perforation leads to a hymen that is termed imperforate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>The function of the hymen is not clear but is thought to include innate immunity as it provides a physical barrier to infections during the pre-pubertal period when the vaginal immunity is not fully developed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Imperforate hymen is rarely associated with other female genital tract malformations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref>] although some authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0002">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>] have emphasized the need to rule out associated mullerian malformations. It occurs sporadically but few familial cases have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Imperforate hymen can present during three main stages in life;<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>In utero: This is the rarest and occurs due to maternal estrogenic stimulation that leads to uterovaginal secretions filling up the blind vagina and presenting as hydrocolpos diagnosed through obstetric ultrasound [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0006">6</xref>]. The diagnosis should be confirmed post natally.</p></list-item><list-item><p>New-born-infanthood-childhood: In new-born period this may occur due to maternal estrogenic stimulation that leads to uterovaginal secretions filling up the blind vagina and presenting with hydrocolpos [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">10</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>At puberty: This is the commonest. It occurs when a girl starts menstruating and the menstrual blood accumulates in the vagina [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">10</xref>]. The age of presentation (mean, range) is 13.2 and 11-16 years respectively according to Liang et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>] or 12 and 10-15 years respectively according to Lui et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>]. Liang and colleagues did a ten year retrospective analysis of 15 women treated for imperforate hymen through telephone based researcher administered questionnaire and a subsequent physical and sonographic examination. In their study, Lui et al did a ten year retrospective analysis of the data of 15 patients treated for imperforate hymen but did not do any follow up patient interview or examination. Kurgodlu and colleagues argue that the age of presentation is 2.5-4 years after thelarche [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0012">12</xref>].</p></list-item></list>
</p>
      <p>Among the pubertal girls, imperforate hymen will present in the following ways.</p>
      <sec id="S20004">
        <title>Amenorrhea</title>
        <p><list list-type="roman-upper"><list-item><p>Primary amenorrhea<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>This is because the girl has started menstruating but does not experience any menstrual flow as the blood accumulates in the vagina, then in the uterus and occasionally, eventually into the fallopian tubes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref>].</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>Secondary amenorrhea<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>This can occur following spontaneous closure of previously perforate hymen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>]. This can happen with a micro perforate or stenosed hymen. In such initial light periods will be experienced but continuous stenosis leads to complete obstruction and amenorrhea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>It can also occur as a result of stenosis of the hymenal opening following surgical or sexual trauma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Lastly, it can occur as failure of hymenotomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">10</xref>]. In the months following hymenotomy the patient experiences her menstrual flow but the margins of the hymenotomy incision adhere and eventually occlude the vaginal outflow leading to amenorrhea.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cryptomenorrhea</p></list-item></list>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S20005">
        <title>Pain</title>
        <p>Recurrent cyclical lower abdominal/pelvic pains (up to 60%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0002">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0011">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0012">12</xref>]. This is due to continued distension of the vagina and uterus by accumulating menstrual blood.</p>
        <p>Low back pain (38-40%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0013">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0014">14</xref>]. Occurs as referred pain following irritation of the sacral plexus and nerve roots by the distended vagina and uterus.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S20006">
        <title>Obstruction</title>
        <p><list list-type="roman-upper"><list-item><p>Urinary outflow obstruction and its complications (58%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">09</xref>]<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Acute urine retention (3-60%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">09</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0013">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0015">15</xref>].This occurs by a number of mechanisms<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>Pressure on the bladder by the distended uterus causing angulation at the bladder neck and kinking of the urethra [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">10</xref>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Direct pressure on the urethra causing urethral tamponade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">10</xref>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>The bulging hymen distends the vagina and may cause cephalad angulation at the urethral meatus further stretching the urethra and worsening tamponade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0015">15</xref>].</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>Complications of prolonged or recurrent urine retention /obstruction<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>Hydroureters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0002">2</xref>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hydronephrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0002">2</xref>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Renal failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Acute bacterial nephritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0016">16</xref>]</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>Vaginal outflow obstruction- Cryptomenorrhea</p></list-item><list-item><p>Intestinal obstruction<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Constipation (20-27%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0013">13</xref>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Tenesmus</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>Lymphovenous obstruction</p></list-item></list>
</p>
        <p>Compression of the pelvic veins and lymphatics can impair lymphovenous return from the lower limbs leading to oedema [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S20007">
        <title>Mass</title>
        <p><list list-type="roman-upper"><list-item><p>Distended uterus felt as pelvic mass on abdominal examination (20%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>The distended vagina is felt as a pelvic mass on digital rectal examination</p></list-item><list-item><p>A bluish bulging hymen is observed beneath the labia (60%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>A cystic retropubic mass is revealed on ultra sonography or MRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>]</p></list-item></list>
</p>
        <p>With above in mind and a high index of suspicion, it is easy to make a diagnosis of imperforate hymen. Late presentation may be accompanied with complications such as ruptured hematosalpinx [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0011">11</xref>], endometriosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0015">15</xref>] and infection (pyocolpos and nephritis) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0016">16</xref>]. A clinical diagnosis negates the need for extensive laboratory and radiological investigations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0010">10</xref>] and reduces the delay of intervention and length of hospital stay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0009">9</xref>].</p>
        <p>The management is aimed at re-establishing vaginal outflow and mainly consists of surgical hymenotomy under local or general anaesthesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref>]. Simple vertical, T-shaped, cruciform, X-shaped and cyclical incisions may be used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0004">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>]. X-shaped incision has the advantage of reduced risk of injury to the urethra-which should be stented during the procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007">7</xref>]. Pressure on the uterus in order to expel more blood is discouraged as it can lead to retrograde flow through the tubes causing endometriosis and tubal adhesions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0015">15</xref>]. Hymenectomy and hymenotomy with a two week indwelling catheter have also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>]. The outcome is good and the recurrences are rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S0008">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Imperforate hymen is a rare condition but should be easy to diagnose when it presents. It should be suspected in pubertal girls who presented with acute abdominal pain.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="S0009">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The author declares no competing interest.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagai</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Life threatening acute renal failure due to imperforate hymen in an infant</article-title>
          <source>Paediatrics International.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <month>4</month>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>280</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eksioglu</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imperforate hymen causing bilateral hydroureteronephrosis in an infant with bicornuate uterus</article-title>
          <source>Urology Case Reports</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>2012</volume>
          <fpage>102683</fpage>
          <comment>Epub 2012 Jun 7</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Basaran</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hymen sparing surgery for imperforate hymen; case reports and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J pediatr Adolesc Gynecol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>e61</fpage>
          <lpage>e64</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19646660</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dane</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imperforate hymen-a rare cause of abdominal pain: two cases and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J pediatr Adolesc Gynecol.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          <lpage>247</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17673137</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Long-term follow-up of women who underwent surgical correction for imperforate hymen</article-title>
          <source>Arch Gynecol Obstet.</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>269</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14605815</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ayaz</surname>
              <given-names>UM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ultrasonographic diagnosis of congenital hydrometrocolpos in prenatal and newborn period: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Medical ultrasonography.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>234</fpage>
          <lpage>236</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21894295</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ercan</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imperforate hymen causing hematocolpos and acute urinary retention in an adolescent girl</article-title>
          <source>Taiwanese Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>118</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21482390</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>Z.A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imperforate hymen: a rare case of secondary amenorrhea</article-title>
          <source>J Obstet Gynaecol.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21281009</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lui</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A retrospective study on imperforate hymen and hematocolpos in a regional hospital</article-title>
          <source>Hong Kong J emerg med.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>435</fpage>
          <lpage>440</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abu-Ghanem</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Recurrent urinary retention due to imperforate hymen after hymenotomy failure: a rare case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Urology.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>180</fpage>
          <lpage>182</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21256574</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kloss</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hematocolpos secondary to imperforate hymen</article-title>
          <source>Int J Emerg Med.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>481</fpage>
          <lpage>482</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21373333</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kurgodlu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous rupture of the imperforate hymen in an adolescent girl with hematocoplometra</article-title>
          <source>ISRN obstetrics and Gynecology</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>2011</volume>
          <fpage>520304</fpage>
          <comment>Epub 2010 Sep 29</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21637362</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mou</surname>
              <given-names>JWC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imperforate hymen: cause of lower abdominal pain in teenage girls</article-title>
          <source>Singapore Med J</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>e378</fpage>
          <lpage>e379</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19960149</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Drakonaki</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hematocolpometra due to an imperforate hymen presenting with low back pain</article-title>
          <source>J Ultrasound Med.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>321</fpage>
          <lpage>322</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20103807</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anselm</surname>
              <given-names>OO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ezegwui</surname>
              <given-names>UH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imperforate hymen presenting as acute urinary retention in a 14-year old Nigerian girl</article-title>
          <source>J Surg Tech case Rep.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>84</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22091343</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>LY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imperforate hymen complicated with pyocolpos and lobar nephronia</article-title>
          <source>J Chin Med Assoc.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>224</fpage>
          <lpage>227</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16835985</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
