<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24346922</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3876009</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20132488</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Bazex Syndrome<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref>
</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>S&#xED;ndrome de Bazex</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rodrigues J&#xFA;nior</surname>
            <given-names>Ismael Alves</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gresta</surname>
            <given-names>Let&#xED;cia Trivellato</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cruz</surname>
            <given-names>Rafaela Carolina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carvalho</surname>
            <given-names>Giselly Gomes</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Moreira</surname>
            <given-names>Melissa Heringer Chamon Barros Quint&#xE3;o</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> MD, Dermatologist, MSc in Pathology at the Federal University of Minas
Gerais (UFMG) - Professor at Instituto Metropolitano de Ensino Superior Medical School
(IMES). PhD (in course) in Pathology at the Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG) -
Belo Horizonte (MG), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> MD, pathologist, MSc in Pathology at the Federal University of Minas
Gerais(UFMG) - Professor at Instituto Metropolitano de Ensino Superior Medical School
(IMES). PhD (in course) in Pathology at the Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG) -
Belo Horizonte (MG), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> Medical student at Instituto Metropolitano de Ensino Superior (IMES)-
Ipatinga (MG), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> MD Post-graduated in psychiatry - Instituto de pesquisa e ensino medico
(IPEMED) - Rio de Janeiro (RJ), Brazil.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing address:</bold> Ismael Alves Rodrigues J&#xFA;nior, Rua Aleijadinho
215 Apt. 1001 - Cidade Nobre, 35162-352 - Ipatinga - MG, Brazil.
E-mail:<email>ismaelalvesrodrigues@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>6 Suppl 1</issue>
      <fpage>209</fpage>
      <lpage>211</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Acrokeratosis Paraneoplastica or Bazex syndrome is a dermatologic manifestation
usually associated with the diagnosis of squamous cell carcinoma of the upper
aerodigestive tract. We report a case with exuberant clinical manifestations,
exemplifying the typical cutaneous lesions in this rare syndrome, in a patient with
squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>Acroceratose paraneopl&#xE1;sica ou s&#xED;ndrome de Bazex &#xE9; uma
manifesta&#xE7;&#xE3;o cut&#xE2;nea paraneopl&#xE1;sica rara, geralmente
associada a carcinoma de c&#xE9;lulas escamosas do trato aerodigestivo superior.
Relata-se um caso com manifesta&#xE7;&#xF5;es cl&#xED;nicas exuberantes,
ilustrativo quanto &#xE0;s les&#xF5;es cut&#xE2;neas t&#xED;picas da
s&#xED;ndrome, em paciente portadora de carcinoma de c&#xE9;lulas escamosas do
es&#xF4;fago.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Paraneoplastic syndromes</kwd>
        <kwd>Skin</kwd>
        <kwd>Skin abnormalities</kwd>
        <kwd>Skin diseases</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Paraneoplastic syndromes are defined as clinical, biochemical, hormonal, hematological,
neurological or dermatological disorders, associated to a neoplasm, but not directly
caused by the primary tumor invasion or by its metastases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref></sup> They occur in 1 to 7% of all cancers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Cutaneous alterations may be indicators of malignancy, thus helping on the diagnosis of
a primary tumor by means of physical exam or biopsy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Bazex syndrome is a paraneoplastic syndrome more frequently associated to squamous cell
carcinomas of the higher aerodigestive tract, and described for the first time by Bazex
<italic>et al</italic>. in 1965. It affects primarily Caucasian males over 40 years
of age, and it is characterized by a psoriasiform eruption of typical distribution,
palmoplantar keratosis and symmetric onychodystrophy. Nose and ears are affected in 63%
and 79% of patients respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> One
hundred and forty-five cases were already described, of which only twelve were
women.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>We report the case of a female patient, with esophageal squamous cell carcinoma,
associated to a typical and exuberant cutaneous manifestation, characterizing Bazex
syndrome. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Seventy-three year-old female, dark-skinned, farm worker sought medical attention due to
pruritus and the presence of skin lesions in hands and feet for the last 40 days. She
presented with edema and a well-delimited violet coloration extending through the distal
half of the dorsal area of the hands to the tips of the digits. The fingers were swollen
and the nails presented a yellow hyperchromia and onychomadesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>). Edema and violet coloration repeated the same pattern on
the feet, appearing more pronounced at the distal half, and extending over the dorsal
area of the toes. Onychomadesis and hyperchromia were also present on the feet. </p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Lesions on the dorsal area of the hands and onychomadesis</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0209-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient was reluctant, responding only vaguely to the questions on the anamnesis.
She declared herself a former smoker and a former drinker. Physical examination did not
show any alterations besides voluntary guarding during the abdominal palpation. The main
hypothesis proposed was of acrokeratosis paraneoplastica with differential diagnoses of
tinea or psoriasis. Laboratory exams showed discreet normocytic and normochromic anemia,
kidney and liver functions were normal and fungal tests on skin scrapings were positive
for dermatophytes on the dorsal area of the feet. Subsequently we ordered abdominal and
pelvic ultrasounds, chest x-rays, upper digestive endoscopy and colonoscopy, and a
course of ketoconazole was prescribed for systemic use. </p>
      <p>After thirty days, the patient returned, showing violet, slightly infiltrated,
desquamative lesions, located on the nose, auricular pavilions, dorsal area of hands,
feet and toes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>). Symmetric palmoplantar
keratoderma, with lamellar desquamation was also present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3A</xref>). There was a worsening on hand and feet pruritus. Also noticeable
were the rare blisters over the violet lesions on the dorsal areas of the hands and feet
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3B</xref>). The patient's lips were also
affected by the violet discoloration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>).
Abdominal examination evidenced painful hepatomegaly; the liver border was located 10 cm
from the right costal margin, with blunt and irregular edges. Abdominal ultrasound
showed hepatic nodules and lymphadenomegaly. Pelvic ultrasound was normal.
Anatomopathological examination of the skin on the dorsal area of the hand found
discreet superficial psoriasiform chronic dermatitis, with pigmentary dispersion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>). Contrasted esophageal x-rays detected
Zenker's diverticulum and distal esophageal stenosis. Upper digestive endoscopy
demonstrated cancer of the esophagus and the biopsy confirmed a poorly differentiated
esophageal squamous cell carcinoma. The patient died a few days after the diagnosis was
completed. </p>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>A:</bold> violet, infiltrative, desquamative erythematous plaque on the
nose. <bold>B:</bold> similar lesion in the left auricular pavilion, also present
on the right ear</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0209-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>A:</bold> Plantar keratoderma. <bold>B:</bold> blister over the violet
lesion on the medial side of the foot</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0209-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Anatomopathological exam of the skin on the dorsal area of the hand showing
discreet, superficial, psoriasiform, chronic dermatitis, with pigmentary
dispersion (enlarged 10x).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0209-g04"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Bazex syndrome's physiopathology is still not well understood. Velez and Howard
proposed, as a possible mechanism, the crossed reactions between tumor and skin
antigens, the action of growth factors produced by the cancer cells and also zinc
deficiency associated to the neoplasm.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup> In 67% of cases reported on the medical literature, cutaneous
manifestations precede in approximately one year, the diagnosis of cancer.
Paraneoplastic acrokeratosis is highly specific for upper aerodigestive and lung
neoplasms, however, rare reports point to the possibility of an association with
bladder, prostate and breast cancer as well as liposarcoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup> In 18% of patients, cutaneous lesions and cancer are
diagnosed concomitantly and in 15% of the cases the diagnosis of cancer occurs
first.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>All of the patients present with one or more of the following signs: desquamative
erythematous lesions with a bluish or violet discoloration, onychodystrophy or
keratoderma. Lesions are typically located on acral regions; they are symmetric and
usually resistant to conventional treatments.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup> The appearance of blisters in hands and feet is common in
African-American patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup> Pruritus
is a rare manifestation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Bazex syndrome can progress in three stages: <bold>(1)</bold> cutaneous lesions in ears,
fingers and nails; <bold>(2)</bold> palmoplantar keratosis; <bold>(3)</bold> involvement
of knees, elbows and torso. The primary tumor tends to become symptomatic during the
stage of palmoplantar keratosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Histological findings are unspecific, resulting in the description of one superficial
psoriasiform dermatitis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> Among the differential diagnoses are
psoriasis, eczemas, pityriasis rubra pilaris, Reiter syndrome, tinea, acquired
palmoplantar keratoderma, syphilis, porphyria cutanea tarda, and acquired epidermolysis
bullosa.</p>
      <p>The improvement of lesions is described in 91% of the cases after the primary tumor is
treated. The cutaneous condition is refractory to topical treatment, which may be
attempted with coal tar, salicylic acid, vitamin D analogues, corticoids and UVB
radiation. Systemic treatment also presents inconsistent results in studies with
etretinate, corticoids and antibiotics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Paraneoplastic syndromes may simulate other diseases, deferring the diagnosis of the
primary tumor. The exuberance of the clinical manifestations described in this report
illustrates the Bazex syndrome and draws the dermatologist attention to the possibility
of this diagnosis. Our report is an exception to the rule, while describing a
dark-skinned, female patient, with pruriginous lesions, an altogether unusual
presentation of acrokeratosis paraneoplastica.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Work performed at Instituto Metropolitano de Ensino Superior (IMES) - Ipatinga (MG),
Brazil. </p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial Support: None</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES </title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramos-E-Silva</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carvalho</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carneiro</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cutaneous paraneoplasia</article-title>
          <source>Clin Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>541</fpage>
          <lpage>547</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21855730</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Toro</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rinaldo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silver</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Politi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferlito</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paraneoplastic syndromes in patients with oral cancer</article-title>
          <source>Oral Oncol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>14</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19932048</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Poligone</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christensen</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazova</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heald</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bazex syndrome (acrokeratosis paraneoplastica)</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>369</volume>
          <fpage>530</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17292773</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fasanmade</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farrell</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perkins</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bazex syndrome (acrokeratosis paraneoplastica): persistence of
cutaneous lesions after successful treatment of an associates oropharyngeal
neoplasm</article-title>
          <source>Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>138</fpage>
          <lpage>139</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abreu Velez</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howard</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of cutaneous paraneoplastic
disorders</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Ther</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>662</fpage>
          <lpage>675</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21054710</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Louvel</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vaul&#xE9;on</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boucher</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raoul</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acrokeratosis Paraneoplastica (Bazex' Syndrome) Associated With
Metastatic Squamous Cell Esophageal Carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>5128</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18838705</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abrou</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hope</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson-Richards</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozog</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acrodermatitis paraneoplastica responding to topical PUVA
treatment</article-title>
          <source>Photodermatol Photoimmunol Photomed</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17254036</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chapireau</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adlam</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cameron</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paraneoplastic syndromes in patients with primary oral cancersa
systematic review</article-title>
          <source>Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>338</fpage>
          <lpage>344</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833419</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reis</surname>
              <given-names>VMS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pires</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martins</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Criado</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegas</surname>
              <given-names>JRP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xFC;ller</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bazex's paraneoplastica acrokeratosisa case report</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>551</fpage>
          <lpage>553</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferlito</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rinaldo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paraneoplastic syndromes in patients with cancer of the larynx and
hypopharynnx</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>502</fpage>
          <lpage>513</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17727081</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
