<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Interv Aging</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Interv Aging</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinical Interventions in Aging</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1176-9092</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1178-1998</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove Medical Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23610516</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3628529</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CIA.S39536</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">cia-8-391</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Managing myelodysplastic syndromes in very old patients: a teaching case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Niscola</surname>
            <given-names>Pasquale</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-391"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Palombi</surname>
            <given-names>Massimiliano</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-391"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-cia-8-391"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trawinska</surname>
            <given-names>Monika Malgorzata</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-391"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tendas</surname>
            <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-391"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Giovannini</surname>
            <given-names>Marco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-391"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Scaramucci</surname>
            <given-names>Laura</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-391"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Perrotti</surname>
            <given-names>Alessio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-391"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Fabritiis</surname>
            <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-391"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="af1-cia-8-391">Hematology Unit, Sant&#x2019;Eugenio Hospital, Rome, Italy</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1-cia-8-391">Correspondence: Pasquale Niscola, Hematology Division, San Eugenio Hospital, Piazzale dell&#x2019;Umanesimo 10, 00144 Rome, Italy Tel +39 06 5100 3241 Fax +39 06 5100 2390 Email <email>pniscola@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Dove Press titles changed from ppub to collections in 2009.
								Fake ppub written to satisfy Coll Date Type=ppub-->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <fpage>391</fpage>
      <lpage>394</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2013 Niscola et al, publisher and licensee Dove Medical Press Ltd</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The introduction of hypomethylating agents in the treatment of myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS) has significantly changed the clinical scenario of these diseases, which afflict predominantly older individuals. However, some concerns regarding the optimal application of these innovative and costly agents in the treatment of geriatric high-risk MDS remain. We report here the case of a nonagenarian treated with hypomethylating agents achieving a long-lasting clinical response and a significant improvement in her functional status. Our case confirmed that functional status and biological status, rather than the chronological age alone, can substantially guide the plan of an appropriate treatment strategy in high-risk MDS patients; moreover, the current case emphasizes the need for targeted studies in the field of geriatric MDS in order to formulate guidelines on the appropriate use of these costly agents, so that candidate patients can receive adequate treatment to preserve their quality of life and life expectancy, but at the same time avoiding unnecessary costs deriving from the use of high-cost drugs for those in whom a significant therapeutic result cannot be reasonably expected.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>myelodysplastic syndromes</kwd>
        <kwd>azacitidine</kwd>
        <kwd>older patients</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS), with an incidence rate of four to five new cases per 100,000 population per year,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cia-8-391">1</xref> a median age of about 70 years,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cia-8-391">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-cia-8-391">2</xref> and mainly chronic course, are frequently managed in clinical practice by a hematologist. The majority of individuals with MDS are of older age, frail, and often afflicted by several comorbidities;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-cia-8-391">2</xref> only a minority of patients are suitable for potentially curative approaches, such as intensive chemotherapy and stem cell transplantation.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cia-8-391">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-cia-8-391">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cia-8-391">4</xref></p>
      <p>Recently, low-dose chemotherapy and targeted agents, such as lenalidomide and azacitidine,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cia-8-391">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cia-8-391">4</xref> have been adopted with favorable results in groups of patients with MDS. The introduction of hypomethylating agents in the treatment of MDS has significantly changed the clinical scenario of this disease.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cia-8-391">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-cia-8-391">5</xref> However, some concerns regarding the optimal application of these innovative and costly agents<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-cia-8-391">6</xref> in the treatment of geriatric MDS remain.</p>
      <p>In light of our recent experience in this setting, we report herein the case of a very old patient with MDS whom we have followed for the last 3 years. The present case provides, in our opinion, some interesting discussion points in regards to the diagnosis, management, and treatment of MDS in elderly patients.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>The patient was a 91-year-old woman kept under our care because of peripheral blood (PB) trilinear pancytopenia. The patient underwent routine tests, which excluded medical illnesses, infectious diseases, and other secondary conditions of altered blood counts, such as deficiency disorders, tumors, bleeding, and so on. A bone marrow (BM) examination was not initially performed given the patient&#x2019;s very advanced age and her unwillingness to submit to the diagnostic procedure. The morphological analysis of the PB smear showed anisopoikilocytosis of erythrocytes and platelets, along with hypogranularity and nuclear hyposegmentation of granulocytes; no circulating immature cells were found. These findings were suggestive of an MDS framework and the patient was regularly followed up.</p>
      <p>However, the patient experienced worsening cytopenia; the patient had an ever increasing transfusion requirement of packed red blood cells and platelet concentrates. Given the difficulty of traveling to our treatment facility so frequently to receive transfusion support, the patient was followed at her home by our specialized team of hematological home care.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-cia-8-391">7</xref> During the following months, the patient was cared for at her home with increased transfusion requirement, persistent thrombocytopenia (platelet count around 1000/&#x3BC;L) with platelet transfusion refractoriness, and episodes of mucocutaneous bleeding. In other respects, the patient was well and did not have significant comorbidities; in addition, despite the disturbances related to cytopenia, she maintained an active life and a satisfactory personal independence in activities of daily living in her own home (Barthel<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-cia-8-391">8</xref> and Katz<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-cia-8-391">9</xref> indexes were 60% and 4/6, respectively), with the support and presence of her loved ones.</p>
      <p>About 2 years after the diagnosis of suspected MDS, with the patient being almost 94 years old, a BM was performed. The morphological analysis of the BM smear showed a marked trilinear dysplasia with 15% blasts. Cytogenetic analysis showed a normal karyotype. Thus, the MDS was classified as intermediate grade 2 and intermediate risk according to International Prognostic Scoring System (IPSS)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-cia-8-391">10</xref> and World Health Organization adapted Prognostic Scoring System (WPSS),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-cia-8-391">11</xref> respectively. A full reassessment of the general conditions made it possible to highlight the lack of relevant comorbidities or complications of the underlying disease; the MDS-specific comorbidity index<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-cia-8-391">12</xref> score was 0.</p>
      <p>After a frank discussion with the patient and her family, 5-azacytidine (75 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, schedule 5 + 2 + 2)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-cia-8-391">13</xref> was offered. The patient was properly informed and gave her consent. The treatment was administered on an outpatient basis, whereas the transfusion support was given at home.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-cia-8-391">8</xref> The therapy was well tolerated and the cytopenia gradually improved until near-normalization of PB counts and complete transfusion independence, which were achieved after the third course of 5-azacitidine. To date, six courses of 5-azacitidine have been administered and a BM aspirate showed an absence of blast cells, although BM dysplastic features persisted; her hemogram is near-normal. We plan to continue the treatment as long as it remains effective and well tolerated.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Our experience outlined some concerns and decisions that hematologists encounter daily in managing elderly MDS patients, especially in light of the availability of new drugs that can alter the course of the disease. In fact, the clinical scenario of MDS has changed in the last few years from a treatment approach limited to symptom control and disease-related clinical complications to the possibility of achieving significantly long-lasting hematological responses,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14-cia-8-391">14</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16-cia-8-391">16</xref> survival benefits,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17-cia-8-391">17</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21-cia-8-391">21</xref> and improvement in quality of life<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20-cia-8-391">20</xref> by novel agents. It has been reported that treatment with 5-azacitidine provides significantly better therapeutic results than other traditional treatments; 5-azacitidine has firmly established a standard of care. The use of 5-azacitidine in our case suggests three main discussion points.</p>
      <p>First, if MDS is suspected, should it be fully diagnosed in very elderly patients? MDS diagnosis can be ruled out only through BM examination, but performing BM aspiration can be painful and carries a small risk of adverse events; thus, it is often avoided or postponed.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22-cia-8-391">22</xref> It is important to note that if MDS worsens and leads to acute myeloid leukemia progression, postponing BM examination may result in the loss of the useful therapeutic window for the administration of new drugs such as hypomethylating agents. Thus, in our opinion, the point remains open to the discussion.</p>
      <p>Second, should very elderly MDS patients be treated? Although the financial cost of hypomethylating agents is substantial, it should be weighed against the patient&#x2019;s potential benefits, in terms of improvement in clinical outcomes, quality of life, and transfusion requirements.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-cia-8-391">6</xref> Moreover, the therapeutic effects of hypomethylating agents are not related to patient age; indeed, favorable responses have been achieved in patients over 75 years of age,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-cia-8-391">15</xref> such as in our patient. The IPSS<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-cia-8-391">10</xref> and WPSS<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-cia-8-391">11</xref> have an established role in treatment decision making; however, other important aspects, such as the presence of comorbid illnesses and functional status impairment (extremely frequent in very elderly individuals) should be taken into account.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cia-8-391">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-cia-8-391">5</xref> Consequently, in very old MDS patients, the identification of patients who may benefit from hypomethylating agents may be a concern. Once again, this question remains unanswered; however, we hope that future studies could, and should, clarify this matter of crucial importance.</p>
      <p>Third, where should very elderly MDS patients be treated? The application of supportive care measures has critical value in preserving the quality of life and functional performance of these patients;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cia-8-391">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-cia-8-391">5</xref> in this regard, our case illustrated the significant role that specialized home care service can play in the management of MDS patients.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-cia-8-391">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21-cia-8-391">21</xref> Indeed, elderly patients are frail and their access to the hospital may be difficult due to several factors: complex and severe symptom burden, the impairment of daily living activities, social isolation, financial issues, and psychological limitations. Thus, in our opinion, the best setting in which to manage elderly patients with MDS is home care; however, a specialized home care team, networking with the hospital and the other local services, is required for adequate management of these complex patients at home.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, to the best of our knowledge, we have reported on the oldest MDS patient treated with 5-azacitidine. In light of our experience, we would like to emphasize the need for targeted studies in the field of geriatric MDS in order to formulate guidelines on the appropriate use of costly new drugs, such as hypomethylating agents, in order to ensure adequate treatment to preserve patients&#x2019; quality of life and life expectancy, but at the same time avoiding unnecessary costs associated with the use of high-cost drugs for those in whom a real benefit cannot be reasonably expected.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Disclosure</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors have no affiliations or financial involvement with any organization or entity with a financial interest in or financial conflict with the subject matter or materials discussed in the manuscript. This includes employment, consultancies, honoraria, stock ownership or options, expert testimony, grants or patents received or pending, or royalties. No writing assistance was utilized in the production of this manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="b1-cia-8-391">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Greenberg</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Attar</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
            <collab>National Comprehensive Cancer Network</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: myelodysplastic syndromes</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21233243</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2-cia-8-391">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sekeres</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schoonen</surname>
              <given-names>WM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kantarjian</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characteristics of US patients with myelodysplastic syndromes: results of six cross-sectional physician surveys</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <issue>21</issue>
          <fpage>1542</fpage>
          <lpage>1551</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957672</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3-cia-8-391">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santini</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alessandrino</surname>
              <given-names>PE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Angelucci</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
            <collab>Italian Society of Hematology</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical management of myelodysplastic syndromes: update of SIE, SIES, GITMO practice guidelines</article-title>
          <source>Leuk Res</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1576</fpage>
          <lpage>1588</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20149927</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4-cia-8-391">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ritchie</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lachs</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of myelodysplastic syndromes in the geriatric patient</article-title>
          <source>Curr Hematol Malig Rep</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20425432</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5-cia-8-391">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ritchie</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Safety and efficacy of azacitidine in the treatment of elderly patients with myelodysplastic syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Clin Interv Aging</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>173</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22791989</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6-cia-8-391">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Greenberg</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cosler</surname>
              <given-names>LE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferro</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lyman</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The costs of drugs used to treat myelodysplastic syndromes following National Comprehensive Cancer Network Guidelines</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>942</fpage>
          <lpage>953</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18926103</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7-cia-8-391">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Niscola</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tendas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giovannini</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transfusions at home in patients with myelodysplastic syndromes</article-title>
          <source>Leuk Res</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>684</fpage>
          <lpage>688</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22336393</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8-cia-8-391">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tendas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niscola</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ales</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Disability and physical rehabilitation in patients with advanced haematological malignancies followed in a home care program</article-title>
          <source>Support Care Cancer</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1559</fpage>
          <lpage>1560</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19701814</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9-cia-8-391">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hartigan</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A comparative review of the Katz ADL and the Barthel Index in assessing the activities of daily living of older people</article-title>
          <source>Int J Older People Nurs</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>204</fpage>
          <lpage>212</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20925877</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10-cia-8-391">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Greenberg</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>LeBeau</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>International scoring system for evaluating prognosis in myelodysplastic syndromes</article-title>
          <source>Blood</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>2079</fpage>
          <lpage>2088</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9058730</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11-cia-8-391">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Malcovati</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Germing</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuendgen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Time-dependent prognostic scoring system for predicting survival and leukemic evolution in myelodysplastic syndromes</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>23</issue>
          <fpage>3503</fpage>
          <lpage>3510</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17687155</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12-cia-8-391">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Della Porta</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malcovati</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strupp</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Risk stratification based on both disease status and extra-hematologic comorbidities in patients with myelodysplastic syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Haematologica</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>441</fpage>
          <lpage>449</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21134982</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13-cia-8-391">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lyons</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cosgriff</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Modi</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hematologic response to three alternative dosing schedules of azacitidine in patients with myelodysplastic syndromes</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>1850</fpage>
          <lpage>1856</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19255328</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14-cia-8-391">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia-Manero</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myelodysplastic syndromes: 2012 update on diagnosis, risk-stratification, and management</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hematol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>692</fpage>
          <lpage>701</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22696212</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15-cia-8-391">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seymour</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fenaux</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silverman</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of azacitidine compared with conventional care regimens in elderly (&#x2265;75 years) patients with higher-risk myelodysplastic syndromes</article-title>
          <source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>218</fpage>
          <lpage>227</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20451404</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16-cia-8-391">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fenaux</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mufti</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hellstr&#xF6;m-Lindberg</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Azacitidine prolongs overall survival compared with conventional care regimens in elderly patients with low bone marrow blast count acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>562</fpage>
          <lpage>569</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20026804</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17-cia-8-391">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fenaux</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mufti</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hellstrom-Lindberg</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
            <collab>International Vidaza High-Risk MDS Survival Study Group</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Efficacy of azacitidine compared with that of conventional care regimens in the treatment of higher-risk myelodysplastic syndromes: a randomised, open-label, phase III study</article-title>
          <source>Lancet Oncol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>223</fpage>
          <lpage>232</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19230772</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18-cia-8-391">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silverman</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demakos</surname>
              <given-names>EP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peterson</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Randomized controlled trial of azacitidine in patients with the myelodysplastic syndrome: a study of the cancer and leukemia group B</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>2429</fpage>
          <lpage>2440</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011120</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19-cia-8-391">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gurion</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vidal</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gafter-Gvili</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>5-azacitidine prolongs overall survival in patients with myelodysplastic syndrome &#x2014; a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
          <source>Haematologica</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>303</fpage>
          <lpage>310</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19773261</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20-cia-8-391">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kornblith</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herndon</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
              <suffix>2nd</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silverman</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impact of azacytidine on the quality of life of patients with myelodysplastic syndrome treated in a randomized phase III trial: a Cancer and Leukemia Group B study</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>2441</fpage>
          <lpage>2452</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011121</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b21-cia-8-391">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Niscola</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Fabritiis</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cartoni</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Home care management of patients affected by hematologic malignancies: a review</article-title>
          <source>Haematologica</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>1523</fpage>
          <lpage>1529</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17082010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b22-cia-8-391">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brunetti</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tendas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meloni</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pain and anxiety associated with bone marrow aspiration and biopsy: a prospective study on 152 Italian patients with hematological malignancies</article-title>
          <source>Ann Hematol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1233</fpage>
          <lpage>1235</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21287348</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
