<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10987407</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3113182</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Unilateral Diaphragmatic Agenesis Precluding Laparoscopic Cholecystectomy</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wakai</surname>
            <given-names>Abel</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MB</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Winter</surname>
            <given-names>Desmond C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>O'Sullivan</surname>
            <given-names>Gerald C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MCh</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <aff>FRCSI, Department of Surgery, Mercy Hospital and University College, Cork, Ireland.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address reprint request to: Mr. A. Wakai, FRCSI, <addr-line>44 Littlepace Wood, Clonee, Dublin, Republic of Ireland</addr-line>. Telephone: <phone>+353-21-346325</phone>, Fax: <fax>+353-21-344-230</fax>, E-mail: <email>wakai@indigo.ie</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Sep</season>
        <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>259</fpage>
      <lpage>261</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2000 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jsls-4-3-259.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>Complete absence of a hemidiaphragm or diaphragmatic agenesis in adulthood is rare with only one previous report in the literature. Its significance in relation to performing laparoscopic procedures has not been documented previously.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods:</title>
          <p>We report a case of previously undiagnosed diaphragmatic agenesis in adulthood precluding laparoscopic cholecystectomy and comprehensively review the literature for papers relevant to diaphragmatic agenesis in adulthood.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results:</title>
          <p>Diaphragmatic agenesis in adulthood may complicate and preclude laparoscopic cholecystectomy. The principles of investigation and management of diaphragmatic agenesis complicating laparoscopic surgery are discussed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions:</title>
          <p>In adults with diaphragmatic agenesis and intrathoracic abdominal viscera precluding laparoscopic cholecystectomy, conservative management is recommended.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Diaphragmatic agenesis</kwd>
        <kwd>Laparoscopic cholecystectomy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Growth failure of the diaphragm during embryogenesis (diaphragmatic agenesis [DA]) is associated with significantly higher morbidity and mortality rates in the perinatal period compared to the more common posterolateral (Bochkalek) defect in congenital diaphragmatic hernia, even following surgical repair.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> While the clinical course of diaphragmatic agenesis in neonates is well documented, there is a paucity of information on the significance of this condition in adulthood. We report the case of an adult patient in whom previously asymptomatic unilateral DA precluded laparoscopic cholecystectomy. To the authors' knowledge, only one other case of asymptomatic unilateral DA presenting in adulthood has been reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 41-year-old male presented with a two-year history of progressively worsening fatty food intolerance, flatulence, dyspepsia and intermittent right upper quadrant pain radiating to his scapula. It had become increasingly severe and caused sleep disturbance. He had no other co-morbid medical conditions and an unremarkable past medical history. On admission, physical examination revealed absent breath sounds and dullness to percussion in the right lung base but was otherwise unremarkable. Liver function tests revealed a slightly elevated gamma-glutamyl- transaminase (55 IU/L) but was otherwise normal. Postero-anterior and right lateral plain film chest radiographs were suggestive of a right diaphragmatic hernia. Abdominal ultrasound was confirmatory of right diaphragmatic herniation of the abdominal viscera, making it impossible to visualize the gallbladder. Laparoscopy revealed right hemidiaphragm agenesis with an elevated and rotated intra-thoracic liver <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>)</bold>. Bowel and omentum were in the right hemithorax <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>)</bold>. Furthermore, the central tendon of the diaphragm was absent with a pericardial defect <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>)</bold>. The gallbladder was not visualized at laparoscopy, precluding laparoscopic cholecystectomy. He was followed on an out-patient basis and was asymptomatic until seven months later when he presented with a five-day history of anorexia, jaundice and constant right upper quadrant pain radiating to his right subscapular region. Abdominal ultrasound revealed dilatation of the intra- and extra-hepatic bile ducts suggestive of choledocholithiasis. Endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP) demonstrated common bile duct dilatation with choledocholithiasis. ERCP with endoscopic sphincterotomy, stone extraction and stenting of the common bile duct was performed. Following ERCP, he was commenced on gallstone dissolution therapy with ursodeoxycholic acid (250 mg twice daily orally).</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Liver and omentum in right hemithorax via laparoscope.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-4-3-259-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Large bowel with attached omentum within right hemithorax via laparoscope.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-4-3-259-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Pericardial defect revealing myocardium as seen from abdomen at laparoscopy.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-4-3-259-g03"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Bingham, in 1959, first distinguished DA as a distinct anatomical entity from the more common posterolateral congenital diaphragmatic defect (Bochdalek) in an infant who died shortly after birth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref></sup> Until a decade ago, DA was considered exceedingly rare with only one case report of survivors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> There has been an increased incidence of DA in neonates with congenital diaphragmatic hernia since the early 1980s due to improved perinatal care. The reported incidence is 27-31% of cases of congenital diaphragmatic hernia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> Experience on the management of neonatal DA as a distinct clinical entity is thus increasing.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> Consequently, the incidence of adults with DA is likely to increase, and the management dilemmas of the case presented here may occur more frequently in the future.</p>
      <p>Diagnosis of DA in adults is based on clinical findings and imaging studies. Dullness to percussion and absent or diminished breath sounds in a lung field may indicate a congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Imaging studies (chest radiography, and abdominal ultrasound) are confirmatory. In adults with DA presenting with cardiorespiratory or gastrointestinal symptoms, the main principle of diagnosis should be to systematically investigate the gastrointestinal tract to rule out pathology in the herniated intrathoracic viscera.</p>
      <p>Surgical repair of DA in adulthood is complex. Difficulties arise in deciding the operative approach, reducing the densely adherent intra-thoracic visceral contents and repairing the extensive diaphragmatic defect. Although the patient had no other co-morbid medical condition, we decided on conservative management because aggressive surgical intervention would have involved an open cholecystectomy through a thoracoabdominal incision with difficulty in safely reducing the intra-thoracic liver and reconstructing the diaphragm. Furthermore, gallstone extraction was successfully performed by ERCP, and the patient had survived into adulthood without medical problems related to the DA. Emphasis was therefore placed on managing the choledocholithiasis endoscopically, supplemented with gallstone dissolution therapy. This minimalist approach was successful without exposing the patient to an extensive precarious surgical intervention to repair the diaphragmatic defects. The patient remains well and asymptomatic on follow-up of 36 months.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>In adults with DA precluding laparoscopic cholecystectomy, conservative management is advocated. The focus should be on elimination of symptoms rather than diaphragmatic repair.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Diaphragmatic agenesis as a distinct clinical entity</article-title>. <source>J Paediatr Surg</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzelepis</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ettensohn</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McCool</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Unilateral absence of the diaphragm in an asymptomatic adult</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>1301</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3191776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>JAW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Herniation through congenital diaphragmatic hernia defects</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>. <year>1959</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13800779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brereton</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Unilateral agenesis of the diaphragm</article-title>. <source>J Paediatr Surg</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>848</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>850</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
