<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Lab Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJLM</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Korean Journal of Laboratory Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1598-6535</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Society for Laboratory Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21474988</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3115999</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3343/kjlm.2011.31.2.118</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinical Microbiology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Case Report</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Case of Bacteremia by <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> Coincident with Massive Hemorrhage of Esophageal Varices</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Won</surname>
            <given-names>Dahae</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>An</surname>
            <given-names>Dongheui</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Mi-Na</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Young Sang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>M.D.</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Asan Medical Center, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Internal Medicine, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Asan Medical Center, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Corresponding author: Mi-Na Kim, M.D. Department of Laboratory Medicine, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, 86 Asanbyeongwon-gil, Songpa-gu, Seoul 138-736, Korea. Tel: +82-2-3010-4511, Fax: +82-2-478-0884, <email>mnkim@amc.seoul.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>31</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>118</fpage>
      <lpage>121</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2011 The Korean Society for Laboratory Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 42-yr-old man with hepatitis B virus associated liver cirrhosis was admitted to the emergency room because of multiple seizures, a history of chills and myalgia over the previous 2 weeks, and 3 days of melena. He was febrile with a temperature of 38.0&#x2103;. There were no symptoms and signs related to the genitourinary system, skin, or joints. Three sets of blood cultures were obtained and oxidase-positive, gram-negative diplococci were detected after 25.9-26.9 hr of incubation in all aerobic vials. The organism was positive for catalase and oxidase, and was identified as <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic>, using a Vitek <italic>Neisseria-Haemophilus</italic> Identification card (bioM&#xE9;rieux Vitek, Inc., USA). Further, 16S rRNA sequencing of this isolate revealed a 99.9% homology with the published sequence of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> strain NCTC 83785 (GenBank Accession No. NR_026079.1). Acute bleeding by variceal rupture seems to be a likely route of introduction of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> from the mucosa into the blood. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first case of gonococcal bacteremia in Korea.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Bacteremia</kwd>
        <kwd>Esophageal varices</kwd>
        <kwd>Hemorrhage</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p><italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> is a well-known cause of sexually transmitted diseases such as genital, pharyngeal, and anorectal infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Bloodstream invasion, however, occurs only in 0.5-3% of the infections and results in disseminated gonococcal infection (DGI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Only one case of DGI has been reported previously in Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Here, we report a patient with <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> bacteremia in whom massive variceal hemorrhage occurs coincidently.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>On June 5th, 2010, a 42-yr-old man was admitted to the hospital via the emergency room due to multiple seizures, a history of chills, myalgia over the previous 2 weeks, and 3 days of melena. Hepatitis B virus (HBV)-associated liver cirrhosis was diagnosed 2 yr ago. The patient was treated in a primary clinic and his cough improved; however, myalgia and melena continued and worsened after 4 days. At admission, he was pale and febrile with a temperature of 38.0&#x2103;. Intermittent fever of 37.8-38.0&#x2103; continued until hospital day 3. The patient had a blood pressure of 108/64 mmHg, a pulse of 86/min, and a respiratory rate of 20/min. There were no signs and symptoms related to the genitourinary systems, skin, and joints. L-tube irrigation was performed, and the aspirate was bloody and had old clots. Laboratory investigations showed a Hb of 4.6 g/dL, a leukocyte count of 19.4&#xD7;10<sup>3</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup>, a platelet count of 51&#xD7;10<sup>3</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup>, a C-reactive protein level of 10.56 mg/dL, prothrombin time (international normalized ratio) of 1.58, AST/ALT of 56/55 IU/L, ALP of 102 IU/L, BUN/creatinine of 37/1.1 mg/dL, and total protein/albumin of 3.5/1.5 g/dL. Three sets of blood cultures were taken and gram-variable cocci in clusters were detected after a 25.9- to 26.9-hr incubation in aerobic vials. Initially, cocci were reported as gram-positive. In 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 35&#x2103;, tiny, glistening, and raised colonies grew after overnight incubation. The colonies grew to 1-2 mm in diameter after a 2-day incubation on both blood agar and chocolate agar plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). No growth was observed on MacConkey agar. The bacterium was positive for catalase, oxidase, and acid production from glucose but not maltose. It was identified, with 98% probability, as <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> (bionumber 464001) by the Vitek <italic>Neisseria-Haemo-philus</italic> Identification (NHI) card (bioM&#xE9;rieux Vitek, Inc., Hazelwood, MO, USA). Gram staining of the colonies revealed gram-negative diplococci. Sequencing of 16S rRNA covering nucleotides 30-1,370 of this isolate showed the greatest homology (99.9%) to the published sequence of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> strain NCTC 83785 (GenBank Accession No. NR_026079.1), followed by 98.6% homology to <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic> 8013 (GenBank Accession No. FM 999788.1). The isolate was penicillinase-positive on an NHI card. It was resistant to penicillin, ciprofloxacin, and tetracycline; and susceptible to cefuroxime, cefotaxime, and cefepime by disk diffusion on GC agar plates after a 20- to 24-hr incubation at 35&#x2103; and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The patient received endoscopic variceal ligation to control hemorrhage of esophageal varices. Cefotaxime was started empirically in the emergency room, and vancomycin was added after the report of positive blood cultures of gram-positive cocci on day 2. On day 3, fever was no longer present, and follow-up blood cultures were negative. The patient was discharged on day 8. He received variceal ligation twice more: 1 and 2 months later. Urine and throat swabs were obtained when he visited the outpatient clinic on September 28th, and were cultured on modified Thayer-Martin agar plates and blood agar plates. All were negative for <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>. At that time, he reported that he had not had sexual contact with his wife for several months, and that he had traveled to China during the previous April. He has a son.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p><italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> is a pathogenic <italic>Neisseria</italic> species that mainly causes genital infections, and, less frequently, also causes pharyngeal and anorectal infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Dissemination occurs in only 0.5-3% of the gonococcal infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Disseminated infections typically present with low-grade fever, skin lesions, tenosinovitis, and migratory polyarthralgias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Only one case of DGI with polyarthralgias and skin lesions has been previously reported in Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. This is the second case of DGI, and, to the best of our knowledge, the first culture-proven bacteremia of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> in Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. DGI is often preceded by asymptomatic mucosal infections. Predisposing risk factors for dissemination include being a female, a homosexual or bisexual male, recent menstruation, pregnancy, immediate postpartum states, gonococcal pharyngitis, complement deficiencies, and systemic lupus erythematosus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Because this patient had HBV-associated liver cirrhosis, he may have had a complement deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Liver cirrhosis patients are susceptible to immune and nutritional deficiencies, including vitamin, protein, immunoglobulin, and complement deficiencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], which cause increased morbidity and mortality of infectious diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Although the patient's medical history and physical examinations related to other risk factors were not taken initially in this case, he had neither female-related risk factors nor exhibited homosexual behavior.</p>
      <p>Because the patient had no symptoms related to the skin or joints, DGI was hardly suspected, even when <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> was identified from blood cultures. In this case, intermittent fever, a leukocyte count of 19.4&#xD7;10<sup>3</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup>, and a C-reactive protein level of 10.56 mg/dL indicated a stage of acute inflammation. Therefore, there was on acute onset of dissemination of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> at admission without time enough to involve skin and the joints. Gonococcal bacteremia is often intermittent and only half of the patients with DGI have positive cultures from blood or synovial fluid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Positive results, with practically the same time to positivity in all three sets of blood cultures, suggested direct introduction of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> into the blood stream, or endocarditis, a rare, life-threatening condition of DGI. However, no signs or symptoms of endocarditis were observed during a 6-month follow-up. Esophageal variceal rupture was the only mucosal breakage in this case. Therefore, it was speculated that asymptomatic gonococcal pharyngitis preceded dissemination, and that ruptured vessels on the esophageal mucosa were a likely route of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> dissemination.</p>
      <p>The <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> isolated from this patient was penicillinase-positive, resistant to penicillin, ciproflocxacin, and tetracycline, but sensitive to cefuroxime, cefotaxime, and cefepime. This resistance pattern was consistent with the previous report of resistance rates of Korean gonococcal isolates against penicillin, quinolone, tetracycline, and ceftriaxone (55.4%, 95.7%, 10-34%, and 0%, respectively, in 2008) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. For treatment of DGI, intramuscular or intrave-nous injection of 1 g ceftriaxone every 24 hr is recommend-ed and it should be continued for 24-48 hr after an improvement of symptoms is observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Initial 7-day empirical therapy of cefotaxime should be sufficient to provide a bacteriological cure, and prevent progression of DGI in this case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>Biochemical testing of this organism indicated <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>; however, fair growth of the bacteria on blood agar as well as on chocolate agar made that identification more suspicious because it is known that some <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> strains can grow, but more slowly, and less well, on commercially available sheep blood agar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. The pathogens were detected from all vials between 25.9 and 26.9 hr. This is longer than the average detection time for common gram-negative pathogens isolated from blood cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Severe liver cirrhosis complicated with variceal hemorrhage is clearly associated with an increased risk of bacteremia by opportunistic pathogens that live in the gastrointestinal tract, such as <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Bacterial infections have been reported among 35-66% of patients with cirrhosis who have variceal hemorrhage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Thus, 16S rRNA sequencing was required to confirm the identification. Certain strains such as Por1A serovar and AHU auxotype are alleged to be prone to dissemination; however, this assumption has been challenged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] and these strains are rare in Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Further phenotypic or serologic characterization of this isolate was not performed.</p>
      <p>In this case, unusual clinical conditions of the patient, combined with the microbiological characteristics of the isolates, postponed the identification of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>. Hemorrhage of esophageal varices should be considered as a risk factor for DGI in patients in which <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> grows from blood cultures.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <collab>Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute</collab>
          <article-title>Twentieth informational supplement, M100-S20</article-title>
          <source>Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <publisher-loc>Wayne, PA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name>
          <fpage>84</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Winn</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Koneman's color atlas and textbook of diagnostic microbiology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <edition>6th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
          <fpage>574</fpage>
          <lpage>578</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marrazzo</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Mandell</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</article-title>
          <source>Principles and practice of infectious diseases</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <edition>7th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
          <fpage>2762</fpage>
          <lpage>2765</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>GC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moon</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of concomitant disseminated gonococcal infection with acute viral hepatitis C</article-title>
          <source>Infect Chemother</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>175</fpage>
          <lpage>180</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ellison</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
              <suffix>3rd</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Curd</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohler</surname>
              <given-names>PF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reller</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Judson</surname>
              <given-names>FN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Underlying complement deficiency in patients with disseminated gonococcal infection</article-title>
          <source>Sex Transm Dis</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>201</fpage>
          <lpage>204</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2830678</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kourilsky</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leroy</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peltier</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Complement and liver cell function in 53 patients with liver disease</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>790</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4796289</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Homann</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varming</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>H&#xF8;g&#xE5;sen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mollnes</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graudal</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomsen</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acquired C3 deficiency in patients with alcoholic cirrhosis predisposes to infection and increased mortality</article-title>
          <source>Gut</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>544</fpage>
          <lpage>549</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9176087</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sobhonslidsuk</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roongpisuthipong</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nantiruj</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kulapongse</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Songchitsomboon</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sumalnop</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Impact of liver cirrhosis on nutritional and immunological status</article-title>
          <source>J Med Assoc Thai</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>982</fpage>
          <lpage>988</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11759979</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ashare</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stanford</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hancock</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stark</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lilli</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birrer</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chronic liver disease impairs bacterial clearance in a human mo-del of induced bacteremia</article-title>
          <source>Clin Transl Sci</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>199</fpage>
          <lpage>205</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20443893</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bang</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>WB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bacteremia is a prognostic factor for poor outcome in spontaneous bacterial peritonitis</article-title>
          <source>Scand J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>697</fpage>
          <lpage>702</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17654346</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tapsall</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Limnios</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abu Bakar</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Darussalam</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ping</surname>
              <given-names>YY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buadromo</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surveillance of antibiotic resistance in <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> in the WHO Western Pacific and South East Asian regions, 2007-2008</article-title>
          <source>Commun Dis Intell</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20521493</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Workowski</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berman</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sexually transmitted diseases treatment guidelines, 2006</article-title>
          <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16888612</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Janda</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaydos</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baron</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neisseria</article-title>
          <source>Manual of clinical microbiology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <edition>9th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>608</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shim</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical relevance of time-to-positivity in BACTEC9240 blood culture system</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Lab Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>276</fpage>
          <lpage>283</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20603588</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bert</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ouattara</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leflon-Guibout</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnston</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marcon</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic diversity and virulence profiles of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> isolates causing spontaneous bacterial peritonitis and bacteremia in patients with cirrhosis</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>2709</fpage>
          <lpage>2714</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519468</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ko</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peck</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical significance of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infection in patients with chronic liver diseases</article-title>
          <source>Liver Int</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>1333</fpage>
          <lpage>1338</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20492505</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rerknimitr</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chanyaswad</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kongkam</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kullavanijaya</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Risk of bacteremia in bleeding and nonbleeding gastric varices after endoscopic injection of cyanoacrylate</article-title>
          <source>Endoscopy</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>644</fpage>
          <lpage>649</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18561097</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goulis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patch</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burroughs</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bacterial infection in the pathogenesis of variceal bleeding</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>353</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>142</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10023916</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yum</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryeom</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Auxotype and antibiotic resistance pattern of <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> isolated in Korea</article-title>
          <source>J Korean Soc Microbiol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>507</fpage>
          <lpage>515</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Colonies of <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> on chocolate (A) and blood agar plates (B) after a 2-day incubation.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjlm-31-118-g001"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
