<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Interv Aging</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Interv Aging</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinical Interventions in Aging</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1176-9092</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1178-1998</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dove Medical Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23569366</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3615840</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/CIA.S42174</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">cia-8-341</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Rapid Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Basal cell carcinomas in elderly patients treated by cryotherapy</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chiriac</surname>
            <given-names>Anca</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-cia-8-341">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mihaila</surname>
            <given-names>Doina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-cia-8-341">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Foia</surname>
            <given-names>Liliana</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-cia-8-341">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-cia-8-341"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Solovan</surname>
            <given-names>Caius</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-cia-8-341">4</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1-cia-8-341"><label>1</label>Department of Dermatology, Nicolina Medical Center, Ia&#x15F;i, Romania</aff>
      <aff id="af2-cia-8-341"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, St Maria Children&#x2019;s Hospital, Ia&#x15F;i, Romania</aff>
      <aff id="af3-cia-8-341"><label>3</label>Surgical Department, Grigore T Popa University of Medicine and Pharmacy, Ia&#x15F;i, Romania</aff>
      <aff id="af4-cia-8-341"><label>4</label>Victor Babe&#x15F; University of Medicine, Timi&#x15F;oara, Romania</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1-cia-8-341">Correspondence: Liliana Foia Surgical Department, Grigore T Popa University of Medicine and Pharmacy, 16 Str Universitatii, Ia&#x15F;i, RO-700115, Romania Email <email>lilifoia@yahoo.co.uk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Dove Press titles changed from ppub to collections in 2009.
								Fake ppub written to satisfy Coll Date Type=ppub-->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <fpage>341</fpage>
      <lpage>345</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2013 Chiriac et al, publisher and licensee Dove Medical Press Ltd</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted noncommercial use, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Basal cell carcinoma is a malignant skin tumor with high incidence in our country, especially in rural areas, on sun-exposed skin (particularly on the face) in elderly patients. We present three cases of basal cell carcinoma with good results with cryotherapy. This report aims to outline and to prove that in some difficult situations, a simple, inexpensive, easy-to-perform procedure with no contraindications and with minimal side effects (erythema, mild pain) can be applied and resolve such cases.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>basal cell carcinoma</kwd>
        <kwd>cryotherapy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Case reports</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 1</title>
        <p>An 84-year-old woman was transferred from the cardiovascular department, where she was hospitalized for heart failure and atrial fibrillation, for a lesion on the dorsal aspect of the left foot that had developed a few months before hospitalization. She had no history of malignancies, nor previous trauma or sun or other type of radiation exposure. On dermatological examination, a round ulceration 21 mm in diameter surrounded by an inflammatory rim (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-cia-8-341">Figure 1</xref>) was observed. No pain, no pruritus, no palpable lymph nodes were associated.</p>
        <p>A biopsy specimen from the central part of the ulceration was taken, and the histopathological examination showed several basaloid island nests in the dermis, small hyperchromatic nuclei, and a palisading aspect, which led to a diagnosis of basal cell carcinoma &#x2013; superficial type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-cia-8-341">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>Taking into consideration the heart failure, the atrial fibrillation, and anticoagulant therapy, topical cryotherapy (liquid nitrogen applied with a cotton swab) daily for 5 days was the optimal therapeutic choice accepted by the patient, her family, and the cardiologist.</p>
        <p>Considering that according to most clinical practice guidelines for the management of basal cell carcinomas, the treated area should exceed 5 mm, after careful delineation of the excision area with a pen; liquid nitrogen was applied with a cotton swab of a size that covered the tumor plus 5 mm around it. In many cases, we applied more than the theoretically delineated line, taking care of the surrounding normal skin by covering it with sterile drape.</p>
        <p>With only one ibuprofen tablet administration before the procedure and no anesthesia, the daily wound cryotherapy application was started. The patient did not complain of any side effects (except some slight pain), and finally, after a short hospitalization of a few hours, she was discharged from the hospital with minimal erythema and was monitored for more than a year and a half.</p>
        <p>During the follow-up period, no other biopsy postcryotherapy was available, due to the age of the patient, associated diseases, and family disapproval. In regular clinical examinations, no cutaneous lesions that could possibly raise the suspicion of recurrence were observed, mild erythema and xerosis being comfortable and handled toward good evolution by emollients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-cia-8-341">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 2</title>
        <p>A 78-year-old woman was transferred from the cardiovascular department, where she was hospitalized for heart failure and hypertension, for a slow progressive lesion on the left tragus, observed by the patient a few years before the hospitalization. The medical history report included no malignancies, trauma or exposure to sun or other type of radiations.</p>
        <p>Dermatological examination revealed an ulcerated tumor surrounded by inflammation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-cia-8-341">Figure 4</xref>); the area was painful when touched and was not associated with any pruritus or palpable lymph nodes.</p>
        <p>A punch biopsy was taken, and histopathology led to a diagnosis of basal cell carcinoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-cia-8-341">Figure 5</xref>). Cryotherapy was also applied once daily for 7 days, with ibuprofen orally when needed, without hospitalization or bandage application (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-cia-8-341">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 3</title>
        <p>A 78-year-old female patient was referred to us from the otorhinolaryngology department for a basal cell carcinoma of the nose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-cia-8-341">Figure 7</xref>), confirmed by histopathological report of a previous biopsy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-cia-8-341">Figure 8</xref>). She was under treatment for dementia, and the family refused any surgical intervention. The patient was confused, under medication, and no medical data were provided by the family.</p>
        <p>We applied 2 weeks&#x2019; (one application per 2-day interval) liquid nitrogen with a cotton swab (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-cia-8-341">Figure 9</xref>), through the same protocol described above, no anesthesia or other medication being necessary during the period of applications. There was no bleeding during the procedure, and very good compliance and cooperation from the patient.</p>
        <p>Based on clinical grounds, we consider the final outcome excellent, with no claimed symptoms or local tumor recurrence at 1-year follow-up.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Healthy tissue and malignant tissue cannot survive in extremely cold conditions, and will die due to ice formation in the fluid outside cells which results in cellular dehydration and intracellularly ice formation at &#x2212;40&#xB0;C or even less. The resulting intracellular ice crystals destroy the cells, bursting from both swelling caused by ice expansion inside the cell or shrinking caused by water exit from the cell, the ice forming within small tumor vessels, causing clotting. Since the average blood-clotting time is approximately 10 minutes and the extreme cold is maintained for at least 10&#x2013;15 minutes, the lethal ice temperatures have been reached.</p>
      <p>For lesions located on the nose, eyelids, and external ear, excision is complicated. Topical photodynamic therapy (PDT) has been previously applied with some results, but required pretreatment and displayed risk for recurrences,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cia-8-341">1</xref> associated or not with imiquimod.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-cia-8-341">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-cia-8-341">3</xref> In these cases, cryotherapy is a good alternative to surgery.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cia-8-341">1</xref></p>
      <p>PDT is generally well tolerated, but besides its price, has many side effects, ie, erythema, edema, erosions, and most patients complaining of severe pain that can last for days after the procedure.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-cia-8-341">4</xref> This is not the case for cryotherapy, where slight erythema and mild pain can be related by some of the patients, important facts, especially when considering the selected age-group.</p>
      <p>PDT is a form of phototherapy, a very different type of action than cryotherapy,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-cia-8-341">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-cia-8-341">6</xref> that requires expensive modern equipment, skillful medical staff. The costs of the procedures are enhanced, and it is also a blind method of tumoral tissue destruction.</p>
      <p>Cryotherapy is much easier to use, even in a trained general practitioner office, the method requiring minimal investments, with high effectiveness (although with no histological control), and it is easily accepted by most patients in some critical conditions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-cia-8-341">7</xref> Our cases were superficial basal cell carcinomas (as one can see in the clinical pictures and histopathological images).</p>
      <p>The report of Peikert<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cia-8-341">1</xref> emphasizes the good response of cryosurgery even in deeper or nodular basal carcinoma. In his report, 69 patients with 100 nonfacial tumors, &#x2264;2 cm in diameter, consisting of superficial basal cell carcinoma, superficial nodular basal cell carcinoma with papillary dermal invasion, squamous cell carcinoma in situ, and squamous cell carcinoma with papillary dermal invasion, were treated with curettage and cryotherapy. And the results were more than promising: no recurrences after 1 year of follow-up. His conclusion was (like ours): &#x201C;Curettage and cryosurgery is a simple, highly effective, and reliable treatment method for select, low-risk non-melanoma skin cancers.&#x201D;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-cia-8-341">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-cia-8-341">6</xref></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Cryotherapy is an alternative treatment option when surgical removal of a tumor may be difficult or, for some patients, impossible; it is a localized therapy with minimal invasion, less costly, less pain during and after the procedure, and can be done in an outpatient clinic or during a short hospitalization.</p>
      <p>Although further research is needed to determine its long-term effectiveness, cryotherapy has been shown to be effective in selected patients.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Disclosure</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="b1-cia-8-341">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peikert</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prospective trial of curettage and cryosurgery in the management of non-facial, superficial, and minimally invasive basal and squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Int J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>1135</fpage>
          <lpage>1138</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22126880</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2-cia-8-341">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Messeguer</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Serra-Guillen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Echeverria</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A pilot study of clinical efficacy of imiquimod and cryotherapy for the treatment of basal cell carcinoma with incomplete response to imiquimod</article-title>
          <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>879</fpage>
          <lpage>881</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21752102</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3-cia-8-341">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moutran</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maatouk</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stephan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomb</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment of nodular basal cell carcinoma with cryotherapy and reduced protocol of imiquimod</article-title>
          <source>Cutis</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>256</fpage>
          <lpage>257</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23270198</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4-cia-8-341">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ericson</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wennberg</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lark&#xF6;</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Review of photodynamic therapy in actinic keratosis and basal cell carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Ther Clin Risk Manag</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18728698</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5-cia-8-341">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mi</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chai</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zuo</surname>
              <given-names>YG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A randomized clinical comparative study of cryotherapy plus photodynamic therapy vs cryotherapy in the treatment of multiple condylomata acuminata</article-title>
          <source>Photodermatol Photoimmunol Photomed</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>176</fpage>
          <lpage>180</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21729164</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6-cia-8-341">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lezcano</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Martino</surname>
              <given-names>OB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Knopfelmacher</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bolla de Lezcano</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bowen&#x2019;s disease treated with cryotherapy combined with topical 5% imiquimod. Alternative treatment to surgery in elderly patients with co-morbidities</article-title>
          <source>N Dermatol Online</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>61</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7-cia-8-341">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Talebi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farmanbar</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abolfazli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarraf Shirazi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of physiological hyperpigmentation of oral mucosa by cryosurgical treatment: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Dent Res Dent Clin Dent Prospects</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>148</fpage>
          <lpage>151</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23277862</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Ulceration on the dorsal aspect of the left foot: inflammatory rim around the ulceration, desquamation, and diffuse erythema.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Proliferation of basaloid cell with palisading disposition (hematoxylin and eosin, 40&#xD7;).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Clinical aspect after therapy: xerosis, small linear erosion, desquamation.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>The tumoral lesion at admission.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f5-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Islands of basaloid cells with palisading disposition in the upper dermis, with contraction around them (hematoxylin and eosin, 40&#xD7;).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig5"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f6-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Clinical aspect after cryotherapy: no ulceration, no tumoral lesion, just a slight area of erythema.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig6"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f7-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 7</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A small bleeding tumor covered by crust on the nose, multiple actinic keratosis on the face.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig7"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f8-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 8</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Basal cell carcinoma: typical nuclear palisading at the peripheral layer of the tumor (hematoxylin and eosin, 100&#xD7;).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig8"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f9-cia-8-341" position="float">
      <label>Figure 9</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Cryotherapy procedure.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cia-8-341Fig9"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
