<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Otorhinolaryngologica Italica</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0392-100X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1827-675X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pacini Editore SpA</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23620643</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3631812</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title xml:lang="en">Unusual presentation of obstructive sleep apnoea
syndrome due to a giant mandible osteoma:
case report and literature review</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="it">
          <trans-title>Presentazione atipica di una sindrome delle apnee ostruttive notturne causata da un osteoma gigante della mandibola: presentazione del caso e revisione della letteratura</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>TARSITANO</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>MARCHETTI</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Maxillofacial Surgery Unit, Policlinico S. Orsola-Malpighi, "Alma Mater Studiorum", University of Bologna, Italy</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">Address for correspondence: Achille Tarsitano, Maxillofacial Surgery Unit, "S. Orsola-Malpighi" Hospital, University of Bologna, via G. Massarenti 9, 40100 Bologna, Italy. Tel. +39 051 6364204. E-mail: <email xlink:href="achilletarsitano@gmail.com">achilletarsitano@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>33</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>63</fpage>
      <lpage>66</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Copyright by Societ&#xE0; Italiana di Otorinolaringologia e Chirurgia Cervico-Facciale</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way. For details, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>SUMMARY</title>
        <p>Osteomas are benign lesions composed of mature compact and/or cancellous bone that grow continuously. Their pathogenesis is unknown. It has been considered to be a neoplasm, a developmental or reactive osteogenic lesion resulting from muscle traction on the periosteum, or due to trauma. Herein, we report an unusual case of giant osteoma of the mandible depressing the lateral pharyngeal wall, interfering with normal respiration during the night. The uniqueness of this case is related to snoring and sleep apnoea symptoms. In fact, he presented to our Department because daytime sleepiness hindered his work, and not for the evident facial swelling. We reported our experience in diagnosis, treatment and follow-up of this uncommon disease. Polysomnography, CT scan and 3-D PAS volume analysis are useful tools to study in detail the aetiology of apnoea and assess outcomes.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="it">
        <title>RIASSUNTO</title>
        <p>Gli osteomi dei mascellari sono lesioni ossee costituite da matrice ossea compatta e spongiosa che si accresce in maniera incontrollata. La patogenesi non &#xE8; ben conosciuta. Queste lesioni sono state variamente considerate come neoplasie, neoformazioni di natura reattiva risultanti da trazioni muscolari sul periostio, o secondarie a traumi. In questo articolo presentiamo un caso atipico di osteoma gigante della mandibola dislocante la parete laterale del faringe e causante un'interferenza con la respirazione notturna del paziente. L'unicit&#xE0; di questo caso &#xE8; correlata, oltre che alle dimensioni dell'osteoma, alla sintomatologia di presentazione, compatibile con un quadro di sindrome delle apnee ostruttive del sonno. Di seguito riportiamo la nostra esperienza nella diagnosi, trattamento e follow-up di questo caso. Esami polisonnografici TC e morfologico-volumetrici dello spazio aereo posteriore sono stati di utile ausilio per l'identificazione dell'eziologia e la valutazione degli outcomes successivi al trattamento.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>KEY WORDS</title>
        <kwd>Obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Giant osteoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Mandible tumours</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="S1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Osteomas are benign lesions composed of mature compact and/or cancellous bone that grow continuously. Osteomas are histologically characterized by the proliferation of either compact or cancellous bone. They may arise from endosteal or periosteal surfaces and occur as single or multiple lesions with considerable variation in size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>. Osteomas are essentially tumours of craniofacial bone, rarely affecting the extragnathic skeleton, although cases of soft tissue osteomas arising within the bulk of skeletal muscles have been reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04"><sup>4</sup></xref>. Their pathogenesis is unknown. It has been considered to be a neoplasm, a developmental or reactive osteogenic lesion resulting from muscle traction on the periosteum, or due to trauma <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05"><sup>5</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Osteomas exhibit continuous growth rather than growth cessation at adulthood, and this characteristic is the major feature distinguishing them from other bony exostoses such as tori <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07"><sup>7</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>In addition, bony exostoses such as tori, unlike osteomas, have a predilection for specific sites in jawbones <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08"><sup>8</sup></xref>. Osteomas of the jaws may arise on the surface of the bone as a polypoid or sessile mass (periosteal osteoma), in the medullary bone (endosteal osteoma) or in the soft tissue (extraskeletal osteoma). Osteomas occur more frequently in the mandible than the maxilla, and males are affected more frequently than females with a ratio of about 2:1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09"><sup>9</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Age at presentation has ranged from 14 to 58 years, with a mean of about 29.4 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09"><sup>9</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Here, we report an unusual case of giant osteoma of the mandible depressing the lateral pharyngeal wall, which interfered with normal respiration during the night causing sleep apnoea. Diagnostic procedures, surgical management, follow-up and the available literature are discussed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 41-year-old Caucasian man was seen with a slowly progressive, painless swelling of the mandible. The patient was a bus driver, and his chief complaint was snoring and daytime sleepiness. He also stated that the swelling had existed since the age of 14 years, when a diffuse bony enlargement of the right side of the mandible was first noted. The patient was in good health with no history of previous facial trauma or contributory medical factors. The continuous growth resulted in dysphagia and facial asymmetry.</p>
      <p>On extraoral examination, a hard, subcutaneous, painless mass of the right mandible angle was found. The sensibility of the lower lip was undisturbed. On intraoral inspection, a shift of the right oropharyngeal wall was seen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Polysomnography, orthopantomography and CT scan were performed.</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intraoral inspection showing a swelling of the right oropharyngeal wall.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-63-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Polysomnography showed a severe grade of obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome, with an apnoea-hypopnea index (AHI index) of 31. CT showed a diffuse enlargement of the entire right mandible extending caudally to the lateral and medial side. On the surface polypoid bony swellings were seen. The bony mass protruded into the pharynx and displaced the oropharyngeal lateral wall to the contralateral side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Colonoscopy was performed and Gardner's syndrome was excluded.</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Axial CT-scan showing diffuse enlargement of the entire right mandible extending to the lateral and medial side.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-63-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Because of the symptoms described, facial asymmetry and the progression of the lesion, it was decided to perform an operative correction of the right mandible. Under general anaesthesia with naso-endotracheal intubation, the mandible was approached extraorally using submandibular access (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The submandibular gland was preserved.</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intra-operative image showing the large mandibular mass that was approached extraorally using submandibular access.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-63-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Using a saw and chisel, the lobular part of the lateral and medial side of the corpus and ascending ramus were resected and the mandible was reshaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Histological examination showed a compact, lamellar bony structure diagnosed as osteoid osteoma.</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intra-operative image showing the surgical field after resection of medial side and mandible reshaping.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-63-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Postoperative three-dimensional CT showed a more acceptable contour of the mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F5" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Postoperative three-dimensional CT-scan showing a more acceptable mandible contour.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-63-g005"/>
      </fig>
      <p>A significant change of posterior airway space (PAS) was achieved leading to normal oropharyngeal anatomy. A 3-dimensional volumetric analysis of PAS was performed using CT data, and showed a normal volume of 25.92 cc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F6" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 6.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>3-D volumetric analysis of posterior airway space (PAS) performed using 3-D CT data that showed a normal PAS anatomy and an airway volume of 25.92 cc.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-63-g006"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Post-operative polysomnography showed an AH index of 8. The following 6 years were uneventful and there was a decline in dysphagia with a satisfying aesthetic result. Furthermore, the patient reported that he no longer snored.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Osteoma of the jaws is rare. In instances of mandibular involvement, the most common sites are the angle and lower border of the body <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04"><sup>4</sup></xref>. The lesions generally arise in close proximity to areas of muscle attachment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>, as in this case. They are mostly unilateral, pedunculated, mushroom- like masses. In the present case, the origin of the osteoma could be both central and peripheral as it caused diffuse enlargement of the mandible.</p>
      <p>Since osteomas of the skull can be part of Gardner's syndrome, this possibility has to be excluded. This syndrome is based upon the presence of numerous adenomatous colorectal polyps, soft and hard tissue abnormalities, and congenital hypertrophy of the retinal pigment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><sup>10</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Osteomas are often noted in the sixth decade, but reports range from 14 to 58 years, with a mean of 29.4 years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09"><sup>9</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Although the aetiology and pathogenesis of osteoma is still unclear, traumatic, congenital, inflammatory or endocrine causes have been considered as possible aetiologic factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><sup>11</sup></xref>. Most peripheral osteomas appear to have a very slow growth rate. They often go undetected, since they are usually asymptomatic, unless incidentally noted on a routine radiographic survey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><sup>12</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>On occasion, peripheral osteomas may expand to the extent that they cause facial asymmetry and functional impairment as in the current case report.</p>
      <p>The uniqueness of this case is related to snoring and sleep apnoea symptoms presented by the patient. In fact, he presented to our Department because of daytime sleepiness which hindered his work rather than for facial swelling.</p>
      <p>In recent medical literature, to our knowledge, there are no cases of obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome due to mandible osteoma. We also report our experience in diagnosis, treatment and follow-up of this uncommon disease. Polysomnography, CT scan and 3-D PAS volume analysis are useful tools to study in detail the aetiology of apnoea and assess outcomes.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bodner</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gatot</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sion-Vardy</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Peripheral osteoma
of the mandibular ascending ramus</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>1446</fpage>
          <lpage>1449</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9846545</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Richards</surname>
              <given-names>HE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strider</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Short</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large peripheral
osteoma arising from the genial tubercle area</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg
Oral Med Oral Pathol</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>268</fpage>
          <lpage>271</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3458130</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kaplan</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calderon</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buchner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Peripheral osteoma of the
mandible: a study of 10 new cases and analysis of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>467</fpage>
          <lpage>470</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8169708</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Longo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Califano</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maria</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
              <prefix>De</prefix>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Solitary osteoma of
the mandibular ramus: report of a case</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Maxillofac
Surg</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>698</fpage>
          <lpage>700</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11381400</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolinsky</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grodjesk</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Solitary peripheral
osteoma of the jaws: report of a case and review of the
literature</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Surg</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>452</fpage>
          <lpage>455</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6929330</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cutilli</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quinn</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Traumatically induced peripheral
osteoma: report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>667</fpage>
          <lpage>667</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1437033</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ertas</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tozoglu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Uncommon peripheral osteoma of
the mandible: report of two cases</article-title>
          <source>J Contemp Dent Pract</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>98</fpage>
          <lpage>104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12937600</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sayan</surname>
              <given-names>NB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ucok</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karasu</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Peripheral osteoma of
the oral and maxillofacial region: a study of 35 new cases</article-title>
          <source>J
Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>1299</fpage>
          <lpage>1301</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12420263</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bosshardt</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gordon</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westerberg</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A recurrent
peripheral osteoma of the mandible: report of a case</article-title>
          <source>J Oral
Surg</source>
          <year>1971</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>446</fpage>
          <lpage>450</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5283383</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pierce</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weisbord</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McKusick</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gardner's syndrome: formal genetics and statistical analysis of a large Canadian kindred</article-title>
          <source>Clin Genet</source>
          <year>1970</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>65</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bessho</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murakami</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iizuka</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Osteoma in mandibular
condyle</article-title>
          <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>372</fpage>
          <lpage>372</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3112270</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Viswanatha</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Maxillary sinus osteoma: two cases
and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>202</fpage>
          <lpage>205</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22767988</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
