<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Orthop</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Orthop</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ORT</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Orthopaedica</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1745-3674</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1745-3682</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Informa Healthcare</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24460109</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3940983</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/17453674.2014.885355</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ORT_A_885355_O</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Editorial and Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Atypical fracture of the femur in a patient using denosumab &#x2013; a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="a1" contrib-type="author" corresp="no">
          <name>
            <surname>Schilcher</surname>
            <given-names>J&#xF6;rg</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="a2" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Aspenberg</surname>
            <given-names>Per</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AF0001"><institution>Orthopedics, Department of Clinical and Experimental Medicine, Faculty of Health Science</institution>, <addr-line>Link&#xF6;ping University</addr-line>, <country>Sweden</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email xlink:href="per.aspenberg@liu.se">per.aspenberg@liu.se</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>85</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>6</fpage>
      <lpage>7</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Nordic Orthopaedic Federation</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the source is credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A woman born in 1930 was diagnosed with osteoporosis in 2000, and was started on treatment with alendronate. Her lumbar T-score in 2010 was &#x2013;3.0. In 2008, she had a displaced atypical fracture of her left femur, which healed uneventfully after intramedullary nailing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). No radiographs of her contralateral femur were obtained. She continued taking alendronate until it was stopped in September 2010. In February 2011, she received a single zoledronate infusion. No bisphosphonate was given after that, due to reduced kidney function. She received a first injection of denosumab in April 2012 and then every 6 months, with the last and fourth injection in October 2013.</p>
    <fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Left femur. Atypical fracture while using alendronate, 2008.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ORT-85-06-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <p>The patient has been generally healthy otherwise, with no drugs known to influence the skeleton. She took long daily walks until September 2013. At this time&#x2014;29 months after the last zoledronate injection and after 16 months on denosumab&#x2014;she noted slight pain in her right thigh and knee. In October, the pain increased and soon necessitated the use of a walking frame. She sought acute medical attention after being unable to rise from a chair on January 5, 2014. Radiographs showed 2 focal thickenings of the lateral diaphyseal cortex, 1 of them with a visible crack (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). She was operated with an intramedullary nail on the day after.</p>
    <fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Right femur. Multifocal atypical fractures while using denosumab 2014 (overview and magnification). Note the visible crack.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ORT-85-06-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="ss1">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>It is apparent from the current literature that bisphosphonates cause atypical fractures, although rarely, through their anti-resorptive activity. Because denosumab is also anti-resorptive, it should be no surprise if it causes atypical fractures (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Aspenberg 2014</xref>). The producer warns of this complication in the product label, and mentions that suspected atypical fractures have occurred in their studies, although they do not go into detail.</p>
      <p>This is the third case of denosumab-associated atypical fracture reported in the literature that can be reached via PubMed. The first report appeared online in October 2013 (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Drampalos 2014</xref>) and is printed in this issue of Acta Orthopaedica. The second case was published online in December (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Thompson 2013</xref>). There is another report of a spontaneous subtrochanteric fracture in a patient receiving denusomab, but that patient had hyperparathyroidism and her fracture did not meet the radiographic criteria for an atypical fracture (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Paparodis 2013</xref>).</p>
      <p>All 3 patients reported with atypical fractures had used a bisphosphonate before switching to denosumab. In the first patient, bilateral fractures occurred 1 and 13 months after the drug switch (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Drampalos 2014</xref>). The second case also had bilateral fractures. She had rheumatoid arthritis and had used a corticosteroid and immune modulatory drugs. She had been free of bisphosphonates for 12 years when her first atypical fracture appeared, 3 months after the first injection of denosumab. She then had another, incomplete atypical fracture diagnosed 1 year later, after which denosumab use was stopped (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Thompson 2013</xref>). In our patient, the time between the last zoledronate injection and surgery was almost 3 years. The bisphosphonate-associated risk of atypical fracture diminishes rapidly after use of the drug is discontinued (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Schilcher et al. 2011</xref>), and the long time after cessation in our case speaks against the bisphosphonate being a cause&#x2013;&#x2013;although it is possible that the fracture emerged before the patient noted symptoms.</p>
      <p>The short duration of denosumab use before the appearance of the atypical fractures in the 3 cases argues in favor of the theory that atypical fractures are a consequence of impaired targeted remodeling of fresh microcracks, rather than being a consequence of generally altered bone material properties (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Aspenberg 2014</xref>). It is unlikely that a reduction of general bone remodeling for less than a year would increase the brittleness of the femoral cortex.</p>
      <p>Atypical fractures occur also in patients without anti-resorptive drugs, and only future epidemiologic studies with radiographic adjudication will tell about the strength of the association with denosumab.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>PA has received research support from Amgen related to denosumab.</p>
      <p>JS collected the data and PA wrote the manuscript; both authors revised it.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aspenberg</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Denosumab and atypical femoral fractures</article-title>
          <source>Acta Orthop</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24171676</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Drampalos</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skarpas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barbounakis</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Michos</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Atypical femoral fractures bilaterally in a patient receiving denosumab</article-title>
          <source>Acta Orthop</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24171686</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paparodis</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buehring</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pelley</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Binkley</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23337161?dopt=Abstract">A case of an unusual subtrochanteric fracture in a patient receiving denosumab</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Endocr Pract</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>e64</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23337161</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schilcher</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Micha&#xEB;lsson</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aspenberg</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21542743?dopt=Abstract">Bisphosphonate use and atypical fractures of the femoral shaft</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>364</volume>
          <issue>18</issue>
          <fpage>1728</fpage>
          <lpage>37</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21542743</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>RN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armstrong</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heyburn</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24389366?dopt=Abstract">Bilateral atypical femoral fractures in a patient prescribed denosumab &#x2013; a case report</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Bone</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <comment>pii: S8756-3282(13)00549-8</comment>
          <comment>doi: 10.1016/j.bone.2013.12.027</comment>
          <comment>Epub ahead of print</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
