<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pamj</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1937-8688</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21436947</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3063496</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Life Sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Medicine</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Neuroendocrine differentiation in a case of cervical cancer</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mona Mohamed</surname>
            <given-names>Rashed</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alemayehu</surname>
            <given-names>Bekele</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Department of Pathology, General Organization of Teaching Hospitals and Institutes, Egypt</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label> Department of Pathology, Jimma University, Ethiopia</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Mona M. Rashed, MD, Department of Pathology, Damanhour National Medical Institute, affiliated to the: General Organization of Teaching Hospitals and Institutes, Egypt</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <elocation-id>4</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9;Mounia Serraj et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract abstract-type="executive-summary">
        <p>Neuroendocrine neoplasms may occur in the uterine cervix, although rarely; it accounts for 0.5-1% of all malignant tumors of the uterine cervix. A case report of an Ethiopian female presented at the Gynecology Out-Patient Clinic at Jimma University Hospital, complaining from irregular vaginal bleeding over the previous three months. Clinically there was a cauliflower cervical mass; histopathologically it was formed of sheets of small cell tumor; that further showed neuroendocrine differentiation, as demonstrated by chromogranin-A positivity. It is important to differentiate small cell carcinoma from other malignant tumors of the uterine cervix. Morphological features play an important role in making a diagnosis and the immunohistochemistry study can offer an additional useful assistance.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Key words:</title>
        <kwd>Cervical cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>cervix</kwd>
        <kwd>chromogranine A</kwd>
        <kwd>small cell carcinoma</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Neuroendocrine neoplasm may occur in the uterine cervix; it accounts for 0.5-1% of all malignant tumors of the uterine cervix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>]. It is generally accepted that the integration of HPV into the host genome is the single most important event in evolution of cervical carcinomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. Almost all neuroendocrine carcinomas of the cervix are associated with HPV 18 or seldom HPV 16 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>]. Neuroendocrine carcinomas most likely develop from neuroendocrine cells occurring in the normal endocervix or from stimulated multipotential reserve cells of the endocervical epithelium undergoing neuroendocrine metaplasia and hyperplasia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Neuroendocrine tumors of uterine cervix are divided into small and large cell type as well as carcinoid and atypical carcinoid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. Small cell neuroendocrine carcinoma of the uterine cervix is a rare tumor with a highly aggressive clinical course and poor prognosis due to the high frequency of lymph node involvement at an early stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>]. It is important to differentiate small cell carcinoma of the uterine cervix from other malignant tumors of the cervix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>]. Morphological features, cytopathology and histopathology as well as the immunocytochemistry studies play important roles in making an accuratediagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="case report" id="s2">
      <title>Patient and case report</title>
      <p>An Ethiopian female patient presented at the Gynecology Out-Patient Clinic at Jimma University Hospital, she was 42 years old; complaining of irregular vaginal bleeding over the previous three months. On clinical examination there was a cervical cauliflower mass about 4x4 cm, covering the entire cervical surface. The cervical mass was bleeding on touch. The pelvic ultrasound revealed a bulky cervix with a heterogeneous echo-pattern; moderate pelvic fluid collections were noticed. The patient was serologically negative for HIV. Total abdominal hysterectomy with bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy was performed. The uterus was of normal size with no recognizable tumors either grossly of microscopically. The lymph nodes couldn&#x2019;t be assessed. The tumor was staged as Stage IB2: T1b2 N0 M0</p>
      <p>Histo-pathological examination of the cervical mass revealed tumor cells arranged into lobules and solid sheets, the tumor was composed of small undifferentiated cells that showed palisading at the periphery of clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1</xref>). The tumor cells presented pleomorphic nuclei, with hyperchromatic nuclei, hyperchromatic granular chromatin and the cytoplasm was scanty. Moreover the nuclear-cytoplasmic ratio was high and there was an evidence of increased mitosis as well as apoptotic changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">figure 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>Immuno-histochemical study was done aiming to recognize neuroendocrine differentiation of the tumor. The paraffin-embedded sections of the cervix were immune-histochemically characterized with antibody to chromogranin-A, the bound antibodies were detected by a standard avidinbiotin complex method with a peroxidase and diaminobenzidine color development system. The cervical tumor showed neuroendocrine differentiation, as demonstrated by chromogranin-A positivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figure 3</xref>).</p>
      <p>The diagnosis was pathologically reported as &#x201C;Small Cell Type of Neuroendocrine Cancer of Uterine Cervix&#x201D; and the patient was referred to the Oncology Department at Addis Ababa University for chemo-radiotherapy.</p>
      <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1:</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Tumor composed of small undifferentiated cells that showed palisading at the periphery of clusters (H&amp;Ex200)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pamj-06-04-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2:</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The tumor cells presenting pleomorphic nuclei, with hyperchromatic nuclei with hyperchromatic granular chromatin and the cytoplasm is scanty (H&amp;Ex200)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pamj-06-04-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3:</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The cervical tumor showing neuroendocrine differentiation, as demonstrated by chromogranin-positivity (Chromogranin-Ax400)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pamj-06-04-g003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Small cell carcinomas of neuroendocrine origin are considered to be the poorly differentiated variety of carcinoid tumors; it is a rare tumor with a highly aggressive clinical course and poor prognosis due to the high frequency of lymph node involvement at an early stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>]; thus neuroendocrine differentiation is an indicator of poor prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>The normal endocervix contains as many as 20% of argyophilic cells resembling endocrine cells; cervical neuroendocrine tumor formation can arise from these cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>]. Savargaonkar et al reported that neuroendocrine differentiation was present in 20.9% of his series study of cervical carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>Clinically, abnormal vaginal bleeding is the most commonly reported symptoms. In spite of the neuroendocrine origin of this tumor, the clinical carcinoid syndrome in the neuroendocrine tumors of the cervix is very unusual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]; but on the other hand, a primary carcinoid tumor other than the cervix, with direct secretion of its mediators into the systemic circulation could be responsible for the carcinoid syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>The distinction of squamous, glandular and neuroendocrine carcinomas of the cervix is clinically significant for at least two reasons. First, a poorly differentiated carcinoma of glandular origin, even with early invasion, is likely to have a worse prognosis than a similar squamous tumor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. Second, neuroendocrine carcinomas are inherently more aggressive than their squamous counterparts and are managed with different protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]. Expression of chromogranin A, synaptophysin, and various other proteins involved in the formation of neurosecretory granules or CD 56, a neural cell adhesion molecule, can be used as markers of neuroendocrine differentiation, as in neuroendocrine carcinomas of other organs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. Neuroendocrine carcinomas of the cervix are regarded as highly aggressive tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>] with subclinical hematogenous and lymphatic metastases frequently even in early disease. Neuroendocrine features in poorly differentiated carcinomas of the cervix indicate a poor outcome [15]. Sixty-five percent of patients with cervical non-small cell neuroendocrine carcinomas die within 3 yr of diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="s4">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>We concluded that it is important to differentiate small cell carcinoma from other malignant tumors of the uterine cervix. The diagnosis of small cell neuroendocrine carcinoma depends on the combination of light microscopy and immunohistochemistry. Morphological features play an important role in making a diagnosis and the immunohistochemistry study can offer an additional useful assistance.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="interest" id="s5">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="contribution" id="s6">
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p><bold>M.Rashed</bold> was the pathologist responsible for confirming the diagnosis of the case by the immunohistochemistry study. <bold>A. Bekele</bold> was the first to see the case as neuroendocrine carcinoma and both shared the ideas in reporting this case report.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Gilks</surname>
            <given-names>CB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Young</surname>
            <given-names>RH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gersell</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clement</surname>
            <given-names>PB</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Large cell carcinoma of the uterine cervix: a clinicopathologic study of 12 cases.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol.</source>
          <year>1997 Aug</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>(8)</issue>
          <fpage>905</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9255253</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chu</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Small Cell Carcinoma of the Uterine Cervix: A Case Report with Emphasis on Cytopathological Findings.</article-title>
          <source>Tzu Chi Med J.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>(6)</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mannion</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>WS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Man</surname>
            <given-names>YG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhuang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Albores-Saavedra</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tavassoli</surname>
            <given-names>FA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Endocrine tumors of the cervix: Morphologic assessment expression of human papilloma virus, and evaluation for loss of heterozygosity on 1p, 3p, 11q, and 17p.</article-title>
          <source>Cancer.</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>1391</fpage>
          <lpage>1400</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9762941</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Conner</surname>
            <given-names>MG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Richter</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moran</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hameed</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Albores-Saavedra</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Small cell carcinoma of the cervix: A clinicopathologic and immunohistochemical study of 23 cases.</article-title>
          <source>Ann Diagn Pathol.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>345</fpage>
          <lpage>348</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12478483</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Savargaonkar</surname>
            <given-names>PR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hale</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mutton</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Manning</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buckley</surname>
            <given-names>CH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Neuroendocrine differentiation in cervical carcinoma.</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Pathol.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8655680</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Albores-Saavedra</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gersell</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gilks</surname>
            <given-names>CB et al</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Terminology of endocrine tumors of the uterine cervix: results of a workshop sponsored by the College of American Pathologists and the National Cancer Institute.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med.</source>
          <year>1997 Jan</year>
          <volume>121</volume>
          <issue>(1)</issue>
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9111090</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bermudez</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vighi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garcia</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sardi</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Neuroendocrine cervical carcinoma: a diagnostic and therapeutic challenge.</article-title>
          <source>Gynecol Oncol.</source>
          <year>2001 Jul</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <issue>(1)</issue>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11426959</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Koch</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Azumi</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Furlong</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jha</surname>
            <given-names>RC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kehoe</surname>
            <given-names>TE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Trowbridge</surname>
            <given-names>CH</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>O&#x2019;Dorisio TM, Chrousos GP and Clement SC. Carcinoid Syndrome Caused by an Atypical Carcinoid of the Uterine Cervix.</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab.</source>
          <year>1999 Nov</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <issue>(11)</issue>
          <fpage>4209</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10566674</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Stockdale</surname>
            <given-names>AD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leader</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Phillips</surname>
            <given-names>RH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Henry</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The carcinoid syndrome and multiple hormone secretion associated with a carcinoid tumour of the uterine cervix Case report.</article-title>
          <source>Br J Obstet Gynaecol.</source>
          <year>1986 Apr</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <issue>(4)</issue>
          <fpage>397</fpage>
          <lpage>401</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2421758</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Benda</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Histopathologic prognostic factors in early stage cervical carcinoma.</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <issue>(21)</issue>
          <fpage>27</fpage>
          <lpage>34</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9023825</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ambros</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shah</surname>
            <given-names>KV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kurman</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Evaluation of histologic, morphometric, and immunohistochemical criteria in the differential diagnosis of small cell carcinomas of the cervix with particular reference to human papillomavirus types 16 and 18.</article-title>
          <source>Mod Pathol.</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <month>9</month>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>(5)</issue>
          <fpage>586</fpage>
          <lpage>93</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1722042</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Dallenbach-Hellweg</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Doeberitz</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Trunk</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Color Atlas of Histopathology of the Cervix Uteri; Malignant Tumor, Neuroendocrine Types</article-title>
          <edition>Second Edition.</edition>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>O&#x2019;Hanlan</surname>
            <given-names>KA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goldberg</surname>
            <given-names>GL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jones</surname>
            <given-names>JG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Runowicz</surname>
            <given-names>CD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ehrlich</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rodriguez-Rodriguez</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Adjuvant therapy for neuroendocrine small cell carcinoma of the cervix: review of the literature.</article-title>
          <source>Gynecol Oncol.</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <month>11</month>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>(2)</issue>
          <fpage>167</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660433</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Barret</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davos</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leuchter</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lagasse</surname>
            <given-names>LD</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Neuroendocrine features in poorly differentiated and undifferentiated carcinomas of the cervix.</article-title>
          <source>Cancer.</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <season>Nov 1</season>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <issue>(9)</issue>
          <fpage>2325</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2830956</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
