<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Trop Med Hyg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0002-9637</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1476-1645</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21363970</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3042808</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2011.10-0672</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Images in Clinical Tropical Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Chronic, Progressive Back Pain, Fever and a Noticeable Paravertebral Mass</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Villaverde</surname>
            <given-names>Homarh</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gotuzzo</surname>
            <given-names>Eduardo</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Seas</surname>
            <given-names>Carlos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AFF1">Instituto de Medicina Tropical Alexander von Humboldt, Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia, Lima, Peru; Departamento de Enfermedades Infecciosas, Tropicales y Dermatol&#xF3;gicas, Hospital Nacional Cayetano Heredia, Lima, Peru</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">*Address correspondence to Carlos Seas, Instituto de Medicina Tropical Alexander von Humboldt. Av. Honorio Delgado 430, Lima 31, Peru. E-mail: <email>carlos.seas@upch.pe</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <volume>84</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>363</fpage>
      <lpage>363</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene's Re-use License which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A 46-year-old woman presented with an 8-month history of fever, lumbar pain, and a slowly growing right paravertebral mass. She reported regular consumption of unpasteurized goat cheese. The physical examination revealed a fluctuant right paravertebral mass and marked pain on palpation over the lumbar spine at the L3-L4 level. A computed tomography (CT) scan of the spine revealed erosions of the end plates of L3 and L4 and the antero-superior angle of L3, narrowing of the intervertebral space between L3 and L4, and new bone formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Widening of the right iliopsoas muscle was also observed on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). A tube agglutination test for brucellosis was positive at 1/640, and a CT-guided percutaneous drainage of the paravertebral mass yielded purulent material from which <italic>Brucella melitensis</italic> was isolated in culture. Doxycycline, gentamycin, and rifampicin were started with good clinical response. Bacterial vertebral osteomyelitis may be caused by pyogenic bacteria, <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, and <italic>B. melitensis</italic>. Tuberculosis predominantly affects the thoracic spine; paravertebral masses are common, but new bone formation is unusual. Pyogenic vertebral osteomyelitis, mainly caused by <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, presents very similarly to brucellosis both clinically and radiographically. Brucellosis caused by <italic>B. melitensis</italic> is acquired mostly by eating contaminated dairy products. Vertebral osteomyelitis and iliopsoas abscess are recognized complications of untreated brucellosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref> Triple antibiotic therapy seems to improve clinical outcome.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) CT scan of the spine showing erosions on the antero-superior angle of the vertebral body of L3, narrowing of the intervertebral disc space between L3 and L4, erosions on the end plates of these two vertebral bodies, and new bone formation. (<bold>B</bold>) Widening of the right iliopsoas muscle.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="tropmed-84-363-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) MRI of the spine. Hypointensity on T1-weighted images at the L3-L4 level and narrowing of the L3-L4 intervertebral disc space. (<bold>B</bold>) Hyperintesity on T2-weighted images and marked widening of the right iliopsoas muscle.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="tropmed-84-363-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="present-address">
        <p>Authors' addresses: Homarh Villaverde, Instituto de Medicina Tropical Alexander von Humboldt, Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia, Lima, Peru, E-mail: <email>villaverde77@gmail.com</email>. Eduardo Gotuzzo and Carlos Seas, Instituto de Medicina Tropical Alexander von Humboldt, Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia and Departamento de Enfermedades Infecciosas, Tropicales y Dermatol&#xF3;gicas, Hospital Nacional Cayetano Heredia, Lima, Peru, E-mails: <email>eduardo.gotuzzo@upch.pe</email> and <email>carlos.seas@upch.pe</email>.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Colmenero</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruiz-Mesa</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plata</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berm&#xFA;dez</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mart&#xED;n-Rico</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Queipo-Ortu&#xF1;o</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reguera</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2008</year>
          <article-title>Clinical findings, therapeutic approach, and outcome of brucellar vertebral osteomyelitis</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>426</fpage>
          <lpage>433</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18181740</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bayindir</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sonmez</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aladag</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buyukberber</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <year>2003</year>
          <article-title>Comparison of five antimicrobial regimens for the treatment of brucellar spondylitis: a prospective, randomized study</article-title>
          <source>J Chemother</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>466</fpage>
          <lpage>471</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14598939</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
