<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Otorhinolaryngologica Italica</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0392-100X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1827-675X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pacini Editore SpA</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227903</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3825037</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title xml:lang="en">Intramuscular haemangioma of the levator anguli
oris: a rare case</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="it">
          <trans-title>Angioma intramuscolare del muscolo elevatore dell'angolo della bocca: un raro caso clinico</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>KOLTSIDOPOULOS</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>TSEA</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>KAFKI</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SKOULAKIS</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department of Otolaryngology, General Hospital of Volos "Achillopoulio", Volos, Greece</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">Address for correspondence: Petros Koltsidopoulos, Department of Otolaryngology, General Hospital of Volos "Achillopoulio", Polimeri 134, 38222 Volos, Greece. Fax +30 24210 25462. E-mail: <email xlink:href="petkoltsid@yahoo.gr">petkoltsid@yahoo.gr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>33</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>350</fpage>
      <lpage>352</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Copyright by Societ&#xE0; Italiana di Otorinolaringologia e Chirurgia Cervico-Facciale</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way. For details, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>SUMMARY</title>
        <p>Intramuscular haemangiomas are benign malformations of blood vessels occurring in skeletal muscles. Because of the rarity of these lesions, their deep location and variable clinical presentation, they often pose diagnostic difficulties. We herein present the first reported case of intramuscular haemangioma occurring in the levator anguli oris muscle. A 26-year-old man was referred to our Department for evaluation and management of a progressive swelling of the right cheek. Based mainly on the imaging findings, a preoperative diagnosis of intramuscular haemangioma was made and surgery was performed. During intervention, a highly vascular soft tissue mass was identified within the levator anguli oris muscle. The lesion was completely removed via an intraoral approach, and histopathological examination showed an intramuscular haemangioma.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="it">
        <title>RIASSUNTO</title>
        <p>Gli emangiomi intramuscolari sono malformazioni benigne di origine vascolare che si localizzano all'interno della muscolatura scheletrica. A causa della rarit&#xE0; di queste lesioni, la loro profonda localizzazione e la loro variabilit&#xE0; nella presentazione clinica, pongono spesso delle difficolt&#xE0; diagnostiche. Il caso presentato in questo articolo &#xE8; il primo emangioma intramuscolare del muscolo elevatore dell'angolo della bocca, riportato in letteratura. Trattasi di un uomo di 26 anni valutato presso la nostra clinica per progressiva tumefazione in corrispondenza della guancia destra. Sulla base dei reperti clinico-radiologici, &#xE8; stata posta diagnosi pre-operatoria di emangioma intramuscolare e per tale motivo &#xE8; stato sottoposto a exeresi chirurgica. Durante l'intervento, &#xE8; stata identificata una massa altamente vascolarizzata di tessuto molle all'interno del muscolo elevatore dell'angolo della bocca. La lesione &#xE8; stata completamente escissa tramite approccio intraorale e l'esame istopatologico ha confermato la diagnosi di emangioma intramuscolare.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>KEY WORDS</title>
        <kwd>Intramuscular haemangioma</kwd>
        <kwd>Levator anguli oris</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="S1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Intramuscular haemangiomas (IMHs) are relatively uncommon angiomatous malformations. They appear most often in the trunk and extremities, while their occurrence in the head and neck region is rare. In the head, the masseter muscle is the most frequently involved site. Clinically, diagnosis of IMHs is difficult. As a result, inappropriate treatment planning is a common problem that can lead to incomplete excision and unnecessary risk to the facial nerve. IMHs usually present in childhood or early adult life, are treated by complete surgical excision and carry an excellent prognosis.</p>
      <p>To the best of our knowledge, the present case is the first intramuscular haemangioma within the levator anguli oris reported in the literature.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 26-year-old man was referred to our Department for evaluation and management of a painless swelling of the right cheek (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The lesion had been present for 10 years and had gradually increased in size. The patient complained of cosmetic deformity. Clinical examination showed a diffuse mass situated about 2 cm superior to the right side of the upper lip. The lesion was soft, compressible, mobile and not adherent to skin. The overlying skin was slightly erythematous. No pulsation, bruits or thrills were noted. There was no evidence of neck lymphadenopathy.</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clinical appearance of the lesion.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-350-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>A subsequent computerized tomography (CT) scan revealed a 4.6 &#xD7; 1.9 cm soft tissue mass of the same density as muscle, arising from within the muscles of the cheek (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). There was no underlying bone involvement of the upper jaw. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) showed heterogeneous, intramuscular lesion at the same location (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The mass was hyperintense to the masseter muscle on T2-weighted images. The imaging findings, history of long duration of the swelling and the clinical finding of discolouration of the overlying skin raised suspicion of a vascular lesion. On that basis, angiography was performed, and the patient underwent bilateral common carotid arteriography via the right femoral artery that confirmed the vascular nature of the lesion. In particular, the right common carotid injection showed that the mass consisted of a collection of tortuous vessels of varying calibre. Two main feeding vessels were detected, one originating from the right facial artery and another from the right internal maxillary artery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Based on these findings, a provisional diagnosis of intramuscular haemangioma was made and surgery was scheduled.</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Axial CT showed the presence of a soft tissue mass arising within the muscles of the right cheek.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-350-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Coronal T2-weighted MRI revealing a heterogeneous, intramuscular lesion.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-350-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Arteriogram of right external carotid artery showing the two feeding vessels of the lesion.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-350-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The lesion was removed via an intraoral approach under general anaesthesia. During intervention, a highly vascular soft tissue mass was identified within the levator anguli oris muscle. The lesion was excised together with a margin of the normal surrounding muscle to prevent recurrence. Several small feeding vessels were individually ligated by bipolar diathermy. Blood loss during the procedure was minimal, allowing for complete excision. The postoperative period was uneventful. The histopathological examination showed small vessels growing between fibres of skeletal muscle, consistent with a diagnosis of intramuscular haemangioma of small vessel (capillary) type. The patient remains free of symptoms and there is no evidence of postoperative recurrence at 6 months (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F5" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Appearance of the patient at 6 months after surgical excision of the tumour mass.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-350-g005"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Intramuscular haemangioma is an uncommon vascular malformation, accounting for less than 1% of all haemangiomas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01"><sup>1</sup></xref>. It affects mainly the trunk and extremities where the muscle volume is larger. Approximately 13% of these lesions present in the head and neck region <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02"><sup>2</sup></xref>. In the head, the masseter muscle is the most frequently involved site <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>. Rarer sites include the orbicularis oris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05"><sup>5</sup></xref>, depressor anguli oris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06"><sup>6</sup></xref> and orbicularis oculi muscle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07"><sup>7</sup></xref>. To the best of our knowledge, our case is the first reported of IMH within the levator anguli oris muscle.</p>
      <p>Intramuscular haemangiomas generally present as progressively enlarging and often painful lesions. Because of their deep location, they rarely display any clinical signs or symptoms that suggest a vascular nature, such as pulsations, thrills or bruits. Overlying skin discolouration is also uncommon. The absence of pathognomic clinical findings and the rare incidence of these lesions make accurate pre-operative diagnosis difficult <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08"><sup>8</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09"><sup>9</sup></xref>. Namely, only 8% of all cases of intramuscular haemangioma are diagnosed before surgical intervention <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02"><sup>2</sup></xref>. A variety of muscle neoplasms, benign muscular hypertrophy, congenital cysts and lymphadenopathies are commonly confused in differential diagnosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09"><sup>9</sup></xref>. In our case, the discolouration of the overlying skin in combination with the imaging findings led to the presumptive diagnosis of intramuscular haemangioma.</p>
      <p>For preoperative diagnosis of intramuscular hemangioma, plain radiographs, CT scan, MRI and angiography may be helpful. Plain soft tissue x-ray views occasionally demonstrate phleboliths within the lesion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><sup>10</sup></xref>. MRI is thought to be more helpful than CT as it provides better detection and delineation of the extent of the IMH <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><sup>11</sup></xref>. The lesions are characteristically much brighter on T2- than T1-weighted imaging due to the increased free water present within stagnant blood in the vessels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12"><sup>12</sup></xref>. Angiography usually clarifies the vascular nature of the lesion, demonstrates feeding vessels and identifies its extent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04"><sup>4</sup></xref>. In our case, pre-operative diagnosis of IMH was strongly guided by the findings of arteriography. However, angiography should be performed if there is a strong suspicion of a vascular deformity.</p>
      <p>Various treatment methods have been used in the management of intramuscular haemangioma including steroid injections, radiation therapy, injection of sclerosing agents, cryotherapy and electrocoagulation. However, the optimal management is the surgical resection with wide margins of surrounding normal muscle because of the infiltrative nature of the IMH <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13"><sup>13</sup></xref>. The choice of surgical approach depends on the extent and location of the lesion. In our case, intraoral excision was used to achieve the best possible cosmetic result. Preoperative embolisation is indicated for large tumours with multiple or large calibre feeding vessels to minimize blood loss <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14"><sup>14</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, the possibility of an IMH should be included in the differential diagnosis of any facial mass. The appropriate radiologic examinations can enhance accurate preoperative diagnosis and optimal treatment planning. Surgical resection, well beyond the gross limits of the lesion, is generally considered the ideal therapeutic approach for IMH.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tumors and tumor like lesions of the soft tissue</article-title>
          <source>Pathology of the head and neck</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <edition>2nd Ed.</edition>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Marcel Dekker</publisher-name>
          <fpage>900</fpage>
          <lpage>901</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>JES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Haemangioma of skeletal muscle</article-title>
          <source>Br J Surg</source>
          <year>1957</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>496</fpage>
          <lpage>501</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13510618</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enzinger</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hemangioma of skeletal muscle. An
analysis of 89 cases</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1972</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5061701</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ivey</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delfino</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sclaroff</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intramuscular hemangioma.
Report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>295</fpage>
          <lpage>300</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6935579</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nam</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hwang</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intramuscular hemangioma of the lower
lip</article-title>
          <source>J Craniofac Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>958</fpage>
          <lpage>959</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17667695</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blackburn</surname>
              <given-names>TK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boyle</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intramuscular haemangioma
within depressor anguli oris</article-title>
          <source>Br J Oral Maxillofac
Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>234</fpage>
          <lpage>235</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16242821</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Skoulakis</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maistrou</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drivas</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intramuscular haemangioma
of the orbicularis oculi muscle of the orbit</article-title>
          <source>Acta
Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>263</fpage>
          <lpage>265</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18198758</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Avci</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yim</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Misirliogolu</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intramasseteric hemangioma</article-title>
          <source>Plast Reconst Surg</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>1748</fpage>
          <lpage>1749</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932639</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Demir</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oktem</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Celebioglu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rare case of intramasseteric
cavernous hemangioma in a three-year-old boy: a diagnostic
dilemma</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>458</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15224828</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mandel</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intramuscular hemangioma with phleboliths or
choristoma?</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1511</fpage>
          <lpage>1512</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11732048</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Buetow</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kransdorf</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moser</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Radiographic
appearance of intramuscular haemangioma with emphasis
on MR imaging</article-title>
          <source>Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>154</volume>
          <fpage>563</fpage>
          <lpage>567</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2154914</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kanaya</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saito</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gama</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intramuscular hemangioma
of masseter muscle with prominent formation of phleboliths:
a case report</article-title>
          <source>Auris Nasus Larynx</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>591</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18207684</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ichimura</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nibu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Essentials of surgical treatment
for intramasseteric hemangioma</article-title>
          <source>Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>252</volume>
          <fpage>125</fpage>
          <lpage>129</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7662343</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haughton</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hemoclip-Gelfoam emboli in the treatment
of facial arteriovenous malformations</article-title>
          <source>Neuroradiology</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1196489</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
