<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Head Face Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Head Face Med</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Head &amp; Face Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1746-160X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23758697</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3684544</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1746-160X-9-15</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-160X-9-15</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Peripheral compound odontoma erupting in the gingiva</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Hanemann</surname>
            <given-names>Jo&#xE3;o AC</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>jachanemann@uol.com.br</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Oliveira</surname>
            <given-names>Denise T</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>denisetostes@usp.br</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Garcia</surname>
            <given-names>Nat&#xE1;lia Galv&#xE3;o</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>natggalvao@hotmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Santos</surname>
            <given-names>Mariana RG</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>mari-rates@hotmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Pereira</surname>
            <given-names>Alessandro AC</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>alessandro.unifal@uol.com.br</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Clinic and Surgery, Area Stomatology, Alfenas Federal University, Minas Gerais, Alfenas, Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Stomatology, Area of Pathology, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of S&#xE3;o Paulo, Al. Dr. Oct&#xE1;vio Pinheiro Brisolla, 9-75, Bauru, SP 170120-901, Brazil</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <fpage>15</fpage>
      <lpage>15</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 Hanemann et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Hanemann et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.head-face-med.com/content/9/1/15"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Peripheral odontoma arising in the extraosseous soft tissues is rare and if not removed early, may enlarge over time and eventually erupt in the oral cavity.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 15-year-old girl presented with &#x201C;denticles on the gingiva&#x201D;. During the intraoral examination, seven small tooth-like structures were found. These were exposed in the anterior left gingiva between the permanent maxillary lateral incisor and canine teeth, and the left first premolar was absent. Radiographic examination revealed irregular tooth-like structures without evidence of bone involvement.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The lesion was surgically removed, and the specimens were analyzed histopathologically. The diagnosis of compound odontoma was established.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Clinical significance</title>
          <p>This is the twelfth reported case of peripheral odontoma in the gingiva and the first one that erupted in the oral cavity.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Peripheral odontoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Compound odontoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Erupted</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Odontomas are the most common type of odontogenic tumors and they are often associated with permanent or temporary tooth eruption disturbances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. According to the latest classification of the World Health Organization (WHO, 2005), two types of odontomas can be recognized: complex odontomas and compound odontomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Clinically, odontomas are either intraosseous or extraosseous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The intraosseous odontomas occur inside the bone and may eventually erupt into the oral cavity (erupted odontoma). Peripheral odontoma arising in the extraosseous soft tissues is rare and have a tendency to exfoliate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>We report a case of a 15-year-old girl with a peripheral compound odontoma characterized by multiple rudimentary teeth which erupted spontaneously in the anterior maxillary region. Based in the related English literature, this is the first reported case of peripheral compound odontoma with several teeth erupted in the gingiva.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>The patient, a 15-year-old girl was referred to the Stomatology Clinic of Alfenas Federal University with the complaint of &#x201C;denticles on the gingiva&#x201D;. The patient reported that when she was 12 years old, she perceived the emergence of small asymptomatic mass in the anterior maxillary region and one year later multiple denticles erupted at the injury site. During the intraoral examination, the residual root of a deciduous tooth that had been destroyed by caries lesions and six small tooth-like structures were found exposed in the anterior left gingiva between the permanent maxillary lateral incisor and canine teeth (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A). The denticles had dental biofilm and the gum around them was shown to be swollen and reddened. Radiographic examination revealed irregular tooth structures composed of crown, root and pulp without evidence of bone involvement (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B). A clinical diagnosis of peripheral compound odontoma erupting in the gingiva was made. The absence of the left first premolar was also observed. The compound odontoma was surgically removed, and no bony erosion beneath the tumor was detected (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A-C). The specimens were sent for histopathological analysis which confirmed that it was a compound odontoma with enamel, dentin, pulp chamber, and cementum in the same order of arrangement as that of a normal tooth, surrounded by thin epithelium (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A). These structures were embedded in dense fibrous connective tissue containing a mononuclear inflammatory infiltrate and bacterial colonies (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B).</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clinical and radiographic of small tooth-like structures erupted in the gingiva.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-160X-9-15-1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Surgical removal of the lesion.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-160X-9-15-2"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histopathological analysis of gingival tissue around the small tooth-like structures.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-160X-9-15-3"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Postoperatively there was no complication and the suture was removed ten days after surgery. At this time, there was satisfactory healing of the operated region. After one month, the patient showed complete healing of the lesion and the gingival contour in the region of the lateral incisor and canine teeth had been fully restored (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). After this she was referred to the dental clinic for completion of her dental treatment. So far, she has shown no signs of recurrence.</p>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>After one month.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-160X-9-15-4"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Odontomas are generally asymptomatic lesions and they constitute causal findings in the course of routine radiological studies, particularly in the second and third decades of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Compound odontomas are more frequent than the complex type and they show a predilection for the anterior maxillary region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Peripheral or soft tissue odontomas are extremely uncommon with about twelve compound odontomas reported in the related English literature, including the present case, as summarized in Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. In this table it may be observed that there is a predilection for children and young persons and in over 50% of cases the lesions affected the palatal region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The histogenesis of this type of odontoma has been associated with soft tissue remnants of the odontogenic epithelium such as gingival rests of Serres, which seem to retain the ability to pursue epithelial-mesenchymal interactions that could lead to odontoma formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. In our patient, the clinical oral examination showed the residual root of a deciduous tooth that had been destroyed by caries lesions, six small tooth-like structures exposed in the oral cavity and absence of the left first premolar. Thus, it is suggested that the odontoma may have arisen from this premolar germ.</p>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Reported cases of peripheral developing compound odontoma</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
          <colgroup>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="left"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead valign="top">
            <tr>
              <th align="left">
                <bold>Author/Year</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="left">
                <bold>Gender/Age</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="left">
                <bold>Localization</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="left">
                <bold>Erupted in oral cavity</bold>
              </th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody valign="top">
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                <bold>Present case 2013</bold>
                <hr/>
              </td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">F/15 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Anterior maxillary region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Friedrich et al. 2010</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">M/3 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Palatal region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Silva et al. 2009</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Case 1- M/8 months<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Case 1 &#x2013; palatal region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Case 2- M/5 months<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Case 2 &#x2013; palatal region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Ide et al. 2008</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">F/7 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Anterior mandible region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Bernardes et al. 2008</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">M/12 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Anterior maxillary region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Kintarak et al. 2006</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">F/13 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Palatal region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Takeda et al. 2005</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">F/2 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Palatal region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Ide et al. 2000</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">M/39 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Anterior maxillary region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Ledesma-Montes et al. 1996</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">F/3 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Posterior mandible region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Giunta et al. 1990</bold>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Case 1- F/5 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Case 1 &#x2013; palatal region<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Case 2- M/21 year old<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Case 2- posterior mandible<hr/></td>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">
                <bold>TOTAL</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="left">&#xA0;</td>
              <td align="left">12 cases</td>
              <td align="left">&#xA0;</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Although peripheral odontomas have a limited potential for growth, Ide; Shimoyama; Horie, (2000), the case here reported reinforces the idea that if the lesion had not been surgically removed in early developmental stage, it might have erupted into the oral cavity. The eruptive mechanism of peripheral odontoma remains uncertain and it appears to be different from tooth eruption because of the absence of periodontal attachment in odontomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>The majority of erupted odontomas described are intraosseous and related to non-erupted teeth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Therefore, it may be postulated that the eruptive force of non-erupted teeth plays an important role in odontoma eruption. In the absence of non-erupted teeth, some authors believe that odontoma eruption is due to severe bone resorption at the site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Others report that the mechanism behind the eruption may involve both the bony remodeling of the jaws and the increase in tumor size over time, since the force required to move the odontoma is not linked to the contractility of fibroblasts, as is the case with teeth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>On the other hand, the exposure of denticles from the peripheral compound odontoma in the gingiva, as illustrated in the present case, could represent a tendency to exfoliation, as suggested by Shekar et al., due to its growth over time, rather than a real process of tooth eruption.</p>
      <p>Histopathological analysis showed that the tooth-like structures were composed of enamel, dentin, pulp chamber, and cementum in the same order of arrangement as that in a normal tooth. These structures were surrounded by thin epithelium and embedded in dense fibrous connective tissue, demonstrating their peripheral origin. The rudimentary denticles that had erupted from the odontoma had a fragile insertion into the gingival tissue which was clinically confirmed by accentuated tooth mobility. The fibrous connective tissue contained mononuclear inflammatory infiltrate and bacterial colonies was clinically characterized by inflammation of the gums due to the presence of dental biofilm, probably caused by the difficulty of cleaning in the region.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In summary, due to the rare occurrence of peripheral odontomas, the present case is the first report of an erupted peripheral odontoma. However, it is necessary for dentists to be aware that peripheral odontomas, if not removed early, may enlarge over time and eventually erupt in the oral cavity, compromising both periodontal health and esthetics. Moreover, it is important to note that the increased tooth mobility caused by these lesions may result in the spontaneous exfoliation of these denticles, which may lead to the patient swallowing them.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Clinical significance</title>
      <p>This is the twelfth reported case of peripheral odontoma in the gingiva and the first one that erupted in the oral cavity.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this Case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>JACH operated and monitored the patient. DTO performed the microscopic diagnosis and assisted in drafting of paper. NGG accompanied the clinical case and drafted the article. MRGS accompanied the clinical case and drafted the article. AACP assisted in the surgery. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Oliveira</surname>
            <given-names>BH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Campos</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mar&#xE7;al</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Compound odontoma- diagnosis and treatment: three case reports</article-title>
          <source>Oral Pathology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>151</fpage>
          <lpage>157</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Serra-Serra</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Berini-Ayt&#xE9;s</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gay-Escoda</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Erupted odontomas: a report of three cases and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>299</fpage>
          <lpage>303</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Vengal</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arora</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ghosh</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pai</surname>
            <given-names>KM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Large erupting complex odontoma: a case report</article-title>
          <source>JCDA</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>169</fpage>
          <lpage>172</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17355809</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Junquera</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vicente</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Roig</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Olay</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rodr&#xED;guez-Recio</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Intraosseus odontoma erupted into the oral cavity: an unusual pathology</article-title>
          <source>Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>248</fpage>
          <lpage>251</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15876969</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Shekar</surname>
            <given-names>SE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rao</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gunasheela</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Supriya</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Erupted compound odontome</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Oral and Maxillo Facial Pathology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0973-029X.48758</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bernardes</surname>
            <given-names>VF</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title>Gingival peripheral odontoma in child: case report of an uncommon lesion</article-title>
          <source>Brazilian J Oral Sci</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>1624</fpage>
          <lpage>1626</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ide</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimoyama</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Horie</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Gingival peripheral odontoma in an adult: case report</article-title>
          <source>J Periodontol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>830</fpage>
          <lpage>832</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2000.71.5.830</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10872967</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ide</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mishima</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saito</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kusama</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Rare peripheral odontogenic tumors: report of 5 cases and comprehensive review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Silva</surname>
            <given-names>AR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carlos-Bregni</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vargas</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de Almeida</surname>
            <given-names>OP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lopes</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Peripheral developing odontoma in newborn. Report of two cases and literature review</article-title>
          <source>Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>612</fpage>
          <lpage>615</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Friedrich</surname>
            <given-names>RE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Furhmann</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scheuer</surname>
            <given-names>HA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zustin</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Small peripheral developing odontoma of the maxilla in a 3-year-old patient depicted on cone-beam tomograms</article-title>
          <source>In Vivo</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>895</fpage>
          <lpage>898</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21164051</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kintarak</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kumplanont</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kietthubthew</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chungpanich</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A nodular mass of the anterior palatal gingival</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tripleo.2006.01.018</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16831665</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Takeda</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oikawa</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Satoh</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Eruption odontoma and peripheral odontoma (English abstract)</article-title>
          <source>Oral Med Pathol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ledesma-Montes</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Perez-Bache</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garc&#xE9;s-Ortiz</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Gingival compound odontoma</article-title>
          <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>296</fpage>
          <lpage>297</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0901-5027(06)80061-5</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8910117</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Giunta</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kaplan</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Peripheral, soft tissue odontomas: two case reports</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>406</fpage>
          <lpage>411</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0030-4220(90)90312-G</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2314871</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
