<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Neuropathol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin. Neuropathol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Dustri</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinical Neuropathology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0722-5091</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Dustri-Verlag Dr. Karl Feistle</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22551918</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3657470</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5414/NP300451</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Neuropathology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Identification of t(1;19)(q12;p13) and ploidy changes in an ependymosarcoma: a cytogenetic evaluation </article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tabbarah</surname>
            <given-names>Abeer Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carlson</surname>
            <given-names>Austin W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oviedo</surname>
            <given-names>Angelica</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ketterling</surname>
            <given-names>Rhett P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
            <given-names>Fausto J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology, George Washington University, Washington, D.C.,</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA,</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Children&#x2019;s and Women&#x2019;s Health Centre of BC Anatomic Pathology, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada and</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Pathology, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">Correspondence to Fausto J. Rodriguez, MD Department of Pathology, Division of Neuropathology, Johns Hopkins University, 720 Rutland Avenue - Ross Building &#x2013; 512B, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA <email>frodrig4@jhmi.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>31</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>142</fpage>
      <lpage>145</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Dustri-Verlag Dr. K. Feistle</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012 </copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gliosarcoma, a recognized subtype of glioblastoma, is a biphasic tumor exhibiting distinct glial and sarcomatous components. Ependymosarcomas are rarer, biphasic ependymal tumors exhibiting sarcomatous change. Genetic abnormalities associated with this curious phenotype are not well understood. We are presenting the first karyotype of ependymosarcoma with identification of a clonal t(1;19)(q12;p13). Fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) was performed with a probe set targeting 1q23 and 19p13.3. Although the tumor did not show evidence of t(1;19)(q23;p13.3) by FISH, increased ploidy was a feature of the sarcomatous component. On clinical follow-up the patient is doing well without evidence of recurrence 55 months after initial resection, and postoperative treatment with irradiation and temozolomide. The significance of the genetic alterations we describe associated with sarcomatoid change in ependymal neoplasms, and ultimately their prognostic relevance, merits further study. </p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Key words </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction </title>
      <p>Gliosarcoma, a variant of glioblastoma, is a biphasic malignant glial tumor composed of a glial and a sarcomatous component. In most cases, the glial component is astrocytic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>]. However, there have been reports of the glial component being oligodendroglial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>] or ependymal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>]. The terms oligosarcoma and ependymosarcoma have been proposed for such composite tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. </p>
      <p>Given the rarity of these tumors, genetic characterization and elucidation of specific alterations underlying their development are lacking in the literature. In this report we present conventional cytogenetic findings of an ependymosarcoma case, along with fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) analysis for ploidy. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Materials and methods </title>
      <sec id="sub-s1">
        <title>
Case history
</title>
        <p>Clinical and pathologic features of this tumor have been previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. Briefly, the patient was a 13-year-old girl who presented with new onset seizures. Magnetic resonance imaging revealed an enhancing calcified mass with surrounding edema in the right frontal lobe. Gross total resection revealed a firm, nodular, well demarcated, focally infiltrating mass. Postoperatively, the patient underwent radiation therapy and received temozolomide. Microscopic examination revealed an ependymosarcoma composed of focal myxopapillary-like ependymal areas and a sarcomatous component resembling fibrosarcoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="Figure1">Figure 1</xref>a,&#xA0;b). Immunohistochemical stains supported the morphologic impression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. On updated clinical follow-up, the patient is alive and without evidence of recurrent disease during her last clinic visit, 55 months after resection. Her seizures are well controlled by medication. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sub-s2">
        <title>
Cytogenetic analysis
</title>
        <p>Metaphase chromosomes were prepared and G-banded for karyotyping using standard methods on cultured cells obtained from fresh tumor tissue. Dual fluorescence FISH was performed using probes designed from bacterial artificial chromosomes (BAC) targeting <italic>PBX1</italic> (1q23) and <italic>E2A</italic> (e.g., <italic>TCF3</italic> at 19p13.3). The <italic>PBX1</italic> and <italic>E2A</italic> BACs were labeled with Spectrum Orange-dUTP<sup>TM</sup> (Vysis Inc., Downers Grove, IL, USA) and Spectrum Green-dUTP<sup>TM</sup> (Vysis Inc.), respectively, as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>]. Only FISH evaluation was performed separately in the ependymal and sarcomatous components. </p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results </title>
      <p>Conventional cytogenetic analysis demonstrated the following clonal abnormalities: 44,X,-3,-9,-11,?dup(11)(q13q23),der(19)t(1;19)(q12;p13),+mar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="Figure1">Figure 1</xref>c). A subset of metaphases demonstrated a tetraploid subclone with the same abnormalities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="Figure1">Figure 1</xref>d). FISH analyses using probes designed to identify <italic>PBX1</italic>/<italic>E2A</italic> fusion associated with t(1;19)(q23;p13.3) in precursor B-cell ALL were performed, since it was the closest probe set available to evaluate t(1;19). There was no evidence of <italic>PBX1</italic>/<italic>E2A</italic> fusion. However, the glial component showed 2-4 <italic>PBX1</italic> (red) and 1-2 <italic>E2A</italic> (green) FISH signals (75% of cells) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="Figure1">Figure 1</xref>e), while the mesenchymal areas had more of a range of FISH signals, with ~&#xA0;40% of nuclei demonstrating 5&#xA0;&#x2013;&#xA0;6 <italic>PBX1</italic> and 4 <italic>E2A</italic> signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="Figure1">Figure 1</xref>f). These signal patterns were consistent with the karyotypic findings, supporting that the glial component was diploid and the sarcomatous component more tetraploid, although cells for conventional cytogenetics were not separated prior to analysis. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Discussion </title>
      <p>Ependymosarcomas are rare tumors, with less than 20 cases reported in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>]. Reports include 2 cases of subependymoma with sarcomatous change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>], 1 case of mixed subependymoma-rhabdomyosarcoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>], and 15 cases of sarcomatous change in ependymoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>]. The ependymomas described have been classified as WHO Grade II or Grade III [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>]. Seven of the 15 ependymosarcomas were described in the original resection specimens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>], while 8 were described in recurrent tumor specimens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>]. Seven of the 15 cases were described after the patient had received radiation therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. Whether these tumors are radiation induced depends on a number of factors, including defining the time interval required between the radiation and the development of the sarcomatous component [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. </p>
      <p>Multiple studies over the years have attempted to elucidate the pathogenesis of gliosarcomas. Initially, the glial and mesenchymal components were thought to arise from different cells of origin as per the &#x201C;polyclonal hypothesis&#x201D;. The mesenchymal element was thought to develop from fibroblasts, pluripotent cells of the vascular adventitia or perivascular spaces, vascular smooth muscle cells, or monohistiocytic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>]. According to the &#x201C;monoclonal hypothesis&#x201D;, the mesenchymal component develops from glial precursors during tumor progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>]. More recent molecular genetic studies have shown that both glial and mesenchymal components share common genetic aberrations in most instances, therefore supporting the monoclonal hypothesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. Chromosomal imbalances identified in gliosarcomas include gains on chromosomes 7, X, 9q, 12q, and 20q, and losses on chromosomes 10, 9p, 13q, and 17 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>]. Genetic imbalances are similar in both glial and sarcomatous components in most cases studied. </p>
      <p>It is of interest that molecular cytogenetic study of this example of ependymosarcoma demonstrated increased ploidy changes in the sarcomatous component. The sarcomatous component of this tumor also had polysomies of chromosomes 11 and 12 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. In addition, another case of ependymosarcoma (of 4 cases tested) in the series by Rodriguez et al. (Case 2) also displayed polysomies of chromosomes 11 and 12 restricted to the sarcomatous component. This combination of findings is intriguing, and raises the possibility that ploidy changes may in part explain the development of this unique morphologic variation at the genetic level. </p>
      <p>Rearrangements involving chromosomes 1 and 19 have been reported in multiple cancers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>]. A t(1;19)(q12;p13) has been detected in 3 cases of malignant melanoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>]. The breakpoint in chromosome 19 appeared similar to that reported in precursor B-cell leukemia, and at the time the human insulin receptor gene, grossly mapping to this region, was felt to be the involved. However, subsequently it was discovered that precursor B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia has a <italic>PBX1</italic>/<italic>E2A</italic> fusion gene characterized by either a der(19)t(1;19)(q23;p13.3) or t(1;19)(q23;p13.3).The probe set designed to identify these translocations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>] was used in the FISH analysis of our case. A t(1;19)(q23;q13) has also been reported in a medulloblastom aand glioblastoma [22]. Another case involving 19p13 is seen in t(1;19)(p22;p13.1), identified for the first time in a mixed epithelial stromal tumor (MEST) of the kidney [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. Not unlike ependymosarcomas, MEST are biphasic tumors composed of epithelial and mesenchymal elements. Lui et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>] reported similar cytogenetic findings in a highly malignant primitive soft tissue sarcoma, suggestive of a rhabdomyosarcoma variant, with a hypertetraploid karyotype and t(1;19)(q12;q13.2). The increased ploidy and t(1;19) involving 1q12 are similar to the findings we report in the sarcomatous component in our case, although detailed mapping is lacking. </p>
      <p>The relationship of these genetic alterations with prognosis is unclear at the present time. Sarcomatoid change occurring in tumors outside the nervous system portends more aggressive behavior. The prognosis in the prior ependyomosarcoma series was variable, not uniformly dismal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>], and the patient in this report remains disease free 55 months after resection. The genetic alterations described in this case of ependymosarcoma are intriguing. Future studies should be of value in clarifying their clinical and/or biological significance, and identifying the specific genes involved in these alterations. </p>
      <fig id="Figure1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Increased ploidy in sarcomatous component of ependymosarcoma. An ependymosarcoma with distinct ependymal (a) and sarcomatous (b) components was subjected to cytogenetic analysis. Conventional cytogenetics revealed several clonal abnormalities, including a t(1;19)(q12;p13) translocation (arrow) (c). In addition a subset of metaphases demonstrated tetraploidy (d). Dual color FISH studies performed in the ependymal (e) and sarcomatous (f) components demonstrated a lack of <italic>PBX1/E2A</italic> fusion, but increased ploidy in the sarcomatous component.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="clinneuropathol-31-142-01"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="b1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Actor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobbers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#xFC;schges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knobbe</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Reifenberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><article-title>Comprehensive analysis of genomic alterations in gliosarcoma and its two tissue components.</article-title><source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source>.
<year>2002</year>;
<volume>34</volume>:
<fpage>416</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>427</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1002/gcc.10087 </elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12112531</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Behling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Birbe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Veznadaroglu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Flanders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><article-title>Gliosarcoma arising from an anaplastic ependymoma: a case report of a rare entity.</article-title><source>Hum Pathol</source>.
<year>2004</year>;
<volume>35</volume>:
<fpage>512</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>516</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1016/j.humpath.2003.10.018</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15116335</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Biernat</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguzzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sure</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleihues</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegi</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><article-title>Identical mutations of the p53 tumor suppressor gene in the gliomatous and the sarcomatous components of gliosarcomas suggest a common origin from glial cells.</article-title><source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source>.
<year>1995</year>;
<volume>54</volume>:
<fpage>651</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>656</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.&#x200B;1097/00005072-199509000-00006</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7666053</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Boerman</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Herath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Borell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer-Klein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchhof</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raap</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheithauer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><article-title>The glial and mesenchymal elements of gliosarcomas share similar genetic alterations.</article-title><source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source>.
<year>1996</year>;
<volume>55</volume>:
<fpage>973</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>981</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1097/00005072-199609000-00004</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8800093</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheithauer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><source>Tumors of the Central Nervous System, AFIP Atlas of Tumor Pathology, Series 4.</source><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Registry of Pathology</publisher-name>;
<year>2007</year>;
</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Comp&#xE9;rat</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Couturier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyromaure</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieillefond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Benign mixed epithelial and stromal tumor of the kidney (MEST) with cytogenetic alteration.</article-title><source>Pathol Res Pract</source>.
<year>2005</year>;
<volume>200</volume>:
<fpage>865</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>867</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1016/j.prp.2004.05.004</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15792135</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Higashino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Inamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikezaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshiura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>A lateral ventricular gliosarcoma arising in an ependymoma.</article-title><source>Clin Neuropathol</source>.
<year>2001</year>;
<volume>20</volume>:
<fpage>219</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>223</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11594507</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagahiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>an immunohistochemical, ultrastructural and fluorescence bridization study.</article-title><source>Pathol Int</source>.
<year>1998</year>;
<volume>48</volume>:
<fpage>595</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>602</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1111/j.1440-1827.1998.tb03956.x</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9736406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Kano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikota</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurosaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>A case of an anaplastic ependymoma with gliosarcomatous components.</article-title><source>Brain Tumor Pathol</source>.
<year>2009</year>;
<volume>26</volume>:
<fpage>11</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1007/s10014-008-0240-x</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19408092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Kepes</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastian</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><article-title>Gliosarcoma developing from an irradiated ependymoma.</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol</source>.
<year>1996</year>;
<volume>92</volume>:
<fpage>515</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>519</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1007/s004010050554</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8922064</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedley-Whyte</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Martuza</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><article-title>Sarcomatous proliferation of the vasculature in a subependymoma.</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol</source>.
<year>1989</year>;
<volume>78</volume>:
<fpage>332</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>335</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1007/BF00687765</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2763807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedley-Whyte</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Martuza</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><article-title>Sarcomatous proliferation of the vasculature in a subependymoma: a follow-up study of sarcomatous dedifferentiation.</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol</source>.
<year>1990</year>;
<volume>80</volume>:
<fpage>573</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>574</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1007/BF00294623</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2251917</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name><surname>Wejde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosj&#xF6;</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyt&#xF6;l&#xE4;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>A highly aggressive primitive mesenchymal tumor with a translocation (1;19)(q12;q13.2).</article-title><source>Cancer Genet Cytogenet</source>.
<year>2001</year>;
<volume>127</volume>:
<fpage>128</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>133</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1016/S0165-4608(00)00437-4</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11425451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Mitelman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>A breakpoint map of recurrent chromosomal rearrangements in human neoplasia.</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source>.
<year>1997</year>;
<volume>15</volume>:
<fpage>417</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>474</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1038/ng0497supp-417</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9140409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Parmiter</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaban</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Herlyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowell</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><article-title>A t(1;19) chromosome translocation in three cases of human malignant melanoma.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source>.
<year>1986</year>;
<volume>46</volume>:
<fpage>1526</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1529</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3943110</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#xF6;n&#xFC;-Lebleblicioglu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleihues</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohgaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic profile of gliosarcomas.</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source>.
<year>2000</year>;
<volume>156</volume>:
<fpage>425</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>432</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1016/S0002-9440(10)64746-3</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10666371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheithauer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudzinskiy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlodavsky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schooley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Landolfi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Gliosarcoma arising in oligodendroglial tumors (&#x201C;oligosarcoma&#x201D;): a clinicopathologic study.</article-title><source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>.
<year>2007</year>;
<volume>31</volume>:
<fpage>351</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>362</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1&#x200B;097/01.pas.0000213378.94547.ae</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17325476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheithauer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Oviedo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mork</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><article-title>Ependymal tumors with sarcomatous change (&#x201C;ependymosarcoma&#x201D;): a clinicopathologic and molecular cytogenetic study.</article-title><source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>.
<year>2008</year>;
<volume>32</volume>:
<fpage>699</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>709</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1097/PAS.0b0&#x200B;13e318158234e</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18347506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketterling</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><article-title>Interphase FISH to detect PBX1/E2A fusion resulting from the der(19)t(1;19)(q23;p13.3) or t(1;19)(q23;p13.3) in paediatric patients with acute lymphoblastic leukaemia.</article-title><source>Br J Haematol</source>.
<year>2005</year>;
<volume>129</volume>:
<fpage>45</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1111/j.1&#x200B;365-2141.2&#x200B;005&#x200B;.0&#x200B;5415.x</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15801954</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheithauer</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><article-title>Subependymoma with rhabdomyosarcomatous differentiation: report of a case and literature review.</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source>.
<year>1991</year>;
<volume>28</volume>:
<fpage>761</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>768</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1227/00006123-199105000-00024</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1876259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Vajtai</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhlen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Rapid spontaneous malignant progression of supratentorial tanycytic ependymoma with sarcomatous features - &#x201C;Ependymosarcoma&#x201D;.</article-title><source>Pathol Res Pract</source>.
<year>2010</year>;
<volume>206</volume>:
<fpage>493</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>498</lpage>
<elocation-id>doi:10.1016/j.prp.2009.07.013</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19853384</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="print"><name><surname>Vagner-Capodano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mugneret</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zattara-Cannoni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Favre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Figarella-Branger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentet</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lena</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><article-title>Translocation 1;19 in two brain tumors. </article-title><source>Cancer Genet Cytogenet</source>.
<year>1997</year>; <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9242210</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
