<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Care</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes Care</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">diacare</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">dcare</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes Care</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Diabetes Care</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0149-5992</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1935-5548</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23704685</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3661783</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2664</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dc12-2664</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Online Letters: Observations</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Anti-Insulin Receptor Antibodies Related to Hypoglycemia in a Previously Diabetic Patient</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Maiza</surname>
            <given-names>Jean-Christophe</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Caron-Debarle</surname>
            <given-names>Martine</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vigouroux</surname>
            <given-names>Corinne</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PHD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schneebeli</surname>
            <given-names>St&#xE9;phane</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Endocrinology and Metabolic Diseases, Hospital Groupe Hospitalier Sud Reunion, Saint-Pierre, France</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Pierre et Marie Curie University-Paris 6, UMR_S938, Paris, France</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>INSERM, UMR_S 938, Saint-Antoine Research Centre, Paris, France</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup>Department of Clinical Biochemistry and Hormonology, Hospital Tenon, Paris, France</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: Jean-Christophe Maiza, <email>jean-christophe.maiza@chu-reunion.fr</email>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>36</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>e77</fpage>
      <lpage>e77</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2013 by the American Diabetes Association.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link> for details.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="e77.pdf"/>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="1"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>We report the case of a 47-year-old woman who was referred to our unit for hypoglycemia. She was diagnosed with diabetes at age 30 years and was previously treated with metformin, sulfonylureas, and glucagon-like peptide 1 agonists. Despite interruption of her treatments, she had for 1 month clinical features evoking hypoglycemic spells, with adrenergic and neuroglycopenic symptoms subsiding after glucose administration. Her BMI was 23.8 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. She had axillary acanthosis nigricans but no lipodystrophy. Continuous glucose monitoring showed hypoglycemia down to 2.1 mmol/L, mostly during fasting periods, and hyperglycemia up to 13.7 mmol/L in the absence of any treatment. HbA<sub>1c</sub> was 15%. During a fasting test, venous glucose concentration dropped to 2.5 mmol/L with concomitant low serum levels of C-peptide, insulinemia, and proinsulinemia: &lt;1.40, &lt;3, and 3.6 pmol/L, respectively (reference ranges in healthy subjects 17.8&#x2013;173, 370&#x2013;1,470, and 3.3&#x2013;28 pmol/L, respectively). Plasma levels of cortisol, somatostatin, IGF-1, and Western blot analysis of IGF-2 and its precursors were normal. Thoraco-abdominal computed tomography and whole-body F-18-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography scan did not reveal any abnormality.</p>
    <p>We evaluated the presence of anti-insulin receptor antibodies (AIRAs) using a radioreceptor assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). The patient&#x2019;s total serum and purified immunoglobulin fractions inhibited the binding of a tracer concentration of radiolabeled insulin, consistent with significant titers of AIRAs. Patient&#x2019;s serum and purified immunoglobulins activated proximal (tyrosine phosphorylation of insulin receptor &#x3B2;-subunit and insulin receptor substrate-1) and distal (phosphorylation of Akt/PKB) insulin-signaling pathways in vitro in a dose-dependant manner, mimicking insulin action.</p>
    <p>There was no clinical evidence of either systemic lupus erythematosus or another autoimmune disease, and the search for anti-nuclear, anti-DNA, anti-thyroid, anti-GAD, and anti-insulin antibodies was negative. Serum protein electrophoresis was also normal. A high-dose corticosteroid therapy (1 mg/kg prednisone) was introduced for 1 month with a progressive decrease over 4 months, which allowed a complete disappearance of hypoglycemic events. Because of persistent hyperglycemia, decreasing doses of corticosteroid were associated with insulin therapy. Search for serum AIRA after 3 months of treatment was negative.</p>
    <p>The occurrence of non&#x2013;insulin-mediated hypoglycemia requires the search for tumors secreting somatostatin, IGF-1, IGF-2, or its precursors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). After having ruled out those diagnoses, we detected serum AIRAs that activated insulin signaling in our patient. The concomitant disappearance of hypoglycemia and AIRAs after corticosteroid therapy strongly suggested that AIRAs were the cause of hypoglycemias. In most reported cases, AIRAs have been shown to occur in a context of autoimmune-associated disease&#x2014;mostly preexisting systemic lupus erythematosus, primary biliary cirrhosis, or Hashimoto thyroiditis. AIRAs were generally responsible for rapidly progressive insulin-resistant diabetes, sometimes associated with spontaneous hypoglycemia with hyperinsulinemia that could be due to an impairment of insulin degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). In our patient, we could not rule out the responsibility of preexisting AIRAs in the development of diabetes, and AIRAs did not induce hyperinsulinemia. First-line treatment is usually corticosteroid therapy, but the therapeutic strategies are not well defined because of the rarity of the disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). Our report highlights the fact that non&#x2013;insulin-mediated hypoglycemia must lead to the search of AIRAs even in case of preexisting long-lasting diabetes and in the absence of autoimmune-associated disease.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p>
      <p>J.-C.M., M.C.-D., C.V., and S.S. wrote the manuscript. J.-C.M. was involved in the management of the patient and wrote the manuscript. M.C.-D. and C.V. did the laboratory analysis and wrote the manuscript. S.S. was involved in the management of the patient and wrote the manuscript. J.-C.M. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Auclair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigouroux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Desbois-Mouthon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, Antiinsulin receptor autoantibodies induce insulin receptors to constitutively associate with insulin receptor substrate-1 and -2 and cause severe cell resistance to both insulin and insulin-like growth factor I. J Clin Endocrinol Metab <year>1999</year>;84:3197&#x2013;3206</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cryer</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelrod</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/><collab>Endocrine Society</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation and management of adult hypoglycemic disorders: an Endocrine Society Clinical Practice Guideline</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19088155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupsa</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Soos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Semple</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Autoimmune forms of hypoglycemia</article-title>. <source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19440117</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arioglu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Andewelt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Diabo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical course of the syndrome of autoantibodies to the insulin receptor (type B insulin resistance): a 28-year perspective</article-title>. <source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11889410</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
