<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Life</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMedLife</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Medicine and Life</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1844-122X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1844-3117</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Carol Davila University Press</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Romania</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20302202</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3019027</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JMedLife-03-80</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Presentation</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Erythrodermic atopic dermatitis with late onset&#x2013;case presentation
</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lancrajan</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bumbacea</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Giurcaneanu</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="A1">
          <label>*</label>
          <institution>Department of Oncologic Dermatology and Allergology, 
Elias University Emergency Hospital, Bucharest</institution>
          <country>Romania</country>
        </aff>
        <aff id="A2">
          <label>**</label>
          <institution>&#x2018;Carol Davila&#x2019; University of Medicine 
and Pharmacy&#x2013; Bucharest</institution>
          <country>Romania</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp><bold>Correspondence to:</bold>Calin Giurcaneanu  MD, PhD,
Chairman, Department of Oncologic Dermatology and Allergology, Elias University Hospital, 17 Marasti Bvd, District 
1, Bucharest, Romania</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>80</fpage>
      <lpage>83</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;Carol Davila University Press
</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>This is 
an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work 
is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atopic dermatitis is a chronic inflammatory disease, usually associated with a personal or family history 
of atopic diseases such as AD, allergic rhinitis or asthma that most commonly arise in childhood and present 
with elevated IgE serum in up to 85% of patients. The severity of AD is based on the extent of affected 
areas, itch intensity and appearance of skin lesions.</p>
        <p>Here, we present the case of a 21&#x2013;year&#x2013;old female patient with generalized erythematous 
eczematous skin lesions, flexural lichenifications accompanied by intense pruritus, painful fissures and 
erosions resulting from scratching. She also presented erythematous plaques with thin scales on the scalp. 
The patient had no personal or familial history of AD, allergic rhinitis or asthma and the onset of 
cutaneous symptoms presented severe exacerbation in the last 2 months of the last 3 years. The main 
laboratory findings were&#x2013;high serum eosinofilia (2,400/&#xB5;L) and very high total IgE serum 
(11449UI/L). The flare remission was induced with systemic treatment (corticotherapy, oral H1 antihistamines, 
and antibiotherapy) and topical therapy (UVB 311nm, topical glucocorticoids and hydration).</p>
        <p>It is very important to recognize AD as a cause of erythroderma, especially in a patient with a late onset of 
the disease, in order to treat it promptly and to prevent ulterior recurrences, by educating the patient to have
an adequate life style and to treat the recurrences at the very first symptoms.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="Introduction" id="sec1-1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Atopic dermatitis is an inflammatory, relapsing, chronic skin disease that usually begins in infancy and
 it presents with dry skin, erythematous&#x2013;edematous and veziculous papules and plaques accompanied by 
intense pruritus. Rubbing and scratching lead to erosions, fissures and lichenification. The predilected sites 
are flexures, neck, face, eyelids, wrists and dorsa of feet and hands or can be generalized in severe disease 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. The lesions are easily colonized with <italic>Staphylococcus aureus
</italic> which exacerbates the skin inflammation and maintains the vicious cycle by secreting exotoxins that may 
act as superantigens stimulating the activation of T cells and macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1
</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Atopic dermatitis is frequently associated with a personal or family history of atopic diseases such as 
atopic dermatitis, allergic rhinitis or asthma. Significant proportions of affected children have persistent 
atopic dermatitis after puberty and are at risk of developing respiratory allergies. The underlying 
pathophysiologic and genetic mechanisms are yet unknown but involve interactions between genetic factors, the 
immune system and the environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>The diagnosis is based on clinical aspects of the lesions, the most frequently used criteria being those 
proposed by Hanifin and Rajka. Three of four major criteria are necessary&#x2013;pruritus, typical morphology 
and distribution, chronically relapsing course and atopic personal or family history, in addition to three 
other signs of atopy like xerosis, keratosis pilaris, palmar hyperliniarity, Dennie&#x2013;Morgan infraorbital 
fold, periocular pigmentation, the Hertoghe sign of the lateral eyebrow, white dermografism, 
cheilitis, conjunctivitis, keratoconus, subcapsular anterior cataract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>Food allergy is an important trigger of atopic dermatitis. Skin prick tests or specific IgE serum have a 
high negative predictive value when they are negative. When they are positive they should be followed by 
placebo controlled oral food challenges in patients without history of life threatening reactions after the 
ingestion of specific food for preventing unnecessary dietary limitations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4
</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. Skin prick tests or specific IgE serum are useful 
to determine sensitivity to inhalant allergens such as house dust mite and animal dander 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>&#x2013;
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]. Up to 85% of patients have an elevated IgE serum level.</p>
      <p>The grading of the severity of atopic dermatitis is based on the extent of affected areas, itch intensity 
and appearance of skin lesions. The disease can complicate with erythroderma and risk of exfoliation, 
ocular complications such as keratoconus or keratoconjuctivitis sleep disturbances, psychological disturbances, 
and bacterial or viral skin infections.</p>
      <p>The treatment is complex and requires short term control of acute symptoms followed by long term stabilization 
and flare prevention with minimal side effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Case report" id="sec1-2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>We present the case of D.F., a 21&#x2013;year&#x2013;old female patient, with generalized erythematous 
skin lesions, flexural lichenifications accompanied by intense pruritus, painful fissures and erosions resulting 
from scratching. The whole body was covered with fine branny scales. She also presented erythematous plaques 
with thin scales on the scalp. The onset of cutaneous symptoms lasted for 3 years before the admission in our 
clinic with xerosis and erythematous and edematous plaques on the arms, neck and face, accompanied by 
intense pruritus. She was ocasionally treated with oral antihistamines but the lesions progressed in time on 
the trunk and legs. The scratching led to erosions and lichenification followed by painful fissures on the 
neck , anterior torax and at the flexures.</p>
      <p>The patient had no personal or familial history of allergic rhinitis or asthma. She had no other chronic 
medical conditions and was not on any medication. Physical examination, revealed a strong pulse, with a regular 
heart rhythm and a rate of 84 bpm, blood pressure of 110/60 mm Hg, weight of 54 kg. There were no signs 
of lymphadenopathy.(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1</xref>)</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Fig 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>First presentation : eritematous-edematous , veziculous , extensive lesions  with lichenification 
and erosions from scratching</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JMedLife-03-80-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The complete blood count (CBC) showed leukocytosis (a white blood cell count of 11,3 &#xD7; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#xB5;L)
 with high serum eosinofilia (2,440/&#xB5;L), and very high total IgE serum (11449UI/L). Skin punch biopsy 
showed moderate acanthosis and spongiosis and dermal infiltration composed of lymphocytes, hystiocytes 
and eosinophils. In atopic dermatitis, histopathology is nonspecific, being useful for differential diagnosis.</p>
      <p>Differential diagnosis in this case, included other conditions that could lead to exfoliative 
erythrodermic syndrome: erythrodermic psoriasis, lymphoma, leukemia, cutaneous drug reaction, allergic 
contact dermatitis, seborrheic dermatitis, pityriazis rubra pilaris and pemphigus foliaceus.</p>
      <p>After definite diagnosis, the treatment was started promptly. She received a high dose of systemic 
corticosteroids&#x2013;Prednisone 40mg (0,75mg/kgC) with gradual tapering of dose with 5 mg every 3 days, to a 
daily dose of 20 mg, then with a slower decrease, 5 mg every week, to prevent the rebound of symptoms. She 
also received a 7 days systemic antibiotherapy and oral antihistamines. Intensified skin hydration and 
topical corticosteroids were instituted during the tapering period, in order to suppress the rebound 
flaring associated with the narrow UVB band (311nm).</p>
      <p>The evolution was very good, with a complete clearance of lesions in about six weeks. After the cessation 
of systemic therapy and topical corticosteroids we insisted on a long term maintenance therapy with adequate 
cleaning and hydration of the skin, avoiding the irritating factors and potential allergens.
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2</xref>)</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Fig 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>After 2 weeks of treatment : considerable improvement of lesions </p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JMedLife-03-80-g002"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Discussions" id="sec1-3">
      <title>Discussions</title>
      <p>Exfoliative erythroderma is a serious, possible life threatening reaction. There is considerable heat 
dissipation and fluid loss due to the dilatation of capillaries. Moreover, high output cardiac failure, 
electrolyte imbalance and loss of serum protein may appear due to exfoliation. The patient may feel cold and 
present pruritus, fatigue, weakness, anorexia, weight loss and malaise. There is a high risk of secondary 
skin infection with S. aureus and even sepsis. Treatment should be instituted promptly, with supportive measures 
such as fluid and electrolyte replacement, systemic antibiotherapy if signs of infection are still present in 
the treatment of the underlying disease. Diagnosis is difficult and it is  based on the history of the 
preexisting disease and pathognomonic signs and symptoms. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]</p>
      <p>In this case, the late onset of the disease and the lack of personal or familial history of atopic diseases 
made the diagnosis harder to put. Arguments pro atopic dermatitis diagnosis were intense pruritus, 
lichenifications at flexures and on the neck and the high IgE serum level. </p>
      <p>We put differential diagnosis with other possible causes of erythrodermic reactions. The graduate onset, and 
the considerable period of time since the beginning of symptoms excluded a <bold><italic>cutaneous drug reaction
</italic></bold>. Psoriasis generally presents hyperkeratotic plaques of scalp or knees and elbows. The skin 
punch biopsy showes parakeratotic hyperkeratosis and polymorphonuclear cells in the epidermis forming 
microabcesses of Munro in the stratum corneum.<bold><italic> Severe allergic contact dermatitis</italic></bold> presents with an eruption that starts in a sensitized patient after repeated exposures to the allergen at 
the site of exposure with ulterior generalization. <bold><italic>Sezary syndrome</italic></bold> is a variant 
of cutaneous T cell lymphoma presenting erythroderma, peripheral lymphadenopathy and cellular infiltrations 
of atypical lymphocytes in the skin and blood. It usually occurs in patients over 60 years old. <bold><italic>Pemphigus foliaceus</italic></bold> may present as exfoliative erythroderma. It is a superficial form 
of pemphigus, with acantholysis in the granular layer of epidermis due to the circulation of autoantibodies to 
a 160&#x2013;kDa intercellular antigen (desmoglein 1), in the desmosomes of keratinocytes. </p>
      <p>The intensive treatment, the lack of other chronic medical conditions and the good cooperation with the 
patient helped in the complete resolution of lesions without other complications or side effects. 
Systemic anti&#x2013;inflammatory treatment for the acute phase is rapidly effective, but long&#x2013;term use 
should be avoided, as side effects are inevitable. Topical therapy should be instituted with a tapering of the 
doses in order to prevent the rebound flaring.</p>
      <p>Considering that atopic dermatitis is a chronic relapsing disease, it is very important that the 
patient understands her condition in order to have an adequate life style and, in the mean time, to avoid 
unnecessary measures and constrains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13
</xref>].</p>
      <p>The skin must be thoroughly cleansed with non-irritant and low allergic formulas. The bath should be short and 
the use of bath oils is necessary to avoid dehydration. Topical emollients should be applied directly after the 
bath for a better penetration, after the gentle drying of the skin.  Emollients should be used twice, daily, in 
order to reestablish and preserve the hydrolipid film of the skin, and restore the epidermal barrier function, 
which is able to prevent water loss and allergen penetration trough damaged skin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">
14</xref>]. Studies show that moisturizers used regularly decrease the need for topical corticosteroids 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Avoiding the irritants such as detergents, chlorine in the pool water, rough clothing fabrics or wool is 
necessary because they can contribute to the alteration of skin barrier favorising water loss 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. In addition, the environmental temperature and humidity should be 
moderate to avoid excessive sweating. It is important to control the exposure to allergens such as house dust mite 
or animal dander. Individual food allergies should be investigated and incriminated aliments should be removed 
from the diet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. Contact sensitizations should be diagnosed and 
implicated factors avoided [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>].</p>
      <p>A broad set of immunomodulatory agents have been used for severe atopic dermatitis refractory to other 
therapies, but their use is limited because of systemic toxicities and high costs. Cyclosporine A is a 
systemic calcineurin inhibitor used after organ transplantation. Multiple studies demonstrated that patients 
with refractory disease benefit from short&#x2013;term cyclosporine treatment. However, the disease relapses 
rapidly after cessation of therapy. This therapy is associated with systemic side effects such as elevated 
serum creatinine level, renal impairment or hypertension. Topical calcineurin inhibitors&#x2013;Tacrolimus 
and Pimecrolimus&#x2013;are safe and effective therapy for children of 2 years old and older and for adults. 
The most frequent side effect was a burning sensation at the application site. Due to the fact that it may 
restore the immunologic Th1&#x2013;Th2 imbalance, the recombinant interferon&#x2013; gamma, showed persistent long 
term improvement. However, the wide use has been limited by its high cost and difficulty in predicting 
responders. Intravenous immunoglobulin showed good responses and should be considered in refractory cases, but 
the major disadvantage is the high cost [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13
</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Conclusions" id="sec1-4">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>It is very important to recognize atopic dermatitis as a cause of erythroderma, especially in a patient with 
late onset of the disease and no personal or familial history of allergic diseases. Moreover, it is of high 
interest to treat it promptly and to prevent ulterior recurrences by educating the patient to have an adequate 
life style and to treat the flares at the very first symptoms.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hanifin</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajka</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnostic features of atopic dermatitis</article-title>
          <source>Derm Venerol</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>44</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Freedberg</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eisen</surname>
              <given-names>AZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Fitzpatrick's Dermatology in General Medicine</source>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bouguniewicz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eichenfield</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Current management of atopic dermatitis and interruption of atopic march</article-title>
          <source>J. Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>140</fpage>
          <lpage>149</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Isolauri</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turjanmaa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Combined skin prick and patch testing enhances identification of food allergy in infants with atopic dermatitis
</article-title>
          <source>J. Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8568142</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Darsow</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ring</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Airborne and dietary allergens in atopic eczema: a comprehensive review of diagnostic tests</article-title>
          <source>Clin Exp Dermatol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>544</fpage>
          <lpage>551</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11122226</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Niggermann</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of atopy patch test in diagnosis of food allergy in infants and children with atopic dermatitis</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Allergy Immunol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11380896</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roehr</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riebel</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Atopy patch tests, together with determination of specific IgE levels, reduce the need for oral food challenge in children with atopic dermatitis</article-title>
          <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>548</fpage>
          <lpage>553</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11240959</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bindslev&#x2013;Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Standardization of double blind, placebo-controlled food challenges</article-title>
          <source>Allergy</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>75</fpage>
          <lpage>77</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11298015</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Darsow</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laifaoui</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The prevalence of positive reactions in the atopy patch test with aeroallergens and food allergens in subjects with atopic eczema: a European multicenter study</article-title>
          <source>Allergy</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>1318</fpage>
          <lpage>1325</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15507101</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ring</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kunz</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bieber</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The &#x2018;atopy patch test&#x2019; with aeroallergens in atopic eczema</article-title>
          <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>195</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Darsow</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vieluf</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ring</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Atopy patch test with different vehicles and allergen concentration. An approach 
to standardization</article-title>
          <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>677</fpage>
          <lpage>684</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7897150</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoare</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li Wan Po</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Systematic review of treatments for atopic eczema</article-title>
          <source>Health Technol Assess</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>191</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11134919</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Darsow</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lubbe</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taieb</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seidenari</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wollenberg</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calza</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giusti</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ring</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Position paper on diagnosis and treatement of atopic dermatitis</article-title>
          <source>JEADV</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>286</fpage>
          <lpage>295</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15857453</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loden</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersson</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Improvement in skin barrier function in patients with atopic dermatitis after treatment with a moisturizing cream (Canoderm)</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <fpage>264</fpage>
          <lpage>267</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10233220</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manzini</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferdani</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Contact sensitization in children</article-title>
          <source>Contact Dermatitis</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>12</fpage>
          <lpage>17</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mortz</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersen</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Allergic contact dermatitis in children and adolescents</article-title>
          <source>Contact Dermatitis </source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10475509</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
