<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Orthop Traumatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Orthop Traumatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Orthopaedics and Traumatology : Official Journal of the Italian Society of Orthopaedics and Traumatology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1590-9921</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1590-9999</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21103903</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3014474</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">119</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10195-010-0119-6</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Osseous erosion by herniated nucleus pulposus mimicking intraspinal tumor: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoshioka</surname>
            <given-names>Shinji</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Sairyo</surname>
            <given-names>Koichi</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+81-44-8443333</phone>
            <fax>+81-44-8442470</fax>
            <email>sairyokun@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sakai</surname>
            <given-names>Toshinori</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tamura</surname>
            <given-names>Tatsuya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kosaka</surname>
            <given-names>Hirofumi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yasui</surname>
            <given-names>Natsuo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Orthopedics, Institute of Health Biosciences, The University of Tokushima Graduate School, Tokushima, Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Teikyo University Mizonokuchi Hospital, 3-8-3 Mizonokuchi, Takatsu-ku, Kawasaki, 213-8507 Japan </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>257</fpage>
      <lpage>261</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2010</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Erosion of spinal osseous structure, so-called scalloping, has been rarely reported associated with herniated nucleus pulposus (HNP). We report a rare case of HNP causing erosion of the spinal osseous structure (including lamina). The patient was an 81-year-old woman with 3-year history of low-back pain and left leg radiating pain. Muscle weakness of the left leg was also apparent. Computed tomography following myelography showed severe compression of the dural sac at the level of L3&#x2013;L4; furthermore, erosion of the lamina, pedicle, and vertebral body was noted, indicating that the space-occupying mass was most probably a tumorous lesion. The mass also showed calcification inside. During the surgery, the mass was confirmed to be an HNP with calcification. Following resection, the pain disappeared. Surgeons should be aware of the possibility of scalloping of the vertebrae caused by HNP mimicking a tumorous lesion.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Herniated nucleus pulposus</kwd>
        <kwd>Scalloping</kwd>
        <kwd>Erosion</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2010</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Increased intraspinal pressure exerted by an expanding mass such as a slow-growing intraspinal tumor is a common cause of erosion (scalloping) of the posterior vertebral wall [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. As for other causes of scalloping, communicating hydrocephalus, Marfan syndrome, Ehlers&#x2013;Danlos syndrome, ankylosing spondylitis, neurofibromatosis, achondroplasia, Morquio syndrome, Hurler syndrome, acromegaly, tuberculosis, and fungal infections have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Erosion of the spinal osseous structure by herniated nucleus pulposus (HNP) has rarely been reported. Only 10 HNP cases with scalloping have been reported in the pertinent English-language literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p>
      <p>We describe an uncommon case of HNP causing erosion of the vertebral body, the pedicle, and the lamina, which was initially diagnosed to be a tumorous lesion located in the spinal canal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>The patient was an 81-year-old woman with 3-year history of low-back pain and left leg radiating pain. Her symptoms had gradually worsened until she was not able to walk unaided. Finally, she was referred to our hospital for surgical intervention.</p>
      <p>Neurological examination showed a positive straight-leg raising test at 20&#xB0; and positive femoral nerve stretching testing on the left side. Muscle weakness found in the left quadriceps was 4-/5, and that of the left tibialis anterior was 4/5. Hypoesthesia was noted in the left leg at the L4 area.</p>
      <p>Plain AP and lateral radiographs of the lumbar spine are shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. There was no spinal abnormality except for osteoporosis (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) demonstrated an L2&#x2013;L4 T-score of &#x2212;2.5. Computed tomographic (CT) myelography following myelography at L3&#x2013;L4 showed a tumorous mass with partial calcification in the spinal canal, and erosion of the adjacent L4 vertebral body, pedicle, and lamina. These findings suggested an intraspinal tumorous lesion (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The right panel in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the slice corresponding to the cranial aspect of the L4 pedicle, and the left panel shows the one corresponding to the caudal aspect of the L4 pedicle. Red arrows indicate the location of scalloping, and white arrows, the calcification in the mass.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Plain AP and lateral radiographs of the lumbar spine</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10195_2010_119_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e280"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>CT myelography following myelography at L3&#x2013;L4 showing a tumorous mass with partial calcification in the spinal canal. The <italic>right panel</italic> shows the slice corresponding to the cranial aspect of the L4 pedicle. The <italic>left panel</italic> shows the slice corresponding to the caudal aspect of the L4 pedicle. <italic>Red arrows</italic> indicate the location of scalloping, and <italic>white arrows</italic>, the calcification in the mass</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10195_2010_119_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e301"/></fig></p>
      <p>Magnetic resonance (MR) sagittal images showed a mass at L3&#x2013;L4 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). The mass extended caudally and strongly compressed the dural sac. Axial MR images showed that the mass was located on the right side and caused scalloping (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Arrows in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b indicate the location of scalloping.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> MR sagittal images showing a mass at L3&#x2013;L4. The mass extended caudally and strongly compressed the dural sac. <bold>b</bold> Axial MR images showing the mass located on the right side and the scalloping (<italic>red arrows</italic>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10195_2010_119_Fig3_HTML" id="d30e329"/></fig></p>
      <p>Because of the long clinical history and the MR images, we considered the tumor to be not malignant, but rather most likely to be an HNP, and therefore did not perform biopsy prior to removing it. However, we should have done a biopsy for differential diagnosis of slow-growing malignant tumors to ensure safer treatment.</p>
      <p>L4 hemilaminectomy was required to remove the entire mass from the spinal canal. A voluminous calcified mass was found beneath the left L4 nerve root. The L4 nerve root was displaced laterally, adhered to the mass. The mass partially contained calcified tissue. After removal of the mass, erosion of the vertebral body was noted. Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> shows the removed tissue 3&#xA0;days after fixation in 10% formic acid. Apparently, it was not a tumor, but HNP tissue. Histopathological findings were consistent with those of calcified HNP. Postoperative MR images revealed that the thecal sac was totally decompressed (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Scalloping was also clearly seen on postoperative MRI (arrows in the right panel). Postoperatively, her leg pain subsided, but muscle weakness remained. The patient was asked whether data concerning her case could be submitted for publication, and she consented.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>The surgical specimen shown after fixation in 10% formic acid. On macroscopic examination, it seems to be an HNP</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10195_2010_119_Fig4_HTML" id="d30e348"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Postoperative MR images revealed that the thecal sac was totally decompressed. Scalloping was also clearly seen on postoperative MRI (<italic>arrows</italic> in the <italic>right panel</italic>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10195_2010_119_Fig5_HTML" id="d30e363"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>It is well known that increased intraspinal pressure exerted by an expanding mass such as an intraspinal tumorous lesion may cause erosion (scalloping) of the spinal osseous structures. Ependymoma, dermoid cysts, epidermoid cysts, schwannoma, lipomas, and lymphomas frequently show thinning of laminae and pedicles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Dural ectasia, associated with inherited disorders such as Marfan syndrome, and Ehlers&#x2013;Danlos syndrome, and neurofibromatosis is also a cause of scalloping of vertebral bodies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. There have been few reports, however, of scalloping of the spinal osseous structures caused by HNP.</p>
      <p>The present case showed erosion of the L4 vertebral body, pedicle, and lamina by a calcified herniated mass of the L3&#x2013;L4 intervertebral disc. There have been 10 cases of bone erosion due to HNP reported in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Most cases showed erosion in the posterior wall of the vertebral bodies (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Vadala et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] stated that thinning of the laminae and pedicles was commonly seen associated with a tumorous lesion, and that this kind of scalloping was not observed in cases with HNP. An HNP would usually cause scalloping of the vertebral bodies only, if there were any [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In the present case, erosive change occurred in the lamina as well as the vertebral body. No previous report showed such wide erosion of the spinal osseous structure by HNP as shown in the present case.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Summary of the characteristics of previous cases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Case</th><th align="left">Authors</th><th align="left">Sex, age (years)</th><th align="left">Clinical history</th><th align="left">Location of herniation</th><th align="left">Location of scalloping</th><th align="left">Calcification</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Vadala et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td align="left">Female, 39</td><td align="left">More than 1&#xA0;year</td><td align="left">L5</td><td align="left">Vertebral body</td><td align="left">&#x2212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Male, 45</td><td align="left">7&#xA0;years</td><td align="left">L5</td><td align="left">Vertebral body</td><td align="left">&#x2212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Male, 41</td><td align="left">Several years</td><td align="left">L5/S</td><td align="left">Vertebral body</td><td align="left">&#x2212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Female, 55</td><td align="left">3&#xA0;years</td><td align="left">L5</td><td align="left">Vertebral body</td><td align="left">&#x2212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">Norfray et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td align="left">Female, 43</td><td align="left">3&#xA0;years</td><td align="left">S1</td><td align="left">Vertebral body</td><td align="left">&#x2212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Male, 48</td><td align="left">7&#xA0;years</td><td align="left">L4</td><td align="left">Neural foramen</td><td align="left">&#x2212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Male, 41</td><td align="left">3&#xA0;years</td><td align="left">L5</td><td align="left">Vertebral body</td><td align="left">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">Briceno et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td align="left">Male, 46</td><td align="left">19&#xA0;years</td><td align="left">L4</td><td align="left">Vertebral body and pedicle</td><td align="left">&#x2212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">Flak et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td><td align="left">Male, 28</td><td align="left">1.5&#xA0;years</td><td align="left">S1</td><td align="left">Vertebral body</td><td align="left">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">Berthelot et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td align="left">Male, 61</td><td align="left">Several weeks</td><td align="left">T10</td><td align="left">Vertebral body</td><td align="left">+</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Present case</td><td align="left">Yoshioka et&#xA0;al.</td><td align="left">Female, 82</td><td align="left">3&#xA0;years</td><td align="left">L4</td><td align="left">Vertebral body, pedicle, and lamina</td><td align="left">+</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Several authors have advocated that long clinical history of pain and chronic pressure due to large-size HNP could cause bone erosion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Nine of the 11 cases reported so far, including the present case, had history of pain longer than 1&#xA0;year (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Vadala et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] also suggested that old HNPs might cause a mechanical irritating action on the small vascular structures of the bone cortex. Additionally, our patient was an 81-year-old woman with overt osteoporosis. We supposed that an elderly patient with osteoporosis suffering for a long period from pain caused by an HNP was likely to show erosion of spinal osseous structures.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <sec id="d30e721">
        <title>Conflict of interest</title>
        <p>None.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="d30e726">
        <title>Open Access</title>
        <p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>El Khamary</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alorainy</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case 100: spinal epidural meningioma</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>241</volume>
          <fpage>614</fpage>
          <lpage>617</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2412040203</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17057078</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jaiswal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shetty</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajasekaran</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Giant cystic intradural schwannoma in the lumbosacral region: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Orthop Surg (Hong Kong)</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>102</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18453671</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koeller</surname>
              <given-names>KK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenblum</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morrison</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neoplasms of the spinal cord and filum terminale: radiologic-pathologic correlation</article-title>
          <source>Radiographics</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1721</fpage>
          <lpage>1749</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiographics.20.6.g00nv151721</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11112826</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guinto</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madewell</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Swischuk</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>David</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The vertebral body: radiographic configurations in various congenital and acquired disorders</article-title>
          <source>Radiographics</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>485</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiographics.8.3.3380991</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3380991</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cole</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spinal extradural arachnoid cysts: clinical, radiological, and surgical features</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurg Focus</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>E6</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/foc.2007.22.2.6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17608349</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Handler</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rorke</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Epstein</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MR of spinal cord ganglioglioma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Neuroradiol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>879</fpage>
          <lpage>887</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9613504</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tabaddor</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lamorgese</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lumbar epidermoid cyst following single spinal puncture: case report</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>1168</fpage>
          <lpage>1169</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1202013</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wakely</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The posterior vertebral scalloping sign</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>239</volume>
          <fpage>607</fpage>
          <lpage>609</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2392040224</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16641360</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crawford</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parikh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schorry</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Von Stein</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The immature spine in type-1 neurofibromatosis</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>123</fpage>
          <lpage>142</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.F.00836</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17272429</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frazier</surname>
              <given-names>DD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campbell</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garray</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiesel</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bohlman</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elsment</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fungal infections of the spine: report of eleven patients with long-term follow-up</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>560</fpage>
          <lpage>565</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11315785</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Funasaki</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Winter</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lonstein</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Denis</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pathophysiology of spinal deformities in neurofibromatosis. An analysis of seventy-one patients who had curves associated with dystrophic changes</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>692</fpage>
          <lpage>700</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8175817</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ho</surname>
              <given-names>NC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hadley</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francomano</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case 47: dural ectasia associated with Marfan syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>223</volume>
          <fpage>767</fpage>
          <lpage>771</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2233000971</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034948</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Joseffer</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Modern imaging of spinal tuberculosis</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg Spine</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>145</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/spi.2005.2.2.0145</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15739525</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Misra</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morgan</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thoracolumbar spinal deformity in achondroplasia</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurg Focus</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>E4</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15766221</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Winter</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moe</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bradford</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lonstein</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pedras</surname>
              <given-names>CV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weber</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spine deformity in neurofibromatosis. A review of one hundred and two patients</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>677</fpage>
          <lpage>694</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">110813</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berthelot</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maugars</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bertrand-Vasseur</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lalande</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prost</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dorsal scalloping by calcified disc herniation</article-title>
          <source>Spine</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>106</fpage>
          <lpage>107</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-199501000-00019</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7709268</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Briceno</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fazl</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Willinsky</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gertzbein</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sequestrated lumbar intervertebral disc associated with vertebral erosion</article-title>
          <source>Spine</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>898</fpage>
          <lpage>899</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-198908000-00026</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2781404</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flak</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Knickerbockes</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case report 567: chronic disc herniation causing bone erosion</article-title>
          <source>Skeletal Radiol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>481</fpage>
          <lpage>482</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00368621</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2814560</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Norfray</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gado</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Becker</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Resnick</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sartoris</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extruded nucleus pulposus causing osseous erosion of a lumbar vertebral body. A report of three cases</article-title>
          <source>Spine</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>941</fpage>
          <lpage>944</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-198808000-00017</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3187721</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vadala</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dove</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garbagna</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unusual osseus changes in lumbar herniated discs: CT features</article-title>
          <source>J Comput Assist Tomogr</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>1045</fpage>
          <lpage>1049</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004728-198511000-00008</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4056135</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
