<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24346894</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3876008</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20131986</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Borderline tuberculoid leprosy and type 1 leprosy reaction in a hepatitis
C patient during treatment with interferon and ribavirin<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref>
</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Hansen&#xED;ase boderline tubercul&#xF3;ide e rea&#xE7;&#xE3;o hans&#xEA;nica do tipo 1 em
paciente com hepatite C durante tratamento com interferon e
ribavirina</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Santos</surname>
            <given-names>M&#xF4;nica</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Franco</surname>
            <given-names>Emily dos Santos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ferreira</surname>
            <given-names>Paulo Luis da Costa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Braga</surname>
            <given-names>Wornei Silva Miranda</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> PhD in tropical medicine. Dermatologist at the Alfredo da Matta
Foundation - Manaus (AM), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> M.D. Pathology resident at the Get&#xFA;lio Vargas University Hospital -
Manaus (AM), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> M.D. Infectologist at the Tropical Medicine of Amazonas Foundation
(FMT-AM) - Manaus (AM), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> PhD in tropical medicine. Infectologist at the Tropical Medicine of
Amazonas Foundation (FMT-AM) - Manaus (AM), Brazil.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing address:</bold> M&#xF4;nica Santos Av. Pedro Texeira, 25 - Dom Pedro,
69040-000 - Manaus - AM, Brazil. E-mail: <email>m.n.souza.santos@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>6 Suppl 1</issue>
      <fpage>109</fpage>
      <lpage>112</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hepatitis C is an inflammatory disease of the liver caused by a single-stranded RNA
virus belonging to the Hepacivirus genus in the Flaviviridae family, called the
hepatitis C virus. After initial infection, 70% to 85% of the patients develop
chronic hepatitis C with hepatic fibrosis. In addition to specific liver changes,
various extrahepatic manifestations have been associated with the hepatitis C virus
infection or with medications used to treat the condition. We report the case of a
patient with chronic hepatitis C who presented with the signs and symptoms of
borderline tuberculoid leprosy and type 1 reaction four months after the start of
treatment with a pegylated interferon/ribavirin combination.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>A hepatite C &#xE9; uma doen&#xE7;a inflamat&#xF3;ria f&#xED;gado causada por um v&#xED;rus RNA de fita
simples, pertencente ao g&#xEA;nero Hepacivirus e &#xE0; fam&#xED;lia Flaviviridae, denominado de
v&#xED;rus da hepatite C. Ap&#xF3;s infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o inicial 70 a 85% dos pacientes infectados evoluem
para hepatite C cr&#xF4;nica, com fibrose progressiva. Al&#xE9;m das altera&#xE7;&#xF5;es hep&#xE1;ticas
espec&#xED;ficas, v&#xE1;rias manifesta&#xE7;&#xF5;es extra-hep&#xE1;ticas t&#xEA;m sido relacionadas &#xE0; infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o
pelo v&#xED;rus da hepatite C ou &#xE0;s medica&#xE7;&#xF5;es utilizadas no seu tratamento. Nesse
trabalho, apresenta-se caso de paciente portador de hepatite C cr&#xF4;nica, que
manifestou um quadro hansen&#xED;ase boderline tubercul&#xF3;ide e rea&#xE7;&#xE3;o hans&#xEA;nica do tipo I,
quatro meses ap&#xF3;s in&#xED;cio do tratamento com interferon peguilado associado &#xE0;
ribavirina.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Hepatitis C</kwd>
        <kwd>Interferons</kwd>
        <kwd>Leprosy</kwd>
        <kwd>Therapeutics</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Hepatitis C is an inflammatory disease of the liver caused by a single-stranded RNA
virus belonging to the <italic>Hepacivirus</italic> genus in the
<italic>Flaviviridae</italic> family, called the hepatitis C virus. After initial
infection, only 15% to 30% of hepatitis C patients recover spontaneously, while 70% to
85% develop chronic hepatitis C, which is defined as HCV persisting for more than six
months after infection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref></sup> The main
consequence of chronic hepatitis C is progressive hepatic fibrosis, which can lead to
cirrhosis, liver failure and hepatocellular carcinoma. In addition to specific liver
changes, various extrahepatic manifestations have been associated with HCV
infection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup> Dermatologic changes
constitute a significant part of the spectrum of extrahepatic manifestations in
hepatitis C and can be divided into those associated with the presence of HCV itself and
those caused by medications used to treat the condition.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> Among the manifestations commonly associated with HCV,
the most notable are cryoglobulinemia, porphyria cutanea tarda, leukocytoclastic
vasculitis and livedo reticularis. Hepatitis C is normally treated with a pegylated
interferon/ribavirin combination to prevent it from progressing to the chronic
form.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup> Despite the undeniable
benefits of this combination, when used in clinical practice it can lead to a range of
adverse effects, including dermatologic complications, many of which are the result of
the immunomodulatory effects of interferon. These effects may also include the
exacerbation of existing cutaneous diseases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 57-year-old male with hepatitis C using pegylated interferon and ribavirin for
treatment of hepatitis C. Four months after the start of the treatment, disseminated
cutaneous lesions appeared, as well as intense pain along the course of the cubital and
fibular nerves. Dermatologic examination revealed small and large, highly infiltrated
erythematous plaques on his back, arms and legs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure
1</xref>). Physical examination revealed thickened cubital and fibular nerves that
were highly painful to palpation. The patient reported that he had developed a small
erythematous plaque on his back two years previously, which had been treated
unsuccessfully as dermatophytosis. In light of the clinical history and the results of
the dermatological examination, a hypothesis of borderline tuberculoid leprosy with type
I reaction was put forward and an incisional biopsy was performed. A histological exam
revealed granulomatous inflammatory infiltrate in the upper dermis and around blood
vessels and hair follicles, but Wade staining and bacteriological examination were
negative (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>). The Mitsuda reaction was
positive. As the diagnosis was confirmed, six months of multidrug therapy for
paucibacillary (PB) leprosy was started, together with an initial 80 mg/day dose of
prednisolone, which was then gradually reduced. After the case was discussed with the
hepatology team, the decision was taken to interrupt the interferon and ribavirin
treatment until the treatment for PB leprosy was completed. There was a clinical
improvement in the patient's leprosy reaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure
3</xref>), and he was discharged as cured after completing MDT for PB leprosy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>). Six months ago, the patient again began
treatment for hepatitis C with interferon and ribavirin, but obtained no sustained
virological response and awaiting this release for use of pegylated interferon and
ribavirin associated with protease inhibitor (telaprevir or boceprevir). At the time of
writing, the patient is undergoing follow-up at the dermatology and hepatology services
and has not presented with any clinical manifestations of leprosy reaction. </p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous plaques with dense infiltrate on the trunk and arms</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0109-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histological examination revealed granulomatous inflammatory infiltrate in the
dermis made up of lymphocytes, epithelioid cells and multinucleated giant cells.
The infiltrate touches the epidermis in several places, surrounds vessels and hair
follicles and does not have a halo of lymphocytes</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0109-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Reduced plaque infiltration after treatment with oral corticosteroids was
started</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0109-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Lesions were clinically cured six months after the end of the multidrug therapy
(MDT) for paucibacillary (PB) leprosy</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0109-g04"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Leprosy is a chronic granulomatous condition caused by <italic>Mycobacterium
leprae</italic>, which affects the skin, peripheral nervous system and, sometimes,
other organs and systems. During the natural course of the disease, manifestations
related to exacerbation of cellular immunity or the formation of immunocomplexes (known,
respectively, as type 1 and type 2 leprosy reactions) may occur.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup> Type 1 reaction or reversal reaction is
an acute inflammatory episode in the skin and peripheral nerves that is found in up to
30% of leprosy patients and commonly causes physical disabilities. Multidrug
chemotherapy and viral infections (such as the hepatitis B or C viruses and HIV) are
associated risk factors. It generally manifests in borderline forms, with a clinical
picture characterized by signs of acute inflammation, such as pain, redness,
infiltration and swelling of preexisting lesions. New lesions may also appear. Neural
involvement is also common and can lead to deformities if not diagnosed and treated
early.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup> The nerves most
frequently affected are the cubital, radial, median, tibial and fibular nerves. The
whole reversal reaction is associated with a sudden increase in cell-mediated immunity
and is an example of a delayed hypersensitivity reaction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup> In type 1 leprosy reaction, there is participation of T
lymphocytes with production of TH1-type cytokines, especially IL-2 and IFN-&#x3B3;. Although
type 1 leprosy reaction can be triggered by the viral infection itself, in the case
under discussion, it is more likely that the reaction was caused by the use of
interferon, as the patient believed that he had been infected with HCV for at least ten
years, but had not had similar episodes previously. In addition, there are reports in
the literature of autoimmune events, such as thyroiditis and vitiligo, being
precipitated by interferon therapy as a result of the T helper 1 response
induced.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup> Interferons are
natural proteins modifying immunobiological response, effective antiviral,
antiproliferative and immunomodulator. The immunomodulatory effect of the product
includes various actions on elements of the immune system, such as stimulation
activities lytic natural killer cells, cytotoxic T lymphocytes and macrophages on
infected tumor cells, modification of the production of antibodies by B cells,
regulation of expression of MHC antigens in the cell membrane and stimulating the
production of interferon alpha<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref></sup> In
the case described here, the patient probably already had undiagnosed leprosy, as he had
reported having an erythematous plaque on his back, and the use of pegylated interferon
may have triggered the reversal reaction as this is an immune-mediated reaction. </p>
      <p>In this paper, we report the case of a patient with chronic hepatitis C who presented
with the signs and symptoms of borderline tuberculoid leprosy and type 1 reaction four
months after starting treatment with a pegylated interferon/ribavirin combination.
Multidisciplinary follow-up allowed reversal reaction to be diagnosed and early
treatment to be started, thus avoiding any potential disabilities.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <p>* Work performed at the Doutor Heitor Vieira Dourado Tropical Medicine of Amazonas
Foundation (FMT-HVD) - Manaus (AM), Brasil.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial Support: None</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES </title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bonkovsky</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehta</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hepatitis C: a review and update</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>182</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11174373</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Poynard</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuen</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ratziu</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lai</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Viral hepatitis C</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>362</volume>
          <fpage>2095</fpage>
          <lpage>2100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14697814</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agnello</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosa</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extrahepatic disease manifestations of HCV infection: some current
issues</article-title>
          <source>J Hepatol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>341</fpage>
          <lpage>352</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739110</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Caramez</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gi&#xE1;como</surname>
              <given-names>CG Di</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>LKVM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lupi</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Altera&#xE7;&#xF5;es dermatol&#xF3;gicas na hepatite C</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras Clin Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>53</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hepatitis C and the skin</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Clin</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>449</fpage>
          <lpage>458</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12170878</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mendon&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brito-Melo</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antunes</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teixeira</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immunology of leprosy</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>343</fpage>
          <lpage>350</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nery</surname>
              <given-names>JAC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sales</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Illarramendi</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duppre</surname>
              <given-names>NC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jardim</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machado</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Contribution to diagnosis and management of reactional states: a
practical approach</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          <lpage>375</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goulart</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Penna</surname>
              <given-names>GO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Imunopatologia da hansen&#xED;ase: a complexidade dos
mecanismos da resposta imune do hospedeiro ao Mycobacterium leprae</article-title>
          <source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>365</fpage>
          <lpage>375</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12170333</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cacoub</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bourli&#xE8;re</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>L&#xFC;bbe</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dupin</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buggisch</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dusheiko</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatological side effects of hepatitis C and its treatment: patient
management in the era of direct-acting antivirals</article-title>
          <source>J Hepatol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>463</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21884670</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rego</surname>
              <given-names>VPA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machado</surname>
              <given-names>PRL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martins</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trindade</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paran&#xE1;</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Caracter&#xED;sticas da rea&#xE7;&#xE3;o tipo 1 e associa&#xE7;&#xE3;o com v&#xED;rus
B e C da hepatite na hansen&#xED;ase</article-title>
          <source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>546</fpage>
          <lpage>549</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17992411</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
