<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Malar J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Malar. J</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Malaria Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1475-2875</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23914838</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3737032</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1475-2875-12-271</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-12-271</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Hyposplenism revealed by <italic>Plasmodium malariae</italic> infection</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Hommel</surname>
            <given-names>Benjamin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>benjaminhommel@hotmail.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Galloula</surname>
            <given-names>Alexandre</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>Agalloula@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Simon</surname>
            <given-names>Anne</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>anne.simon@psl.aphp.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Buffet</surname>
            <given-names>Pierre</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>pierre.buffet@psl.aphp.fr</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Parasitology-Mycology Laboratory, Assistance Publique H&#xF4;pitaux de Paris, Groupe Hospitalier Piti&#xE9;-Salp&#xEA;tri&#xE8;re, 47 Boulevard de l'H&#xF4;pital, 75651, Paris, Cedex 13, France</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>H&#xF4;pital Piti&#xE9;-Salp&#xEA;tri&#xE8;re, Service de M&#xE9;decine Interne, Boulevard de l'h&#xF4;pital, 75651, Paris, Cedex 13, France</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>INSERM, UMR-S 945, Paris, France</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <fpage>271</fpage>
      <lpage>271</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 Hommel et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Hommel et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.malariajournal.com/content/12/1/271"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Hyposplenism, due to splenectomy, inherited red blood cell disorders or acquired conditions such as celiac disease, has an important impact on the severity of malaria, especially in non-immune patients. Conversely, that malaria may reveal functional hyposplenism has not been described previously.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>A 31-year old gardener was diagnosed with an uncomplicated attack of <italic>Plasmodium malariae</italic> 11&#xA0;years after leaving the endemic area. In addition to trophozoites and schizonts, thick and thin smears also showed Howell-Jolly bodies, pointing to functional hyposplenism. This was later confirmed by the presence of a calcified spleen in the context of S/&#x3B2;&#x2009;+&#x2009;sickle-cell syndrome in a patient previously unaware of this condition.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Malaria may reveal hyposplenism. Although Howell-Jolly bodies are morphologically similar to nuclei of young <italic>Plasmodium</italic> trophozoite, distinction on smears is based on the absence of cytoplasm and irregular size of Howell-Jolly bodies. In the patient reported here, hyposplenism was revealed by the occurrence of <italic>P. malariae</italic> infection relatively late in life. Timely diagnosis of hyposplenism resulted in the implementation of appropriate measures to prevent overwhelming infection with capsulated bacteria. This observation highlights the importance of diagnosing hyposplenism in patients with malaria despite the morphological similarities between ring nuclei and Howell-Jolly bodies on thick smears.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Hyposplenism</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Plasmodium malariae</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Howell Jolly bodies</kwd>
        <kwd>Sickle cell syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Malaria</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Hyposplenism corresponds to the impairment of splenic function. This is a serious condition because the spleen plays a major role in immunological and mechanical defences against infections. Diagnosis of spleen dysfunction is based on the measure of its filtering function. The gold standard is the measure of phagocytosis of colloid particles in the spleen using radioisotopic methods. However, quantification of morphological alterations or deformability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] of circulating red blood cells is a more practical marker [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Howell-Jolly bodies are small nuclear remnants from erythroblasts that cannot be removed from red blood cells if the spleen is absent. In sickle cell disease, there is a strong correlation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] between the number of red blood cells harbouring Howell-Jolly bodies, or the number of &#x201C;pitted cells&#x201D; (i e, red blood cells containing small vesicles) in circulation and the intensity of functional hyposplenism. In <italic>Plasmodium</italic> infections, the spleen contributes to innate resistance and limits the magnitude of parasitaemia. This is particularly well established in <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. For other species, such as <italic>Plasmodium malariae</italic>, the influence of hyposplenism on the outcome of infection is poorly documented. Here, is the clinical history report of a patient in whom chronic infection with <italic>P. malariae</italic> (11&#xA0;years after leaving the endemic area) revealed functional hyposplenism and a major sickle cell syndrome.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p>A 31-year-old gardener was admitted to an emergency department in December 2010. He had moved from Mali to France in 1999 and had never travelled back to Africa or to any tropical country. The patient had a surgical history of inguinal abscess. He had no medication, smoked tobacco for 14&#xA0;years and did not drink alcohol. Between 2006 and 2009, he experienced episodes of chronic fever and asthenia. On physical examination the patient was febrile with a temperature of 39&#xB0;C had a 119-beat per minute pulse and a blood pressure of 147/97&#xA0;mmHg. He reported headache, myalgia and lumbar pain. The rest of physical examination was normal.</p>
      <p>The patient was admitted to the internal medicine department. He mentioned repeated flu-like syndromes in the previous three months and recent episodes of rhythmic fever occurring once every three days. At admission, physical examination was unremarkable and main laboratory parameters were: leucocytosis, white blood cells 11.9&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>9</sup>/l&#xA0;N (4.0-10.0), microcytic anaemia with haemoglobin 11.5&#xA0;g/dl&#xA0;N (13.0-17.5) and mean corpuscular volume 72&#xA0;fl&#xA0;N (80&#x2013;100), platelets 252&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>9</sup>/l&#xA0;N(150&#x2013;400), creatinaemia 81&#xA0;&#x3BC;mol/l&#xA0;N (62&#x2013;106), and inflammatory syndrome with C-reactive protein 33&#xA0;mg/l&#xA0;N(&lt;5) and ferritinaemia 2,020&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/l&#xA0;N (30&#x2013;300).</p>
      <p>Thin and thick smears were performed from venous blood. The rosette-like aspect of a schizont (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A), the small size of the erythrocyte-hosting gametocytes on the thin smear (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B) and the absence of Maurer or Sch&#xFC;ffner dots were highly suggestive of <italic>P. malariae</italic> infection, latter confirmed by a positive polymerase chain reaction with primers specific for <italic>P. malariae</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. This diagnosis was consistent with the very long incubation period and the rhythm of fever.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Diagnosis of </bold><bold><italic>Plasmodium malariae </italic></bold><bold>infection and presence of Howell-Jolly bodies.</bold> Thick <bold>(A)</bold> and thin <bold>(B)</bold> smear at admission (original magnification &#xD7;1000, Giemsa &#x2013;R staining). In red squares, a sample of <italic>P. malariae</italic> rings showing morphological similarities between ring nuclei and Howell-Jolly bodies. The absence of cytoplasm is key for the differential diagnosis. <bold>A</bold>. Two leukocyte nuclei, the rosette-like aspect (vertical arrow) of the schizont (<italic>Plasmodium malariae</italic>), and several Howell-Jolly bodies (red arrows). <bold>B</bold>. Small size of the erythrocyte hosting a P. malariae gametocyte (vertical arrow) and unifected red blood cells showing microcytosis, anisochromasia, and target aspect.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1475-2875-12-271-1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Initially, the small, round, purple bodies on the thick smear were interpreted as the nuclei of young trophozoites (rings), thereby strengthening the diagnosis. However, the absence of cytoplasm in contact with these bodies and their markedly variable size contradicted this interpretation. Study of the thin smear confirmed that the bodies corresponded instead to typical Howell-Jolly bodies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The thin smear also showed morphological abnormalities of red cells: microcytosis, anisochromasia, target cells and schistocytes, raising the hypothesis of an associated haemoglobin disorder. Liquid chromatography of haemoglobin revealed a S/&#x3B2;&#x2009;+&#x2009;sickle cell syndrome (HbS 60% and heterozygous beta thalassaemia &#xDF;&#x2009;+&#x2009;with HbA2 6.5% HbF 6.1%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>The patient had no abdominal surgery scars. Due to the presence of Howell-Jolly bodies and the S/&#x3B2;&#x2009;+&#x2009;sickle cell syndrome, a computed tomography scan of the abdominal region was performed and showed an atrophic calcified spleen (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Abdominal CT-scan identify a small calcified spleen (yellow arrow).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1475-2875-12-271-2"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The malaria attack resolved rapidly with a three-day course of oral chloroquine. Clinical and laboratory markers returned to normal in one week. The patient was discharged after being vaccinated for encapsulated bacteria (<italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic> and <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic>) and provided with long-term oral beta-lactams to prevent potential complications of asplenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Malaria prophylaxis was recommended in case of travel to Africa.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In patients with sickle cell anaemia, repeated sequestration crises leading to infarctions generally result in early splenic atrophy with calcifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. This evolution is almost constant in adult patients with homozygous sickle cell disease but is less frequent in patients with the S/&#x3B2; + sickle cell syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Progressive hyposplenism and splenic atrophy in this patient were revealed by a malaria episode, and occurred relatively late in life. Sickle cell trait, i e, the heterozyte form, is protective against severe and fatal <italic>P. falciparum</italic> infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], whereas in homozygosity, protection against severe malaria is counterbalanced by hyposplenism which appear during childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. This observation suggests the existence of a similarly balanced influence of the presence of HbS on the evolution of infection with <italic>P. malariae</italic>.</p>
      <p>Much less is known on the impact of anatomical or functional hyposplenism on the course of infections with <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic>, <italic>Plasmodium ovale</italic>, <italic>Plasmodium knowlesi</italic> and <italic>P. malariae</italic> than on the more frequent <italic>P. falciparum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Indeed, <italic>P. falciparum</italic> infection is more frequently severe and fatal in non-immune splenectomized patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. <italic>Plasmodium malariae</italic> infection can be severe in patients with splenectomy or functional asplenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Here the patient experienced only mild symptoms. It is assumed that in <italic>P. malariae</italic> as observed with <italic>P. falciparum</italic> patients who acquired immunity before becoming asplenic, uncomplicated attacks are more frequent than severe malaria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Presence of Howell-Jolly bodies on a blood sample is a fairly specific indicator of hyposplenism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. In this patient their presence on the thick/thin smear was due to sickle cell anaemia but presence of Howell-Jolly bodies is also be associated with several diseases: bone marrow transplantation (40%), celiac disease (33-76%), HIV infection/AIDS 36 (%), alcoholic liver disease (37-100%) and systemic lupus erythematosus (7.5%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The prevalence of hyposplenism is generally underestimated and the diagnosis often overlooked. This has potentially severe consequences in infectious diseases in general, and in malaria in particular. Detecting hyposplenism can thus be life-saving as it triggers the adoption of appropriate preventive measures against overwhelming infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>This observation highlights the importance of diagnosing hyposplenism in patients with malaria despite the morphological similarities between ring nuclei and Howell-Jolly bodies on thick smears.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Consent was granted by patient for the publication of this case report.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>PB is supported by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation and SANOFI. BH, AS and AG declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>BH and PB wrote the manuscript with contribution of AS. AG made the diagnosis. AG and AS were responsible for the patient&#x2019;s care and treatment and reviewed the manuscript. PB and BH made the microbiological diagnosis. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Prendki</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ndour</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jais</surname>
            <given-names>X</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ciceron</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Settegrana</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buffet</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Reduced deformability of circulating erythrocytes: a marker of hyposplenism</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hematol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>E81</fpage>
          <lpage>E82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajh.23297</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22847468</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Di Sabatino</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carsetti</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Corazza</surname>
            <given-names>GR</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Post-splenectomy and hyposplenic states</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>378</volume>
          <fpage>86</fpage>
          <lpage>97</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)61493-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21474172</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Rogers</surname>
            <given-names>ZR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>WC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iyer</surname>
            <given-names>RV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shalaby-Rana</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dertinger</surname>
            <given-names>SD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shulkin</surname>
            <given-names>BL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>JH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Files</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lane</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>BW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>ST</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ware</surname>
            <given-names>RE</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>BABY HUG: Biomarkers of splenic function in infants with sickle cell anemia: baseline data from the BABY HUG Trial</article-title>
          <source>Blood</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>2614</fpage>
          <lpage>2617</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2010-04-278747</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21217080</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bach</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baier</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pullwitt</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fosiko</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chagaluka</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kalima</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pfister</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Straube</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Molyneux</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Falciparum malaria after splenectomy: a prospective controlled study of 33 previously splenectomized Malawian adults</article-title>
          <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>861</fpage>
          <lpage>867</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trstmh.2005.03.008</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16099487</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Snounou</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Detection and identification of the four malaria parasite species infecting humans by PCR amplification</article-title>
          <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>263</fpage>
          <lpage>291</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8751365</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Schnitzer</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sodeman</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mead</surname>
            <given-names>ML</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Contacos</surname>
            <given-names>PG</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Pitting function of the spleen in malaria: ultrastructural observations</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>1972</year>
          <volume>177</volume>
          <fpage>175</fpage>
          <lpage>177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.177.4044.175</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4339353</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Robertson</surname>
            <given-names>DA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bullen</surname>
            <given-names>AW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hall</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Losowsky</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Blood film appearances in the hyposplenism of coeliac disease</article-title>
          <source>Br J Clin Pract</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6838752</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Buffet</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Safeukui</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Deplaine</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brousse</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Prendki</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thellier</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Turner</surname>
            <given-names>GD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mercereau-Puijalon</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The pathogenesis of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> malaria in humans: insights from splenic physiology</article-title>
          <source>Blood</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>381</fpage>
          <lpage>392</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2010-04-202911</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20852127</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Weatherall</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Genetic variation and susceptibility to infection: the red cell and malaria</article-title>
          <source>Br J Haematol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>141</volume>
          <fpage>276</fpage>
          <lpage>286</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2141.2008.07085.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18410566</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Davidson</surname>
            <given-names>RN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wall</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Prevention and management of infections in patients without a spleen</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>657</fpage>
          <lpage>660</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1198-743x.2001.00355.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11843905</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ozgen</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Akata</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arat</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ozdogan</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Akhan</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ozmen</surname>
            <given-names>MN</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Splenic calcifications in heterozygote sickle cell patients</article-title>
          <source>Abdom Imaging</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>188</fpage>
          <lpage>190</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002619900473</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10024409</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>TN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mwangi</surname>
            <given-names>TW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wambua</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peto</surname>
            <given-names>TE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Weatherall</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gupta</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Recker</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Penman</surname>
            <given-names>BS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Uyoga</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Macharia</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mwacharo</surname>
            <given-names>JK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Snow</surname>
            <given-names>RW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marsh</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Negative epistasis between the malaria-protective effects of alpha&#x2009;+&#x2009;&#x2212;thalassemia and the sickle cell trait</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>1253</fpage>
          <lpage>1257</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1660</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16227994</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Komba</surname>
            <given-names>AN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Makani</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sadarangani</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ajala-Agbo</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Berkley</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Newton</surname>
            <given-names>CR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marsh</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <given-names>TN</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Malaria as a cause of morbidity and mortality in children with homozygous sickle cell disease on the coast of Kenya</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>216</fpage>
          <lpage>222</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/599834</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19514855</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Pearson</surname>
            <given-names>HA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McIntosh</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ritchey</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lobel</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rooks</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Johnston</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Developmental aspects of splenic function in sickle cell diseases</article-title>
          <source>Blood</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>358</fpage>
          <lpage>365</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">760858</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Luzzatto</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Sickle cell anaemia and malaria</article-title>
          <source>Mediterr J Hematol Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>e2012065</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23170194</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Petersen</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hogh</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marbiah</surname>
            <given-names>NT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hanson</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The effect of splenectomy on immunity to <italic>Plasmodium malariae</italic> and <italic>P. falciparum</italic> in a malaria immune donor</article-title>
          <source>Trop Med Parasitol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>68</fpage>
          <lpage>69</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1598514</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tapper</surname>
            <given-names>ML</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Armstrong</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Malaria complicating neoplastic disease</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <fpage>807</fpage>
          <lpage>810</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.1976.03630070051016</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1065254</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Toma</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Malaria in splenectomized patients</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>936</fpage>
          <lpage>937</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8286651</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Groom</surname>
            <given-names>AC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schmidt</surname>
            <given-names>EE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>MacDonald</surname>
            <given-names>IC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Microcirculatory pathways and blood flow in spleen: new insights from washout kinetics, corrosion casts, and quantitative intravital videomicroscopy</article-title>
          <source>Scanning Microsc</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>173</lpage>
          <comment>discussion 173&#x2013;154</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2052921</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Grover</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wethers</surname>
            <given-names>DL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Spleen dysfunction in hemoglobinopathies determined by pitted red cells</article-title>
          <source>Am J Pediatr Hematol Oncol</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>340</fpage>
          <lpage>343</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00043426-198824000-00015</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3239712</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
