<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641541</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3057600</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">200110664</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Eosinophilic cellulitis (Wells' syndrome) successfully treated with low-dose cyclosporine.</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Herr</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>herr@knh.co.kr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Koh</surname>
            <given-names>J. K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department of Dermatology, Asan-Foundation Kangnung Hospital, Kangnung, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Kangnung, Korea.</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2001</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>664</fpage>
      <lpage>668</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eosinophilic cellulitis (Wells'syndrome) is an uncommon skin disorder. We report two adult male patients who had recurrent erythematous plaques and a nodular lesion on the abdomen. The histopathologic feature of their skin biopsies similarly indicated a marked infiltrate of eosinophils in the dermis with the fashion of "flame figures". One of the patients demonstrated blood eosinophilia. Given the clinicohistological findings, the patients fulfilled the criteria for the diagnosis of eosinophilic cellulitis. The skin lesions remained refractory to medications such as corticosteroids, sulfones, antihistamines, and minocycline. Considering the beneficial effect of cyclosporine in the treatment of eosinophilia-associated dermatoses, we speculated that eosinophilic cellulitis might respond to cyclosporine therapy. Thus, each of the two patients was given cyclosporine (microemulsion formulation) at a daily dose of 1.25 or 2.5 mg/kg, i.e., 100 or 200 mg, respectively. Complete remission of the skin eruptions was obtained in both patients during a 3- or 4-week period of treatment. No side effects were observed. Neither of the patients experienced relapse of the disease at least over 10 months after the discontinuation of the cyclosporine therapy. We suggest that administration of low-dose cyclosporine be a safe and useful therapeutic option in patients with eosinophilic cellulitis.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
