<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23739711</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3750894</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0365-05962013000200016</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Non Hodgkin T cell lymphoma: an atypical clinical
presentation<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01"><sup>*</sup></xref></article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Linfoma n&#xE3;o Hodgkin de c&#xE9;lulas T citot&#xF3;xico: uma apresenta&#xE7;&#xE3;o cl&#xED;nica
at&#xED;pica</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Maio</surname>
            <given-names>Paula</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bento</surname>
            <given-names>Diogo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vieira</surname>
            <given-names>Raquel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Afonso</surname>
            <given-names>Ana</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sachse</surname>
            <given-names>Fernanda</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kutzner</surname>
            <given-names>Heinz</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> MD &#x2013; Hospital Physician in Dermatology and Venereology at the Curry
Cabral Hospital &#x2013; Central Lisbon Hospital Center EPE (HCC- CHLN) &#x2013; Lisbon, Portugal</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> MD &#x2013; Hospital Attending Physician in Infectology at the Santa Maria
Hospital &#x2013; North Lisbon Hspital Center EPE (HSM- CHLN) &#x2013; Lisbon, Portugal</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> MD &#x2013; Graduate Hospital Assistant in Dermatology and Venereology at the
Curry Cabral Hospital &#x2013; Central Lisbon Hospital Center EPE (HCC- CHLN) &#x2013; Lisbon,
Portugal</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label> MD - Graduate Hospital Assistant in Dermatopathology at the Curry Cabral
Hospital &#x2013; Central Lisbon Hospital Center EPE (HCC- CHLN) &#x2013; Lisbon, Portugal</aff>
      <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label> MD - Graduate Hospital Assistant in Dermatology at the Portuguese
Oncology Institute (IPO) &#x2013; Lisbon, Portugal</aff>
      <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label> PhD &#x2013; Professor of Dermatopatholgy, Graz Medical University &#x2013; Graz,
Austria</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing address:</bold> Paula Maio - Rua da Benefic&#xEA;ncia, 8 - 1069-166, Lisbon,
- Portugal. - E-mail: <email>paulamaio@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Mar-Apr</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>264</fpage>
      <lpage>267</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cytotoxic lymphomas comprise a spectrum of peripheral T-cell lymphomas that can have
a initial or late cutaneous presentation. We describe a 46-year-old man from Cape
Verde, with a dermatosis involving his face and trunk, consisting of monomorphic
papules with a smooth surface and both motor and sensory polyneuropathy.The
hypothesis of leprosy was supported by the clinical and initial hystopathological
findings and the patient was referred to our hospital with suspected Hansen's
disease. In the new skin and lymph node biopsies a lymphocyte population was
identified whose immunohystochemistry study allowed the diagnosis of T-cell lymphoma
with expression of cytotoxic markers. The patient was started on chemotherapy with
initial remission of the skin lesions but, subsequently, progression of systemic
disease.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>Os linfomas citot&#xF3;xicos compreendem um espectro de linfomas de c&#xE9;lulas T perif&#xE9;ricos
e linfomas Natural Killer que podem ter express&#xE3;o cut&#xE2;nea prim&#xE1;ria ou secund&#xE1;ria.
Descrevemos o caso de um homem com 46 anos de idade, natural de Cabo Verde,com
dermatose envolvendo a face e tronco constitu&#xED;da por p&#xE1;pulas monomorfas superf&#xED;cie
lisa e polineuropatia sensitivo motora.A hip&#xF3;tese de Hansen&#xED;ase foi colocada
suportada por achados histopatol&#xF3;gicos sugestivos sendo o doente referenciado &#xE0;
consulta de Doen&#xE7;a de Hansen do nosso hospital. Em biopsia de pele e de g&#xE2;nglio
identificou-se prolifera&#xE7;&#xE3;o linfocit&#xE1;ria cujo estudo imunohistoqu&#xED;mico permitiu o
diagn&#xF3;stico de linfoma T com express&#xE3;o de marcadores citot&#xF3;xicos. Iniciou
quimioterapia verificando-se inicialmente remiss&#xE3;o parcial das les&#xF5;es cut&#xE2;neas mas
posteriormente a progress&#xE3;o da doen&#xE7;a sist&#xE9;mica.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Cytotoxicity, immunologic</kwd>
        <kwd>Leprosy</kwd>
        <kwd>Lymphoma, T-Cell, cutaneous</kwd>
        <kwd>Paraneoplastic polyneuropathy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Cytotoxic cutaneous lymphomas are a group of lymphoproliferative disorders characterized
by expression of cytotoxic proteins (TIA-1, granzyme A or B or perforin). <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup> The diagnosis of these conditions can sometimes be clinically and
histopathologically challenging. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>We describe a 46-year-old, black male patient, born in Cape Verde. He first noted,
months prior to presentation, a dermatosis that almost exclusively involved his face and
trunk consisting of multiple small monomorphic papules with an erythematous smooth
surface. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup> The patient reported dysesthesia at the distal ends of both feet and
paroxistical difficulty in mobilizing both feet. These symptoms suggested the existence
of a sensory motor polyneuropathy.A cutaneous biopsy was performed motivated by these
findings. The histopathological evaluation revealed perivascular and periadnexal
inflammatory infiltration of nerve bundles with lymphocytic permeation which, with
simultaneous findings of cutaneous involvement and sensory motor polyneuropathy, could
be consistent with the diagnosis of leprosy. The patient was therefore referred for a
consultation at the hospital regarding the possibility of Hansen's disease. The physical
examination revealed a dermatosis involving the face and the upper torso that consisted
of multiple infracentimetric monomorphic papules and plaques with a smooth erythematous
surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). There was no hypoesthesia in relation to skin lesions.
Examination of ganglionic chains revealed several adenopathies below the chin and in
axillary chains. The adenopathies that were found were over one centimeter in diameter,
with a hard consistency. Palpation of the abdomen revealed no masses or organomegaly. </p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clinical presentation. Multiple small monomorphic papules on the face</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0264-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clinical presentation (left sideof the face). Multiple small monomorphic papules
and plaques slightly infiltrateds</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0264-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The neurological examination did not reveal thickening or pain upon palpation of the
nerve roots. There was slight hypoesthesia at the distal end of both feet, with
diminished thermal, tactile and pain sensitivity. </p>
      <p>The patient also reported weight loss of 12 kg(&gt;10%) during the past year which had
never been taken into consideration. The patient denied any other constitutional
symptoms, including fever, anorexia and malaise. </p>
      <p>The supplementary study revealed: normocytic normochromic anemia(10.4 g/dL), white blood
cell count with lymphocytosis(3500) and thrombocytopenia (94000),VS 71mm in 1st hour,
&#x3B2;2-microglobulin(8.0 mg/dL) and LDH(689 U/L) and negative results for HIV, HTLV, EBV. </p>
      <p>PCR applied to a biopsy performed from the synovial tissue proved negative for
<italic>M. leprae</italic>. </p>
      <p>Body axial tomography showed severe ganglion involvement of the axillary and inguinal
lymph nodes and mild splenomegaly with multiple small parenchymal nodules. The skin
biopsy revealed diffuse lymphoid infiltration in the dermis composed of CD3, CD4
positive T-cells, some of which had CD8 positivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figures 3</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">5</xref>). The axillary lymph node biopsy identified a lymphocytic
proliferation composed of small cells with CD2, CD3 positive cells and CD7, CD8, CD20
negative cells, and TIA expression allowing the diagnosis of T-cell lymphoma with
cytotoxic expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Figure 6</xref>). The study of
T-cell receptors rearrangement by PCR confirmed the monoclonality of the cell population
based on the analysis of gamma genes.The absence of typical clinical lesions and the
typical histological markers of Hansen's disease, the successively negative nasal smears
and skin swabs, together with the PCR detection technique for <italic>M. leprae,
</italic>allowed for the exclusion of a Hansen's disease diagnosis. The evaluation by a
neurologist allowed a correlation between lymphoma and demyelinating neuropathy to be
characterized as a rare paraneoplastic syndrome. </p>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Hystopatology (H&amp;E). Dermal intense and difuse infiltration of lymph cells</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0264-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Immunochemistry study (CD3). Lymph cell infiltrate showing CD3 positivity</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0264-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Immunochemistry (CD4). Lymph cells infiltrate showing CD4 positivity</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0264-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Immunochemistry study (TiA). The immunochemistry study showing a difuse infiltrate
of lymph cells with cytotoxic expression (TiA+)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0264-g06"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient was started on chemotherapy with CHOP (cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin,
vincristine and prednisolone), which led to partial remission of the cutaneous lesions
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Figure 6</xref>) but with subsequent loss of
response. Second line therapeutic management with ESHAP (etoposide, methylprednisolone,
cytarabine and cisplatin ) was then initiated with no noticeable clinical response. The
patient was then started on a CMOPP chemotherapy regimen (cyclophosphamide,
mechlorethamine, vincristine, procarbazine and prednisolone), but at 12 months follow-up
there was invariable progression of the systemic disease, resulting in the patient&#xB4;s
death.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The heterogeneous cutaneous clinical presentation of T-cell lymphomas, together with the
frequent occurrence of nonspecific histological findings in cutaneous biopsies, creates
significant diagnostic difficulties. The cutaneous lymphoma classification is also a
challenge, in addition to the problem that until a few years ago there was no consensus
between the WHO and the EORTC (European Organization for Research and Treatment of
Cancer). <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> The new classification allows for more uniformity regarding both the diagnosis
and therapeutic approach to these lymphomas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>In the case of our patient, there was already systemic involvement at the date of
diagnosis, and in these circumstances this lymphoma could not be classified as primary
cutaneous T-cell lymphoma. These lymphomas are characterized by a transient partial
response to chemotherapy and by its association with a poor prognosis. The demyelinating
neuropathy has been otherwise described since lymphomas have been reported to
occasionally involve the peripheral nervous system. This damage is more often caused by
non-Hodgkin T-cell lymphomas, the cells of which can infiltrate the nerve sheath and
cause axonal damage, or by an autoimmune process where antineuronal antibodies are
directed against intracellular antigens. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Furthermore our patient's lymphoma exhibited cytotoxic behavior characterized by the
expression of molecules such as TIA, perforin and granzyme B. The expression of these
molecules is of great diagnostic use and helps the dermatologist to classify lymphoma;
however, the use of these markers lacks clinical and phenotypic specificity. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup> The surface markers expressed in malignant T-cells: CD2, CD3, CD4, CD25 and CD52
were the first therapeutic targets to be identified. However, the presence of these
receptors, even in normal T-cells, implies that therapy with monoclonal antibodies or
immunotoxins inevitably results in different degrees of immunosuppression. New classes
of therapeutic agents have emerged, particularly those that act by inhibiting histone
deacetylase(HDAC).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup> These molecules are intended to induce apoptosis in malignant T-cells. Immuno
modulators such as interferon and toll-like receptor agonists (TLR), also have a
particularly important role in the treatment of primary cutaneous lymphomas (CTCL).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup> While most classical cytotoxic drugs have limited effectiveness in the treatment
of lymphomas, agents that inhibit the metabolism of purine and pyrimidine (nucleoside
analogues) seem to have some additional efficacy in cases of T-cell lymphoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref></sup> Clinical trials currently underway will better define therapeutic strategies for
these lymphomas. </p>
      <p>We stress the importance of this case due to the uncommon clinical presentation, in
particular the simultaneous neurological and skin involvement that required a thorough
investigation of multiple differential diagnoses. This may ultimately result in a later
diagnosis of Non-Hodgkin's peripheral T-cytotoxic lymphoma.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <p>* Study conducted at the Curry Cabral Hospital - Central Lisbon Hospital Center EPE
(HCC- CHLN) - Lisbon, Portugal.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial Support: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of Interests: none</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Slater</surname>
              <given-names>DN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The new World Health Organization-European Organization for Research
and Treatment of Cancer classification for cutaneous lymphomas: a practical
marriage of two giants</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>153</volume>
          <fpage>874</fpage>
          <lpage>880</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16225594</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kanavaros</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boulland</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petit</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arnulf</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaulard</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Expression of cytotoxic proteins in peripheral T-cell and Natural
Killer cell Lymphomas: Association with extranodal site, NK or T gamma delta
phenotype, anaplastic morphology and cd30 expression</article-title>
          <source>Leuk Lymphoma</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>317</fpage>
          <lpage>326</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10830738</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Swerdlow</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>NL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaffe</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pileri</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stein</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <source>WHO Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid
Tissues</source>
          <edition>4th edition</edition>
          <publisher-loc>France</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>IARC</publisher-name>
          <year>2008</year>
          <size units="pages">439 p.</size>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paulli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berti</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cutaneous T-cell lymphomas (including rare subtypes). Current
concepts. II</article-title>
          <source>Haematologica</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>1372</fpage>
          <lpage>1388</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15531460</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kelly</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karcher</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lymphoma and peripheral neuropathy: a clinical review</article-title>
          <source>Muscle Nerve</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>301</fpage>
          <lpage>313</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15543550</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blaes</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tschernatsch</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paraneoplastic neurological disorders</article-title>
          <source>Expert Rev Neurother</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>1559</fpage>
          <lpage>1568</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20925471</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Massone</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chott</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Metze</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kerl</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Citarella</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vale</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Subcutaneous, blastic natural killer (NK), NK/T-cell, and other
cytotoxic lymphomas of the skin: a morphologic, immunophenotypic and molecular
study of 50 patients</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>719</fpage>
          <lpage>735</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15166664</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia-Herrera</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chuang</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villamor</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colomo</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pittaluga</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nonhepatosplenic &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T-cell lymphomas represent a spectrum of
aggressive cytotoxic T-cell lymphomas with a mainly extranodal
presentation</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>1214</fpage>
          <lpage>1225</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21753698</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Erter</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alinari</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Darabi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gurcan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garzon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marcucci</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>New targets of therapy in T-cell lymphomas</article-title>
          <source>Curr Drug Targets</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>482</fpage>
          <lpage>493</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20196721</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Piccaluga</surname>
              <given-names>PP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agostinelli</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tripodo</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gazzola</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bacci</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sabattini</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>European T cell Lymphoma Study Group.Peripheral T-cell lymphoma
classification: the matter of cellular derivation</article-title>
          <source>Expert Rev Hematol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>415</fpage>
          <lpage>425</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21801133</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
