<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJO</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22569389</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3361823</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJO-60-225</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0301-4738.95880</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Brief Communications</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Ivermectin treatment for massive orbital myiasis in an empty socket with concomitant scalp pediculosis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Puthran</surname>
            <given-names>Neelam</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hegde</surname>
            <given-names>Vidya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anupama</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Andrew</surname>
            <given-names>Sheena</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Ophthalmology, Yenepoya Medical College, Mangalore, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Dr Neelam Puthran, A-10/303, Florida Estate, Keshav Nagar, Mundhwa, Pune 411036, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="neelamputhran@rediffmail.com">neelamputhran@rediffmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>60</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>225</fpage>
      <lpage>227</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We report a rare case of massive orbital myiasis following recent lid injury, occurring in the empty socket of an elderly lady, who had concurrent scalp pediculosis. The orbital myiasis was effectively treated with the broad-spectrum antiparasitic agent, ivermectin, thus precluding the need for an exploratory surgery. Ivermectin was also effective in managing the concurrent scalp pediculosis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Ivermectin</kwd>
        <kwd>lid laceration</kwd>
        <kwd>orbital myiasis</kwd>
        <kwd>scalp pediculosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Orbital myiasis, or maggot infestation, is a rare condition with very few reports having been published worldwide.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>] Management of orbital myiasis may range from simple manual removal of the maggots to destructive surgeries of the globe and orbit.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>] With the advent of the broad-spectrum antiparasitic drug, ivermectin, there is now a safe and noninvasive means of tackling maggots, especially those buried deep in the orbital tissues.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>] Although introduced into veterinary medicine as an anthelmintic, ivermectin is also useful against ectoparasites like lice.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>]</p>
    <sec id="sec1-1">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 70-year-old female presented with complaints of painful swelling of the right side of the face and the presence of wormy creatures in the lids and orbit on the right side, of 4 days duration. Her sleep was disturbed due to their constant movement.</p>
      <p>She had undergone bilateral cataract surgeries elsewhere 2 years ago and the right eye had been removed 8 months ago. No documentary details were available. The patient reported that she had sustained accidental injury to the right upper lid, about 10 days earlier. She did not take any treatment for the same. Enquiry revealed that the patient was from a rural background and had close contact with goats.</p>
      <p>Examination revealed an elderly, unkempt lady with right-sided facial cellulitis. There were large, maggot infested ulcerations involving the medial parts of the right upper and lower lids as well as the ipsilateral lacrimal sac area. The right orbit was anophthalmic, foul smelling, and ridden with numerous maggots, some of which were present in multiple deep pockets of the lids and orbital tissue [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>]. Ophthalmic examination of the left side revealed no abnormality other than pseudophakia. The presence of severe scalp pediculosis was noticed and a dermatologist's consultation was taken. ENT examination was normal.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Right orbital myiasis</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-60-225-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Immediate treatment consisted of injection Tetanus Toxoid, oral diclofenac, and instillation of 0.3% gatifloxacin eye drops, four times a day in the right orbit. Laboratory investigations and X-ray orbits were normal. Manual removal of maggots was done several times a day, initially following turpentine wash, and later under topical anesthesia [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>]. However, several maggots continued to remain deeply buried in pockets in the lids and orbit. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) suggested a suspicion of early erosion of the medial orbital wall on the right side. The retro-orbital compartment including the optic canal was normal [Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>].</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Maggots removed manually</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-60-225-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Magnetic resonance imaging axial STIR signal showing inflammation of right lateral orbital wall</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-60-225-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Magnetic resonance imaging axial T2 of right orbit showing anophthalmia with marked inflammation of right medial orbital wall and lateral displacement of right medial rectus</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-60-225-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient was administered a single oral dose of 12 mg of ivermectin, following which she had a dramatic relief from pain. 1% ivermectin drops prepared by dissolving the tablet in distilled water was additionally instilled four times a day in the right orbit for a week. Dead maggots were easily removed and rapid wound healing ensued. The patient was discharged with a healthy socket [Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>] and a louse-free head. At final count, over a hundred maggots were removed, varying from 10 to 15 mm in size. The parent fly could not be identified.</p>
      <fig id="F5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Healing of lids after treatment with ivermectin</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-60-225-g005"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F6" position="float">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Well-healed lids with a healthy, maggot-free socket</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-60-225-g006"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-2">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Although maggot infestations are common in the tropics, only between 5 and 14% of all cases involve the ocular tissues,[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>] and most ophthalmologists have little experience with this condition. Maggots are the larvae of those dipteran flies which need a host for completion of their life cycle. The definitive hosts for maggots are goats and sheep. Man is an accidental host, and trauma is an important risk factor. Myiasis cases tend to occur in the spring and summer. Our patient presented in the monsoon season with a recent lid laceration and a history of close contact with goats.</p>
      <p>Orbital myiasis tends to endanger the globe and may extend into neighboring areas, such as the paranasal sinuses or the intracranial cavity.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] Our patient had an empty socket filled with maggots, which threatened to erode the medial orbital wall.</p>
      <p>The aim of treatment is to remove the maggots. We found that the maggots avoided bright light, but the presence of air bubbles helped in locating them. Maggots tend to resist removal by digging in their hook like structures. Forceful removals may result in incomplete extractions leading to granulomatous inflammation and calcification.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>] One may try to coax the maggots out by blocking their breathing holes with petroleum jelly, or the parasites may be killed by turpentine oil or hypertonic saline induced dehydration, prior to manual extraction.</p>
      <p>Orbital myiasis proceeding to globe invasion may entail removal of the globe, while erosion into surrounding structures may necessitate orbital exenteration. In 1995, a review of 429 cases of orbital exenterations revealed that as many as 9 had been done for deep orbital myiasis.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]</p>
      <p>In recent years, the broad-spectrum antiparasitic agent, ivermectin, has been successfully used as a noninvasive means to treat orbital myiasis.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>]</p>
      <p>Scalp pediculosis has been reported to predispose to scalp myiasis.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>] Although this patient had heavy scalp pediculosis, scalp myiasis did not occur, possibly because she habitually wore a head scarf. Pediculosis too is amenable to treatment with ivermectin.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>]</p>
      <p>In view of the massive, mixed parasitic infestation and the persistence of deeply buried maggots, and in order to avoid exploratory surgery, it was decided to treat the patient with ivermectin. Ivermectin is a semi-synthetic macrolide which was introduced as a safe anthelmintic in mammals. The oral dose of ivermectin is 200 &#x3BC;g/kg body weight. The drug may also be used topically as a 0.1% or 0.8% solution in birds and animals.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>] It has been used as a 1% solution in the treatment of scabies.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>] Ivermectin inhibits neurotransmission by causing hyperpolarization of the neurons and myocytes of invertebrates. Safety of ivermectin is very high in humans.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>] Common side effects on oral administration are dizziness, headaches and muscle pains. No adverse reactions were observed in our patient.</p>
      <p>Systemic antibiotics may not be required since secondary pyogenic infection is precluded by the antibacterial activity of the maggots themselves.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>] Emphasis on personal hygiene is an important preventive measure.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desai</surname>
              <given-names>RU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ehrlich</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fulminant orbital myiasis in the developed world</article-title>
          <source>Br J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>1565</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17947277</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thakur</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chauhan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sood</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vidi, vini, vinci: External ophthalmomyiasis infection that occurred, and was diagnosed and treated in a single day: A rare case report</article-title>
          <source>Oman J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>130</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20927210</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gunalp</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gunduz</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duruk</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Orbital exenteration: A review of 429 cases</article-title>
          <source>Int Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>177</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8926130</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Osorio</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moncada</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molano</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valderrama</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gualtero</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franco-Paredes</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Role of Ivermectin in the treatment of severe orbital myiasis due to Cochliomyia hominivorax</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <date-in-citation>Last cited 2006 Sep 15</date-in-citation>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>e57</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <comment>Available from:
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/507038">http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/507038</uri></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16912935</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment of Pediculushumanus var.capitis infestation in Cowlitz County, Washington, with ivermectin and the Lice Meister comb</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>923</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilhelmus</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myiasis palpebrum</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>496</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3963118</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human myiasis in North America (1952-1962 Inclusive)</article-title>
          <source>Fla Entamol</source>
          <year>1964</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuda</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagaji</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurose</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyasato</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sasai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoneda</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Furuncular cutaneous myiasis caused by Dermatobia hominis larvae following travel to Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Int J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8850042</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hemmings</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matthews</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alexander</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human myiasis in western Jamaica: five years after the implementation of a screwworm eradication programme</article-title>
          <source>West Indian Med J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>341</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18198739</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Knemidocoptiasis in birds: Laura Wade, DVM, DABVP (avian practice)</article-title>
          <date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2010 Jan 8</date-in-citation>
          <comment>Available from
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://veterinarymedicine.dvm360.com/vetmed/article">http://veterinarymedicine.dvm360.com/vetmed/article</uri></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Victoria</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trujillo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topical ivermectin: a new successful treatment for scabies</article-title>
          <source>Pediatric Dermatol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>63</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guzzo</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Furtek</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Porras</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tipping</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clineschmidt</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of escalating high doses of ivermectin in healthy adult subjects</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>1122</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12362927</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrews</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hay</surname>
              <given-names>NP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bourgoise</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The anti-microbial activity of maggot secretions: results of a preliminary study</article-title>
          <source>J Tissue Viability</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>127</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10808842</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
