<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ups J Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ups. J. Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">UPS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Upsala Journal of Medical Sciences</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0300-9734</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2000-1967</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Informa Healthcare</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23697667</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3713385</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/03009734.2013.801541</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">UPS_A_801541_O</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Neoplastic pericarditis as the initial manifestation of a papillary thyroid carcinoma</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="a1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsoukalas</surname>
            <given-names>Nikolaos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="a2" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kostakis</surname>
            <given-names>Ioannis D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="a3" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Demiri</surname>
            <given-names>Stamatina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="a4" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Koumakis</surname>
            <given-names>Georgios</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="a5" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Barbounis</surname>
            <given-names>Vasileios</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="a6" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Barbati</surname>
            <given-names>Kalypso</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="a7" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Efremidis</surname>
            <given-names>Anna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AF0001"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, &#x2018;401' General Military Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Athens</addr-line>, <country>Greece</country></aff>
        <aff id="AF0002"><sup>2</sup><institution>
Second Department of Propedeutic Surgery, &#x2018;Laiko' General Hospital, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Athens</addr-line>, <country>Greece</country></aff>
        <aff id="AF0003"><sup>3</sup><institution>Second Department of Medical Oncology, &#x2018;Agios Savvas' Anticancer Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Athens</addr-line>, <country>Greece</country></aff>
        <aff id="AF0004"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Pathology, Hellenic Red Cross Hospital &#x2018;Korgialeneio-Benakeio'</institution>, <addr-line>Athens</addr-line>, <country>Greece</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">Correspondence: Nikolaos Tsoukalas, MD, MSc, Medical Oncologist, <institution>Department of Medical Oncology, &#x2018;401' General Military Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>10-12 Gennimata N. Street, 11524 Ampelokipi, Athens</addr-line>, <country>Greece</country>. <fax>+30 2107494095</fax>. <email xlink:href="tsoukn@yahoo.gr">tsoukn@yahoo.gr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>03</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>118</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>196</fpage>
      <lpage>198</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Informa Healthcare</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the source is credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neoplastic pericarditis represents approximately 5%&#x2013;7% of the cases with acute pericarditis and is rarely the initial manifestation of malignancy. The most common cause is lung cancer, followed by breast cancer, lymphomas, leukemia, and esophageal cancer. Neoplastic pericardial disease is extremely rare in thyroid cancer, especially as the first manifestation. Here, we present a papillary thyroid carcinoma that was manifested with pericarditis and cardiac tamponade in a 49-year-old female.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <kwd>Cardiac tamponade</kwd>
        <kwd>neoplastic pericarditis</kwd>
        <kwd>pericardial effusion</kwd>
        <kwd>thyroid cancer</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="ss1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Neoplastic pericarditis represents approximately 5%&#x2013;7% of the cases with acute pericarditis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0002 CIT0003 CIT0004">1-4</xref>). Theoretically, any malignant tumor may cause pericarditis/pericardial effusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0002">1,2</xref>) through direct extension or metastasis via lymphatic or blood vessels into the pericardium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003 CIT0005">3,5</xref>). However, the most common malignancy causing pericarditis/pericardial effusion is lung cancer, followed by breast cancer, lymphomas, leukemia, and esophageal cancer. Primary neoplasms of the pericardium, such as mesothelioma, are very rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0002 CIT0003 CIT0005">1-3,5</xref>). Only few cases of neoplastic pericarditis in patients with thyroid cancer have been reported in the literature. Here, we present a case of papillary thyroid carcinoma that was manifested with pericarditis and cardiac tamponade.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="ss2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 49-year-old female, who was a heavy smoker, but with negligible previous medical history, was admitted to a hospital due to stridor, dyspnea, cough, and hoarseness. Physical examination revealed no pathological signs, blood tests were normal, and the patient was treated with corticosteroids without a definite diagnosis. Ten days later, she developed epigastric pain that radiated to the left scapula and the left supraclavicular fossa. She was admitted to a hospital, where an echocardiogram and a chest CT scan revealed the presence of pericardial effusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). During her hospitalization, she developed cardiac tamponade, for which she urgently underwent pericardiocentesis. Blind biopsies were taken from the pericardium and the upper lobe of the left lung, which showed malignant cells forming papillae and invading lymphatic and blood vessels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). However, it was not possible to identify the primary origin of the neoplasm, despite the thorough investigation with abdominal CT scan and technetium-99m-MDP bone scan. In addition, blood tests were normal, apart from the values of CEA (20.6 ng/mL (normal value: &lt;4.7 ng/mL)) and CA-125 (341.4 IU/mL (normal value: &lt;34 IU/mL)). The patient received one cycle of chemotherapy with carboplatin 5AUC, docetaxel 60 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, and bevacizumab 5 mg/kg for a neoplasm of unknown primary origin, which improved her symptoms.</p>
      <fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Chest CT scan in which the pericardial effusion is revealed.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="UPS-118-196-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histological images with malignant cells from the papillary thyroid carcinoma. A: Biopsy of the pericardium (hematoxylin and eosin stain, 100&#xD7;); B: Histological examination of the thyroid gland (hematoxylin and eosin stain, 200&#xD7;).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="UPS-118-196-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Afterwards, she was admitted to our department for further investigation and treatment. The physical examination revealed a palpable nodule of the right lobe of the thyroid gland, and the ultrasound demonstrated diffuse heterogeneity of the same lobe. Nevertheless, the ultrasound failed to reveal any specific suspicious area, and the serum concentration of thyroglobulin was normal (17.7 ng/mL (normal value: &lt;78 ng/mL)). The cytological examination after a blind fine-needle aspiration biopsy of the right lobe of the thyroid gland revealed the presence of a papillary thyroid carcinoma. Subsequently, a cervical MRI was performed, demonstrating extensive lymphadenopathy. The patient underwent total thyroidectomy and bilateral lymph node dissection. The histological examination verified the presence of a stage IVC (T3N1bM1) papillary carcinoma with high-grade (grade III) malignancy and sporadic anaplastic changes, lymphovascular and perineural invasion, and metastatic infiltration of the cervical lymph nodes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>). A reexamination of the pericardial fluid from the pericardiocentesis revealed the expression of thyroglobulin by the malignant cells. An I<sup>131</sup> scan was also performed, but without demonstrating abnormal I<sup>131</sup> uptake. The patient's treatment was continued with the use of the same chemotherapy regimen for a total of six cycles without any major adverse events and with excellent tolerance.</p>
      <p>After the completion of chemotherapy, a FDG-PET scan was performed with negative results. Afterwards, the follow-up was based on physical examination, blood tests, and imaging examinations. Unfortunately, the disease relapsed six months later with a very aggressive clinical course due to lung metastases and cardiac tamponade. It was not possible to administer any anticancer treatment at that time, and she passed away due to respiratory and cardiac failure.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="ss3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>As mentioned previously, approximately 5%&#x2013;7% of pericardial effusions have a malignant origin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0002 CIT0003 CIT0004">1-4</xref>). Most patients with neoplastic pericardial disease have an already diagnosed malignancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>). Acute pericarditis or pericardial effusion is the initial manifestation of malignancy in about 4% of the cases with pericardial disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0003">1,3</xref>), but this percentage rises to approximately 20% in large, symptomatic effusions without obvious origin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0005">1,5</xref>), as in our case. Risk factors for malignant etiology are cardiac tamponade at presentation, as in our case, recurrent or incessant pericarditis, no response to non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, and a history of malignancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0002 CIT0003">1-3</xref>). Cytological examination of pericardial fluid or pericardial biopsy is required for a diagnosis to be made (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0002 CIT0003 CIT0005">1-3,5</xref>). However, pericardial effusion is detected in only 12%&#x2013;25% of patients with metastasis to the pericardium, but cardiac tamponade, which developed in our patient, is relatively rare among them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0005">5</xref>).</p>
      <p>Neoplastic pericardial disease is extremely rare in thyroid cancer, especially as the initial manifestation. Several cases have been reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0006 CIT0007 CIT0008 CIT0009 CIT0010 CIT0011 CIT0012 CIT0013 CIT0014 CIT0015 CIT0016">6-16</xref>). Neoplastic pericarditis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0006 CIT0009">6,9</xref>), massive pericardial effusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0013">13</xref>), or cardiac tamponade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007 CIT0008 CIT0010 CIT0012 CIT0016">7,8,10,12,16</xref>) have been reported as the first manifestation of a previously occult thyroid cancer. On the other hand, malignant pericardial effusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0014 CIT0015">14,15</xref>) or cardiac tamponade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0011">11</xref>) have also been diagnosed in patients with already diagnosed thyroid cancer. Most cases have pertained to papillary carcinoma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0007 CIT0009 CIT0010 CIT0011 CIT0014 CIT0015 CIT0016">7,9-11,14-16</xref>), as in our patient, whereas a follicular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0013">13</xref>) and a mucin-producing carcinoma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0008">8</xref>) have also been described as causes of neoplastic pericardial disease.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="ss4">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Neoplastic pericardial disease is most commonly caused by lung cancer, followed by breast cancer, lymphomas, leukemia, and esophageal cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0002 CIT0003 CIT0005">1-3,5</xref>), and is rarely the first manifestation of malignancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001 CIT0003">1,3</xref>). However, thyroid cancer, and especially papillary carcinoma, should be included in the differential diagnosis of pericarditis/pericardial effusion.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>
<bold><italic>Declaration of interest:</italic></bold> The authors report no conflicts of interest. The authors alone are responsible for the content and writing of the paper.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Imazio</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brucato</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Derosa</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lestuzzi</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bombana</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scipione</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19262208?doptAbstract">Aetiological diagnosis in acute and recurrent pericarditis: when and how</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Med (Hagerstown)</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19262208</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Imazio</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spodick</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brucato</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trinchero</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Markel</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adler</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20487049?doptAbstract">Diagnostic issues in the clinical management of pericarditis</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Int J Clin Pract</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>1384</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20487049</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Imazio</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brucato</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayosi</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Derosa</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lestuzzi</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macor</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20925146?doptAbstract">Medical therapy of pericardial diseases: part II: Noninfectious pericarditis, pericardial effusion and constrictivepericarditis</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Med (Hagerstown)</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>785</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20925146</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Azam</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoit</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20406240?doptAbstract">Treatment of pericardial disease</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Ther</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>308</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20406240</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Refaat</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>WE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21928406?doptAbstract">Neoplastic pericardial effusion</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Clin Cardiol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>593</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21928406</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nissimov</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machtey</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salomon</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4704618?doptAbstract">Thyroid carcinoma with pericardial involvement simulating rheumatic heart disease</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Harefuah</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4704618</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haskell</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>French</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/4006558?doptAbstract">Cardiac tamponade as the initial presentation of malignancy</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Chest</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>70</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4006558</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Motoba</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujita</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miura</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakurai</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishikawa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawai</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/3001207?doptAbstract">A case of mucin-producing adenocarcinoma of the thyroid presented with cardiac tamponade as an initial manifestation</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Nihon Naika Gakkai Zasshi</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>1283</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3001207</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Janci&#x107;-Zguricas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jankovi&#x107;</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/3562345?doptAbstract">Occult papillary carcinoma of the thyroid gland revealed by cancer pericarditis</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Pathol Res Pract</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>181</volume>
          <fpage>761</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3562345</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kovacs</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mullen</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crockford</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8143231?doptAbstract">Cardiac tamponade as the initial presentation of papillary thyroid carcinoma</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Can J Cardiol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>279</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8143231</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Puigfel</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falces</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castell&#xE1;</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roig</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8758680?doptAbstract">[Metastatic cardiac tamponade in a patient with papillary carcinoma of the thyroid]</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Med Clin (Barc)</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <fpage>197</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8758680</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de la G&#xE1;ndara</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Espinosa</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xF3;mez Cerezo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feliu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia Gir&#xF3;n</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9247105?doptAbstract">Pericardial tamponade as the first manifestation of adenocarcinoma</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Acta Oncol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>429</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9247105</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chiewvit</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pusuwan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiewvit</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pleehachinda</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Attanatho</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mongkharuk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9803073?doptAbstract">Metastatic follicular carcinoma of thyroid to pericardium</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>J Med Assoc Thai</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>799</fpage>
          <lpage>802</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9803073</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fukuda</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saito</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imai</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishii</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miwa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11110437?doptAbstract">Metastatic cardiac papillary originating from the thyroid in both ventricles with a mobile right ventricular pedunculated tumor</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Jpn Circ J</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>890</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11110437</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ignjatovi&#x107;</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stani&#x107;</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11332365?doptAbstract">[Multiple intrathoracic compression syndrome of thyroid etiology]</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Vojnosanit Pregl</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>709</fpage>
          <lpage>16</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11332365</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez Valverde</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xF3;mez Ramos</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molt&#xF3; Aguado</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balsalobre</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menarguez</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mauri</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15698739?doptAbstract">Pericardial tamponade as initial presentation of papillary thyroid carcinoma</ext-link>
</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15698739</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
