<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosntds</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1935-2727</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1935-2735</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22039555</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3201911</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PNTD-D-11-00097</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001290</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Symposium</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Spontaneous Clearance of <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> in a Case of Buruli Ulcer</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gordon</surname>
            <given-names>Claire L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Buntine</surname>
            <given-names>John A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hayman</surname>
            <given-names>John A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lavender</surname>
            <given-names>Caroline J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fyfe</surname>
            <given-names>Janet A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hosking</surname>
            <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
            <given-names>Paul D. R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Infectious Diseases, Austin Health, Melbourne, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Surgery, Box Hill Hospital, Melbourne, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Surgery, Monash University, Melbourne, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <label>4</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Anatomy and Developmental Biology, Monash University, Melbourne, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff5">
        <label>5</label>
        <addr-line>WHO Collaborating Centre for Mycobacterium ulcerans (Western Pacific Region) and Victorian Infectious Diseases Reference Laboratory, Melbourne, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff6">
        <label>6</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Pathology, Box Hill Hospital, Melbourne, Australia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Small</surname>
            <given-names>Pamela L. C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">University of Tennessee, United States of America</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>Paul.Johnson@austin.org.au</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <elocation-id>e1290</elocation-id>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Gordon et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="3"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Buruli ulcer (BU) is an infection of skin and soft tissue caused by <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic>, a toxin-producing environmental mycobacterium. Significant advances in the treatment of BU have been made over the past decade with the introduction of effective antibiotic therapy and there is a greater understanding of the pathogenesis and host immune response. Although it is generally held that early BU lesions may heal spontaneously, to our knowledge, there are no previously published cases that definitively document spontaneous resolution of culture-confirmed BU.</p>
    <sec sec-type="" id="s2">
      <title>Presentation of Case</title>
      <p>The patient was a 72-year-old man from Melbourne, Australia, who had visited his holiday house in Point Lonsdale, an endemic area of BU on the coast 70 km to the southwest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Johnson1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Johnson2">[2]</xref>, most weekends for the past 28 years. He had a past medical history of coronary artery disease but was otherwise fit and active. In October 2008 he noted a 5-week history of a slowly progressive painless papule with a punctate centre on his left ankle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001290-g001">Figure 1</xref>). His most recent visit to Point Lonsdale was 2 weeks before the lesion appeared.</p>
      <fig id="pntd-0001290-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001290.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Clinical appearance and laboratory characteristics.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0001290.g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The diagnosis of BU was made unconventionally. The patient's 12-year-old grandson was attending a clinic with his mother for treatment of IS<italic>2404</italic> PCR-confirmed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Fyfe1">[3]</xref> BU on his lower back as reported elsewhere <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Gordon1">[4]</xref>. During the consultation she mentioned that her father also had a progressive lesion on his ankle. She was given a dry specimen swab to take home with instructions on how to sample her father's ankle lesion. Material from the ankle swab tested positive for acid-fast bacilli (AFB) by Ziehl-Neelsen (Z-N) staining and <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> infection was confirmed by PCR and later by culture. A repeat swab taken by the treating clinician (PDRJ) 2 weeks later was again positive for AFB, and PCR again confirmed <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> infection. Culture from this second specimen was ultimately negative, although the culture result was not available at the time management decisions had to be taken. Antibiotics were considered but not prescribed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Johnson3">[5]</xref>, as there was a potential interaction between the patient's cardiac medications and rifampicin. Instead, excision with primary closure was performed without the use of antibiotics or other treatment modalities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001290-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Sections of the excised tissue showed a 3-mm area of skin ulceration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001290-g002">Figure 2</xref>, left panel) with mixed inflammatory cell infiltration and granulation tissue extending into subcutaneous fat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0001290-g002">Figure 2</xref>, right panel). AFB were not detected, but the appearances were considered consistent with <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> infection in a healing or resolving phase of the infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Johnson4">[6]</xref>. The excised tissue specimen was divided into five sub-sections and all portions screened by both PCR and culture according to standard operating procedures. Generally, this means that the entire sub-section of tissue is cut into smaller pieces and homogenised in a bottle containing glass beads and 2 ml of phosphate buffered saline. If the sub-section is too large to fit into the bead bottle, smaller pieces of tissue are taken from throughout the specimen to maximise the likelihood of sampling organisms. One ml of tissue homogenate is then processed for PCR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Fyfe1">[3]</xref> and 1 ml used for culture in BACTEC 12B bottles and on Brown and Buckle medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Mac1">[7]</xref> incubated at 31&#xB0;C for up to 12 weeks. <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> was no longer detected by either method. The patient gave informed consent for publication.</p>
      <fig id="pntd-0001290-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001290.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Histopathology of excised lesion.</title>
          <p>Left panel: Section of excised skin ulcer, showing one ulcer margin with fibrinous exudate in the base of the ulcer. Granulation tissue with a mixed inflammatory cell infiltrate extends into subcutaneous fat (H&amp;E, orig mag &#xD7;40). Right panel: Section from the base of the ulcer, showing granulation tissue with a mixed inflammatory cell infiltrate. Acid-fast bacilli were not seen in a Z-N stained section of the same area (H&amp;E, orig mag &#xD7;200).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0001290.g002"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="" id="s3">
      <title>Case Discussion</title>
      <p>Buruli ulcer has an alarming potential for progressive tissue destruction and has the potential to leave patients permanently disabled due to widespread necrosis of subcutaneous fat, extensive fibrous scar tissue formation, and contractures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Johnson4">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-WansbroughJones1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-vanderWerf1">[9]</xref>. However, even when no effective therapy is available, progression may cease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Hayman1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Sizaire1">[11]</xref>. The human immune system is therefore able to contain <italic>M. ulcerans</italic>, albeit after some years and considerable tissue destruction. The details of how this final victory is won are of great importance to researchers working on BU vaccines.</p>
      <p>Our patient first noted a lesion 5 weeks before the first diagnostic specimen was obtained. AFB were seen, IS<italic>2404</italic> PCR was positive, and <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> was isolated by culture. The diagnosis was reconfirmed with a second swab. The lesion was excised a month later but no AFB were detectable by then, and both PCR and culture were negative. Of note, the patient's grandson who visited his grandfather's house at Point Lonsdale contemporaneously developed a large progressive BU over his lower back <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Gordon1">[4]</xref>.</p>
      <p><italic>M. ulcerans</italic>, like <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> and <italic>M. leprae</italic>, does not cause clinical disease in all exposed individuals. Gooding et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Gooding1">[12]</xref> showed that the prevalence of antibodies to <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> in exposed household controls in Queensland was similar to that in patients with proven BU using a whole cell antigen preparation. Similar findings with more specific antigens have confirmed this observation in West Africa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Diaz1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Pidot1">[14]</xref>. However, antibodies to <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> are not <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> specific and are encountered in persons from endemic and non-endemic regions, which makes it difficult to evaluate evidence for spontaneous remission based on the presence of antibodies. As with most infectious diseases, variation in host immune response genes is likely to influence susceptibility. In a study performed in Ghana, the SLC11A1 (NRAMP1) D543N polymorphism, which confers susceptibility to tuberculosis and leprosy, has been linked to increased susceptibility to BU, with an estimated 13% population attributable risk <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Stienstra1">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p>However, it also likely that inoculum size influences outcome. For example, our patient may have received a lower initial inoculum than his grandson, although the natural inoculum size has not been definitively established. Fenner noted that the protective effect of BCG against <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> in a mouse model could be overcome by increasing the inoculum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Fenner1">[16]</xref>. Unlike the grandson, it is also possible that our patient had a prior exposure to <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> that may have immunised him and enhanced his ability to control his infection, as he reported very frequent visits to Point Lonsdale where transmission of <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> has been common since at least 2002 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Johnson1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Johnson2">[2]</xref>.</p>
      <p>This report of spontaneous clearance of <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> from a small but clinically apparent BU confirms previous anecdotal and some systematic field observations in patients likely to have BU, but from whom definitive laboratory confirmation was not available <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Thangaraj1">[17]</xref>. For example, Revill et al. reported that 29% of patients with small nodular lesions diagnosed clinically healed spontaneously while receiving placebo during a randomised study of clofazamine therapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Revill1">[18]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The key virulence factor of <italic>M. ulcerans</italic>, mycolactone, has potent cytotoxic and immunosuppressive properties that act both locally and systemically. Initially, the histology of BU lesions shows bland necrosis with a remarkable absence of an acute inflammatory response (reviewed in Sch&#xFC;tte et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Schutte1">[19]</xref>). However, natural halting of progressive infection, or treatment with antibiotics, appears to be associated with the development of a vigorous Th-1 response, the development of delayed type hypersensitivity to mycobacterial antigens, and intense granulomatous inflammation on histology (reviewed by Demangel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Demangel1">[20]</xref> and Sch&#xFC;tte et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Schutte1">[19]</xref>). At present, no satisfactory model exists to explain how the human host is able to sterilize active <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> infections that are likely to be producing increasing local concentrations of mycolactone, particularly as mycolactone itself does not appear to stimulate the production of neutralising antibodies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pntd.0001290-Schutte1">[19]</xref>. The mechanism by which this occurs will be of great interest, as a vaccine able to induce this sterilizing response should be highly effective for both primary prevention and as an adjuvant to therapy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="" id="s4">
      <title/>
      <boxed-text id="pntd-0001290-box001" position="float">
        <sec id="s4a">
          <title>Key Learning Points</title>
          <list list-type="bullet">
            <list-item>
              <p>Some people with confirmed Buruli ulcer are able to spontaneously eradicate <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> before they develop destructive lesions.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>This suggests a major role for adaptive immunity in protection against <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> infection.</p>
            </list-item>
            <list-item>
              <p>When new treatments for <italic>M. ulcerans</italic> are evaluated the possibility of spontaneous resolution needs to be considered.</p>
            </list-item>
          </list>
        </sec>
      </boxed-text>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>There were no sources of funding for this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Johnson1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Azuolas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavender</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinear</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title><italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> in mosquitoes captured during outbreak of Buruli ulcer, southeastern Australia.</article-title>             <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>1653</fpage>             <lpage>1660</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18217547</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Johnson2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Quek</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Consensus recommendations for the diagnosis, treatment and control of <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> infection (Bairnsdale or Buruli ulcer) in Victoria, Australia.</article-title>             <source>Med J Aust</source>             <volume>186</volume>             <fpage>64</fpage>             <lpage>68</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17223765</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Fyfe1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavender</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Globan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2007</year>             <article-title>Development and application of two multiplex real-time PCR assays for the detection of <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> in clinical and environmental samples.</article-title>             <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>             <volume>73</volume>             <fpage>4733</fpage>             <lpage>4740</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17526786</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Gordon1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Buntine</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavender</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>All-oral antibiotic treatment for buruli ulcer: a report of four patients.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e770</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000770">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000770</ext-link></comment>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21152060</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Johnson3">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Should antibiotics be given for Buruli ulcer?</article-title>             <source>Lancet</source>             <volume>375</volume>             <fpage>618</fpage>             <lpage>619</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20137806</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Johnson4">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinear</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pluschke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Buruli ulcer (M. ulcerans infection): new insights, new hope for disease control.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Med</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>e108</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0020108">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020108</ext-link></comment>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15839744</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Mac1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mac</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolhurst</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>1948</year>             <article-title>A new mycobacterial infection in man.</article-title>             <source>J Pathol Bacteriol</source>             <volume>60</volume>             <fpage>93</fpage>             <lpage>122</lpage>          </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-WansbroughJones1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wansbrough-Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title>Buruli ulcer.</article-title>             <source>BMJ</source>             <volume>330</volume>             <fpage>1402</fpage>             <lpage>1403</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15961795</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-vanderWerf1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Werf</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stienstra</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Adjei</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2005</year>             <article-title><italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> disease.</article-title>             <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>             <volume>83</volume>             <fpage>785</fpage>             <lpage>791</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16283056</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Hayman1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1993</year>             <article-title>Out of Africa: observations on the histopathology of <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> infection.</article-title>             <source>J Clin Pathol</source>             <volume>46</volume>             <fpage>5</fpage>             <lpage>9</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8432888</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Sizaire1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sizaire</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nackers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Comte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Portaels</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title><italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> infection: control, diagnosis, and treatment.</article-title>             <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>             <volume>6</volume>             <fpage>288</fpage>             <lpage>296</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16631549</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Gooding1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Robins-Browne</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2002</year>             <article-title>Cytokine profiles of patients infected with <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> and unaffected household contacts.</article-title>             <source>Infect Immun</source>             <volume>70</volume>             <fpage>5562</fpage>             <lpage>5567</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228283</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Diaz1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobeli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeboah-Manu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensah-Quainoo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedlein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Use of the immunodominant 18-kiloDalton small heat shock protein as a serological marker for exposure to <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Clin Vaccine Immunol</source>             <volume>13</volume>             <fpage>1314</fpage>             <lpage>1321</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17021247</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Pidot1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pidot</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsollier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Migot-Nabias</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2010</year>             <article-title>Serological evaluation of <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> antigens identified by comparative genomics.</article-title>             <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>             <volume>4</volume>             <fpage>e872</fpage>             <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0000872">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000872</ext-link></comment>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21072233</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Stienstra1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stienstra</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Werf</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Oosterom</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Graaf</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>             <year>2006</year>             <article-title>Susceptibility to Buruli ulcer is associated with the SLC11A1 (NRAMP1) D543N polymorphism.</article-title>             <source>Genes Immun</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>185</fpage>             <lpage>189</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16395392</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Fenner1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1957</year>             <article-title>Homologous and heterologous immunity in infections of mice with <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> and <italic>Mycobacterium balnei</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Am Rev Tuberc</source>             <volume>76</volume>             <fpage>76</fpage>             <lpage>89</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13444620</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Thangaraj1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thangaraj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wansbrough-Jones</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2003</year>             <article-title>Emerging aspects of Buruli ulcer.</article-title>             <source>Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther</source>             <volume>1</volume>             <fpage>217</fpage>             <lpage>222</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15482116</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Revill1">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Revill</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ateng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>1973</year>             <article-title>A controlled trial of the treatment of <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> infection with clofazimine.</article-title>             <source>Lancet</source>             <volume>2</volume>             <fpage>873</fpage>             <lpage>877</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4126917</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Schutte1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schutte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pluschke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Immunosuppression and treatment-associated inflammatory response in patients with <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> infection (Buruli ulcer).</article-title>             <source>Expert Opin Biol Ther</source>             <volume>9</volume>             <fpage>187</fpage>             <lpage>200</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19236249</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pntd.0001290-Demangel1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">             <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demangel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinear</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group>             <year>2009</year>             <article-title>Buruli ulcer: reductive evolution enhances pathogenicity of <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic>.</article-title>             <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>             <volume>7</volume>             <fpage>50</fpage>             <lpage>60</lpage>          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19079352</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
