<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Auton Res</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinical Autonomic Research</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0959-9851</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1619-1560</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21796353</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3210944</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">133</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10286-011-0133-7</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Prolonged post-faint hypotension can be reversed by dynamic tension</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wieling</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>w.wieling@amc.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rozenberg</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schon</surname>
            <given-names>I. K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Karemaker</surname>
            <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Westerhof</surname>
            <given-names>B. E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jardine</surname>
            <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Medicine, Academic Medical Centre, University of Amsterdam, Meibergdreef 9, 1105 AZ Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Anatomy, Embryology and Physiology, Heart Failure Research Center, Academic Medical Centre, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>BMEYE B.V., Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Laboratory for Clinical Cardiovascular Physiology, AMC Centre for Heart Failure Research, Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of General Medicine, Christchurch Hospital, Christchurch, New Zealand </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>21</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>415</fpage>
      <lpage>418</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2011</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>A severe variant of vasovagal syncope, observed during tilt tests and blood donation has recently been termed &#x201C;prolonged post-faint hypotension&#x201D; (PPFH). A 49-year-old male with a life-long history of severe fainting attacks underwent head-up tilt for 20&#xA0;min, and developed syncope 2&#xA0;min after nitroglycerine spray. He was unconscious for 40&#xA0;s and asystolic for 22&#xA0;s. For the first 2&#xA0;min of recovery, BP and HR remained low (65/45&#xA0;mmHg and 40 beats/min) despite passive leg-raising. Blood pressure (and symptoms) only improved following active bilateral leg flexion and extension (&#x201C;dynamic tension&#x201D;). During PPFH, when vagal activity is extreme, patients may require central stimulation as well as correction of venous return.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2011</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>In this edition of Clinical Autonomic Research we describe the hemodynamic data of seven patients with a prolonged recovery after a vasovagal faint [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. All patients were bradycardic, very hypotensive and highly symptomatic, complaining of weakness, malaise and nausea. This severe variant of vasovagal syncope was already described in 1919 by Cotton and Lewis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] and has been reported since by several authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. It is also known to occur in the setting of blood donation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. We propose to coin the term &#x201C;prolonged post-faint hypotension&#x201D; (PPFH) for this condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. We postulate that in PPFH, sustained high vagal outflow results in pronounced bradycardia and decreased cardiac contractility resulting in loss of cardiac output and systemic blood pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p>
      <p>In the seven patients we studied 30&#xB0; head-down tilting, a manoeuver that increases venous return, did not significantly increase blood pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In the present case history we demonstrate that dynamic leg flexion and extension (dynamic tension) can be applied as an intervention to reverse PPFH.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Case history</title>
      <p>A 49-year-old male patient was referred to our syncope unit with a medical history suggestive of intermittent convulsive vasovagal syncope. The episodes were induced by pain and had persisted since childhood. He used no medications and had no history of cardiovascular or neurological disease.</p>
      <p>A diagnostic tilt table test was performed using a Nexfin device [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Stroke volume was computed by pulse wave analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>The upper arm blood pressure, measured via sphygmomanometer with the patient lying supine prior to tilt was 136/82&#xA0;mm Hg and the heart rate 65&#xA0;beats/min. Haemodynamic adjustments were normal during the first 20&#xA0;min of unmedicated head-up tilt. About 2&#xA0;min after nitroglycerine administration, severe vasovagal syncope occurred, associated with an asystolic period of 22&#xA0;s. The patient was rapidly tilted back to the horizontal position. Myoclonic jerks and snoring were observed during the ensuing period of unconsciousness which lasted about 40&#xA0;s. After this a stable blood pressure signal was obtained (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Initial BP was 65/45&#xA0;mm Hg and HR 40&#xA0;beats/min. The patient was severely symptomatic, complaining of general malaise, weakness and nausea. Leg-raising for 90&#xA0;s achieved minimal increase in BP and HR and the symptoms remained; however, CO increased from 4.0 to 5.1&#xA0;L/min during this time (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). After lowering the legs BP returned to very low values. The patient then undertook bilateral leg flexion and extension exercises (dynamic tension) over a 70-s period. This manoeuver resulted in a rapid recovery of HR and CO. As HR increased, symptoms disappeared. In the last 10&#xA0;s of this exercise HR increased to 80&#xA0;beats/min, CO to 6.0&#xA0;L/min and BP to 115/70&#xA0;mm Hg. After stopping exercise, BP returned to low values and mild symptoms recurred (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Effects of leg-raising and leg contraction and extension exercises on blood pressure. (<bold>a</bold>) Supine Control. (<bold>b</bold>) Effect of leg-raising post-faint. Note only minimal change in blood pressure and no change in heart rate. (<bold>c</bold>) Effect of leg contraction and extension (rowing). Note marked increases in heart rate and blood pressure</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10286_2011_133_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Comments</title>
      <p>PPFH occurred in 7/391 (1.8%) consecutive patients referred to our syncope unit over a period of 20&#xA0;months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In a study of more than 6 million whole blood donations syncopal-type adverse reactions occurred in 2.7% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Prolonged duration of syncope (and recovery) was present in only 1.5% of these syncopal-type adverse reactions. Another variant of delayed recovery from vasovagal syncope is the patient who initially regains his (or her) blood pressure in the horizontal position, but stands up too quickly and suffers a further attack. &#x201C;Status vasovagalis&#x201D; has been suggested to describe this derangement of the circulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Sir Thomas Lewis (1881&#x2013;1945) reported that this phenomenon could last up to 1&#xA0;h after the first attack [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Despite its low frequency, PPFH is a clinically relevant condition, since patients are highly symptomatic and recovery is severely protracted.</p>
      <p>In hypovolemic states passive leg-raising is reported to be effective by increasing central blood volume and thereby cardiac output. This intervention is generally advised to reverse post-faint hypotension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. However, our observations in this study and the ineffectiveness of head-down tilting in the PPFH series [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] would suggest that manoeuvers that increase venous return [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] do not help these patients. Thus, to overcome PPFH, something more than an increase in venous return is needed.</p>
      <p>In our patient, we observed that active rapid flexion and extension of the legs, a manoeuver that increases venous return and stimulates the central pathways, resulted in rapid recovery of heart rate and blood pressure with disappearance of symptoms (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This is in excellent accordance with the findings of Engel and Romano that whole body exercise can overcome the vasovagal reaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. These investigators showed, like we did, that the effects of dynamic exercise are transient if the inhibiting stimulus is very strong [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Like Cotton and Lewis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] we observed that heart rate slowing and symptoms go hand in hand. In previous studies we used lower body tensing to abort impending faints and this intervention is now generally accepted to be effective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Under the circumstances of PPFH, we prefer dynamic tension because during faint, muscle tone is impaired [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and patients find sustained static exercise difficult to perform.</p>
      <p>Based on our observation in this case history, the older literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and our recent findings in patients with vagovagal syncope [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] we postulate that diminished capacity to activate the central sympathetic pathways and thereby overcome exaggerated vagal activity is a key abnormality in patients with severe vasovagal faints. Furthermore, there is good evidence that exercise is a potent mechanism for inhibiting the vagus and increasing sympathoconstrictor activity via central command or muscle chemo and mechanoreflexes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Other time-honoured remedies employed to ameliorate prolonged recovery after a faint include slapping the face, splashing it with cold water and administering smelling salts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Smelling salts (sal volatile), a combination of ammonium carbonate and perfume, were quite popular in the 19th century to revive fainting ladies of delicate sensibilities. A smelling salt container was held under the nose. Slightly noxious fumes coming from the container irritated the mucous membranes lining the nose, throat and lungs resulting in a stimulatory effect. Today, smelling salts are still used to revive boxers in the ring. These time-honoured remedies have a strong historical track record and may have a sound theoretical basis as a means of stimulating central excitatory sympathetic pathways and inhibiting vagal outflow. Additional measures mentioned to improve recovery after a vasovagal faint are drinking cold water or cold soup, or eating something. However, no actual physiologic measurements have been undertaken to support the effectiveness of these interventions.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Open Access</title>
      <p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Busweiler</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jardine</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frampton</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wieling</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sleep syncope: important clinical associations with phobia and vagotonia</article-title>
          <source>Sleep Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>929</fpage>
          <lpage>933</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2010.04.013</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20817601</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cavallaro</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sandroni</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marano</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of passive leg raising for prediction of fluid responsiveness in adults: systematic review and meta-analysis of clinical studies</article-title>
          <source>Intensive Care Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>1475</fpage>
          <lpage>1483</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-010-1929-y</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20502865</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cotton TF, Lewis T (1918&#x2013;1919) Observations upon fainting attacks due to inhibitory cardiac impulses. Heart 7:23</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eder</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dy</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kennedy</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The American Red Cross donor hemovigilance program: complications of blood donation reported in 2006</article-title>
          <source>Transfusion</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>1809</fpage>
          <lpage>1819</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1537-2995.2008.01811.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18631167</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eeftinck Schattenkerk</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lieshout</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meiracker</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nexfin noninvasive continuous blood pressure validated against Riva-Rocci/Korotkoff</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hypertens</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>378</fpage>
          <lpage>383</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajh.2008.368</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19180062</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Engel</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Romano</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLin</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vaosdepessor and carotid sinus syncope: EEG, ECG and clinical observations</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <year>1944</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>100</fpage>
          <lpage>119</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Engel</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Romano</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Studies of syncope; biologic interpretation of vasodepressor syncope</article-title>
          <source>Psychosom Med</source>
          <year>1947</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>288</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18904528</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gastaut H (1974) Syncopes: generalized anoxic cerebral seizures. In: Magnus O, Haas AM (eds). Handbook of clinical neurology, Chapter 42, Vol 15. North Holland, Amsterdam, 815&#x2013;836</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harms</surname>
              <given-names>MPM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wesseling</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pott</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jenstrup</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goudoever</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Secher</surname>
              <given-names>NH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lieshout</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Continuous stroke volume monitoring by modelling flow from non-invasive measurement of arterial pressure in humans under orthostatic stress</article-title>
          <source>Clin Sci</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>301</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/CS19990061</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10464054</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harms</surname>
              <given-names>MPM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lieshout</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jenstrup</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pott</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Secher</surname>
              <given-names>NH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Postural effects on cardiac output and mixed venous oxygen saturation in humans</article-title>
          <source>Exp Physiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>611</fpage>
          <lpage>616</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/eph8802580</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12955161</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jardine</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krediet</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cortelli</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frampton</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wieling</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sympatho-vagal responses in patients with sleep and typical vasovagl syncope</article-title>
          <source>Clin Sci</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>345</fpage>
          <lpage>353</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/CS20080497</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19281451</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krediet</surname>
              <given-names>CTP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dijk</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Linzer</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lieshout</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wieling</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of vasovagal syncope. Controlling or aborting faints by leg crossing and muscle tensing</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>1684</fpage>
          <lpage>1689</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000030939.12646.8F</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12270863</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vasovagal syncope and the carotid sinus mechanism</article-title>
          <source>Br Med J</source>
          <year>1932</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>873</fpage>
          <lpage>876</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.1.3723.873</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20776843</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moya</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ammirati</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blanc</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brignole</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Guidelines for the diagnosis and management of syncope (version 2009): the Task Force for the Diagnosis and Management of Syncope of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC)</article-title>
          <source>Eur Heart J</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>2631</fpage>
          <lpage>2671</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehp290</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19713422</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Poles</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boycott</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Syncope in blood donors</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1942</year>
          <volume>240</volume>
          <fpage>531</fpage>
          <lpage>535</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(00)58098-2</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rowell</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Leary</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reflex control of the circulation during exercise: chemoreflexes and mechanoreflexes</article-title>
          <source>J Appl Physiol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>407</fpage>
          <lpage>418</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2228848</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vasovagal syncope: prevalence and presentation. An algorithm of management in the aviation environment</article-title>
          <source>Eur Heart J Suppl</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>D109</fpage>
          <lpage>D113</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11543489</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thijs</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wieling</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dijk</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Status vasovagalis</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>373</volume>
          <fpage>2222</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(09)60305-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19560603</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baker</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The carotid sinus reflex in health and disease</article-title>
          <source>Medicine</source>
          <year>1933</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <lpage>354</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005792-193309000-00003</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wieling W, Rozenberg J, Schon IK, Karemaker JM, Westerhof BE, Jardine DL (2011) Haemodynamic mechanisms underlying prolonged post-faint hypotension. Clin Auton Res. doi:10.1007/s10286-011-0134-6</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
