<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10527338</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3113162</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pneumomediastinum as a Complication of Extraperitoneal Laparoscopic Inguinal Hernia Repair</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Ramia</surname>
            <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pardo</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cubo</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Padilla</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hern&#xE1;ndez-Calvo</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Servicio de Cirug&#xED;a General y Aparato Digestive, Complejo Hospitalario de Ciudad Real, Ciudad Real, Spain.</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address reprint request to: Dr. J.M. Ramia, <addr-line>C/ Maternidad 1, 4&#xBA; B, 13001 Ciudad Real, SPAIN</addr-line>. Telephone: <phone>34-26-221678</phone>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Sep</season>
        <year>1999</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>233</fpage>
      <lpage>234</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 1999 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jsls-3-3-233.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 52-year-old man with left indirect groin hernia was admitted for elective inguinal repair using the totally extraperitoneal (TEP) approach. After an uneventful intubation, TEP repair of the hernia was performed with three midline trocars. Immediately after extubation, the patient noted severe chest pain. There was a decrease in PaO<sub>2</sub> saturation, and neck subcutaneous emphysema was detected. There was no emphysema of the abdomen or of the back. A chest film and thoracic computed tomographic (CT) scan confirmed the presence of pneumomediastinum without pneumothorax. The patient was discharged without complications.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Totally extraperitoneal hernia repair</kwd>
        <kwd>Laparoscopy</kwd>
        <kwd>Pneumomediastinum</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>The role of laparoscopic herniorraphy (LH) remains controversial. The totally extraperitoneal (TEP) method is essentially a laparoscopic modification of Stoppa's repair.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> Certain potential intraoperative complications have been reported with laparoscopic hernia repair.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> We report a case of pneumomediastinum and subcutaneous emphysema of the neck, without pneumothorax, after TEP repair.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 52-year-old man, American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) level I, 75 kg, 173 cm, with left indirect groin hernia was admitted for elective inguinal repair using the TEP operation. After an uneventful intubation, TEP repair of the hernia utilizing three midline trocars technique was performed. At the beginning of the procedure, SO<sub>2</sub> was 98%, blood pressure 140/65 and FetCO<sub>2</sub> was 34 mm Hg. Operation time was 32 minutes, with a mean intra-abdominal pressure of 11-12 mm Hg. During the procedure, a small noncomplicated break of the peritoneum was detected and closed with staples. No hemodynamic changes were detected. Immediately after extubation, the patient had severe chest pain, O<sub>2</sub> saturation decreased to 84%, FetCO<sub>2</sub> increased to 44 mm Hg, and subcutaneous emphysema of the neck was detected. There was no emphysema of the abdomen or of the back. A chest film and thoracic computed tomographic (CT) scan <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>)</bold> confirmed the presence of pneumomediastinum without pneumothorax. Fiberoptic bronchoscopy did not reveal any tear in the upper airway. After two hours of mechanical ventilation, the emphysema resolved, and the patient was extubated without any problem. The patient was discharged asymptomatic 48 hours after surgery.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>CT thoracic scan with arrows showing pneumomediastinum.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-3-3-233-g01"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Theoretical advantages of laparoscopic hernioplasty are less pain and a quicker return to normal activity. Complications of TEP laparoscopic hernioplasty are reported infrequently. Bowel, bladder and vessel injuries, bleeding in the preperitoneal space, severe testicular pain, hemoscrotum or nerve entrapment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> noted with TEP hernioplasty have also have been described in open procedures. The detractors of LH mainly criticize the laparoscopic approach as usually being performed under general anesthesia with higher costs and an unknown recurrence rate. However, large series have been published showing a low recurrence rate (0% - 1%).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> In fact, LH is now performed as a day-case procedure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref></sup> TEP repair is performed by dissecting the preperitoneal space and insufflating carbon dioxide to maintain an operative space without pneumoperitoneum. This method potentially avoids the risks of intra-abdominal organ lesions and peritoneal adhesions.</p>
      <p>Air may enter the mediastinum from the esophagus, trachea, bronchi, lung, neck, abdomen or retroperitoneal space, producing mediastinal emphysema or pneumomediastinum. Pneumomediastinum is a very rare complication of intra-abdominal laparoscopic procedures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> CO<sub>2</sub> usually passes through the hiatus secondary to a congenital anomaly, weak points, defects or a tear in the diaphragm. High-working CO<sub>2</sub> pressure or a prolonged insufflation time can also lead to pneumomediastinum. A recent article described a TEP procedure complicated by hypercarbia and the development of massive subcutaneous emphysema without hemodynamic instability.</p>
      <p>This was thought to be due to a high intra-abdominal insufflation pressure that ranged between 14 and 18 mm Hg.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Two cases of pneumothorax have also been previously described during TEP.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref></sup> It is thought that pneumothorax as a complication of TEP is most likely related to high insufflation pressure and the length of the procedure, itself. Both cases occurred in healthy patients without hiatal or diaphragmatic hernia, and the condition was solved without the placement of a chest tube. Pneumomediastinum was present in both cases.</p>
      <p>A retroperitoneal route could be postulated on extraperitoneal procedures, but no retroperitoneal air was present on CT, and no back emphysema was detected. In our case, a hiatal route is the most reasonable explanation for the occurance of pneumomediatinum as insufflation time was short, working pressure was low, and bronchoscopy ruled out an airway disruption.</p>
      <p>We conclude that pneumomediastinum can occur after extraperitoneal laparoscopic hernia procedures due to small tears in the peritoneum that occur even with low-working pressures. Only early diagnosis and treatment can avoid serious complications.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wegener</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Arregui</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic totally extraperitoneal herniorraphy</article-title>. <source>Problems Gen Surg</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>185</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>191</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klopfenstein</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaggero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic extraperitoneal inguinal hernia repair complicated by subcutaneous emphysema</article-title>. <source>Can J Anaesth</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>523</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7628034</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaneh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Day-case laparoscopic hernia repair</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>1361</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8944451</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopy surgery: anesthesic implications</article-title>. <source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1272</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7831596</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overdijk</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rademaker</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Odoom</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic fundoplication: a new technique with new complications?</article-title>
<source>J Clin Anesth</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7946369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferzli</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pneumothorax as a complication of laparoscopic inguinal hernia repair</article-title>. <source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9069149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lackey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bilateral pneumothoraces complicating peritoneoscopy</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6231212</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
