<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann R Coll Surg Engl</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann R Coll Surg Engl</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bulletin</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Annals of The Royal College of Surgeons of England</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0035-8843</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1478-7083</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Royal College of Surgeons</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23131211</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3954311</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/003588412X13373405387131</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">387131</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Online Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Stapled diverticulectomy for solitary caecal diverticulitis</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="lrh">STAPLED DIVERTICULECTOMY FOR SOLITARY CAECAL DIVERTICULITIS</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Uwechue</surname>
            <given-names>RU</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="C1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
          <email>uzouwechue@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Richards</surname>
            <given-names>ER</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kurer</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AF0001">
          <addr-line>Scarborough and North East Yorkshire Healthcare NHS Trust,</addr-line>
          <country>UK</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="C1"><addr-line>Surgical Registrar, Scarborough General Hospital, Woodlands Drive, Scarborough, North Yorkshire YO12 6QL,</addr-line><country>UK</country> E: <email>uzouwechue@gmail.com</email><phone>+44 (0)1723 368 111</phone><fax>+44 (0)1723 377 223</fax></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>94</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <fpage>e235</fpage>
      <lpage>e236</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 Royal College of Surgeons</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caecal diverticulitis is an uncommon phenomenon in western countries. The clinical diagnosis is often difficult as it mimics other acute abdominal conditions like appendicitis, colitis or neoplasia. Diagnosis is often made at operation. Operative strategy has been controversial and there is no broad consensus emerging. We report the case of a 71-year-old woman, known to have chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, who presented acutely with right iliac fossa pain. A clinical diagnosis of appendicitis was made. At laparoscopy, a solitary, inflamed, gangrenous caecal diverticulum was found. A laparoscopic stapled diverticulectomy was performed. The patient made a steady post-operative recovery. Histology confirmed diverticulitis. We conclude that stapled diverticulectomy for solitary caecal diverticulitis is a safe and effective surgical strategy when confronted with this scenario.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Caecal diverticulitis</kwd>
        <kwd>Laparoscopic</kwd>
        <kwd>Diverticulectomy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Caecal diverticulitis was first described by Potier in 1912. It is a well recognised pathological entity yet it is still uncommon in Western society. It has a higher prevalence in Asian populations.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p>
    <p>Presentation is commonly with a history of right-sided abdominal pain and a clinical examination indistinguishable from appendicitis. Caecal diverticulitis is frequently diagnosed at laparoscopy or laparotomy and various treatment options have been described in the literature.</p>
    <sec id="ch38_sau1">
      <title>Case history</title>
      <p>A 71-year-old woman was admitted to our hospital complaining of several days of acute onset abdominal pain. Her pain started as a dull central ache that had migrated to the right lower quadrant. She was known to have chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and her exercise tolerance was significantly restricted. Examination revealed tenderness and guarding in the right iliac fossa, over McBurney&#x2019;s point. Her inflammatory markers were raised, her total white cell count was 11.8 &#xD7; 10<sup>9</sup>/l (normal range: 4&#x2013;11 &#xD7; 10<sup>9</sup>/l) and her C-reactive protein was 116mg/l (normal range: &lt;6mg/l). A clinical diagnosis of appendicitis was made and she was taken to the operating theatre for a diagnostic laparoscopy.</p>
      <p>A 10mm umbilical balloon port was inserted by open cut-down technique. A left iliac fossa 12mm port and a suprapubic 5mm port were inserted under vision. The appendix was normal and an inflamed and gangrenous solitary diverticulum was noted on the antimesenteric surface of the caecum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig 1</xref>). In view of her co-morbidities, the patient was not felt to be fit for open surgery or an extensive resection. A stapled diverticulectomy was therefore performed using an Endo GIA&#x2122; (Covidien, Dublin, Ireland) stapling device (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2 fig3">Figs 2 and 3</xref>).
<fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Solitary caecal diverticulitis with normal appendix</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9408-e4-01"/></fig>
<fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Diverticulum partially excised</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9408-e4-02"/></fig>
<fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Staple line following resection</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9408-e4-03"/></fig></p>
      <p>Histology confirmed a 3.5cm &#xD7; 3.0cm &#xD7; 1.5cm diverticulum with transmural suppurative inflammation and loss of the mucosal lining. The patient made a slow recovery from surgery. She developed a post-operative chest infection that was treated successfully. She was discharged a week after surgery. At the follow-up appointment two months later, she had made a full recovery. She had developed a port site hernia at the left iliac fossa port but was asymptomatic from this.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="ch38_sau2">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The diagnosis of caecal diverticulitis is difficult to establish accurately pre-operatively. The clinical presentation often mimics that of acute appendicitis as seen in this case. Consequently, the diagnosis is frequently made at the time of surgery for presumed appendicitis.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p>
      <p>Treatment options for caecal diverticulitis vary widely depending on the presentation and local expertise. There is no consensus among surgeons as to the best option. For uncomplicated caecal diverticulitis diagnosed pre-operatively, a conservative approach can be taken with bowel rest and antibiotics.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> However, others advocate aggressive surgical resection in caecal diverticulitis as less than 40% of patients are successfully managed conservatively without recurrent symptoms.<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></p>
      <p>The surgical approach to resection of a solitary caecal diverticulum varies from a simple diverticulectomy to a right hemicolectomy. These can be performed open or laparoscopically. The first report of a laparoscopic diverticulectomy was in 1994.<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Since then, there have been several other reports showing that laparoscopic resection is feasible in experienced hands.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p>
      <p>Our case posed several challenges. First, the patient had COPD, a significant medical co-morbidity. This increased her risk of peri-operative and post-operative complications. It was therefore felt that laparoscopic resection was the most appropriate option in order to reduce these risks as it involved smaller incisions and facilitated faster recovery. Indeed, the patient did suffer from a post-operative chest infection, which was treated successfully.</p>
      <p>Second, the diagnosis was made intra-operatively and a decision as to how to treat this needed to be made intra-operatively. Resection was performed as the diverticulum was gangrenous and perforation was thought to be imminent, the risk of recurrence if left unresected is known to be significant<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> and the surgeon was happy to proceed based on his experience.<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Furthermore, the diagnosis of caecal cancer must always be entertained in all acute abdomens with intra-operative caecal pathology. If suspected, an oncologically sound right colectomy is the treatment of choice. In reference to our case and as is clear from the pictures, we felt cancer was unlikely. This was because we encountered a discrete, well defined, outpouching area of the caecal wall (the solitary caecal diverticulum), which looked gangrenous, and felt rather soft and as though it were about to perforate. We were confident that no characteristics of malignancy were present.</p>
      <p>Finally, the patient developed a port site hernia at the 12mm left iliac fossa incision. We feel that this is most likely a result of the patient&#x2019;s chronic cough that she experiences as part of her COPD. This highlights the importance of careful consideration of port placement and closure technique, taking into account the general condition of the patient. This port site was not sutured at the sheath. In hindsight, it may have been prudent to have closed the sheath.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="ch38_sau3">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>A laparoscopic stapled diverticulectomy for solitary caecal diverticulitis for a safe and effective therapeutic option, especially in patients in whom more radical surgery would pose a high risk. We believe this is the first reported case in the UK.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fitzmaurice</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Acute right iliac fossa pain: not always appendicitis or a caecal tumour: two case reports</article-title>. <source>Cases J</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19173712</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>YC</given-names></string-name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Management of right colon diverticulitis: a 10-year experience</article-title>. <source>World J Surg</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1,929</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1,934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16369713</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Aggressive resection is indicated for cecal diverticulitis</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg</source><year>2003</year>; <volume>185</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559443</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rubio</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Laparoscopic resection of a solitary cecal diverticulum</article-title>. <source>J Laparoendosc Surg</source><year>1994</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7949389</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kurer</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Solitary caecal diverticulitis as an unusual cause of a right iliac fossa mass: a case report</article-title>. <source>J Med Case Rep</source><year>2007</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>132</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
