<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Orphanet J Rare Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Orphanet J Rare Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1750-1172</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24661356</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3987887</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1750-1172-9-40</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-1172-9-40</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letter to the Editor</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Clinical phenotypes of <italic>MAGEL2</italic> mutations and deletions</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Buiting</surname>
            <given-names>Karin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>karin.buiting@uni-due.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Di Donato</surname>
            <given-names>Nataliya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>nataliya.DiDonato@uniklinikum-dresden.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Beygo</surname>
            <given-names>Jasmin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>jasmin.beygo@stud.uni-due.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Bens</surname>
            <given-names>Susanne</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>sbens@medgen.uni-kiel.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>von der Hagen</surname>
            <given-names>Maja</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref>
          <email>maja.Hagenv.der@uniklinikum-dresden.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Hackmann</surname>
            <given-names>Karl</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>karl.Hackmann@uniklinikum-dresden.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>Horsthemke</surname>
            <given-names>Bernhard</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>bernhard.horsthemke@uni-due.de</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Institut f&#xFC;r Humangenetik, Universit&#xE4;tsklinikum Essen, Universit&#xE4;t Duisburg-Essen, Essen, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Institut f&#xFC;r Klinische Genetik, Medizinische Fakult&#xE4;t Carl Gustav Carus, TU Dresden, Dresden, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Institute of Human Genetics, University Hospital Schleswig-Holstein, Campus Kiel &amp; Christian-Albrechts-University Kiel, Kiel, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Neuropediatrics, Technical University Dresden, Dresden, Germany</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <fpage>40</fpage>
      <lpage>40</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 Buiting et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Buiting et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.ojrd.com/content/9/1/40"/>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Letter to the Editor</title>
      <p>Although it has long been known that Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS) is caused by the loss of function of imprinted, paternally expressed genes in 15q11q13, the contribution of the different genes within this region has not yet been completely resolved. Based on the identification of rare deletions affecting only the snoRNA gene cluster <italic>SNORD116</italic> it has been suggested that this is the major locus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Recently, Schaaf et al. have described truncating mutations of <italic>MAGEL2</italic> in four patients with a broad range of clinical phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The authors conclude that "<italic>MAGEL2</italic> loss of function can contribute to several aspects of the PWS phenotype". While this may be true, we think that the available data are not sufficient to justify this conclusion.</p>
      <p>We have recently seen a 3-year-old boy with a paternally inherited deletion of&#x2009;~&#x2009;3.9 Mb that includes <italic>MAGEL2</italic>, but not the <italic>SNRPN/SNORD116</italic> locus (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Figure S1). Apart from delayed motor skills, the boy is asymptomatic (for a detailed clinical description see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). This is the second individual with a <italic>MAGEL2</italic> deletion who certainly does not have PWS; the first one was also described by our group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Here we offer an explanation for the apparently discrepant findings, which is also important for deciphering the role of candidate genes in PWS and other contiguous gene syndromes.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Clinical and molecular findings in the patient. a)</bold> The patient at the age of five months and <bold>b)</bold> at 3 3/12 years. <bold>c)</bold> Pedigree of the family. The patient has the deletion on his paternal chromosome, whereas his father has the deletion on his maternal chromosome. <bold>d)</bold> Schematic overview of the chromosomal region 15q12. Blue boxes and bars, paternally expressed genes; red box, maternally expressed gene; black boxes, biparentally expressed genes; IC, imprinting center. The deletion is indicated by a black horizontal bar. Not drawn to scale. <bold>e)</bold> CGH Array results of the patient.The chromosomal localisation together with the RefSeq genes are shown in the upper part of the plot. The location of the Agilent microarray probesets is given below (green). The region highlighted in light red is deleted. The bottom part shows the gene dosage detected by the probesets (squares). Green - reduced dosage, black - normal dosage, red &#x2013; increased dosage. Genomic coordinates are according to hg18. Please note that in the UCSC browser the genes <italic>NIPA1</italic> to <italic>TUBGCP5</italic> are in the wrong order due to flanking sequence gaps.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1750-1172-9-40-1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Usually, exome sequencing is performed to identify a gene that is affected in several patients with the same disease. The identification of such a gene is a strong indication that a mutation in this gene causes the disease. Schaaf et al. have started their study with a patient of unknown clinical diagnosis, whose genome was investigated under a <italic>de novo</italic> model only. The other three patients were identified by searching a clinical exome data base. Apparently, an exome-wide analysis under different genetic models was not performed in these patients. Therefore, the number of potentially pathogenic variants in these patients is unknown. In this situation, it is difficult to prove causality, especially when there is no consistent phenotype (since each of the Holm's criteria for PWS refers to a rather common and unspecific clinical sign, many patients with diverse disorders fulfill some of them; these should not be called "PWS phenotypes"). The paternal origin of the <italic>MAGEL2</italic> mutations does not prove causality, because the majority of point mutations occur during spermatogenesis. In summary, it is possible that the <italic>MAGEL2</italic> mutations are innocent bystanders and that the patients have autosomal recessive or X-linked recessive disease (note that all patients are male).</p>
      <p>Even if the <italic>MAGEL2</italic> mutations were causally related to the clinical phenotypes of the patients described by Schaaf et al., it is still possible that they do not contribute to PWS, and there is a precedent for this. In fact, <italic>MAGEL2</italic> is not the first protein-coding gene in the PWS region found to be mutated. The first one is <italic>MKRN3</italic> (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>d), which was found to be mutated in patients with central precocious puberty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In contrast to these patients, patients with PWS typically have incomplete or delayed puberty. The finding that <italic>MKRN3</italic> loss of function alone causes central precocious puberty, but not in combination with the loss of function of the <italic>SNORD116</italic> genes, indicates that the <italic>SNORD116</italic> loss of function is epistatic to <italic>MKRN3</italic> loss of function, probably because the <italic>SNORD116</italic> genes act developmentally upstream of <italic>MKRN3</italic>.</p>
      <p>Another possibility is that there is leaky expression of the maternal <italic>MAGEL2</italic> allele in a subset of neurons in patients with a paternal <italic>MAGEL2</italic> deletion (our patient and PWS patients), but not in patients with a truncating <italic>MAGEL2</italic> mutation (the patients described by Schaaf et al.). A precedent for this situation is the recent finding of stochastic loss of silencing of the imprinted <italic>Ndn/NDN</italic> allele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. These authors find weak expression of the maternal <italic>Ndn</italic> allele in mice with a targeted deletion of the <italic>Ndn</italic> gene that includes the promoter but not in mice with a targeted deletion that does not include the promoter, probably because of promoter competition. We note that the four patients described by Schaaf et al. have an intact promoter on the paternal allele, whereas our two patients and the majority of PWS patients don't.</p>
      <p>We conclude that it is important to distinguish between point mutations and whole gene deletions and that the effect of the genes in the PWS chromosomal region may be epistatic rather than additive. Therefore, the role of <italic>MAGEL2</italic> in PWS remains unclear.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the parents of the patient for publication of this manuscript and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>KB and BH supervised this project. KB and JB planned the experiments and analyzed data. MvdH carried out the clinical evaluation and the clinical diagnostic workup. ND performed dysmorphological evaluation, genetic counseling, collected samples and initiated genetic testing. KH performed and analyzed CGH array analysis. SB performed and analyzed custom array analysis. BH wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 1</title>
          <p>Supplementary information.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1750-1172-9-40-S1.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgement</title>
      <p>We thank the family for participation in this study, Christina Lich and Dorit Schuster for technical assistance and Dr. Julia Richter for support with designing the custom array. This work was supported by the Bundesministerium f&#xFC;r Bildung und Forschung (Network Imprinting diseases, 01GM1114).</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Sahoo</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>del Gaudio</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>German</surname>
            <given-names>JR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shinawi</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peters</surname>
            <given-names>SU</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Person</surname>
            <given-names>RE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garnica</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheung</surname>
            <given-names>SW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beaudet</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Prader-Willi phenotype caused by paternal deficiency for the HBII-85 C/D box small nucleolar RNA cluster</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>719</fpage>
          <lpage>721</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.158</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18500341</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>de Smith</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Purmann</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Walters</surname>
            <given-names>RG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ellis</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Holder</surname>
            <given-names>SE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Van Haelst</surname>
            <given-names>MM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brady</surname>
            <given-names>AF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fairbrother</surname>
            <given-names>UL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dattani</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Keogh</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Henning</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yeo</surname>
            <given-names>GS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>O'Rahilly</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Froguel</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Farooqi</surname>
            <given-names>IS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Blakemore</surname>
            <given-names>AI</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A deletion of the HBII-85 class of small nucleolar RNAs (snoRNAs) is associated with hyperphagia, obesity and hypogonadism</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>3257</fpage>
          <lpage>3265</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddp263</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19498035</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Duker</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ballif</surname>
            <given-names>BC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bawle</surname>
            <given-names>EV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Person</surname>
            <given-names>RE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mahadevan</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alliman</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Traylor</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bejjani</surname>
            <given-names>BA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shaffer</surname>
            <given-names>LG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lamb</surname>
            <given-names>AN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sahoo</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Paternally inherited microdeletion at 15q11.2 confirms a significant role for the SNORD116 C/D box snoRNA cluster in Prader-Willi syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1196</fpage>
          <lpage>1201</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2010.102</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20588305</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Schaaf</surname>
            <given-names>CP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gonzalez-Garay</surname>
            <given-names>ML</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xia</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Potocki</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gripp</surname>
            <given-names>KW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peters</surname>
            <given-names>BA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McElwain</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Drmanac</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beaudet</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Caskey</surname>
            <given-names>CT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Truncating mutations of MAGEL2 cause Prader-Willi phenotypes and autism</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1405</fpage>
          <lpage>1408</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2776</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24076603</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kanber</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Giltay</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wieczorek</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zogel</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hochstenbach</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Caliebe</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kuechler</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Horsthemke</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buiting</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A paternal deletion of MKRN3, MAGEL2 and NDN does not result in Prader-Willi syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>582</fpage>
          <lpage>590</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2008.232</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19066619</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Abreu</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dauber</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Macedo</surname>
            <given-names>DB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Noel</surname>
            <given-names>SD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Brito</surname>
            <given-names>VN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gill</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cukier</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>IR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Navarro</surname>
            <given-names>VM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gagliardi</surname>
            <given-names>PC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kochi</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Longui</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beckers</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>de Zegher</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Montenegro</surname>
            <given-names>LR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mendonca</surname>
            <given-names>BB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carroll</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hirschhorn</surname>
            <given-names>JN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Latronico</surname>
            <given-names>AC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kaiser</surname>
            <given-names>UB</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Central precocious puberty caused by mutations in the imprinted gene MKRN3</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>368</volume>
          <fpage>2467</fpage>
          <lpage>2475</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1302160</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23738509</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Rieusset</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaller</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Unmehopa</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matarazzo</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watrin</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Linke</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Georges</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bischof</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dijkstra</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bloemsma</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Corby</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Michel</surname>
            <given-names>FJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wevrick</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zechner</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Swaab</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dudley</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bezin</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Muscatelli</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Stochastic loss of silencing of the imprinted Ndn/NDN allele, in a mouse model and humans with prader-willi syndrome, has functional consequences</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Genet</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>e1003752</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003752</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24039599</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
