<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17575778</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3015751</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Laparoscopic Nephrectomy for a Nonfunctioning Pelvic Kidney in Preparation for Renal Transplantation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Milhoua</surname>
            <given-names>Paul M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Knoll</surname>
            <given-names>Abraham</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Koi</surname>
            <given-names>Philip T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hoenig</surname>
            <given-names>David M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Ghavamian</surname>
            <given-names>Reza</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <aff>Department of Urology, Montefiore Medical Center/Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, New York, USA.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address reprint requests to: Reza Ghavamian, MD, <addr-line>Associate Professor Urology, Montefiore Medical Center, Department of Urology, 3400 Bainbridge Ave, Fifth Floor, Bronx, NY 10467, USA</addr-line>. E-mail:<email>rghavami@montefiore.org</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Oct-Dec</season>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <season>Oct-Dec</season>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>538</fpage>
      <lpage>540</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2006 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jsls-10-4-538.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pelvic kidneys pose a problem for any planned surgical intervention given their anomalous blood supply. Although minimally invasive approaches have been described for the management of benign conditions, only a handful of reports have described the use of laparoscopy for removal of ectopic or fused kidneys. We describe the laparoscopic removal of a symptomatic pelvic kidney in a patient before renal transplantation. </p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Pelvic kidney</kwd>
        <kwd>Laparoscopy</kwd>
        <kwd>Transplantation</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Renal pelvic ectopia is a relatively rare occurrence, with a reported incidence of 1 in 3000 autopsies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> Although no significant difference exists in the incidence among the sexes, a slightly higher propensity is present for the left side over the right. The majority of patients remain asymptomatic, with most ectopic kidneys discovered as incidental findings during radiological evaluation. However, surgical intervention is often required for those patients who suffer from recurrent infection, symptomatic ureteropelvic junction obstruction, calculi, or chronic pain. </p>
      <p>Laparoscopic and laparoscopic-assisted approaches to pelvic kidneys and those for fused, crossed renal ectopia have previously been described for the treatment of calculi and for the removal of nonfunctioning kidneys.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup>
Herein, we describe our technique for the removal of a symptomatic, pelvic kidney in a patient with end-stage renal disease (ESRD) before a living-related renal transplant. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 58-year-old-man with ESRD was referred by the renal transplantation service for removal of a symptomatic, pelvic right kidney before undergoing a planned living-related renal transplantation (LRRT). The patient had been undergoing hemodialysis for 2 years and had a longstanding history of vague lower abdominal pain secondary to nephrolithiasis within the pelvic kidney and recurrent urinary tract infections. Physical examination revealed a soft abdomen with a palpable mass in the right lower quadrant. Contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) of the abdomen and pelvis with 3-dimensional (3-D) reconstructions revealed the left kidney to be within its normal anatomical location and a sizable pelvic right kidney (8&#xD7;5.5&#xD7;2 cm) with mild hydronephrosis containing a 2.5-cm calculus <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>)</bold>. Further imaging revealed the right renal artery to arise from the right common iliac artery, with the right renal vein draining into the left common iliac vein. Several smaller accessory veins were also demonstrated to drain into the right internal iliac vein. The patient underwent a laparoscopic pelvic nephrectomy via a 3-port approach <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>)</bold>. At the discretion of the renal transplant service, concomitant allograft renal transplantation was deferred secondary to concern over infection. Following initial laparoscopic inspection, the pelvic right kidney was easily identified under the peritoneal reflection just anterior to the sacral promontory. The right external iliac artery was identified, and the parietal peritoneum incised along the root of the small bowel mesentery. Dissection was continued over the kidney until the anteriorly located renal pelvis and ureter were identified. Utilizing sharp and blunt dissection, the kidney was mobilized circumferentially. Anomalous vessels were isolated and divided between surgical clips <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>)</bold>. The ureter was then divided, and the kidney freed from any remaining retroperitoneal attachments and placed within an endocatch bag. Given the size of the pelvic stone, the specimen was not morcellated but was left intact within the endocatch bag. The specimen was removed via the supraumbilical port site. All ports were closed in the standard fashion. Total operative time was 80 minutes, with an estimated blood loss of 80 mL. The patient was discharged home on postoperative day 3 and received an LRRT 6 weeks after having undergone the laparoscopic pelvic nephrectomy. </p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Contrast-enhanced computed tomographic scan of the pelvis, demonstrating the right pelvic kidney with a stone within the renal pelvis.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-10-4-538-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Diagram illustrating the port placement for laparoscopic excision of the pelvic kidney.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-10-4-538-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Laparoscopic image demonstrating right renal artery arising from right common iliac artery.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-10-4-538-g03"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Ectopic kidneys pose a problem for any planned surgical intervention given their anomalous blood supply. As such, adequate preoperative imaging is crucial, whether by 3-D CT scan or magnetic resonance angiography (MRA). In this instance, laparoscopy afforded the well-established benefits of diminished blood loss, shortened operative time, and faster convalescence versus a traditional open procedure. More importantly, the laparoscopic approach to the pelvic kidney avoided violation of the right iliac fossa, which was later used for renal allograft transplantation. </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Retik</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
(eds).
<source>Campbell's Urology</source>. <edition>8th ed.</edition>
<publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>WB Saunders</publisher-name>; <year>2002</year>: <fpage>1885</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1924</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopy nephrectomy in crossed fused renal ectopia</article-title>. <source>Urology</source>. <year>1993</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8212436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pietrow</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names><suffix>II</suffix></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic hand-assisted nephrectomy for crossed fused ectopia with polycystic kidney disease</article-title>.<source>Urology</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15708066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoenig</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalhav</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Elbahnasy</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic pyelithotomy in a pelvic kidney: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>J Soc Laparoendosc Surg</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>165</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bove</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic management of ureteropelvic junction obstruction in patients with upper urinary tract anomalies</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>171</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14665848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moores</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic excision of pelvic kidney with single vaginal ectopic ureter</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Surg</source>. <year>1997</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>634</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9126773</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sriprasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic removal of a multicystic dysplastic pelvic kidney</article-title>. <source>J Endourol</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>805</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11724119</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic pyelovesicostomy for ureteropelvic junction obstruction in a pelvic kidney</article-title>. <source>J Endourol</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15910258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
