<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Res Pediatr Endocrinol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCRPE</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Clinical Research in Pediatric Endocrinology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1308-5727</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1308-5735</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Galenos Publishing</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21274309</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3005755</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4274/jcrpe.v1i6.275</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">42</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Iodine Overload and Severe Hypothyroidism in Two Neonates</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kurto&#x11F;lu</surname>
            <given-names>Selim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ak&#x131;n</surname>
            <given-names>Leyla</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ak&#x131;n</surname>
            <given-names>Mustafa Ali</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>&#xC7;oban</surname>
            <given-names>Dilek</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>
				Erciyes University, Faculty of Medicine, Department of Pediatric Endocrinology, Kayseri, Turkey
			</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>
				Erciyes University, Faculty of Medicine, Department of Neonatology, Kayseri, Turkey
			</aff>
      <aff>
        <phone>+90 352 437 49 37</phone>
        <email>selimk@erciyes.edu.tr</email>
        <addr-line>Erciyes University Faculty of Medicine, Department of Pediatric Endocrinology, Kayseri, Turkey</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>8</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>275</fpage>
      <lpage>277</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Journal of Clinical Research in Pediatric Endocrinology, Published by Galenos Publishing.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iodine overload frequently leads to transient hyperthyrotropinemia or hypothyroidism, and rarely to hyperthyroidism in neonates. Iodine exposure can be prenatal, perinatal or postnatal. Herein we report two newborn infants who developed severe hypothyroidism due to iodine overload. The overloading was caused by excessive use of an iodinated antiseptic for umbilical care in the first case, and as a result of maternal exposure and through breast milk with a high iodine level in the second case. Presenting the two cases, we wanted to draw attention to these preventable causes of hypothyroidism in infants.</p>
        <p><bold>Conflict of interest:</bold>None declared.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Neonate</kwd>
        <kwd>hypothyroidism</kwd>
        <kwd>Iodine overload</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Prenatal, perinatal or postnatal iodine overload can cause problems such as transient hyperthyrotropinemia, hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism in preterm and term infants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>). Herein we report two term neonates who developed hypothyroidism due to iodine overload caused by umbilical care with iodine solution in patient No. 1, and through breast milk in patient No. 2. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>
        <bold>Case 1</bold>
      </p>
      <p>A 13-day-old male was referred to our clinic because of a high thyrotropin (TSH) level (42.9 mU/L) detected in a blood sample taken for congenital hypothyroidism screening on the fourth day of life. The baby&#x2019;s birth weight was 3250 g and his length was 51 cm. History revealed that an iodine-containing antiseptic had been applied 3 times a day for umbilical care since birth. The mother had no autoimmune thyroid disease. On the 8<sup>th</sup> day of life, laboratory data showed a TSH level of 120 mU/L (N: 0.5-6.5 mU/L, by IRMA) and a thyroxine (T4) level of 6.08 &#x3BC;g/dl (N: 8.2-17.2 &#x3BC;g/dl). An X-ray of the knee showed a bone maturation level of 38 gestational weeks. Thyroid ultrasonography revealed a thyroid volume of 1.1 mL (N: 0.79mL) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>). Urinary iodine level was 51 &#x3BC;g/dl (N:10-20 &#x3BC;g/dl). On his 13<sup>th</sup> day of life, thyroid function tests were: Free triiodothyronin (fT3) level 1.79 pg/mL (N: 2.5-3.9 pg/mL), fT4 4.69 pg/mL (N: 9-26 pg/mL), TSH 66.11 mU/L (N: 0.5-6.5 mU/L) and thyroglobulin 2.36 ng/mL (N: 2-106 ng/mL). L-T4 treatment was started in a dose of 13 &#x3BC;g/kg/day. Seven days after initiation of treatment, laboratory data revealed a fT3 level of 5.19 pg/mL, a fT4 level of 27.41 pg/mL and a TSH level of 0.44 mU/L. The L-T4 dose was reduced to 6.5 &#x3BC;g/kg/day. 14 days later, thyroid functions were: fT3: 2.02 pg/mL, fT4:13 pg/mL and TSH: 0.22 mU/L. On the most recent visit (on the 30<sup>th</sup> day of treatment), laboratory results were: fT3: 3.4 pg/mL (N: 2.5-3.9 pg/mL), fT4: 14.29 pg/mL (N:9-26 pg/mL), and TSH: 3.23 mU/L (N: 0.5-6.5 mU/L). The hypothyroidism was accepted to be due to iodine overload caused by excessive application of iodine to the umbilicus. It was decided to continue the replacement therapy in the same dose, and eventually to gradually reduce the dose and discontinue the treatment.  </p>
      <p>
        <bold>Case 2</bold>
      </p>
      <p>A 15-day-old male was referred to our clinic due to a high TSH (26.11 mU/L) and a low fT4 level (6.83 pg/mL). The baby was born by vaginal delivery and an episiotomy was applied during the delivery. The mother used an iodine antiseptic for her episiotomy incision for about 10-12 days postpartum. The baby&#x2019;s knee X-ray showed a bone maturation of 40 weeks. His thyroid volume was reported as 1.04 mL measured by thyroid ultrasonography (N: 0.79mL) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>). Urinary iodine level was 41 &#x3BC;g/dl (N: 10-20 &#x3BC;g/dl). Iodine concentration of the mother&#x2019;s breast milk was 30 &#x3BC;g/dl (N: 10-20 &#x3BC;g/dl). The mother did not have any autoimmune thyroid disease. The hypothyroidism in this case was attributed to iodine overload due to iodine transfer during breastfeeding. L-T4 treatment at a dosage of 8 &#x3BC;g/kg/day was initiated. On the follow-up visit on the 40<sup>th</sup> day of life, while the baby was on the same dose of L-T4, the laboratory data were as follows: fT3: 3.23 pg/mL, fT4:9.9 pg/mL, TSH: 3.04  mU/L.</p>
      <p>It was planned to reduce the L-T4 dose according to the results of the future thyroid function tests and to eventually discontinue the treatment. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Maternal intake of excessive iodine or  contrast agents and the use of drugs or antiseptics containing iodine can cause fetal and neonatal iodine overload via transplacental transport or breastfeeding.  Iodine overload in the neonate can also occur due to the use of contrast agents and iodine antiseptics in the infant during the postnatal period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>). The use of iodine antiseptics during birth increases the iodine level of the cord blood by 50% in minutes and also causes iodine overload in the mother. Iodine levels in maternal urine and breast milk increase tenfold if iodine is used for episiotomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>). Iodinated antiseptics used for umbilical care may also cause iodine overload because they are rapidly absorbed through the excessively permeable skin of the neonates. The low renal clearance of iodine, particularly in newborns with renal insufficiency, can facilitate this condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>). Hypothyroidism due to iodine overload can develop more easily and be more severe in iodine-deficient areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>).</p>
      <p>Hyperthyroidism caused by iodine overload is very rare in newborns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>). However, recall of hyperthyrotropinemic infants encountered in newborn screening has led to an increase in prevalence of cases of overt hypothyroidism and this is more common if iodine overload exists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>). Although the sensitivity threshold may differ interindividually, the fetus and newborn are both quite sensitive to iodine overload (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>). The cut-off points for urinary iodine levels for overload have been reported as 16, 20 or 25 &#x3BC;g/dl by different authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>). Generally, an iodine level above 20 &#x3BC;g/dl in the urine or breast milk can be accepted as iodine overload (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>).</p>
      <p>When iodine overload occurs, hormone biosynthesis in the thyroid gland is blocked by an autoregulation mechanism, known as the Wolff-Chaikoff effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>). TSH-induced cyclic AMP formation, sodium-iodide symporter (NIS) expression, iodine uptake and organification decrease, while MIT/DIT ratio increases, and proteolysis decreases. This effect is transient and ceases within 25-60 hours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>). However, if iodine overloading persists, hypothyroidism becomes evident.</p>
      <p>The management of hypothyroidism caused by iodine overload is controversial. However, it is recommended that overt hypothyroidism should be treated and followed-up (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>). In many centers the treatment is continued until three years of age. Treatment can be tapered down and discontinued at an earlier age if thyroid hormone levels are elevated. It must be kept in mind that it is more important to prevent the iodine overload in both mothers and babies. Health caregivers should be educated on this subject.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bona</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zaffaroni</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perona</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neonatal transient hypothyroidism after excess iodine exposition by amniofetography.</article-title>
          <source>Panminerva Med</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>193</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3211580</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gordon</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rowitch</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitchell</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohane</surname>
              <given-names>IS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topical iodine and neonatal hypothyroidism.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <fpage>1336</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7489070</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nishiyama</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mikeda</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okada</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kotani</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hishinuma</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transient hypothyroidism or persistent hyperthyrotropinemia in neonates born to mothers with excessive iodine intake.</article-title>
          <source>Thyroid</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1077</fpage>
          <lpage>1083</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15650362</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>P&#xFC;nt</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bramswig</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transient neonatal hypothyroidism during breastfeeding after postnatal maternal topical iodine treatment.</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>159</volume>
          <fpage>716</fpage>
          <lpage>717</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11014479</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bryant</surname>
              <given-names>WP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zimmerman</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Iodine-induced hyperthyroidism in a newborn.</article-title>
          <source>Pediatrics</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>434</fpage>
          <lpage>436</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7862489</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kurtoglu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akcakus</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kocaoglu</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gunes</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Budak</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atabek</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karakucuk</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delange</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Iodine status remains critical in mother and infant in Central Anatolia (Kayseri) of Turkey.</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Nutr</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <lpage>303</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15309449</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ares</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quero</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morreale de Escobar</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Iodine balance, iatrogenic excess, and thyroid dysfunction in premature infants.</article-title>
          <source>Semin Perinatol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>407</fpage>
          <lpage>412</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19007678</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lombard</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalla-Vale</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veyrac</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plan</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cambonie</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Picaud</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Severe hypothyroidism after contrast enema in premature infants.</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>168</volume>
          <fpage>499</fpage>
          <lpage>500</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18618140</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weber</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vigone</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rapa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bona</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiumello</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neonatal transient hypothyroidism: aetiological study. Italian Collaborative Study on Transient Hypothyroidism.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>F70</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9797631</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>VC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Svoren</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolfsdorf</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hypothyroidism in a breast-fed preterm infant resulting from maternal topical iodine exposure.</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <fpage>566</fpage>
          <lpage>567</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17011335</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arena-Ansotegui</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Emparanza Knorr</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Iodine antiseptics are not harmLess.</article-title>
          <source>An Esp Pediatr</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>25</fpage>
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10998400</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chanoine</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boulvain</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bourdoux</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pardou</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>VanThi</surname>
              <given-names>HV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ermans</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delange</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Increased recall rate at screening for congenital hypothyroidism in breastfed infants born to iodine over-loaded mothers.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>1207</fpage>
          <lpage>1210</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3196047</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chabrolle</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossler</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Goitre and hypothyroidism in the newborn after cutaneous absorption of iodine.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>495</fpage>
          <lpage>498</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">686777</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book" publication-format="print">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chanoine</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bourdoux</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pardou</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Medeiros-Neto</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaitant</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Frontiers of Thyroidology</chapter-title>
          <source>Frontiers of Thyroidology</source>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Plenium Medical</publisher-name>
          <year>1986</year>
          <fpage>1055</fpage>
          <lpage>1060</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ares</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pastor</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quero</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morreale de Escobar</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid complications, including overt hypothyroidism, related to the use of non-radiopaque silastic catheters for parenteral feeding in prematures requiring injection of small amounts of an iodinated contrast medium.</article-title>
          <source>Acta Paediatr</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>579</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7633159</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Semba</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delange</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Iodine in milk: perpectives for infant health.</article-title>
          <source>Nutr Rev</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>269</fpage>
          <lpage>278</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11518182</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eng</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cardona</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fang</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Previti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alex</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carrasco</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chin</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braverman</surname>
              <given-names>LE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Escape from the acute Wolff-Chaikoff effect is associated with a decrease thyroid sodium/iodide symporter messenger ribonucleic acid and protein.</article-title>
          <source>Endocrinology</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <fpage>3404</fpage>
          <lpage>3410</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10433193</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal" publication-format="online">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aliefendio&#x11F;lu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanli</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cakmak</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>A&#x11F;ar</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Albayrak</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Evliyao&#x11F;lu</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wolff-Chaikoff effect in a newborn: is it an overlooked problem?</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr Surg</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>e1</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
