<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9288639</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054210</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Mixed hepatoblastoma in an adult--a case report and literature review.</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ahn</surname>
            <given-names>H. J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kwon</surname>
            <given-names>K. W.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Y. J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>H. J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hong</surname>
            <given-names>S. P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>D.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>J. S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department of Pathology, Pochon CHA University, Pundang CHA General Hospital, Sungnam, Korea.</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>8</month>
        <year>1997</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>369</fpage>
      <lpage>373</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hepatoblastoma is thought to originate from embryonal hepatic tissue, and most of these tumors occur in children under the age of 2 years. Hepatoblastoma in adults is extremely rare, and the prognosis is much worse than the mixed hepatoblastoma of childhood. We experienced a case of mixed hepatoblastoma in a 51 year old female patient. She had been suffering from a mild pain and a palpable lump in the epigastric area. Serum AFP was 43,850 ng/ml. Computerized tomography and selective abdominal angiography showed a large low-density mass. With a suspicion of hepatocellular carcinoma of the left lobe, a left lateral segmentectomy was performed. The external surface showed a huge protruding mass and the capsule was previously ruptured. On section, the tumor was a 11 x 7 cm sized expanding mass which had a variegated surface composed of yellow-white friable tissue with multifocal hemorrhagic areas. Microscopic examination revealed a tumor consisted of epithelial and mesenchymal elements. The mesenchymal cells were spindle in shape and proliferated over the whole tumor with focal osteosarcomatous differentiation. The epithelial components showed well-differentiated hepatocellular carcinoma-like areas, poorly differentiated acinar or tubular structures.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
