<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23793197</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3754380</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/ABD1806-4841.20131831</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Genitogluteal porokeratosis - Case report<xref ref-type="other" rid="fn03">*</xref>
</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Poroqueratose genitogl&#xFA;tea - Relato de caso</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ferreira</surname>
            <given-names>Fl&#xE1;via Regina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lessa</surname>
            <given-names>Priscila Pacheco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">
2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Alvarenga</surname>
            <given-names>Marcia Lanzoni</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">
3</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Master of Science by Federal University of S&#xE3;o Paulo (UNIFESP) - III Assistant Professor of Dermatology, Department of Medicine, University of Taubat&#xE9;
(UNITAU) - Taubat&#xE9; (SP), Brazil.
</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> Residency in Internal Medicine at the University of Taubate - (UNITAU) - Intern in the Department of Dermatology, University Hospital of Taubat&#xE9; - University
of Taubat&#xE9; (HUT-UNITAU) - Taubat&#xE9; (SP), Brazil.
</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> Specialist in Pathology - I Assistant Professor of Pathology, Department of Medicine, University of Taubat&#xE9; (UNITAU) - Taubat&#xE9; (SP), Brazil.
</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">
MAILING ADDRESS: Fl&#xE1;via Regina Ferreira, Avenida Granadeiro Guimar&#xE3;es, 270 - Centro 12020-130 - Taubat&#xE9; - SP, Brazil. E-mail: <email>dermagica@uol.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>438</fpage>
      <lpage>440</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We report the case of a patient diagnosed with genitogluteal porokeratosis, a disorder of epidermal keratinization. The location described is extremely rare and very often late diagnosed or even misdiagnosed. Histopathology showed a typical cornoid lamella of great value to support this diagnosis. The importance of awareness of this entity by the specialist is emphasized as a differential diagnosis among genital diseases of chronic evolution and difficult treatment.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>Relata-se o caso de um paciente com diagn&#xF3;stico de poroqueratose genitogl&#xFA;tea, uma desordem da queratiniza&#xE7;&#xE3;o epid&#xE9;rmica, cuja localiza&#xE7;&#xE3;o exclusiva &#xE9; extremamente rara, sendo muitas vezes tardia ou erroneamente diagnosticada. A histopatologia demonstra a cl&#xE1;ssica lamela corn&#xF3;ide, de grande valia para elucida&#xE7;&#xE3;o diagn&#xF3;stica. Ressalta-se a import&#xE2;ncia do conhecimento desta entidade pelo especialista como diagn&#xF3;stico diferencial entre as afec&#xE7;&#xF5;es genitais de evolu&#xE7;&#xE3;o arrastada e de dif&#xED;cil tratamento.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Buttocks</kwd>
        <kwd>Genitalia</kwd>
        <kwd>Parakeratosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Porokeratosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Porokeratosis is a primary disorder of epidermal keratinization of unknown aetiology. It presents localized and generalized forms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref></sup> It is thought that the different forms of porokeratosis are phenotypic expressions of a common genetic disorder. Autossomal dominant inheritance of several clinical variants has been reported, as well as sporadic adult-onset cases associated with immunosuppression, AIDS, kidney or liver transplantation, drugs such as thiazide diuretics and immunodeficiency, hematolog-ic malignancies, autoimmune diseases, and occupational exposure to benzene.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B05">5</xref></sup> The involvement of the genital region and extension to adjacent areas occurs in both forms (localized or generalized), and localized presentation confined to these regions is extremely rare, with few cases reported in the literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref></sup> The skin lesions are typically characterized by erythema-tous to brownish papules and plaques with elevated borders, single or multiple.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref></sup> Histopathological examination demonstrates the classic cornoid lamella. The clinical exuberance, rarity and involvement of unusual locations led us to the presentation of this case.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Male patient, 37 years old, complained of the onset of skin lesions on the groin and buttocks for approximately two years accompanied by intense local itching. The dermatological examination showed erythematous papules and plaques with elevated and well-defined borders on the scrotum; brownish macules and papules on the groin and thighs; well-defined brownish erythematous keratotic papules and annular plaques on the buttocks and gluteal cleft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">3</xref>). The lesions started located on the scrotum and groin, with progression to the buttocks region (gluteal cleft). Currently stable. The patient received previous treatment with systemic and topical antifungal drugs, isolated or combined topical corticosteroids, without clinical improvement. No significant personal or familiar pathological history. The previous topical therapy was discontinued, and an incisional biopsy of a papule of the left scrotum was performed. The histopathological examination showed superficial perivascular dermatitis with columns of parakeratosis, consistent with the diagnosis of porokeratosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Scrotum - Papules and plaques with elevated and well-defined borders</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0438-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Groin - brownish macules and papules</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0438-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Buttocks and gluteal cleft - well-defined brownish erythematous keratotic papules and annular plaques</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0438-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Underlying dyskeratotic cells and absence of the granular layer (HE, 100x)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0438-g04"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Porokeratosis is a primary disorder of epidermal keratinization of unknown aetiology. It can be classified into localized and generalized forms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref></sup> The localized forms include porokeratosis of Mibelli, linear porokeratosis, and punctate porokeratosis, and the generalized variants include disseminated superficial porokeratosis, disseminated superficial actinic porokeratosis, and disseminated palmoplantar porokeratosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Porokeratosis involving the genital region occurs in generalized forms or localized confined to the genital area and adjacent sites (buttocks, perineum, groin and thighs), being the latter an extremely rare presentation, generally classified as a plaque-type porokeratosis of Mibelli, with 23 cases reported in the literature. Based on published reports, the skin lesions are typically characterized by well-defined brownish erythematous keratotic papules and annular plaques single or multiple. The center of the lesion can be hyperpigmented or hypopigmented and atrophic. They can be asymptomatic or with severe local itching.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref></sup> There is a predominance of males, and possible increased incidence may be observed in Asian and African American populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B05">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref></sup> The pathogenesis of this entity remains uncertain and both genetic and environmental components have been implicated. Autosomal dominant transmission and associated conditions such as local and systemic immunosuppression have been reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref></sup> Despite presenting a typical cutaneous manifestation the diagnosis is delayed because of the rarity of location, and often misdiagnosed as sexually transmitted disease. The main differential diagnoses are condyloma acuminatum, syphilis (condiloma latum), granuloma annulare, lichen simplex chronicus, extramammary Paget disease and eczema. The skin biopsy is essential for the diagnosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref></sup> Histologically, the characteristic alteration is called cornoid lamella, a column of parakeratotic cells in the epidermis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>A variant called porokeratosis ptychotropica, that was initially described in 1995 as a pruritic eruption of the gluteal cleft, typically involves the buttocks and gluteal cleft mimicking an inflammatory disorder and is an important differential diagnosis in genitogluteal porokeratosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref></sup> Although affecting similar locations, with clinical features that can be histologically superimposable, the ptychotropic form presents an unique feature that is the presence of multiple cornoid lamellae<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B08">8</xref></sup>, not detected in this case. Therefore we preferred the term genitogluteal porokeratosis to encompass both the clinical and histopathological findings of this case.</p>
      <p>The elective treatment is the surgical treatment, depending on the number and the size of the lesions. Other treatment options include cryotherapy (liquid nitrogen), CO2 laser therapy, oral and topical retinoids, topical vitamin D3 analogs, keratolytic agents, 5 - fluorouracil - occlusive and more recently with topical imiquimod 5% and topical diclofenac sodium 3% gel - with symptomatic and stabilizing effects on the lesions, with emphasis on its use in genital or genitogluteal porokeratosis. Photodynamic therapy is also described with different results. Regular monitoring is necessary because of the potential for malignant transformation, although there are no reports yet in the literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref></sup>
</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors thank their colleagues &#xC9;rico Pampado di Santis and Samuel Henrique Mandelbaum for helping with the references.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="other">
        <p>* Study carried out at the University Hospital of Taubat&#xE9; - University of Taubat&#xE9; (HUT-UNITAU) - Taubat&#xE9; (SP), Brazil</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial funding: None</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chou</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuo</surname>
              <given-names>TT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genital porokeratosis: a series of 10 patients and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>155</volume>
          <fpage>325</fpage>
          <lpage>329</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16882170</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Valdivielso-Ramos</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genital porokeratosis</article-title>
          <source>Actas Dermosifiliogr</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>220</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18358198</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sengupta</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Das</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gangopadhyay</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Porokeratosis confined to the genital area: a report of three cases</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>80</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Batra</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamino</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genital porokeratosis</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Online J</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19891931</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sertznig</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Felbert</surname>
              <given-names>VV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Megahed</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Porokeratosis: present concepts</article-title>
          <source>J Eur Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>404</fpage>
          <lpage>412</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marks</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varma</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cantrell</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gold</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muellenhoff</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diclofenac sodium 3% gel as potential treatment for disseminated superficial actinic porokeratosis</article-title>
          <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>42</fpage>
          <lpage>45</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18702625</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wanat</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gormley</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>DD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kovarik</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genitogluteal porokeratosis involving the scrotum: an unusual presentation of an uncommon disease</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Pahtol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>72</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Malek</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chedraoui</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kibbi</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosn</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genitogluteal Porokeratosis: 10 years to make the diagnosis</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermathol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>604</fpage>
          <lpage>606</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gon</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rocha</surname>
              <given-names>SRT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pozetti</surname>
              <given-names>EMO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
              <given-names>VSM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antonio</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Porokeratosis: a clinical study of fifteen cases</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>271</fpage>
          <lpage>275</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
