<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Infect. Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24739742</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3991887</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2334-14-206</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-14-206</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Non-healing old world cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by <italic>L. infantum</italic> in a patient from Spain</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Kroidl</surname>
            <given-names>Arne</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>akroidl@lrz.uni-muenchen.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Kroidl</surname>
            <given-names>Inge</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>ikroidl@lrz.uni-muenchen.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Bretzel</surname>
            <given-names>Gisela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>bretzel@lrz.uni-muenchen.de</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>L&#xF6;scher</surname>
            <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>Loescher@lrz.uni-muenchen.de</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Division of Infectious Diseases and Tropical Medicine, Medical Center of the University of Munich, Leopoldstr. 5, 80802 Munich, Germany</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <fpage>206</fpage>
      <lpage>206</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 Kroidl et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Kroidl et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/14/206"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>The prevalence of Old World Cutaneous Leishmaniasis in the Mediterranean region is increasing and in Southern Europe often caused by <italic>Leishmania infantum.</italic> Spontaneous healing of cutaneous leishmaniasis is commonly observed, especially if caused by <italic>L. major,</italic> whereas <italic>L. infantum</italic> associated lesions have been reported with longer disease duration and decreased tendency for self-limitation, however, available information is sparse.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>We report the case of an otherwise healthy woman from Southern Spain who presented with a seven years persistent, non-healing, painless, central ulcerated, nodular cutaneous lesion with a diameter of 2&#xA0;cm of the forearm. Cutaneous leishmaniasis was diagnosed by smear and histology, showing large amounts of leishmania amastigotes in subepidermal histiocytes and extensive lymphocyte and plasma cell inflammation. <italic>L. infantum</italic> as the causative pathogen was confirmed by restriction fragment length polymorphism and microsatellite-PCR. Systemic or visceral involvement was excluded by negative leishmania serology and clinical presentation, relevant concomitant diseases or immunosuppression were excluded including quantification of immunoglobulin levels and lymphocyte phenotyping. Topical and systemic anti-infectious treatment options, often limited in terms of efficacy, tolerability and long lasting treatment duration, were considered. Treatment was successfully performed by surgical extraction in local anaesthesia only.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>To our knowledge this is the longest reported duration of a <italic>L. infantum</italic> associated cutaneous leishmaniasis indicating a potential long lasting natural evolution of the disease in an otherwise healthy and immunocompetent patient, however, high parasite density may have reflected a lack of a <italic>L. infantum</italic> specific immune response. Complete surgical extraction can be successfully performed as treatment.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Cutaneous leishmaniasis</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>surgical treatment</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>The prevalence of cutaneous leishmaniasis (CL) in the Mediterranean region is increasing and the variety of causative leishmania species is diversifying possibly due to worldwide travel and migration, increase of animal reservoirs, and climate change favouring the spread of the phlebotomine sandfly vectors
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Mediterranean Old World CL (OWCL) can be caused by three different Leishmania species. In Europe, CL is usually associated with zoonotic <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic> infection with domestic dogs as a main reservoir. CL caused by anthroponotic <italic>L. tropica</italic> is common in Western and Southern Asia and has been reported from Greece but not from other parts of Europe
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. <italic>L. major</italic> infection has a zoonotic reservoir in rodents and is absent in Europe but a common cause of OWCL in North Africa, Middle East and some regions in Subsaharan Africa
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. High prevalence rates of <italic>L. infantum</italic> in asymptomatic human carriers from Southern Europe indicate that the disease might be of greater public health relevance
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] as <italic>L. infantum</italic> can also lead to life threatening visceral leishmaniasis (VL) especially in individuals with underlying immunosuppression such as patients with HIV infection. Spontaneous healing of OWCL is commonly observed after several months, especially if caused by <italic>L. major</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], and has been associated in animal models with the development of specific T helper cell Th1 immune responses
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. <italic>L. infantum</italic> associated OWCL seems to have longer disease duration associated with a decreased tendency for self-limitation, however, available information is sparse.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>We report the case of a 35&#xA0;year-old female who presented in January 2013 with a single painless, erythematous, central ulcerated, nodular lesion with a diameter of approximately 2&#xA0;cm on her left forearm (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>a). The patient has a Moroccan family background, but was born and grew up in Germany, and moved in 2006 to the region of Granada in Spain. Within the same year a cutaneous lesion started to appear as an erythematous spot which developed over the following seven years to the current presentation in the absence of systemic symptoms such as fever, weight loss or fatigue. Various topical treatments were without significant effect, swab cultures from the ulcer showed only bacteria of the normal skin flora. We could confirm the diagnosis of OWCL from a small biopsy sample by positive smears (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>b), and histology revealed large amounts of leishmania amastigotes in subepidermal histiocytes and extensive lymphocyte and plasma cell inflammation (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>c and d). PCR diagnostic showed a restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) pattern of <italic>L. donovani/L. infantum complex</italic> in an in-house assay
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Further differentiation was performed at a German reference center (Dr. Gabriele Sch&#xF6;nian, Institute of Microbiology and Hygiene, Humboldt University, Charit&#xE9;, Berlin) using microsatellite-PCR (Marker LIST7039)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] confirming <italic>L. infantum</italic> as the causative pathogen. Systemic involvement or visceral leishmaniasis was excluded by negative serological markers (ELISA, IFT, immunoblot) using <italic>L. infantum</italic> as antigen, absence of systemic clinical symptoms including absence of lymphadenopathy or hepatosplenomegaly in ultrasound diagnostic. Concomitant disease or immunosuppression were excluded by laboratory parameters including normal values for haematology, clinical organ chemistry, plasma protein and quantitative immunoglobulin levels, normal absolute and relative values in lymphocyte phenotyping for T-cell, B-cell and NK cell populations, negative serological testing for HIV, syphilis, hepatitis B and C. No other skin lesions were present, sandfly exposure and family history of similar lesions was not obtained. Although, the patient regularly travelled to Morocco the infection was probably acquired in Spain since the last travel to Morocco had been more than 1&#xA0;year before onset</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Clinical presentation and histology of the </bold><bold><italic>Leishmania </italic></bold><bold>lesion. (a)</bold> Ulcerated, nodular lesion on the left forearm, <bold>(b)</bold> Leishmania amastigotes in a biopsy smear (Giemsa stain), <bold>(c)</bold> excised ulcer with subepidermal lymphocyte and plasma cell inflammation (HE stain), <bold>(d)</bold> large amounts of Leishmania amastigotes in histiocytes (Giemsa stain).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1471-2334-14-206-1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>After a thorough discussion with the patient about therapeutic alternatives such as cryotherapy, topical antimony therapy, or systemic chemotherapy, it was decided to perform a total excision of the lesion in local anaesthesia, taking into consideration its small size and long duration as well as an imminent business trip of the patient. Follow-up visits after 11&#xA0;months showed complete healing with a minimal residual scar.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>This case represents to our knowledge the longest reported duration with seven years persistence of a <italic>L. infantum</italic> CL indicating a potential long lasting natural evolution of the disease in an otherwise healthy and immunocompetent patient. OWCL caused by <italic>L. major</italic> usually heal within 2&#x2013;8 months, and lesions in <italic>L. tropica</italic> infection often heal spontaneously within one year
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Cases of chronic, non-healing cutaneous or mucocutaneous leishmanisis caused by <italic>L. infantum</italic> have been reported mostly in patients with HIV or immunosuppressive treatments, or in patients with atypical clinical presentations such as relapsing CL, leishmaniasis recidivans (LR) or mucosal localizations
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. A maximum duration until spontaneous healing of up to 3&#xA0;years has been reported for typical <italic>L. infantum</italic> OWCL lesions in immunocompetent patients
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. In Turkey, Cukurova region, a CL focus initially linked to <italic>L. infantum</italic> by PCR-RFLP, transmitted by <italic>Phlebotomus tobbi</italic> was described and patients presented mostly with small, non-ulcerative lesions which lasted for at least 2&#xA0;years with only few cases of spontaneous healing
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. As in our case negative leishmania serology was seen in these patients which is probably typical for CL cases caused by <italic>L. infantum</italic>. Recently the causative <italic>Leishmania</italic> strain from this region was revealed by whole genome sequencing as a natural hybrid between <italic>L. infantum</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], indicating that diagnostic molecular methods might have some limitation for species differentiation. Unfortunately, we were not able to isolate the parasite in our case into culture for further specification and origin detection.</p>
      <p>As reviewed by Peters and Sacks
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] chronic or progressive leishmaniasis has been associated by the parasite&#x2019;s ability to evade macrophage defense mechanism such as killing by oxygen-derived free radicals, to produce defects in the induction and expression of cell-mediated immune mechanisms such as suboptimal T-cell receptor (TCR) signaling and the inability of <italic>Leishmania</italic>-infected macrophages to produce IL-12 as the main inducer of IFN-y and CD4+ T cell Th1 differentiation resulting in defected cellular immune response. Furthermore it was speculated that the regulation of adaptive immune responses by CD25&#x2009;+&#x2009;Foxp3+ T regulatory cells in the skin downregulate parasite-specific immunity allowing <italic>Leishmania</italic> species to establish chronic infection. It is speculative if such mechanism applied in our case, either caused by the host&#x2019;s local immune characteristics or special phenotypic properties of the parasite itself &#x2013; such as the hybrid strain from the Cukurova region - evading immune control. Lack of immune control in our case might be supported by high parasite density seen in histology and smear.</p>
      <p>For OWCL, several topical and systemic treatment options are available. However, all have substantial limitations in terms of efficacy and tolerability
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. For <italic>L. infantum</italic> CL there are currently no randomized, placebo-controlled treatment studies available to guide treatment decision. Small observational studies and case reports have described treatment success with intralesional antimonials, cryotherapy or oral triazole antifungals
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Other systemic treatment options such as pentavalent antimony, pentamidine, amphotericin B or miltefosine should be reserved for complex or complicated disease because of the risk of significant toxicity. In uncomplicated OWCL presenting as a single lesion of limited size (&lt;4&#xA0;cm of diameter) surgical excision has also been applied successfully
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], which was also confirmed in our case.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>AK wrote the manuscript, lead patient management, data collection, analysis and discussion of results; IK participated in data collection and discussion; GB lead diagnostic laboratory procedures, TL suggested important intellectual content, discussion of results and participated in manuscript writing and review. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Pre-publication history</title>
      <p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p>
      <p>
        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/14/206/prepub">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/14/206/prepub</ext-link>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>Dr. Gabriele Schoenian from the Institute of Microbiology and Hygiene, Humboldt University, Charit&#xE9;, Berlin for performing microsatellite-PCR leishmania diagnostics.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Antoniou</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gramiccia</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Molina</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dvorak</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Volf</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The role of indigenous phlebotomine sandflies and mammals in the spreading of leishmaniasis agents in the Mediterranean region</article-title>
          <source>Euro Surveill</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>30</issue>
          <fpage>20540</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23929183</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Berens-Riha</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fleischmann</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pratlong</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bretzel</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>von Sonnenburg</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>L&#xF6;scher</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cutaneous leishmaniasis (Leishmania tropica) in a German tourist after travel to Greece</article-title>
          <source>J Travel Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>220</fpage>
          <lpage>222</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1708-8305.2008.00291.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19538585</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mart&#xED;n-S&#xE1;nchez</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pineda</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Morillas-M&#xE1;rquez</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garc&#xED;a-Garc&#xED;a</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Acedo</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mac&#xED;as</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Detection of Leishmania infantum kinetoplast DNA in peripheral blood from asymptomatic individuals at risk for parenterally transmitted infections: relationship between polymerase chain reaction results and other Leishmania infection markers</article-title>
          <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>545</fpage>
          <lpage>548</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15155989</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bailey</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lockwood</surname>
            <given-names>DNJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cutaneous leishmaniasis</article-title>
          <source>Clin Dermatol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>211</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clindermatol.2006.05.008</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17350500</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Peters</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sacks</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Immune privilege in sites of chronic infection: Leishmania and regulatory T cells</article-title>
          <source>Immunol Rev</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>179</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-065X.2006.00432.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16972903</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Sch&#xF6;nian</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nasereddin</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schweynoch</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schallig</surname>
            <given-names>HD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Presber</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jaffe</surname>
            <given-names>CL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>PCR diagnosis and characterization of Leishmania in local and imported clinical samples</article-title>
          <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>358</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0732-8893(03)00093-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12967749</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Jamjoom</surname>
            <given-names>MB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ashford</surname>
            <given-names>RW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bates</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kemp</surname>
            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Noyes</surname>
            <given-names>HA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Towards a standard battery of microsatellite markers for the analysis of the Leishmania donovani complex</article-title>
          <source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>265</fpage>
          <lpage>270</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/000349802125000790</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12061973</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Richter</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hanus</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>H&#xE4;ussinger</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>L&#xF6;scher</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harms</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Mucosal Leishmania infantum infection</article-title>
          <source>Parasitol Res</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>959</fpage>
          <lpage>962</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-011-2356-x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21499751</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>del Giudice</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marty</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lacour</surname>
            <given-names>JP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Perrin</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pratlong</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Haas</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dellamonica</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Le Fichoux</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cutaneous leishmaniasis due to Leishmania infantum. Case reports and literature review</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          <lpage>198</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archderm.134.2.193</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9487211</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Svobodov&#xE1;</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alten</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Z&#xED;dkov&#xE1;</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dvor&#xE1;k</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hlavackov&#xE1;</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Myskov&#xE1;</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Seblov&#xE1;</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kasap</surname>
            <given-names>OE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Belen</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vot&#xFD;pka</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Volf</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by Leishmania infantum transmitted by Phlebotomus tobbi</article-title>
          <source>Int J Parasitol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>251</fpage>
          <lpage>256</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2008.06.016</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18761342</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Rogers</surname>
            <given-names>MB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Downing</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>BA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Imamura</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sanders</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Svobodova</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Volf</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Berriman</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cotton</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Genomic confirmation of hybridisation and recent inbreeding in a vector-isolated Leishmania population</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Genet</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>e1004092</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004092</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24453988</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Morizot</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kendjo</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mouri</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thellier</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>P&#xE9;rignon</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Foulet</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cordoliani</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bourrat</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Laffitte</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Alcaraz</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bodak</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ravel</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vray</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gr&#xF6;gl</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mazier</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Caumes</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lachaud</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buffet</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Travellers with Cutaneous Leishmaniasis Cured Without Systemic Therapy</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>370</fpage>
          <lpage>380</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cit269</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23633111</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Paniz Mondolfi</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stavropoulos</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gelanew</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Loucas</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Perez Alvarez</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Benaim</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Polsky</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schoenian</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sordillo</surname>
            <given-names>EM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Successful treatment of Old World cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by Leishmania infantum with posaconazole</article-title>
          <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>1774</fpage>
          <lpage>1776</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01498-10</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21282455</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Blum</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Desjeux</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schwartz</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Beck</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hatz</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Treatment of cutaneous leishmaniasis among travellers</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>158</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkh058</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14729756</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Azab</surname>
            <given-names>AS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kamal</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>el-Haggar</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Metawaa</surname>
            <given-names>BA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hindawy</surname>
            <given-names>DS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Early surgical treatment of cutaneous leishmaniasis</article-title>
          <source>J Dermatol Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1007</fpage>
          <lpage>1012</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6358304</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
