<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Res Notes</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Res Notes</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Research Notes</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1756-0500</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24405901</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3892063</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1756-0500-7-21</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-0500-7-21</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus enterocolitis sequentially complicated with septic arthritis: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Ogawa</surname>
            <given-names>Yukari</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>apres_midi.1126@i.softbank.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Saraya</surname>
            <given-names>Takeshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>sara@yd5.so-net.ne.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Koide</surname>
            <given-names>Takashi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>takuzoh7-pip33.com@docomo.ne.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Kikuchi</surname>
            <given-names>Ken</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>kikuti@juntendo.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Ohkuma</surname>
            <given-names>Kosuke</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>kobu0805@i.softbank.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Araki</surname>
            <given-names>Koji</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>arakik@ks.kyorin-u.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>Makino</surname>
            <given-names>Hiroshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>makinonpsa@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8">
          <name>
            <surname>Yonetani</surname>
            <given-names>Shota</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>yonekyon0613@msn.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9">
          <name>
            <surname>Takizawa</surname>
            <given-names>Hajime</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>hajime@ks.kyorin-u.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A10">
          <name>
            <surname>Goto</surname>
            <given-names>Hajime</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>h510@ks.kyorin-u.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Kyorin University School of Medicine, 6-20-2 Shinkawa, Mitaka, Tokyo 181-8611, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Infection Control Science, Faculty of Medicine, Juntendo University, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Kyorin University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>9</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <fpage>21</fpage>
      <lpage>21</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 Ogawa et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Ogawa et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1756-0500/7/21"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Although most reports describing patients infected with methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> enterocolitis have been published in Japan, this concept remains a matter of debate and diagnostic criteria have not yet been defined.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>The general status of a 74-year-old Japanese man referred to our hospital (day 1) with severe community-acquired pneumococcal pneumonia gradually improved with antibiotic therapy. Thereafter, up to 4&#xA0;L/day of acute watery diarrhea that started on day 19 was refractory to metronidazole but responded immediately to oral vancomycin. Gram staining stool samples was positive for abundant fecal leukocytes from which dominant methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (10<sup>4</sup>&#xA0;CFU/mL) were isolated, suggesting methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> enterocolitis. High fever with methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteremia was evident at day 30, and suppurative right hip arthritis developed around day 71. All methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains isolated from stools, blood and aspirated synovial fluid separated in the same manner <italic>on p</italic>ulsed-field gel electrophoresis, <italic>as well as two other strains isolated from sputum,</italic> belonged to the same clone as sequence type (ST) 764 (complex clonal 5), and carried SCC<italic>mec</italic> type II.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The clinical, microbiological and molecular biological findings of this patient indicated methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> enterocolitis that led to septic methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> arthritis.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></kwd>
        <kwd>Fecal leukocytes</kwd>
        <kwd>Multilocus sequence typing</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>We describe a 74-year-old man who was diagnosed with methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) enterocolitis that subsequently caused septic arthritis. We reviewed reports of MRSA enterocolitis published in Japan over the past 10 years and characterized the clinical features of MRSA enterocolitis. Here, we discuss the clinical significance of staphylococcal enterotoxins (SEs) and toxic shock syndrome toxin-1 (TSST-1).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 74-year-old Japanese man was transferred to our department from a local hospital under a diagnosis of pneumonia. He had been in good health five days before transfer to our hospital, but with pyrexia and dyspnea upon effort. He had been treated with oral antihyperglycemic drugs to control type 2 diabetes mellitus five years previously. He was a carpenter who did not consume alcohol, but had a smoking history of 44 pack-years. Although he could walk unaided, he seemed very ill. His consciousness level was E4V5M6 (Glasgow coma scale), and his vital signs were: blood pressure, 90/50&#xA0;mmHg; temperature, 37.3&#xB0;C; heart rate, 86 beats per min with sinus rhythm; respiratory rate, 24 breaths per minute; and oxygen saturation, 78% with an oxygen supply of 10&#xA0;L/min delivered via a reservoir mask. He was immediately admitted to the intensive care unit (ICU). Physical findings were normal except for coarse crackles in the bilateral middle to lower lung fields. Upon admission to our hospital (day 1), a chest X-ray revealed infiltration throughout all lung fields except the left upper lung. These results together with positive findings of pneumococcal urinary antigens indicated a diagnosis of pneumococcal pneumonia (CURB 65 score was 3, which is defined as Confusion, Urea nitrogen, Respiratory rate, Blood pressure, and 65 years of age and older; pneumonia severity index was class IV). He was immediately intubated and treated with intravenous meropenem (1.5&#xA0;g/day) plus ciprofloxacin (600&#xA0;mg/day), which gradually improved his respiratory status over a period of two weeks. However, acute watery diarrhea amounting to 4&#xA0;L/day (determined by inserting a rectal tube) together with pyrexia (38&#xB0;C) was evident on day 19 (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Although stool specimens were negative for <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> toxins A and B, pseudomembranous colitis was considered and metronidazole (1&#xA0;g/day) was started via a nasogastric tube (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). However, the watery diarrhea was refractory to metronidazole, and Gram staining stool samples revealed abundant fecal leukocytes (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>), suggesting colonic membranous damage. Although colonic fiberscopy on day 22 provided limited information only as far as the sigmoid portion because the health status of the patient was unstable, definitive evidence of pseudomembranous formation other than membranous edema or hyperemia was not found. Furthermore, methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA; 10<sup>4</sup> colony forming unit/mL) was predominantly isolated from stool cultures on day 19 whereas other enteric bacterial pathogens and parasites or ova were negative, indicating MRSA enterocolitis<italic>.</italic> Vancomycin (VCM; 1&#xA0;g/day) delivered via a nasogastric tube completely resolved the watery diarrhea within a few days. However, at day 30, high fever recurred with moderate watery diarrhea (~500&#xA0;mL/day), and one of two sets of blood cultures was positive for MRSA. Thereafter, intravenous VCM (0.5&#xA0;g/day) with dose adjustment for renal dysfunction was initiated, and repeated blood cultures were negative for MRSA. The total amount of watery diarrhea excreted between days 19 and 34 was 22.43&#xA0;L and the maximum volume per 24&#xA0;h reached 3.50&#xA0;L on day 25.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Clinical course of the patient.</bold> Abbreviations: CLDM, clindamycin; CPFX, ciprofloxacin; DIV, drip infusion; LZD, linezolide; MEPM, meropenem; MRSA, methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>; MZN, metronidazole; TEIC, teicoplanin; VCM, vancomycin.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-21-1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Gram staining findings of stool cultures.</bold> Fecal leukocytes are abundant.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-21-2"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The general status of the patient gradually improved except for persistent low-grade fever, and he was able to walk unaided by day 64. Intermittent pain in the right hip joint started on day 71 after he started rehabilitation for walking (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). A physical examination revealed the obturator or psoas sign, and he was positive for the Gaenslen maneuver, suggesting inflammation at the retroperitoneal or lumbar vertebrae and/or sacroiliac joint. We explored the source of the fever and right hip joint pain using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A and B) and <sup>67</sup>gallium scintigraphy of the hip joint. T2-weighted MRI (T2WI) revealed an area of high intensity around the head of the right femur indicating fluid collection (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A). Fat-saturated T2-weighted images (T2WI) revealed another area of high intensity on the right obturator externus or adducent muscles (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B), suggesting right hip arthritis that <sup>67</sup>gallium scintigraphy confirmed as a hotspot (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>C). Joint drainage fluid collected on day 100 showed abundant leukocytes enclosed by phagocytic gram-positive cocci (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>D) that were later identified as MRSA. Pulsed-field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) showed that the MRSA strains in the samples isolated from stool (day 19), blood (day 30) and synovial fluid (day 100) were identical (Figure&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>), suggesting a hematological spread of MRSA originating from the colonic membrane damaged by MRSA enterocolitis. The PFGE profiles of two strains isolated from sputum on days 10 and 44 and that of a strain isolated from a catheter tip on day 20 were similar, but all three strains differed by one band from strains isolated from stool, blood and synovial fluid specimens. These strains were considered to be derived from the same clone with different subtypes according to Tenover's criteria
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], and they had the same antibiogram (VCM&#x2009;&#x2264;&#x2009;1, teicoplanin&#x2009;&#x2264;&#x2009;1, linezolide 2). These findings suggested that persistent colonized MRSA could co-evolve even in a host environment.</p>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Magnetic resonance imaging of right hip joint.</bold> T2-weighted image (T2WI) of hip joint shows high-intensity area surrounding head of right femur, indicating fluid collection <bold>(A)</bold>. Fat saturated T2WI shows high-intensity area on right obturator externus or adducent muscles <bold>(B)</bold> that appears as a hotspot on gallium scintigram <bold>(C)</bold>. Synovial fluid contains abundant leukocytes that are phagocytically engulfed by gram-positive cocci <bold>(D)</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-21-3"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Analysis of identified methicillin-resistant</bold>&#xA0;<bold><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></bold>&#xA0;<bold>strains on pulsed-field gel electrophoresis.</bold> M, marker; 1, sputum (day 10); 2, stool (day 19); 3, intravenous hyperalimentation catheter (day 20); 4, blood (day 30); 5, sputum (day 44); 6, hip joint synovial fluid (day 100); C, control (<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, strain NCTC 8325).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1756-0500-7-21-4"/>
      </fig>
      <p>None of the findings were consistent with the criteria for confirmed toxic shock syndrome (TSS; fever&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;38.9&#xB0;C, hypotension&#x2009;&#x2264;&#x2009;90&#xA0;mmHg), diffuse erythroderma, desquamation (unless death occurs before desquamation) and the involvement of at least three organ systems) or probable TSS (missing one characteristic for confirmed TSS)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] or pseudomembranous colitis. Thus, he was finally diagnosed with MRSA enterocolitis that subsequently caused septic arthritis in the right hip.</p>
      <p>Indeed, multilocus sequence typing confirmed that the allelic profiles of the MRSA strains obtained from blood, sputum and synovial fluid on days 30, 45 and 100, respectively, were identical (Table&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), belonged to sequence type (ST) 764, clonal complex (CC) 5
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] and carried SCC<italic>mec</italic> type II. These strains carried enterotoxins G and I, but no other SEs or TSST-1. Our patient was discharged uneventfully on day 156 after completing a two-month course of oral linezolide (1200&#xA0;mg/day) with intravenous clindamycin (CLDM; 1200&#xA0;mg/day) followed by teicoplanin (400&#xA0;mg/day) with intravenous CLDM (1200&#xA0;mg/day) infusion.</p>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Toxin gene&#xA0;profiles&#xA0;and&#xA0;multilocus sequence typing of MRSA strains obtained from blood, sputum,&#xA0;and synovial fluid</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
          <colgroup>
            <col align="left"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead valign="top">
            <tr>
              <th align="left" valign="bottom">
                <bold>Source</bold>
                <hr/>
              </th>
              <th colspan="13" align="center" valign="bottom">
                <bold>Detection of toxic genes</bold>
                <hr/>
              </th>
              <th colspan="3" align="center" valign="bottom">
                <bold>SCC</bold>
                <bold>
<italic>mec</italic>
</bold>
                <hr/>
              </th>
              <th colspan="9" align="center" valign="bottom">
                <bold>MLST</bold>
                <hr/>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">&#xA0;</th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>tst</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>eta</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>etb</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>sea</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>seb</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>sec</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>sed</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>see</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>seg</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>seh</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>sei</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>sej</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>pvl</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center"><bold>
<italic>mec</italic>
</bold>&#xA0;<bold>type</bold></th>
              <th align="center"><bold>
<italic>ccr</italic>
</bold>&#xA0;<bold>type</bold></th>
              <th align="center"><bold>SCC</bold>&#xA0;<bold>
<italic>mec</italic>
</bold></th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>arcC</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>aroE</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>glpF</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>gmk</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>pta</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>tpi</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>yqil</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>ST</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>
<italic>CC</italic>
</bold>
              </th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody valign="top">
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">A. blood<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">+<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">+<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">II<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">136<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">12<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">764<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" valign="bottom">Sputum<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">+<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">+<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">II<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">136<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">12<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">764<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">Joint fluid</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">+</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">+</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">-</td>
              <td align="center">A</td>
              <td align="center">2</td>
              <td align="center">II</td>
              <td align="center">1</td>
              <td align="center">136</td>
              <td align="center">1</td>
              <td align="center">4</td>
              <td align="center">12</td>
              <td align="center">1</td>
              <td align="center">10</td>
              <td align="center">764</td>
              <td align="center">5</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <p>A: acetyltransferase, <italic>arc</italic>: carbamate kinase, <italic>aro</italic>: shikimate dehydrogenase, CC: clonal complex, <italic>ccr</italic>: cassette chromosome recombinase, <italic>eta</italic>: exfoliatin toxin a <italic>etb</italic>: exfoliatin toxin b, <italic>glp</italic>: glycerol kinase, <italic>gmk</italic>: guanylate kinase, MLST: multilocus sequence typing, <italic>pta</italic>: phosphate acetyltransferase, <italic>pvl</italic>: Panton-Valentine leukocidine, <italic>sea</italic>: staphylococcal enterotoxin a, <italic>seb</italic>: staphylococcal enterotoxin b, <italic>sec</italic>: staphylococcal enterotoxin c, <italic>sed</italic>: staphylococcal enterotoxin d, <italic>seg</italic>: staphylococcal enterotoxin g, <italic>seh</italic>: staphylococcal enterotoxin h, <italic>sei</italic>: staphylococcal enterotoxin I, <italic>sej</italic>: staphylococcal enterotoxin j, SCC<italic>mec</italic>: Staphylococcal casstte chromosmome <italic>mec,</italic> ST: sequence type, <italic>tpi</italic>: triosephosphate isomerase, <italic>yqi</italic>: acetyle coenzyme.</p>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>MRSA enterocolitis has been identified among Japanese patients since 1985, especially after undergoing gastric resection
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] or being medicated with a third-generation cephalosporin
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Although many studies of MRSA enterocolitis have proceeded in Japan, MRSA is not a frequent cause of antibiotic-associated diarrhea and this notion has remained a matter of debate, as anecdotally reported elsewhere
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Therefore, to summarize and characterize published reports of MRSA enterocolitis in Japan, we intensively reviewed studies over the past decade (Table&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>)
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. We identified 36 (male, n&#x2009;=&#x2009;28; female, n&#x2009;=&#x2009;8) patients (age range, 0 to 91 y; mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD; 59.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;21.3 y) who required a median of seven (range, 2&#x2013;40) days of antibiotics to treat MRSA enterocolitis that was mainly diagnosed from stool cultures. Two were diagnosed at autopsy (patients 1 and 3) and one each was diagnosed by colonoscopy (patient 2) and during surgery (patient 4). Importantly, SEs or TSST-1 have been assessed in only four (11.1%) patients (Nos. 1, 5, 6 and 8); two of them had enterotoxin C and all four had TSST-1. Furthermore, our review of two reports
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] found that patients No. 5 and 6 (Table&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) satisfied the criteria for TSS with typical erythema and desquamation, but the authors had diagnosed them with MRSA enterocolitis. The other two patients (Nos.1 and 8) with TSST-1 did not satisfy the criteria for TSS. None of the other patients with MRSA enterocolitis had cutaneous lesions similar to those of TSS. MRSA colitis clinically resembles TSS in many respects, such as shock, multiple organ failure and pyrexia due to MRSA bacteremia, but it should be differentiated from TSS regardless of the presence of TSST-1.</p>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Summary of methicillin-resistant</bold>&#xA0;<bold>
<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
</bold>&#xA0;<bold>enterocolitis reported in Japan over the past 10 years</bold></p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
          <colgroup>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
            <col align="center"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead valign="top">
            <tr>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Pt. No.</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Age</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Sex</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Underlying disease</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Diagnostic method</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Site of infection</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Duration* (days)</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Enterotoxin/coagulase Type/TSST-1</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Prog.</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center">
                <bold>Ref</bold>
              </th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody valign="top">
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">66<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Appendectomy<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Autopsy<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">All digestive tract<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA/II/+<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">D<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">9<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">31<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Acute pancreatitis<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture with Biopsy<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Colon<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">12<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">D<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">47<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">F<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">UTI<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Autopsy<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Small Intestine<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">D<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">7<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">73<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Esophageal Ca, Gastric CA POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Ileum interposition<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">none<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">19<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">11<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">59<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Gastric Ca<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">C/NA/+<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">12<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">6<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">23<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Infected pilonidal sinus POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">15<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">-/-/+<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">7<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">71<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Peritonitis with mediastinitis POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">18<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">14<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">8<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">72<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Panperitonitis POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A/II/+<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">15<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">9<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">26<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">F<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Tongue Ca POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">7<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">D<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">16<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">75<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">F<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Gallbladder Ca<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">D<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">8<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">11<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">64<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Pancreatitis<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">17<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">12<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">73<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">F<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Pancreatitis<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">17<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">44<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Pancreatitis<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">D<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">17<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">14<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">77<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Pneumonia<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">42<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">18<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">15<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">78<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Ileus POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">20<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">19<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">16<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">78<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">F<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Intestinal perforation POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">D<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">20<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">17<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">39<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Acute mandibular periostitis<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">8<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">21<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">18<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">60<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Lung Ca small intestine metastasis POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">7<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">22<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">19<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">84<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Pneumatosis cystoides intestinalis<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">23<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">20<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">71<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">AMI, CABG<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">24<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">21<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">73<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Sigmoid colon Ca POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">22<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">63<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Rectum Ca POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">23<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">78<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">UTI<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">24<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">91<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">F<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Pneumonia, cholecystitis<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">25<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">59<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Esophageal Ca POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Fecal properties<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">26<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">70<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">F<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Perforation of sigmoid colon Ca POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">27<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">64<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Perforation of amebic colitis POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">28<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">BA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">7<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">29<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">18<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Lymphoblastic lymphoma T-cell type<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">30<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">64<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Renal abscess<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">31<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">88<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">F<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Pneumonia<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">9<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">32<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">64<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Pancreatic Ca POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">33<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">62<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Ileus<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Fluid drainage from ileus tube<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">34<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">66<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Esophageal Ca POS<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">A<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">35<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">26<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">M<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">ALL<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">Stool culture<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">14<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">NA<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">D<hr/></td>
              <td align="center" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">36</td>
              <td align="center">47</td>
              <td align="center">M</td>
              <td align="center">Ileus</td>
              <td align="center">NA</td>
              <td align="center">NA</td>
              <td align="center">9</td>
              <td align="center">NA</td>
              <td align="center">D</td>
              <td align="center">&#xA0;</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <p>A, alive; ALL, acute lymphocytic leukemia; AMI, acute myocardial infarction; BA, bronchial asthma; Ca, carcinoma; CABG, coronary artery bypass grafting; D, dead; Duration*, duration of preceding antibiotics therapy to diagnosis of MRSA enterocolitis; NA, not available; POS, postoperative status; Prog, prognosis; Pt. No, patient number; TSST-1, toxic shock syndrome toxin-1; UTI, urinary tract infection; All patients were described in Japanese and only patients 1 to 20 have been published in English and are cited as references.</p>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Although enterotoxins (A, A and B, D
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] or C
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>], and the bicomponent leukotoxin LukE-LukD
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]) have been detected in strains associated with MRSA enterocolitis, the relevance to this disease of enterotoxins G and/or I that were recognized in our patient remains unknown. Humans are natural reservoirs of <italic>S. aureus</italic>, with intermittent colonization occurring in 30% - 50% of healthy adults
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], 10% of whom harbor this microorganism in the gastrointestinal tract
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. The ratio of nasal MRSA carriage among healthy individuals in Japan is similarly high, at 38.0%
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. In contrast, another report stated that most hospitalized geriatric patients carrying MRSA in the gastrointestinal space were treated with antibiotics
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. These facts imply that most of the reported "MRSA enterocolitis" in Japan might have been caused by preceding antibiotic use and/or presented with one of the clinical features of superantigen-derived toxic shock syndrome due to TSST-1 or undetermined effects of SEs other than those described above. In addition, colonization of MRSA in the digestive tract after antibiotic use might have been misdiagnosed in some patients as a pathogen for diarrhea of undetermined causes.</p>
      <p>Boyce <italic>et al</italic>.
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] reported that among five patients with MRSA enterocolitis in whom fecal leukocytes were examined, two were positive, like our patient. They also stated that the duration of preceding antimicrobial therapy ranged from 2 to 21 days, which is similar to that of other Japanese reports indicating a range of 2 to 42 days (Table&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Boyce <italic>et al</italic>.
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] also reported that the maximum recorded stool volume per 24&#xA0;h period ranged from 475 to 8,250&#xA0;mL in 11 patients with MRSA enterocolitis and that the total volume of stool recorded for the entire diarrheal illness ranged from 745&#xA0;mL to 38.85&#xA0;L, which was identical to that of our patient and other reports (maximum recorded stool volume per 24&#xA0;h ranged from 500&#xA0;mL to 4.0&#xA0;L from patient Nos. 9, 15, 33 and the present patient). Froberg <italic>et al</italic>.
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] reported that MRSA enterocolitis features loosely adherent pseudomembranes in the small intestine, whereas <italic>C. difficile</italic> pseudomembranous colitis locates in the colon where pseudomembranes are tightly adherent. Indeed, the sites of inflammation in patients 1, 2, 3 and 4 in our review comprised the gastric wall (patient 1 at autopsy), small intestine (patient 3 at autopsy; patient 4 by biopsy), or colon (patient 2, by biopsy), indicating that the preferred site of MRSA enterocolitis is the small intestine. Cultured samples from all four patients were positive for MRSA, but only patients 3 and 4 had white pseudomembranes at the small intestine that were MRSA-positive. Although pathological information is scant, MRSA enterocolitis can involve not only the small intestine, but also the colon (Table&#xA0;
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p>
      <p>Colonic fiberscopy indicated that our patient had no apparent pseudomembranes up to the sigmoid portion. Nonetheless, MRSA enterocolitis was the most likely source of the massive diarrhea because <italic>C. difficile</italic> toxin A/B was negative, MRSA was the dominant organism isolated from abundant fecal leukocytes, the watery diarrhea was refractory to metronidazole but susceptible to oral VCM and suppurative MRSA arthritis of the right hip joint occurred after the watery diarrhea or transient MRSA bacteremia were identified. Watanabe <italic>et al</italic>.
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>] found identical (69.2%) or similar (23.1%) PFGE profiles in 12 of 13 samples obtained from the respiratory tract (nasal cavity and/or pharynx and/or sputum) and stool samples from patients infected with MRSA. They speculated that one cause of enterocolitis could be MRSA that originated from colonization of the respiratory tract and was absorbed into the digestive tract. A single genetic event in MRSA strains colonizing the respiratory tract might generate a new MRSA strain that could cause enterocolitis, septicemia and septic arthritis. As the toxin gene profiles among strains from blood, synovial fluid and sputum were identical on MLST (SCC<italic>mec</italic> type II, ST764, CC5), whether or not a single minor genetic change could alter virulence remains uncertain. Further studies are required to clarify the reason for the change in virulence.</p>
      <p>The MRSA strain derived from stool cultures did not thrive. Thus, we could not perform MLST after obtaining convincing PFGE results. Nevertheless, we postulate that our patient had MRSA enterocolitis that was sequentially complicated with septic arthritis. The relationship between MRSA enterocolitis and SEs or TSST-1 together with pathological assessments that could improve understanding of the pathological process involved in MRSA enterocolitis require further exploration.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Any MRSA isolated from patients with diarrhea that is refractory to treatment should be assessed from a multidisciplinary viewpoint considering colonization or pathogens. Our review of published reports suggests that the clinical features MRSA enterocolitis mimic those of TSS, which might reflect undetermined effects of SEs or TSST-1 associated with MRSA infection.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this Case Report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>CC: Clonal complex; CLDM: Clindamycin; Luk: Leukocidin; MLST: Multilocus sequence typing; MRI: Magnetic resonance imaging; MRSA: Methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>; PFGE: Pulsed-field gel electrophoresis; SEs: Staphylococcal enterotoxins; ST: Sequence typing; TSST-1: Toxic shock syndrome toxin-1; VCM: Vancomycin.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>YO, TS, TK, and KO mainly managed the patient. YO, TS, HT, and HG wrote the manuscript. KK, KA, SY, and HM performed microbiological analyses. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tenover</surname>
            <given-names>FC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arbeit</surname>
            <given-names>RD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Goering</surname>
            <given-names>RV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mickelsen</surname>
            <given-names>PA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murray</surname>
            <given-names>BE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Persing</surname>
            <given-names>DH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Swaminathan</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Interpreting chromosomal DNA restriction patterns produced by pulsed-field gel electrophoresis: criteria for bacterial strain typing</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>2233</fpage>
          <lpage>2239</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7494007</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title>Case definitions for infectious conditions under public health surveillance. Centers for disease control and prevention</article-title>
          <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>RR-10</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9148133">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9148133</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
          <source>Multi Locus Sequence Typing home page</source>
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mlst.net/">http://www.mlst.net/</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Morita</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tani</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Adachi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kawai</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) enteritis associated with prophylactic cephalosporin administration and hypochlorhydria, after subtotal gastrectomy</article-title>
          <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>791</fpage>
          <lpage>792</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2039012</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hori</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yura</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shinagawa</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sakurai</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mashita</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mizuno</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Postoperative enterocolitis and current status of MRSA enterocolitis&#x2013;the result of a questionnaire survey in Japan</article-title>
          <source>Kansenshogaku Zasshi</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>701</fpage>
          <lpage>707</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2614102</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Boyce</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Havill</surname>
            <given-names>NL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Nosocomial antibiotic-associated diarrhea associated with enterotoxin-producing strains of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
          <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1828</fpage>
          <lpage>1834</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1572-0241.2005.41510.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16086721</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Fujita</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Honda</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kurihara</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ohba</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Okimoto</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of pseudomembranous enterocolitis caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
          <source>J J A Inf D</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>905</fpage>
          <lpage>909</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ohkouchi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gomi</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tokue</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kikuchi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fujimura</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nukiwa</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Sepsis caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) without effects of vancomycin (VCM), teicoplanin (TEIC) and arbekacin (ABK) treated successfully and safely with intravenous administration of linezolid (LZD)</article-title>
          <source>Jpn J Chemother</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>787</fpage>
          <lpage>792</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tei</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ikeda</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kitada</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimano</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Whole digestive tract infection caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus after appendectomy</article-title>
          <source>J Jpn Surg Assoc </source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1739</fpage>
          <lpage>1743</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3919/jjsa.67.1739</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hamada</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Imaizumi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kikuchi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nishimaki</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kida</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sunakawa</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Souma</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saigenji</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matsubara</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yago</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Continuous regional arterial infusion therapy with biapenem and nafamostat mesilate for severe acute pancreatitis</article-title>
          <source>J Jpn Pancreas Sci</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>578</fpage>
          <lpage>586</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2958/suizo.23.578</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kitahara</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakamura</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iwahashi</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakamori</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ojima</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamaue</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of pseudomembranous enterocolitis caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus in the interposed ileum after esophagectomy</article-title>
          <source>J Jpn Surg Assoc </source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>2524</fpage>
          <lpage>2529</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3919/jjsa.72.2524</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of toxic shock syndrome(TSS) induced by MRSA in post operation period of gastric cancer</article-title>
          <source>Niigata Igakkai Zasshi</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>123</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hayashi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoshizawa</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murayama</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Two cases of toxic shock syndrome treated by blood purification therapy</article-title>
          <source>J Jpn Sci Surg Infect </source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>167</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Higuchi</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ota</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kajiyama</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yazawa</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Uemura</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakamura</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of surgical drainage in post coronary artery bypass grafting complicated with diffusing peritonitis and mediastinitis</article-title>
          <source>J Abdom Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>561</fpage>
          <lpage>565</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Higuchi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Otsuka</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ito</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kawasaki</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fujiwara</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kashiwada</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hayakawa</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Asahi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Saito</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of MRSA enteritis with idiopathic perforation of the sigmoid colon</article-title>
          <source>J Jpn Sci Surg Infect</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Yanagi</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kubota</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matsui</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kadokura</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hanaoka</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Enterocolitis caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) after bilateral neck dissection</article-title>
          <source>Practica Otologica</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>409</fpage>
          <lpage>412</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5631/jibirin.95.409</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mizumoto</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hitani</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Akashi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sasaki</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kurokawa</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Okano</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Taniguchi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takami</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Umeshita</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of gallbladder cancer with duplication of common bile duct and anomalous junction of pancreaticobiliary duct</article-title>
          <source>Jpn J Gastroenterol Surg</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>378</fpage>
          <lpage>382</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5833/jjgs.36.378</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Uchida</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Furukawa</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matsushita</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aimoto</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakamura</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Katsuno</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chou</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tajiri</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The significance of intestine and bacterial translocation in severe acute pancreatitis</article-title>
          <source>The Journal of the Japanese Society of Clinical Studies on Intestinal Microflora</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hatakeyama</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Inomata</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of MRSA enterocolitis occurred after ileus operation</article-title>
          <source>J Jpn Coll Surg</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>882</fpage>
          <lpage>884</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hashimoto</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sakashita</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takamura</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iwako</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shigemoto</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kin</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Massive rectroperitoneal emphysema caused by the stercoral perforation of the sigmoid colon</article-title>
          <source>Jpn J Gastroenterol Surg</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>566</fpage>
          <lpage>570</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5833/jjgs.38.566</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Nishizawa</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Terasaka</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hirai</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kuga</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of shock and DIC because of MRSA enteritis during the medical treatment of odontogenic infection</article-title>
          <source>Ky&#x16B;sh&#x16B; Shika Gakkai Zasshi</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Miyake</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shimizu</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sonoda</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mekata</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murata</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tani</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of intestinal metastasis of lung cancer undedicated preoperative diagnosis</article-title>
          <source>J Jpn Coll Surg</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>787</fpage>
          <lpage>791</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Fujii</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takagi</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of pneumotosis cytoides intestinalis associated with MRSA enteritis</article-title>
          <source>J Jpn Coll Surg</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>3158</fpage>
          <lpage>3161</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Nakai</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakata</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A case of enterocolitis caused by methicillinresistant Staphylococcus aureus after coronary artery bypass grafting</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Med Imabari Med Assoc</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Takesue</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yokoyama</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kodama</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Santou</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakamitsu</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murakami</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Imamura</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miyamoto</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Okita</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tsumura</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Toxin involvement in methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus enteritis in gastroenterological surgery</article-title>
          <source>Gastroenterol Jpn</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>716</fpage>
          <lpage>720</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1765246</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kodama</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Santo</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yokoyama</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takesue</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hiyama</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Imamura</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Murakami</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tsumura</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shinbara</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tatsumoto</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matsuura</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Postoperative enteritis caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
          <source>Surg Today</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>816</fpage>
          <lpage>825</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02385272</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9306604</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Gravet</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rondeau</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harf-Monteil</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grunenberger</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Monteil</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Scheftel</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Prevost</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Predominant Staphylococcus aureus isolated from antibiotic-associated diarrhea is clinically relevant and produces enterotoxin a and the bicomponent toxin LukE-lukD</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>4012</fpage>
          <lpage>4019</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10565923</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Casewell</surname>
            <given-names>MW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hill</surname>
            <given-names>RL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The carrier state: methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>Suppl A</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3091562</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Christie</surname>
            <given-names>CD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lynch-Ballard</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Andiman</surname>
            <given-names>WA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Staphylococcal enterocolitis revisited: cytotoxic properties of Staphylococcus aureus from a neonate with enterocolitis</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>791</fpage>
          <lpage>795</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006454-198811000-00010</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3231500</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
          <name>
            <surname>Komori</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Epidemic Study of Nasal Carriage of Methicillin-Resistant Staphylococci (MRSA and MRC-NS) in the Volunteers without Apparent Infectious Disease</article-title>
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kaken.nii.ac.jp/d/p/14570308.ja.html">http://kaken.nii.ac.jp/d/p/14570308.ja.html</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Masaki</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoshimine</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miyata</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakanishi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Degawa</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takahashi</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kuroki</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Morimoto</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kaida</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>a clinical study of gastrointestinal flora in patients with, or without MRSA colonization in the upper-respiratory tract after introduction of preventive measures of hospital infection</article-title>
          <source>Kansenshogaku Zasshi</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>1260</fpage>
          <lpage>1268</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8708406</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Froberg</surname>
            <given-names>MK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Palavecino</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dykoski</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gerding</surname>
            <given-names>DN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peterson</surname>
            <given-names>LR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Staphylococcus aureus and clostridium difficile cause distinct pseudomembranous intestinal diseases</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>747</fpage>
          <lpage>750</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/423273</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15356793</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Masaki</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Asoh</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Watanabe</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oishi</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sato</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nagatake</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Enterocolitis caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus: molecular characterization of respiratory and digestive tract isolates</article-title>
          <source>Microbiol Immunol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>629</fpage>
          <lpage>634</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1348-0421.2001.tb01295.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11694074</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
