<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1422-0067</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Molecular Diversity Preservation International (MDPI)</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21340004</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3039970</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms12010627</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijms-12-00627</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>HE4 in the Differential Diagnosis of a Pelvic Mass: A Case Report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anastasi</surname>
            <given-names>Emanuela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-12-00627">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-ijms-12-00627">*</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-ijms-12-00627">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Granato</surname>
            <given-names>Teresa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-12-00627">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-ijms-12-00627">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Coppa</surname>
            <given-names>Anna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-12-00627">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Manganaro</surname>
            <given-names>Lucia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-ijms-12-00627">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Giannini</surname>
            <given-names>Giuseppe</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-12-00627">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Comploj</surname>
            <given-names>Sara</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-12-00627">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Frati</surname>
            <given-names>Luigi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-12-00627">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Midulla</surname>
            <given-names>Cecilia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-12-00627">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1-ijms-12-00627"><label>1</label> Department of Molecular Medicine, Sapienza University, Rome 00161, Italy; E-Mails: <email>scomploj@yahoo.it</email> (S.C.); <email>luigi.frati@uniroma1.it</email> (L.F.); <email>cecilia.midulla@uniroma1.it</email> (C.M.)</aff>
      <aff id="af2-ijms-12-00627"><label>2</label> CNR IBPM, Consiglio Nazionale Ricerche, Rome 00161, Italy; E-Mail: <email>teresa.granato@uniroma1.it</email></aff>
      <aff id="af3-ijms-12-00627"><label>3</label> Department of Experimental Medicine, Sapienza University, Rome 00161, Italy; E-Mails: <email>anna.coppa@uniroma1.it</email> (A.C.); <email>giuseppe.giannini@uniroma1.it</email> (G.G.)</aff>
      <aff id="af4-ijms-12-00627"><label>4</label> Department of Radiological Sciences, Sapienza University, Rome 00161, Italy; E-Mail: <email>lucia.manganaro@uniroma1.it</email></aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1-ijms-12-00627"><sup>*</sup>Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: <email>emanuela.anastasi@uniroma1.it</email>; Tel.: +39-0649970556; Fax: +39-0649978381.</corresp>
        <fn id="fn1-ijms-12-00627">
          <label>&#x2020;</label>
          <p>These authors equally contributed to this work.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>627</fpage>
      <lpage>632</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2011 by the authors; licensee Molecular Diversity Preservation International, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This article is an open-access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neoplasms of the ovary present an increasing challenge to the physician. Neoplastic ovarian cysts can resemble endometriomas in ultrasound imaging and need to be carefully considered in the differential diagnosis. We report the case of a woman with a strong family history of hereditary breast and ovarian cancer, who presented with a pelvic mass. The young girl refused oncogenetic counseling and genetic testing, even though she had a 50% <italic>a priori</italic> probability of being a BRCA1 mutation carrier. Pelvic magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and a comparative analysis of the serum concentration of HE-4 and CA125 biomarkers provided accuracy and sensitivity in the diagnosis of a benign ovarian pathology. Based on this experience, we propose that the sensitivity of a screening program based on a HE4 and CA125 assay and MRI in high risk patients with mutations in the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes may be considered a useful pre-operative tool for the differential diagnosis of pelvic masses.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>HE4 tumor marker</kwd>
        <kwd>high-risk patients</kwd>
        <kwd>ovarian cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>endometriosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <p>Ovarian cancer (OC) is the second most common form of gynecological cancer and the first cause of death from gynecological malignancy in the western hemisphere. Epidemiologic studies have clearly established the role of family history as an important risk factor for OC and inherited, highly penetrant germline mutations of the BRCA1 and BRCA2 oncosuppressor genes are responsible for 5&#x2013;10% of the OC cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1-ijms-12-00627">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ijms-12-00627">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>OC is often diagnosed at an advanced stage due to the absence of early symptoms and to the inadequacy of available screening methods, resulting in a low survival rate. The median survival period ranges from 18 to 24 months with an 80% probability of disease recurrence within five years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ijms-12-00627">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Validation of novel biomarkers might help improving the specificity and sensitivity of ovarian cancer diagnosis. In example, studies on the <italic>Human epididymis specific protein</italic> 4 (HE4) alone or in combination with CA125 are being extensively carried out [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ijms-12-00627">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-ijms-12-00627">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Recently, we have shown that not only HE4 is expressed in the early stages of the disease, but it is also an early indicator of disease recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-ijms-12-00627">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>In this case report, we applied the determination of serum concentrations of HE4 and CA 125 to the diagnosis of a pelvic mass that appeared in a young patient at high-risk for ovarian cancer due to her family history of breast cancer associated to a pathogenic BRCA1 gene mutation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>2. Case Presentation and Discussion</title>
      <p>A 24-year-old woman with a strong family history of breast cancer, and potentially at risk for breast and ovarian cancer due to a BRCA1 gene mutation (Q139X, Exon 7) discovered in her relatives (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijms-12-00627">Figure 1</xref>), presented to our institution with a painful pelvic mass, with cyclic exacerbations during menses.</p>
      <p>Transabdominal and transvaginal pelvic ultrasound, with the aid of a color Doppler imaging using a high-frequency probe (7.5 MHz), was performed for the diagnosis of a unilateral adnexal mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-ijms-12-00627">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>The ultrasonographic features showed cystic structures with low level internal echoes and echogenic wall foci, thickened walls and septations, and percystic color Doppler flow.</p>
      <p>Despite the risk of being a mutation carrier due to the presence of the BRCA1 mutation in her mother (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijms-12-00627">Figure 1</xref>), the young girl refused oncogenetic counseling and genetic testing. Informed of the possible diagnostic strategies, the girl also refused laparoscopic surgery.</p>
      <p>Therefore, in order to improve diagnostic accuracy, we suggested pelvic magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-ijms-12-00627">Figures 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-ijms-12-00627">4</xref>) and determination of the serum concentrations of CA125 and HE4 biomarkers.</p>
      <p>Single-shot and high-spatial-resolution with or without fat-suppressed T1 and T2 weighted sequences were performed with a 1.5T Siemens Avanto instrument, which showed several 3 cm cysts in the left ovary. They showed a hyperintense signal in the T2-weighted images for the presence of a fluid-fluid level and a strong hyperintense signal in the fat suppressed T1-weighted images, typical of endometriomas. Furthermore, similar signal characteristics were present in a thin area observed in the posterior uterine wall, referred to as an endometrial implant. In the lower part of the cysts, the hypointense T2-weighted images were referred to as blood clots.</p>
      <p>Serum concentrations of CA125 and HE4 were analyzed by ELISA and, according to the manufacturer&#x2019;s indications, the upper limits for normal values were considered to be 50 pmol/L and 35 U/mL for HE4, and CA125, respectively. Serum samples were collected both at the time of the gynecologic examination and two weeks later (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1-ijms-12-00627">Table 1</xref>). Coherent with the MRI finding, the low levels of HE4 tentatively indicated a non-malignant type of lesion.</p>
      <p>This case of a young woman, potentially at genetic risk for breast and ovarian cancer because of her family history of breast cancer associated with a BRCA1 mutation, who presented with a pelvic mass of uncertain nature, exemplifies the diagnostic challenge that might occur in coping with subjects at genetic risk for this type of neoplasia.</p>
      <p>BRCA1 mutation carriers experience a significantly higher probability of developing OC compared to the general population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ijms-12-00627">2</xref>]. Although our patient had a 50% <italic>a priori</italic> probability of being a BRCA1 mutation carrier, due to presence of the familial mutation in her mother, she refused oncogenetic counseling and genetic testing, thus limiting our ability to more precisely define her individual risk. Therefore, urging the need to pose a correct diagnosis of the pelvic lesion, we approached the case by combining ultrasonography, MRI and determination of the serum levels of HE4 and CA125 biomarkers. The high and increasing levels of CA125 and the stably low levels of HE4 together with the features of the lesion from the MRI imaging suggested the occurrence of endometriosis. A laparoscopic study accepted by the patient at a later stage finally confirmed this evaluation.</p>
      <p>A noninvasive means of discriminating between malignant pelvic masses and benign lesions is important given that approximately 20% of women will develop an ovarian cyst or pelvic mass at some point in their lives. Since serum based assays are noninvasive and relatively inexpensive, it would be ideal to have a biomarker or multimarker panel with sufficient sensitivity and specificity, which are able to discern the malignant potential that significantly improves differential diagnosis of pelvic masses.</p>
      <p>Coupling these markers to techniques such as transvaginal sonography and the more expensive MRI increase the overall positive predictive value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-ijms-12-00627">10</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-ijms-12-00627">12</xref>]. Based on this experience, we propose that determination of HE4 and CA125 serum concentrations together with pelvic ultrasonography and MRI may represent a diagnostic strategy for the early diagnosis of ovarian pathologies, in particular for individuals with a family history of breast/ovarian cancers associated with BRCA1/2 mutations, integrating previously defined intensified surveillance approaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2-ijms-12-00627">2</xref>]. Aware of the need to support such a proposal with prospective studies, we are planning to set a diagnostic trial to define the real cost/benefit of combining pelvic MRI and HE4 and CA125 serum determination in the standard screening of subject at high-risk for ovarian cancer, such as those with BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>3. Conclusions</title>
      <p>We conclude that the association of HE4 and CA125 serum concentration may be used to increase the accuracy in the differential diagnosis of pelvic masses in patients at high risk for ovarian neoplasias.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This study is founded by the University of Rome Sapienza. We are thankful to Giuseppina Gennarini, Valentina Viggiani, Barbara Colaprisca and Silvestra Tudini for their technical assistance.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="b1-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Russo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cal&#xF2;</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruno</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rizzo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bazan</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Fede</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hereditary ovarian cancer</article-title>
          <source>Crit. Rev. Oncol. Hematol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18656380</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Palma</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ristori</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ricevuto</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giannini</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gulino</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>BRAC1 and BRAC2: the genetic testing and the current management options for mutation carriers</article-title>
          <source>Crit. Rev. Oncol. Hematol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16337408</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schink</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Current initial therapy of stage II and IV ovarian cancer: challenges for managed care</article-title>
          <source>Sem. Oncol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hellerstrom</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hellerstron</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SMRP and HE4 as biomarkers for ovarian carcinoma when used alone and in combination with CA125 and/or each other</article-title>
          <source>Adv. Exp. Med. Biol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>622</volume>
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18546615</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kirchhoff</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular characterization of epididymal proteins</article-title>
          <source>Rev. Reprod</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>86</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9685187</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bingle</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singleton</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bingle</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The putative ovarian tumor marker gene HE4 (WFDC2), is expressed in normal tissues and undergoes complex alternative splicing to yeld multiple protein isoforms</article-title>
          <source>Oncogene</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>2768</fpage>
          <lpage>2773</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11965550</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Clauss</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lilja</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lundwall</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The evolution of a genetic locus encoding small serine proteinase inhibitors</article-title>
          <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>333</volume>
          <fpage>383</fpage>
          <lpage>389</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15950183</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anastasi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Granato</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marchei</surname>
              <given-names>GG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Viggiani</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colaprisca</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Comploj</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reale</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frati</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Midulla</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ovarian tumor marker HE4 is differently expressed during the phases of the menstrual cycle in healthy young women</article-title>
          <source>Tumor Biol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>411</fpage>
          <lpage>415</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anastasi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marchei</surname>
              <given-names>GG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Viggiani</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gennarini</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frati</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reale</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>HE4: A new potential early biomarker for the recurrence of ovarian cancer</article-title>
          <source>Tumor Biol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          <lpage>119</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chami&#xE8;</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blasbalg</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goncalves</surname>
              <given-names>MO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carvalho</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abrao</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>IS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accuracy of magnetic resonance imaging for siagnosis and preoperative assessement of deeply infiltrating endometriosis</article-title>
          <source>Int. J. Gynecol. Obstet</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>198</fpage>
          <lpage>201</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guerra</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>F&#xE9;lix</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnetic resonance evaluation of adnexal masses</article-title>
          <source>Acta Radiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>700</fpage>
          <lpage>709</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18568564</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12-ijms-12-00627">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mcintosh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnett</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goodman</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thorpe</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bergan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thornnquist</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scholler</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Briant</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drescher</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Urban</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Assessing lead time of selected ovarian cancer biomarkers. A nested case-control study</article-title>
          <source>J. Natl. Cancer Inst</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>26</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20042715</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1-ijms-12-00627" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Genealogical diagram of the family with indication of the subjects mutated and the type of cancers.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijms-12-00627f1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2-ijms-12-00627" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Transvaginal pelvic ultrasound shows cystic structures with low level internal echoes and echogenic wall foci, thickened walls and septations.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijms-12-00627f2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3-ijms-12-00627" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T2 TSE weighed sequences. Complex images in the left ovary, fluid/fluid level, hypointense images in the declive position, axially.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijms-12-00627f3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4-ijms-12-00627" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T1 VIBE weighed sequences. Marked hyperintense signal observed in the left ovary and a weakly hyperintense thin area is observed in the posterior uterine wall, referred to as an endometril implant.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijms-12-00627f4"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="t1-ijms-12-00627" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>CA125 (expressed as U/mL) and HE4 (expressed as pmol/L) levels, evaluated at a two different times (the first at the moment of the gynecologic examination and the second two weeks later).</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="box" rules="all">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample 1</th>
            <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample 2</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CA 125</bold> (U/mL)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>HE4</bold> (pmol/L)</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
