<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Otorhinolaryngologica Italica</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0392-100X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1827-675X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pacini Editore SpA</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376300</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3870447</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Series</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title xml:lang="en">Transoral robotic surgery for retromolar trigone
tumours</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="it">
          <trans-title>La chirurgia robotica transorale (TORS) nei tumori del trigono retromolare</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>DURMUS</surname>
            <given-names>K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>APUHAN</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>OZER</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, "Arthur G. James" Cancer Hospital and "Richard J. Solove" Research Institute, Comprehensive Cancer Center, The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH, USA;</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label> Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, Bolu Izzet Baysal University, Bolu, Turkey</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">Address for correspondence: Enver Ozer, Department of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, The Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center, 320 W 10th Ave. B216 Starling Loving Hall, Columbus, OH, USA 43210. Tel. 614 293 80 74. Fax 614 293 3193. E-mail: <email xlink:href="enver.ozer@osumc.edu">enver.ozer@osumc.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>33</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>425</fpage>
      <lpage>427</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Copyright by Societ&#xE0; Italiana di Otorinolaringologia e Chirurgia Cervico-Facciale</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way. For details, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>SUMMARY</title>
        <p>The retromolar trigone is a challenging transoral surgical site due to the difficulty of visualization. Our aim is to report a new technique of transoral robotic resection of retromolar trigone tumours. We present three patients with retromolar trigone tumours with pathological diagnosis of squamous cell carcinoma who underwent successful transoral robotic resection. Robotic retromolar trigone resection and concurrent supraomohyoid neck dissections were performed in all patients without any complication. In conclusion, transoral robotic surgery is a safe and feasible technique for resection of malignant retromolar trigone tumours with minimal complications and favourable outcomes.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="it">
        <title>RIASSUNTO</title>
        <p>Le difficolt&#xE0; riscontrate nella corretta esposizione del campo operatorio rendono impegnativo l'approccio transorale al trigono retromolare. Con il presente lavoro &#xE9; nostra intenzione descrivere un approccio innovativo alla resezione dei tumori interessanti il trigono retromolare, mediante chirurgia robotica transorale. Presenteremo tre casi nei quali pazienti con diagnosi di tumore del trigono retromolare ad istologia squamocellulare, sono stati sottoposti con successo ad una resezione della lesione con metodica robotica transorale. In tutti i pazienti sono stati effettuati simultaneamente, e senza registrare alcuna complicanza, sia la resezione del trigono retromolare mediante chirurgia robotica, che lo svuotamento latero cervicale sovraomoioideo. In conclusione la chirurgia robotica transorale, applicata alla resezione dei tumori maligni del trigono retromolare, &#xE9; una tecnica sicura, che offre un outcome favorevole con complicanze minime.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>KEY WORDS</title>
        <kwd>Retromolar trigone</kwd>
        <kwd>TORS</kwd>
        <kwd>Transoral robotic surgery</kwd>
        <kwd>Oral cavity</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="S1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The retromolar trigone (RMT) is the portion of the oral cavity mucosa overlying the ascending ramus of the mandible at the junction of two dental arcades behind the last molar. This region can be a challenging transoral surgical site due to the difficulty of visualization. Cancers originating in the RMT, although rare, are usually squamous cell carcinoma (SCC). On occasion minor salivary gland tumours can also originate from RMT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>. The presence of bone invasion leads to poor prognosis. Sequential therapy starting with surgery is the recommended treatment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Transoral robotic surgery (TORS) has been reported to be safe and feasible in transoral resection of laryngopharyngeal tumours <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08"><sup>8</sup></xref>. However, there has been no report related to transoral robotic RMT resection (TORRR). This report presents a new technique of TORS for RMT cancer resection.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S2">
      <title>Case series</title>
      <sec id="S2a">
        <title>Description of clinical cases</title>
        <p><italic>Case 1:</italic> a 63-year-old Caucasian male presented to a dental clinic with a persistent RMT lesion after dental extraction three months ago. He denied any symptoms other than mild left posterior oral pain. Otolaryngologic exam showed a 2.5 cm ulcerative, erythematous and granular lesion at the left retromolar trigone. Biopsy revealed SCC. He was a heavy smoker and alcohol consumer. The patient was evaluated with CT of the neck to exclude possible mandibular invasion.</p>
        <p>Final pathologic staging after TORRR demonstrated a T1N1 RMT carcinoma with perineural and lymphovascular invasion with negative surgical resection margins. He has completed adjuvant radiotherapy and is disease free at 15 months clinical follow-up.</p>
        <p><italic>Case 2:</italic> a 57-year-old Caucasian male presented to his dentist with a right-sided oral cavity mass. Food occasionally got stuck in this region, but he denied pain, bleeding, or a neck mass. Subsequent biopsy of the 2 cm granular lesion of the right RMT involving the anterior tonsillar pillar showed SCC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). He was also a heavy smoker and drinker. There was no radiological evidence of mandibular invasion in CT of the neck.</p>
        <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Fig. 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Clinical picture showing a right RMT carcinoma.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-425-g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Final pathologic staging confirmed a T1N0 carcinoma with negative surgical margins. He did not need any adjuvant treatment and is disease free at 16 months follow-up.</p>
        <p><italic>Case 3:</italic> an 80-year-old male with history of larynx cancer and previous radiation treatment presented with right sided globus sensation and intermittent pain for 6 weeks. He denied dysphagia, odynophagia or a neck mass. He was a heavy smoker and previous drinker. Physical examination showed a 3 cm ulcerative mobile lesion at the right RMT. Biopsy of the lesion showed SCC. Radiological evaluation with neck CT excluded any mandibular invasion.</p>
        <p>The patient underwent transoral robotic surgery and concurrent bilateral neck dissection. Final pathological staging confirmed T2N2b carcinoma with lymphovascular and perineural invasion. Surgical margins were negative. The patient was disease free at 1 month follow-up. All three RMT carcinoma cases were HPV negative.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S3">
      <title>Surgical technique and results</title>
      <p>Similar surgical steps were followed for all TORRR procedures. Robotic retromolar trigone resection and concurrent selective neck dissections (Levels I-IV) were performed. Standard TORS room setting was used in the surgery. After the transoral intubation a Crowe-Davis mouth gag was placed to expose RMT region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). A straight (0&#xB0;) robotic camera provided optimal exposure without necessitating the 30&#xB0; camera. 5 mm monopolar cautery and Maryland dissectors were used for resection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Mucosa and submucosa were incised deep to mandibular periosteum. The resection plane was reached and resection extended up to anterior tonsillar pillar medial to the mandibular bone. Superficial layer of tongue base muscles and the lingual nerve formed the deep margin of excision. A non-robotic marginal mandibulectomy was needed to get a safe margin for the second case only. Exposed mandibular bone after tumour removal was reconstructed and covered with local mucosal advancement flaps.</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Transoral robotic resection of the left RMT carcinoma; just after the start of the incision.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-425-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Transoral robotic resection of the left RMT carcinoma; in progress.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-425-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Transoral robotic resection of the left RMT carcinoma; excision is complete, and the specimen is free.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-33-425-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The average robotic setup time was 20 min, TORRR time was 7 min, with estimated blood loss of 20 ml for these robotic RMT resections.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Exposure and resection of RMT carcinoma is a challenge especially when it involves the posterior floor of the mouth, base of tongue, or pharynx. Traditional surgical approaches to the RMT region are transoral surgery with or without laser for early stage and open transfacial/transcervical approaches for advanced stage disease. Minimally- invasive procedures with minimal collateral tissue damage are preferred to decrease surgical morbidity, postoperative complications and improve quality of life together with a shorter hospital stay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Robotic assisted surgeries have been popularized more in other surgical fields like gynaecology, urology and cardiac surgery before it was used in the head and neck area in the last four to five years <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04"><sup>4</sup></xref>. Compared to conventional surgical techniques, a robotic transoral approach offers potential advantages. The primary advantage of this approach is decreased surgical morbidity for patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Robotic optics gives magnified three-dimensional visualization with the option of angled camera. Tissue dissection with TORS avoids external incision while respecting the uninvolved tissues that would otherwise be involved in open surgical approaches.</p>
      <p>TORS is shown to be feasible and safe procedure with minimal complications and blood loss <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08"><sup>8</sup></xref>. Advantages of TORS over transoral laser surgery include wide, angled and more comprehensive visualization of the surgical field and significantly shorter operative time. Robotic RMT resections take only 7 min to complete. The only disadvantage of the current robotic tools is the need of a bone resecting robotic arm in the event of bone invasion.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S5">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>TORRR is a feasible, safe and effective procedure with minimal complications and favourable outcomes for the resection of benign and malignant tumours of the RMT. This procedure may be useful in patients where optimal visualization of the RMT lesion is not possible with the naked eye or a straight microscopic view.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ayad</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xE9;linas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guertin</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Retromolar trigone carcinoma
treated by primary radiation therapy: an alternative to the primary surgical approach</article-title>
          <source>Arch Otolaryngol Head
Neck Surg</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>131</volume>
          <fpage>576</fpage>
          <lpage>582</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16027279</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsang</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>KP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment of squamous
cell carcinoma of the retromolar trigone</article-title>
          <source>Laryngoscope</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>916</fpage>
          <lpage>920</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16735888</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsai</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cancer of retromolar
trigone: long-term radiation therapy outcome</article-title>
          <source>Head Neck</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>758</fpage>
          <lpage>763</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11505486</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dallan</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castelnuovo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vicini</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The natural evolution
of endoscopic approaches in skull base surgery: robotic assisted
surgery?</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>390</fpage>
          <lpage>394</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22323850</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weinstein</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O'Malley</surname>
              <given-names>BW</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snyder</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transoral
robotic surgery: radical tonsillectomy</article-title>
          <source>Arch Otolaryngol
Head Neck Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>1220</fpage>
          <lpage>1226</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18086963</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hurtuk</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teknos</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozer</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Robotic-assisted lingual tonsillectomy</article-title>
          <source>Laryngoscope</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>121</volume>
          <fpage>1480</fpage>
          <lpage>1482</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21647894</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mercante</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruscito</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pellini</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transoral Robotic
Surgery (TORS) for tongue base tumors</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol
Ital</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>230</fpage>
          <lpage>235</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24043909</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pellini</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mercante</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruscito</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ectopic lingual goiter
treated by transoral robotic surgery</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol
Ital</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>343</fpage>
          <lpage>346</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227901</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
