<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An. bras. dermatol.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais brasileiros de dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23197217</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3699915</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0365-05962012000600019</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Imaging In Dermatology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dermoscopic clues in the diagnosis of amelanotic and hypomelanotic
malignant melanoma<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></sup></article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Pistas dermatosc&#xF3;picas no diagn&#xF3;stico de melanoma maligno
amelan&#xF3;tico e hipomelan&#xF3;tico</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Steglich</surname>
            <given-names>Raquel Bissacotti</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meotti</surname>
            <given-names>Carolina Degeon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ferreira</surname>
            <given-names>Mariana Silveira</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lovatto</surname>
            <given-names>Louise</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Carvalho</surname>
            <given-names>Andr&#xE9; Vicente Esteves</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Castro</surname>
            <given-names>Carlos Gustavo Carneiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff05">5</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label>M.D., Dermatologist. Member of the Brazilian Society of Dermatology -
Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label>Medical student. - Medical student at the Federal University of Rio
Grande do Sul (UFRGS) - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label>Master of Medical Clinical Sciences, University of Barcelona, Spain. -
Dermatologist at the Irmandade da Santa Casa de Miseric&#xF3;rdia de Porto Alegre
(ISCMPA) - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label>Masters Degree in Pathology - Federal University of Health Sciences of
Porto Alegre (UFCSPA) - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil. - Dermatology preceptor at the
Irmandade da Santa Casa de Miseric&#xF3;rdia de Porto Alegre (ISCMPA) - Porto Alegre
(RS), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff05"><label>5</label>Medical Doctor - Specialist in Dermatology - Private practice - Rio de
Janeiro (RJ), Brazil</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing address:</bold> Raquel Bissacotti Steglich, Irmandade da Santa Casa de
Miseric&#xF3;rdia de Porto Alegre, Rua Professor Annes Dias, 295, 90020-090 - Porto
Alegre, RS, E-mail: <email>raquelsteglich@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>87</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>920</fpage>
      <lpage>923</lpage>
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.anaisdedermatologia.org.br">http://www.anaisdedermatologia.org.br</ext-link>
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/abd">http://www.scielo.br/abd</ext-link>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2012 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The clinical identification of amelanotic malignant melanoma (AMM) and hypomelanotic
malignant melanoma (HMM) becomes difficult due to the lack of pigmentation and to the
diverse clinical presentations. Dermoscopy is very useful in these cases, increasing
the level of suspicion of malignancy. We report 4 cases of amelanotic malignant
melanoma and hypomelanotic malignant melanoma with characteristic dermoscopic
findings. Dermoscopy under polarized light demonstrates vascular polymorphism,
globules and milky-red areas, in addition to chrysalis and multiple blue-gray
dots.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>A identifica&#xE7;&#xE3;o cl&#xED;nica de melanoma maligno amelan&#xF3;tico e
hipomelan&#xF3;tico torna-se dif&#xED;cil devido &#xE0; falta de
pigmenta&#xE7;&#xE3;o e &#xE0;s diversas apresenta&#xE7;&#xF5;es desse tipo
de tumor. A dermatoscopia &#xE9; muito &#xFA;til nestes casos, aumentando o grau
de suspei&#xE7;&#xE3;o de malignidade. Relatamos 4 casos de melanoma maligno
amelan&#xF3;tico e melanoma maligno hipomelan&#xF3;tico com achados
dermatosc&#xF3;picos caracter&#xED;sticos. A dermatoscopia com luz polarizada
demonstra polimorfismo vascular, gl&#xF3;bulos e &#xE1;reas vermelholeitosas,
assim como cris&#xE1;lides e m&#xFA;ltiplos pontos azul-acinzentados.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Dermoscopy</kwd>
        <kwd>Diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Diagnosis, differential</kwd>
        <kwd>Melanoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Melanoma, amelanotic</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>The incidence of cutaneous melanoma has increased considerably during the last decades
in the whole world.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref></sup> Its aggressive behavior and the difficulty to treat in advanced stages makes
early diagnosis crucial.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>AMM and HMM lesions represent approximately 2 to 8 % of all melanomas, presenting
without or with little pigmentation, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup> The scarcity of pigmentation makes these type of tumor hard to identify, making
clinical diagnosis difficult. Dermoscopy is a major instrument allowing the evaluation
of pigment, and above all determining characteristic vascular structures, unseen by
naked eye.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> Such vascular patterns have an important role on the suspicion of melanoma in
doubtful nonpigmented lesions. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORTS</title>
      <p>
<bold>Patient 1: </bold>A 55-year-old female shows an infiltrated, pseudo-vesicular
plaque with well defined borders, 2 X 1,5cm of diameter, on the proximal region of the
left arm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>). Small erythematous papules
are seen on the periphery of the lesion. Dermoscopy under polarized light (DPL):
chrysalis, linear-irregular vessels, globules and milky-red areas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">3</xref>).
Histopathology: nodular AMM, Breslow 11,0 mm, Clark V, with epidermotropic melanoma
metastasis. Simultaneously, presents basal cell carcinoma (BCC) on the frontal region. </p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous plaque with an irregular surface on the left arm with satellite small
papules</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-87-0920-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Dermoscopic image shows linear-irregular vessels (square), milky-red areas
(asterisk) and globules (arrows)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-87-0920-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Dermoscopic evaluation revealing chrysalis (arrows)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-87-0920-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <p>
<bold>Patient 2:</bold> A 63-year-old male with a history of BCC and squamous cell
carcinoma (SCC) in the past presents with an erythematous papule with a bright and
smooth surface on the left flank (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4A</xref>). DPL:
milky-red areas and globules, linear-irregular vessels and residual blue pigmentation
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4B</xref>). The contact dermoscopic exam shows
disappearance of the central pinkish area and consequent white structureless area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4C</xref>). Histopathology: nodular HMM, Breslow 2,5
mm, Clark IV. BCC and SCC on the trunk. </p>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>(A)</bold> Erythematous papule on the left flank. <bold>(B) </bold>Vascular
polymorphism and residual pigmentation at dermoscopy. <bold>(C)</bold> Dermoscopic
examination shows vascular polymorphism (square), blue residual pigmentation
(asterisk) and milky-red areas (arrow)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-87-0920-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <p>
<bold>Patient 3:</bold> A 65-year-old male with history of previous melanoma and BCC
presents with an erythematous plaque, 1,0 cm in diameter, on the left scapular region.
DPL: milky-red areas, central depigmentation, peripheral brown structureless area,
dotted and linear-irregular vessels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Figure 5</xref>).
Histopathology: superficial spread HMM on vertical growing stage, Breslow 1,16 mm ,
Clark IV. </p>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>(A)</bold> Erythematous plaque on the left scapular region. <bold>(B)</bold>
Milky red areas (arrows), central depigmentation, brown structureless area at the
periphery (asterisk), linear-irregular vessels (circle) and dotted vessels
(square)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-87-0920-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <p>
<bold>Patient 4:</bold> A 63-year-old female with history of previous BCC shows on her
left thigh a 1,6 x 1,5 cm erythematous plaque, with a nodule on its inferior portion.
Dark-blue areas are seen on less than 25% of the lesion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Figure 6</xref>). DPL: milky red areas, linear irregular vessels, remaining
dark-blue pigmentation and chrysalis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f07">Figure 7</xref> and
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f08">8</xref>). Histopathology: nodular ulcerated HMM,
Breslow 3,3 mm, Clark IV. </p>
      <fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous plaque, with a nodule on its inferior portion. Some dark-blue areas
are seen on less than 25% of the lesion</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-87-0920-g06"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f07" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 7</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The non-contact dermoscopic exam shows milky red areas (asterisk), atypical
vessels (square)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-87-0920-g07"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f08" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 8</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The contact dermoscopic exam shows milky red areas (arrows), linear irregular
vessels (circle), remaining dark-blue pigmentation (asterisk) and chrysalis (bold
arrow)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-87-0920-g08"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>AMM and HMM present as primary melanomas, recurrent melanomas or metastasis of pigmented
primary melanomas. These lesions can occur without the features commonly seen in other
melanomas, such as asymmetry and altered pigmentation, often leading to misdiagnosis and
inappropriate treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup> Dermoscopic evaluation has been shown to be superior to naked eye examination for
the diagnosis of AMM and HMM.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Residual pigmentation can be seen as blue or grayish areas, pigment network and brown,
gray or black dots and globules.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup> Upon dermoscopic inspection AMM have no melanin pigmentation (light brown, dark
brown, blue, gray, black). HMM may present as partially pigmented lesions with melanin
pigmentation area of less than 25% of the total surface area; or as light-colored
lesions with only light brown, light blue, or light gray pigmentation that may occupy
more than 25% of total surface area - no dark brown, deep blue, or black pigmentation is found.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Macroscopically, AMM and HMM can be confused with BCC, SCC, Paget's disease and benign
lesions of dermatitis, pyogenic granuloma and plantar wart.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup> The reported patients had history or coexistence of BCC and/or SCC. Dermoscopic
evaluation was essential for the correct diagnostic suspicion and proper management. </p>
      <p>Vascular pattern can increase the level of suspicion of AMM and HMM and it varies
according to the level of invasion of the melanoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup> Melanoma can initially show dotted vessels and, as the thickness increases, the
vascular polymorphism increases with hairpin and linear-irregular vessels associated
with milky-red areas, reticular depigmentation and chrysalis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup> Such vascular patterns can only be accurately determined through dermoscopic
examination of the lesions. Considering the reported cases on this article, the only
cases that presented chrysalis were the patients 1 and 4, who presented the thickest
tumors (Breslow 11,0 mm and 3,3 mm). </p>
      <p>Several dermoscopic vascular patterns are observed in different types of benign and
malignant tumors. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup> Dotted vessels represent a significant marker of melanocytic lesions, with a
positive predictive value (PPV) of 90%, and are considered the best dermatoscopic
indicator of the melanocytic origin of a tumor. This vascular pattern can be the only
clue to suspect a AMM, however, it can not be considered a pathognomonic sign, since it
is present in benign lesions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup> Irregular linear vessels and milky-red areas have a PPV of 68% and 77% in the
diagnosis of melanoma, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>The combination of dotted vessels and linear irregular vessels presents itself as the
most frequent dermoscopic finding of AMM.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup> Although AMM and HMM are still a challenge in clinical practice, dermoscopy can
reveal characteristic vascular structures, improving the diagnostic accuracy and being
the key to the diagnosis of melanoma. This technique should be used routinely not only
to pigmented but also to doubtful nonpigmented lesions. </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>Financial funding: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <p>* Work performed at the Irmandade da Santa Casa de Miseric&#xF3;rdia de Porto
Alegre (ISCMPA) - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES </title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maia</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russo</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrari</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
              <given-names>MCSA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acral lentiginous melanoma: a challenge for early
diagnosis</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>553</fpage>
          <lpage>560</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rezze</surname>
              <given-names>GG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soares de S&#xE1;</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neves</surname>
              <given-names>RI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Dermatoscopia</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>261</fpage>
          <lpage>268</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Menzies</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kreusch</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Byth</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pizzichetta</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marghoob</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braun</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermoscopic evaluation of amelanotic and hypomelanotic
melanoma</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>144</volume>
          <fpage>1120</fpage>
          <lpage>1127</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18794455</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Giorgi</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sestini</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Massi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maio</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giannotti</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermoscopy for "true" amelanotic melanoma: A clinical
dermoscopy-pathologic case study</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>341</fpage>
          <lpage>344</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443072</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moloney</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menzies</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Key points in the dermoscopic diagnosis of hypomelanotic melanoma and
nodular melanoma</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>10</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Puig</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Argenziano</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zalaudek</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrera</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palou</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Massi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Melanomas that failed dermoscopic detection: a combined
clinicodermoscopic approach for not missing melanoma</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>1262</fpage>
          <lpage>1273</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17903162</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zalaudek</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kreusch</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giacomel</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrara</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Catrical&#xE0;</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Argenziano</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>How to diagnose nonpigmented skin tumors: a review of vascular
structures seen with dermoscopy: part I. Melanocytic skin tumors</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>361</fpage>
          <lpage>374</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20708469</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Argenziano</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zalaudek</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corona</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sera</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cicale</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrillo</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vascular Structures in Skin Tumors: A Dermoscopy Study</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <fpage>1485</fpage>
          <lpage>1489</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15611426</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pizzichetta</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Canzonieri</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Massarut</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baresic</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borsatti</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menzies</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pitfalls in the dermoscopic diagnosis of amelanotic
melanoma</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>893</fpage>
          <lpage>894</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20398822</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
