<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22643520</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3340974</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-08-109</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4293/108680811X13176785204661</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Laparoscopic Removal of a Copper Intrauterine Device from the Sigmoid Colon</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zeino</surname>
            <given-names>M.Y.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wietfeldt</surname>
            <given-names>E.D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Advani</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ahad</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Younkin</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Hassan</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <aff>Departments of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Surgery, Southern Illinois University, Springfield, Illinois USA.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address correspondence to: Imran Hassan, MD, <addr-line>Department of Surgery, SIU School of Medicine, Springfield, Illinois 62704, USA</addr-line>. Telephone: <phone>(217) 545-7230</phone>, Fax: <fax>(217) 545-7762</fax>, E-mail: <email>ihassan@siumed.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Oct-Dec</season>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>568</fpage>
      <lpage>570</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2011 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jls00411000568.pdf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="precis">
        <p>Removal of a migrated intrauterine device by using minimally invasive procedures is indicated even in select asymptomatic patients.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract>
        <p>IUD translocation to the sigmoid colon after uterine perforation is a rare but serious event. Removal of the IUD in such a situation has been recommended because of the risk of complication, such as fistula formation and colonic perforation. We present the case of a 43-year-old female with a copper T380A IUD embedded in the sigmoid colon, which was removed with minimally invasive techniques.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Intrauterine device</kwd>
        <kwd>Sigmoid colon</kwd>
        <kwd>Perforation</kwd>
        <kwd>Laparoscopy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Uterine perforation is among the most serious complications associated with the insertion of intrauterine devices (IUD). The incidence of uterine perforation has been reported to be between 0.05% and 0.13% or 1.3 to 1.6 per 1000 insertions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> The incidence of this complication depends on various factors, such as the type of IUD, the timing of insertion related to the termination of pregnancy, the position and anatomy of the uterus, insertion technique, and the experience of the operator inserting the IUD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> Uterine perforation can occur iatrogenically during the insertion by the applied mechanical force (primary perforation) or spontaneously afterward (secondary perforation). Fifteen percent of uterine perforations involve adjacent organs, usually the small or large intestines.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> IUD-related complications involving the intestines include obstruction, perforation, ischemia, mesenteric injury, stricture and fistulae.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup></p>
      <p>We describe a case of removal of a copper T380A IUD embedded in the sigmoid colon by using laparoscopic techniques.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 43-year-old, gravida 4, para 4 female had an IUD placed 3 years earlier after her fourth vaginal delivery. She had a lifelong history of back pain that had worsened lately, for which she underwent a pelvic ultrasound that failed to identify her IUD in the uterus. A CT scan of the abdomen and pelvis was performed that showed the IUD in an extrauterine position with the stem embedded in the sigmoid colon wall <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>)</bold>. Bimanual examination revealed a normal-sized uterus without palpable adnexal masses. Part of the IUD was felt through the vaginal wall in the posterior cul-de-sac and was fixed. A flexible sigmoidoscopy was performed, and the stem of the IUD was visualized within the colonic lumen <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>)</bold>. The patient was electively taken to the operating room for attempted laparoscopic removal after a mechanical bowel preparation. Intraoperatively, dense adhesions were seen in the posterior cul-de-sac between the posterior aspect of the uterus and the anterior aspect of the sigmoid colon near the recto sigmoid junction which were taken down using blunt dissection with an atraumatic grasper until the IUD wings embedded in the colon wall were identified <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>)</bold>. The IUD was then removed from the colon and subsequently from the abdominal cavity through the laparoscopic 5-mm port in a similar technique of IUD removal from the uterine cavity, by grasping and pulling on the string and allowing the T wings to bend inside the port. The resultant colotomy was repaired laparoscopically intracorporeally by using 2 interrupted 2-0 silk sutures <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>)</bold>. A flexible sigmoidoscopy was then performed and the colon clamped laparoscopically with an atraumatic grasper proximal to the repair site and insufflated with air. The repair site was submerged under water and no air leak was seen. The patient had an uncomplicated postoperative course and was discharged on day 2 from the hospital and has done well 12 months postoperatively.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>CT scan demonstrating the extrauterine position of the IUD in the colonic lumen. (solid white arrow-head).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jls0041128100001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Endoscopic view of the IUD within the colonic lumen.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jls0041128100002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intraoperative laparoscopic view of the IUD embedded in the colonic wall.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jls0041128100003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intraoperative view of the colonic repair following removal of the IUD.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jls0041128100004"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Most uterine perforations are asymptomatic and therefore unrecognized at the time of insertion.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref></sup> Nonoperative management of a migrating IUD has been recommended in the past because of the morbidity associated with its removal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref></sup> However, this complication can lead to pain, fibrosis, and adhesion formation and in some situations may result in penetration into adjacent organs including the urinary bladder, sigmoid colon, appendix, and small bowel.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> Perforation into the bowel can result in abscess formation, intestinal ischemia, or volvulus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref></sup> Therefore, it has been suggested that surgical exploration and IUD retrieval should be the primary therapeutic approach for patients with an IUD-related complication.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> Arslan et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> in a review of the literature identified 47 cases of uterine perforation complicated by intestinal penetration. The Copper-7 and copper-T IUD accounted for half the reported cases of intestinal perforation in the literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> IUD-related intestinal perforations primarily involved the sigmoid colon, followed by the small intestine and rectum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> Most commonly, patients found to have an IUD partially or completely embedded in the colonic wall were managed with a laparotomy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> With advances in laparoscopy, these situations are being increasingly managed with minimally invasive techniques. Previous reports of laparoscopic exploration and removal of translocated IUD from the sigmoid colon have had variable clinical outcomes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> Inceboz et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> reported the laparoscopic removal of an IUD in the sigmoid colon that resulted in a sigmoid perforation requiring a temporary colostomy. Gungor et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></sup> and Baakdah et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> reported removal of partially embedded IUDs in the sigmoid colon without any adverse consequences. Recently Chi et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> removed an IUD that had completely perforated into the sigmoid colon by performing a laparoscopic-assisted resection of the involved segment of the sigmoid colon. They recommended that partial penetration of an IUD into the colonic wall may be removed laparoscopically with intracorporeal repair of the colonic defect.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> It was also suggested by them that a full-thickness perforation by an IUD into the colonic wall should be managed by resection of the involved colon with primary anastomosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> In our case, we laparoscopically removed the IUD that had completely perforated through the colonic wall into the lumen and intracorporeally repaired the resultant colotomy, avoiding resecting the colon and avoiding the morbidity of not repairing the colotomy. There have been reports in the literature of removing IUDs that are embedded in the colonic wall and are visible within the colon lumen with a colonoscope.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref></sup> The risk of using this approach is that without primarily repairing the colonic defect there can be intraperitoneal contamination from intestinal contents leading to abdominal sepsis and the possible need for an emergent laparotomy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> Therefore, we do not recommend this approach to managing IUDs completely perforating the colon wall. Our experience would suggest that full-thickness perforations of an IUD through the colonic wall can be safely managed without resecting the involved colon by using advanced laparoscopic techniques.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>Use of proper technique in IUD insertion is important to avoid primary uterine perforation. However, spontaneous migration can occur rarely, and it is unpredictable. Use of imaging studies, such as ultrasound and CT scans, are essential to identify the location of the IUD. Removal of the IUD is indicated even in asymptomatic patients, and the use of minimally invasive procedures is feasible in select patients.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arslan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanat-Pektas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yesilyurt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Colon penetration by a copper intrauterine device: a case report with literature review</article-title>. <source>Arch Gynecol Obstet</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18592260</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baakdah</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Asswad</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tulandi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sigmoid penetration by an intrauterine device</article-title>. <source>J Min Invasive Gyn</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mederos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Humaran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Minervini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Surgical removal of an intrauterine device perforating the sigmoid colon: A case report</article-title>. <source>Int J Surg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>62</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic removal of an intrauterine device perforating the sigmoid colon: A case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Am Surg</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1055</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16447479</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inceboz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Caglar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Migration of an intrauterine contraceptive device to the sigmoid colon: a case report</article-title>. <source>Eur J Contracept Reprod Health Care</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15006271</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gungor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonmezer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Atabekoglu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortac</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic management of a translocated intrauterine device perforating the bowel</article-title>. <source>J Am Assoc Gynecol Laparosc</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14738645</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Mukhtar</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ali</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Migration of an intrauterine contraceptive device into the sigmoid colon</article-title>. <source>Saudi Med J</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19370289</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
