<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jkms</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11961299</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3054849</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">200204173</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Mantle cell lymphoma, blastoid variant, diagnosed on the basis of cytomorphology and flow cytometric immunophenotyping of the lymph node aspirate and peripheral blood.</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Mi-Ja</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kee</surname>
            <given-names>Keun-Hong</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>Ho-Jong</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department of Pathology, College of Medicine, Chosun University, Gwangju, Korea.</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2002</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>173</fpage>
      <lpage>178</lpage>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mantle cell lymphoma, blastoid variant (B-MCL), is a very rare type of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma exhibiting an aggressive clinical course. We describe a case of B-MCL showing generalized lymphadenopathy and leukemic conversion in a 62-yr-old man. The case was diagnosed and subclassified as B-MCL on the basis of cyto-morphology and immunophenotype. Microscopic examination of the peripheral blood (PB) showed a spectrum of cells ranging from small mature lymphocytes to medium- and large-sized lymphocytes with blast-like chromatin and prominent nucleoli. The lymphoma cells were monoclonal B cells with moderately intense surface IgM. They were CD5 positive, cyclin D1 positive, CD10 negative, and CD23 negative. The flow cytometric immunophenotyping and DNA ploidy analysis of the PB and material obtained by aspiration cytology supported the diagnosis of B-MCL. These findings underline the utility of aspiration cytology in diagnosing B-MCL when cytomorphologic examination is combined with flow cytometric analysis of immuno-phenotype and demonstration of proliferation markers.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
