<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10917125</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3015376</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Repair of Common Bile Duct Injury with the Round and Falciform Ligament after Clip Necrosis: Case Report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>Enrique G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address reprint request to: Enrique G. Chang, MD, FICS, <addr-line>Sta. Maria Med-Surgical Clinic, 1201 Long Beach Blvd, Long Beach, CA 90813, USA</addr-line>. Telephone: <phone>(562) 432-8949</phone>, Fax: <fax>(310) 983-8748</fax>.
</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Apr-Jun</season>
        <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>163</fpage>
      <lpage>165</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2000 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jsls-4-2-163.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Occasionally, as abdominal surgeons, we are confronted with common bile duct injury noted during video laparoscopic or open cholecystectomy. Usually this is solved by endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP) sphincterotomy and stent, or enteric bypass, suture repair and tube drainage. However, after such procedures, there is a significant number of patients with postoperative stenosis.</p>
        <p>Another alternative to repair common bile duct injury and correct postoperative stenosis is using the round and falciform ligament as circumferencial patch. Due to their closeness to the common bile duct and their adequate blood supply, they make a perfect autologus biological graft.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Stenosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Common bile duct injury</kwd>
        <kwd>Laparoscopic cholecystectomy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE PRESENTATION</title>
      <p>A 32-year-old female was brought to the emergency department at St. Mary Medical Center (affiliated to UCLA of Long Beach, CA), who had laparoscopic cholecystectomy in another hospital by another surgeon. Seven days postoperatvely, she became jaundice and had abdominal pain and sepsis. ERCP by gastroenterology was performed, but the surgeons were unable to insert a stent <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>)</bold>. A clip noted across the common bile duct was leaking bile, and bile peritonitis developed. The patient was then taken to surgery. The surgical clip was removed, but extensive necrosis 4 cm in longitudinal and circumferencial length had developed. The common duct was small, approximately 3 mm; consequently, it proved difficult to do a Roux-en-Y enteric bypass. It could not hold a &#x201C;T&#x201D; tube without leaking bile due to the extensive necrosis. Previous experiences of anatomical dissection and research led me to believe that patching with round and falciform ligament would help the patient. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> With proper retraction, the round ligament was taken down with cautery. It was sutured with proline 5-0 near the injury of the common bile duct, side-to-side to the round and falciform ligament circumferencial patching a &#x201C;T&#x201D; tube No. 10 French placed <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>)</bold> and reinforced using 5-0 chromic interrupted sutures and tacked down with omentum <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>)</bold>.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>ERCP unable to pass the stent because there is a clip across the common duct.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-4-2-163-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Video laparoscopic anatomical photograph of the round and falciform ligament so close to the common bile duct it is able to overlap. With its own blood supply, it makes a perfect autologus graph.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-4-2-163-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Graphic of the side-to-side anastomosis using proline 5-0, running suture stented with a &#x201C;T&#x201D; tube no. 10 French, in this particular patient.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-4-2-163-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient did well postoperatively. A &#x201C;T&#x201D; tube cholangiogram after six weeks of surgery noted a normal-appearing common duct. Subsequently, the &#x201C;T&#x201D; tube was removed three months postoperatively, and ERCP after five months showed a common duct without stenosis as presented in the X-ray films <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>)</bold>.</p>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>ERCP after five months without stenosis. Patient asymptomatic.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jsls-4-2-163-g04"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>In this particular patient, I did not have a better choice than to use a standard procedure, such as ERCP stent, choledoco or hepatic jejunostomy or suturing the common duct with a &#x201C;T&#x201D; tube. The repair of the common duct injury using a round and falciform ligament after a clip necrosis was successful, and the patient was released without symptoms or stenosis of the common duct after 12 months of follow-up. A definite evaluation of the procedure must await a longer period of follow-up and study.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Netter</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Digestive system</source>. <article-title>The Ciba collection</article-title>; <year>1957</year></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Jx</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anatomic bases of vascularized hepatic teres ligament</article-title>. <source>Surg Radiol Anat</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9413074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
