<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22906348</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3407441</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">11-02-036</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4293/108680812X13291597716627</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Laparoscopic-Assisted Vesicocalicostomy for Severe Pelvi-Ureteral Stricture Disease</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Diaz</surname>
            <given-names>Edward C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Glickman Urological and Kidney Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Susan</surname>
            <given-names>Samer</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>Glickman Urological and Kidney Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Patel</surname>
            <given-names>Neil S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>Glickman Urological and Kidney Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Byron H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <aff>Glickman Urological and Kidney Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cabelin</surname>
            <given-names>Mark</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Glickman Urological and Kidney Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Aron</surname>
            <given-names>Monish</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>University of Southern California Institute of Urology, Los Angeles, California, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Stein</surname>
            <given-names>Robert J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <aff>Glickman Urological and Kidney Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, Ohio, USA.</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address correspondence to: Robert J. Stein, MD, <addr-line>Co-director Robotic Surgery, Glickman Urological and Kidney Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Q10, 9500 Euclid Avenue, Cleveland, OH 44195, USA</addr-line>. Telephone: <phone>(216) 445-4800</phone>, Fax: <fax>(216) 445-2267</fax>, E-mail: <email>steinr@ccf.org</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jan-Mar</season>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>163</fpage>
      <lpage>165</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2012 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons, Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jls00112000163.pdf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="precis">
        <p>A laparoscopic approach was of benefit in limiting ultimate incision size in this case of vesicocalicostomy in a patient with severe ureteric stricture disease.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 39-year-old female previously treated with shock wave lithotripsy developed extensive ureteral stricture disease. After 2 unsuccessful attempts at retrograde balloon dilatation, she was evaluated at our center for further management. Successful reconstruction was performed with laparoscopic-assisted vesicocalicostomy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Vesicocalicostomy</kwd>
        <kwd>Laparoscopic</kwd>
        <kwd>Reconstruction</kwd>
        <kwd>Ureteral stricture</kwd>
        <kwd>Hydronephrosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Ureteral obstruction</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>The management of proximal ureteral stricture disease is complex and can require renal autotransplantation, bowel interposition, or even nephrectomy. Although often successful, these interventions can lead to metabolic derangements and loss of renal function. The following case describes the use of laparoscopic assistance for successful management of a complicated stricture using the orthotopic position of the kidney and the patient's native urothelium.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Evaluation of the patient's right upper tract with retrograde pyelogram demonstrated the presence of a 4-cm proximal ureteral stricture with virtually no remaining renal pelvis <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>)</bold>. Estimated GFR was &gt;60mL/min per 1.73m<sup>2</sup>, and a radionuclide scan with ureteral stent in place suggested that the right renal unit contributed 33.6% function while the left kidney contributed 66.4%.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Preoperative Retrograde Pyelogram: &#x223C; 4-cm proximal ureteral stricture with virtually obliterated renal pelvis.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jls0011228390001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The natural right renal position was quite caudal and therefore vesicocalicostomy was planned. With the patient in the flank position, a 4-port laparoscopic access was used to limit the eventual open incision size. The kidney was fully mobilized, and the lower pole calyx was identified and marked using laparoscopic ultrasound. The bladder was also mobilized laparoscopically including division of the contralateral bladder pedicle. A Gibson incision was then created, and the lower pole moiety was amputated without hilar clamping to expose a renal calyx. Nephropexy as caudal as possible was followed by a psoas hitch and Boari flap to approximate the bladder to the renal calyx <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>)</bold>. A stent, Foley catheter, and Jackson-Pratt drain were left in place. A cystogram 10 days postoperatively demonstrated no extravasation, and the Foley catheter was removed <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>)</bold>. The stent was removed 1 month postoperatively. At 2-year follow-up, the patient denies flank symptoms, while renal function and drainage are maintained as documented by diuretic radionuclide scan.</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intraoperative photograph after performing laparoscopic-assisted right vesicocalicostomy with psoas hitch and Boari flap. A) right kidney after lower pole hemi-nephrectomy B) Boari flap</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jls0011228390002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Postoperative cystogram: Right ureteral reflux confirming no extravasation.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jls0011228390003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Complex proximal ureteral stricture disease is a challenging area in reconstructive urology. Classically, ileal interposition, either using an open or minimally invasive technique, and autotransplantation have been the only approaches besides nephrectomy for treating such patients.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> Certainly the use of urothelium in the reconstruction is optimal to prevent metabolic abnormalities.</p>
      <p>Vesicocalicostomy has been previously described in 2 cases of normally positioned kidneys.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref></sup> The authors described successful reconstruction for a solitary kidney as a primary procedure or after failed previous reconstruction. Certainly, kidney position is one of the key aspects regarding the use of vesicocalicostomy in a normally positioned kidney. Furthermore, bladder mobility is an important factor in the success of this particular operation. Bridging lengthy ureteric strictures in patients with low capacity, contracted bladders would most likely be difficult.</p>
      <p>This case highlights the use of a laparoscopic-assisted approach to aid in limiting ultimate incision size. The patient is initially placed in a flank position to facilitate complete laparoscopic renal mobilization, because radical caudal displacement of the kidney is essential. The patient can then be easily rotated on the operating table to a supine and steep Trendelenburg position to fully mobilize the bladder. We did not need to re-prepare and drape the patient, as the rotation of the operation table itself was sufficient. Due to the radical mobilization of the bladder and kidney, a far smaller open Gibson incision was eventually required for the remainder of the procedure. The center of the Gibson incision should approximate the site of the vesicocalicostomy anastomosis. If laparoscopic renal and bladder mobilization were not performed, a lengthy midline incision or perhaps 2 open incisions (one flank and one low midline/Gibson) would have been required.</p>
      <p>The costs associated with laparoscopy have to be weighed against the benefits of a smaller open incision. Although further study is required, it is likely that the decreased size of the incision would provide benefits in terms of perioperative analgesia requirements, decreased length of hospitalization, and shortened convalescence.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In terms of preparing the lower pole calyx, intraoperative ultrasound was used to mark the exact position of the renal papilla. We were then able to use monopolar cautery to excise the lower pole parenchyma while maintaining gentle manual pressure to ensure hemostasis without arterial clamping. Two to 3 sutures were used to control specific vessels. After performing nephropexy to the psoas muscle as caudad as possible and psoas hitch of the bladder as well with PDS suture, a Boari flap was created. 3-0 Vicryl interrupted sutures were then used to approximate the flap to the open calyx, and a running 3-0 Vicryl suture was used to reapproximate the bladder defect.</p>
      <p>Complex ureteric reconstructive procedures can occasionally risk ipsilateral renal function, contralateral renal function, or introduce bowel into the urinary tract. Minimizing these various risks is ideal but sometimes not possible. This case demonstrates that laparoscopic-assisted vesicocalicostomy can be a rare but viable option in select patients with severe pelvi-ureteric stricture disease.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Turna</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic assisted ileal ureter: technique, outcomes and comparison to the open procedure</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <volume>182</volume>:<fpage>1032</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1039</lpage>, <year>2009</year>
<month>9</month><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19616806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zumrutbas</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term outcomes and late complications of laparoscopic nephrectomy with renal autotransplantation</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>. <year>2008</year>
<month>1</month>;<volume>179</volume>:<fpage>240</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18001789</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaidyanathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Boari flap calycovesicostomy: a salvage procedure for giant hydronephrosis due to ureteropelvic junction obstruction</article-title>. <source>J Postgrad Med</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2097353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
