<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Radiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J Radiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJR</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Korean Journal of Radiology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1229-6929</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2005-8330</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Society of Radiology</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23690720</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3655307</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3348/kjr.2013.14.3.497</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Neurointervention</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Case Report</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Congenital Pial Arteriovenous Fistula in the Temporal Region Draining into Cavernous Sinus: A Case Report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Ziyin</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Kun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Chaohua</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Changwei</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaodong</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
            <given-names>Jianjian</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurosurgery, West China Hospital of Sichuan University, Chengdu, Sichuan Province, 610041, China.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Affiliated Hospital of Hainan Medical College, Haikou, Hainan Province, 570102, China.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Corresponding author: Xiaodong Xie, MD, Department of Neurosurgery, West China Hospital of Sichuan University, Chengdu, Sichuan Province, 610041, China. Tel: (86137) 0800-5179, Fax: (8628) 8542-2600, <email>xiaodong_1962@163.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>497</fpage>
      <lpage>500</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 The Korean Society of Radiology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>This report concerns a 4-month-old infant with progressive prominent and redness of his left eye since birth. This report concerns a 4-month-old infant with progressive prominent redness of his left eye since birth. Angiography revealed a congenital pial arteriovenous fistula between the temporal branch of the left posterior cerebral artery and left cavernous sinus through the sphenoparietal sinus, a condition not reported in the literature. The fistula was successfully occluded with two micro-coils by vertebrobasilar approach.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Pial arteriovenous fistula</kwd>
        <kwd>Embolization</kwd>
        <kwd>Infant</kwd>
        <kwd>Cavernous sinus</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Intracranial pial arteriovenous fistula (AVFs) are rare cerebrovascular lesions of the brain that have recently been recognized as a distinct pathological entity, differing from the cerebral arteriovenous malformations (AVMs) in that they lack a true nidus. According to a series reported by Halbach et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), intracranial pial AVFs account for 1.6% of all intracranial vascular malformations. However, congenital AVFs draining into the cavernous sinus in infants are very rare. Here we present the first case of a congenital pial AVF between the temporal branch of the left posterior cerebral artery (PCA) and the left cavernous sinus through the sphenoparietal sinus, successfully treated by a vertebrobasilar approach with the use of two detachable micro-coils.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 4-month-old infant was admitted to the department of ophthalmology in our hospital with progressive proptosis and redness of his left eye since birth. He was uneventfully delivered at full term, weighing 3.1 kg, and from a healthy mother. There was no history of birth trauma, and the neurologic examination was normal. There were no signs of irritability, fever or disturbance of swallowing, and weight gain was good. Blood pressure and heart rate were within normal limits. However, the physical examination revealed engorged conjunctiva, tortuous episcleral vessels, and swollen left eyelids. A slight intermittent systolic bruit was heard over the left global, whose rhythm was consistent with the heartbeat. The ophthalmologist strongly suspected cerebrovascular pathology, so the baby was transferred to the department of neurosurgery.</p>
      <p>An MRI examination revealed orbital edema, proptosis, enlargement and tortuosity of the superior ophthalmic vein, prominence of the left cavernous sinus and enlargement of the extraocular muscles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Digital subtraction angiography (DSA) confirmed the diagnosis, classifying the fistula, and delineating the venous pathways. DSA must be done under general anesthesia by using a 4 Fr diagnostic catheter. A left single hole fistula was confirmed at the temporal branch of the PCA draining directly to cavernous sinus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B, C</xref>).</p>
      <p>After multidisciplinary consultation and consent of their families, endovascular treatment was proposed for this infant. The endovascular treatment was performed under general anesthesia and under full intravenous heparinization. Via a right percutaneous femoral access, a 4 Fr guiding catheter (Evoy, Cordis, Johnson &amp; Johnson Co., Washington DC, USA) was place in the left vertebral artery. The micro-catheter was inserted into the cavernous sinus through the temporal branch of PCA under the guidance of road mapping. Then micro-coils were deployed in the cavernous sinus through the micro-catheter. Cerebral angiography was repeated sequentially after a coil was filled while checking for occlusion of the fistula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). Finally, the fistula was filled with two detachable micro-coils (5 mm &#xD7; 15 cm, 4 mm &#xD7; 8 cm) that completed occluded the fistula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E, F</xref>). Antithrombotic therapy was not implemented after the procedure. Blood pressure was controlled strictly after micro-coils embolization. The systolic blood pressure was kept at approximately 80% of the basal blood pressure for 72 hours after the embolization. The ocular symptoms completely disappeared after four days. The patient was discharged five days after the intervention without any neurological deficit. The MRI examination at nine months showed permanent obliteration of the fistula.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Intracranial pial AVFs are rare cerebrovascular lesions, representing only 1.6% of all brain AVMs in larger reported series (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). They have recently been recognized as a distinct pathological entity from other intracranial AVMs. Unlike the cerebral AVMs and dural AVFs, pial AVFs are comprised of one or more arterial connections to a single venous channel without any intervening nidus of vessels or capillaries. They can be congenital or result from trauma. Congenital pial AVFs are very rare, and little is known regarding their pathophysiological mechanisms. Abnormal angiogenesis, cytokines and associated vascular growth factors may play a role in the formation of congenital pial AVFs, and it is possible that an embryological misstep could produce these lesions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>).</p>
      <p>This case is a congenital pial AVF between the temporal branch of the left posterior cerebral artery and the left cavernous sinus through the sphenoparietal sinus. Anatomically, temporal poles can drain into the sphenoparietal sinus and cavernous sinus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Thus, this type of AVF can occur, although no case like this has been reported. Similar to the carotid cavernous fistulas, a congenital pial arteriovenous fistula draining into cavernous sinus can cause bruit, proptosis, conjunctiva chemosis and symptoms referable to the optic and trigeminal nerves. Fistulas in newborns and infants manifest as enlarged head circumference, heart failure, seizures or intracranial hemorrhage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). In our case, the infant presented only with progressive proptosis and redness of his left eye, so he was admitted to the department of ophthalmology initially. If this infant was continually misdiagnosed as an eye disease, the outcome may have been intracranial hemorrhage or heart failure.</p>
      <p>Little research concerning the natural history of these lesions has been published because they are so rare. There are a few reports regarding spontaneous resolution of a congenital pial AVF draining into the cavernous sinus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). According to one report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), conservative management of pial AVF was associated with mortality in five (63%) of eight patients, so spontaneous closure of pial AVFs is not expected. In our case, the infant had a high-flow, single hole fistula, and the clinical manifestations gradually worsened day by day. Active treatment was necessarily implemented once diagnosed clearly to prevent fatal cerebral hemorrhage and worst neurocognitive prognosis. Endovascular embolization has been proven more efficacious and safe than open surgery in the treatment of cerebral AVFs. A number of different embolization materials options for cerebral AVFs are currently available, such as detachable balloons, detachable micro-coils and Onyx. Probably the detachable balloon and the Onyx are the first choice for traumatic carotid cavernous fitulas and dural cerebral AVFs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). However, micro-coils were used in our case instead of detachable balloon and Onyx. There were two reasons: the femoral artery of the infant was too small to allow the placement of the 8 Fr catheter sheath, and the balloon could not pass through the 4 Fr guiding catheter, while the branch of the PCA was very close to the fistula, and onyx may reflux into the PCA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>).</p>
      <p>Though the fistula was a high flow, it was successfully occluded only with two micro-coils, and angiogram by fluoroscope revealed that the fistula was completely occluded with loose packing. To prevent fistula recanalization, antithrombotic therapy was not implemented after the procedure. The main danger is post-operation cerebral hemorrhage of the feeding arteries, which must be controlled by strict blood pressure monitoring while maintaining the systolic blood pressure at approximately 80% of the basal blood pressure for 72 hours after embolization. Four days after embolization, the symptoms and signs entirely disappeared. The stable occlusion of the fistula has been demonstrated by MRI examination at 9 months.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Halbach</surname>
              <given-names>VV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Higashida</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hieshima</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norman</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Normal perfusion pressure breakthrough occurring during treatment of carotid and vertebral fistulas</article-title>
          <source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>751</fpage>
          <lpage>756</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3118670</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoh</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Putman</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Budzik</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogilvy</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical and endovascular flow disconnection of intracranial pial single-channel arteriovenous fistulae</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>1351</fpage>
          <lpage>1363</lpage>
          <comment>discussion 1363-1364</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846934</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oka</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rhoton</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barry</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Microsurgical anatomy of the superficial veins of the cerebrum</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>711</fpage>
          <lpage>748</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4069326</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amaral</surname>
              <given-names>FT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machado</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>[Congenital cerebral arteriovenous fistula. Diagnostic peculiarity and surgical repair in an infant with heart failure]</article-title>
          <source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>207</fpage>
          <lpage>209</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7778993</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haase</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Congestive heart failure secondary to cerebral arteriovenous fistula</article-title>
          <source>Childs Nerv Syst</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>75</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3401873</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berant</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tadmor</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blieden</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deutsch</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neufeld</surname>
              <given-names>HN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cerebral arteriovenous fistula causing congestive heart failure in infancy</article-title>
          <source>Angiology</source>
          <year>1977</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>684</fpage>
          <lpage>686</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">907217</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sasamori</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hida</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yano</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asano</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iwasaki</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cervical perimedullary arteriovenous fistula in an infant presenting with subarachnoid hemorrhage--case report</article-title>
          <source>Neurol Med Chir (Tokyo)</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>409</fpage>
          <lpage>413</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18812685</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Son</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intracranial pial arteriovenous fistulas</article-title>
          <source>J Korean Neurosurg Soc</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19096703</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nimi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lasjaunias</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berenstein</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endovascular embolization of congenital intracranial pial arteriovenous fistulas</article-title>
          <source>Neuroimaging Clin N Am</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>309</fpage>
          <lpage>317</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paramasivam</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toma</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niimi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berenstein</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>De novo development of dural arteriovenous fistula after endovascular embolization of pial arteriovenous fistula</article-title>
          <source>J Neurointerv Surg</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rivera</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blanc</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piotin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spelle</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moret</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Single hole cerebral arteriovenous fistula between the anterior choroidal artery and the basal vein of Rosenthal in a child</article-title>
          <source>Childs Nerv Syst</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>1521</fpage>
          <lpage>1523</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19517117</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>The MRI/DSA presentation and embolism result of this pial AVF in a 4-month-old infant.</p>
        <p><bold>A.</bold> MRI revealed that proptosis of left eye, prominence of left cavernous sinus and enlargement of extraocular muscles. <bold>B, C.</bold> DSA revealed pial AVF between temporal branch of left PCA and left cavernous sinus through sphenoparietal sinus (<bold>B.</bold> AP image, <bold>C.</bold> LAT image). <bold>D.</bold> Cerebral angiography was repeated sequentially after coil was filled with checking for occlusion of fistula. <bold>E, F.</bold> Angiogram of post-embolization revealed fistula was entirely occluded by using only two micro-coils (<bold>E.</bold> AP image, <bold>F.</bold> LAT image).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjr-14-497-g001"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
