<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23739714</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3750895</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0365-05962013000200017</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Nail apparatus melanoma: a diagnostic opportunity<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01"><sup>*</sup></xref></article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Melanoma do aparelho ungueal: uma oportunidade diagn&#xF3;stica</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carre&#xF1;o</surname>
            <given-names>Ana Maria</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nakajima</surname>
            <given-names>S&#xED;lvia Rocha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pennini</surname>
            <given-names>Silmara N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Candido</surname>
            <given-names>Renato</given-names>
            <suffix>Junior</suffix>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schettini</surname>
            <given-names>Antonio Pedro Mendes</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Resident in Dermatology at the Federal University of (UFAM) &#x2013; Manaus
(AM), Brazil </aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Resident in Dermatology at the Alfredo da Matta Foundation (FUAM) &#x2013;
Manaus (AM), Brazil </aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> Master&#xB4;s Degree &#x2013; Dermatologist Physician at the Alfredo da Matta
Foundation (FUAM) &#x2013; Manaus (AM), Brazil </aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label> Dermatologist Physician at the Alfredo da Matta Foundation (FUAM) &#x2013;
Manaus (AM), Brazil </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing address:</bold> Antonio Pedro Mendes Schettini - Rua Codaj&#xE1;s, 24 -
Cachoeirinha - 69065-130, Manaus, AM. - Brazil - E-mail:
<email>apmschettini@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Mar-Apr</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>268</fpage>
      <lpage>271</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Malignant Melanoma is a high mortality neoplasm. The involvement of the nail
apparatus is rare, with only 2 out of 3 patients seeking medical attention as the
result of recent nail melanocytic lesions. This results in late diagnosis and a
prognosis worse than cutaneous melanoma. We report a female, presenting with
ulcerative lesions with clinical and laboratory features compatible with
leishmaniasis. On return after treatment initiation a longitudinal melanonychia was
observed on her first right finger. Biopsy of the nail matrix was performed.
Histopathology was compatible with melanoma in situ. Longitudinal melanonychia is not
a specific sign for melanoma and it is important that the dermatologist should
identify the suspect lesions correctly. The incidental diagnosis of nail melanoma in
situ in our case significantly impacted the patient's survival.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>Melanoma Maligno &#xE9; uma neoplasia de alta mortalidade, sendo raro o acometimento do
aparelho ungueal. Apenas 2/3 dos pacientes procuram atendimento m&#xE9;dico devido les&#xE3;o
melanoc&#xED;tica ungueal recente, tornando o diagn&#xF3;stico tardio e com progn&#xF3;stico pior
que do melanoma cut&#xE2;neo. Descreve-se um caso de paciente sexo feminino, apresentando
les&#xF5;es ulceradas com caracter&#xED;sticas cl&#xED;nico-laboratoriais compat&#xED;veis com
leishmaniose tegumentar americana. No retorno ap&#xF3;s in&#xED;cio do tratamento foi observada
melanon&#xED;quia longitudinal no primeiro quirod&#xE1;ctilo direito. Realizada bi&#xF3;psia da
matriz ungueal com histopatol&#xF3;gico compat&#xED;vel com melanoma in situ. Melanon&#xED;quia
longitudinal n&#xE3;o &#xE9; sinal espec&#xED;fico de melanoma. A identifica&#xE7;&#xE3;o das les&#xF5;es suspeitas
&#xE9; importante tarefa dos dermatologistas. O diagn&#xF3;stico incidental de melanoma ungueal
in situ do caso relatado resultou em grande impacto na sobrevida da paciente.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Medical oncology</kwd>
        <kwd>Melanoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Nail diseases</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Malignant melanoma is a high mortality neoplasm, with an average 5-year survival rate of
56% in developing countries, despite representing only 4% of all skin cancers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup> Among different types of melanoma, Acral Lentiginous
contributes with 5-10% of cases in Caucasian populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup> Nail apparatus involvement is even rarer, with an estimated
prevalence of 0.7-3.5% of melanomas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Longitudinal melanonychia is the classic clinical presentation of early nail apparatus
melanoma but it can also be a sign of other, more benign, conditions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup> Only 2 out of 3 patients with early
nail apparatus melanoma seek medical attention, which results in late diagnosis in most
cases, leading to worse prognosis than that of cutaneous melanoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup>
Traditional treatment has been the amputation of the affected digit up to the proximal
joint.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>17-year-old female student from Manaus (Amazonas State), Fitzpatrick's phototype III,
presented at the dermatology clinic with two ulcerated lesions. These were consistent
with leishmaniasis, both clinically and by lab (presence of <italic>Leshmania
sp</italic>. amatigotes pattern on direct examination). Pentavalent antimonial was
prescribed. During clinic follow-up, it was noted that the patient had a longitudinal
melanonychia on the right thumb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>). On
questioning, she informed that this had been present for approximately one year. She
also reported family history of melanoma (great-aunt). Dermatoscopic examination
revealed lines varying in color from light brown to black, with different sizes, width
and distances, with the most proximal area being more intense and thicker than the
distal area, forming a triangular shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure
2</xref>). Ungual matrix biopsy was performed by shaving. Histopathology was compatible
with melanoma <italic>in situ </italic>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>).
Surgical management involved excision of ungual apparatus up to periosteal region.
Following histopathology no neoplasm showed in the 40 cuts made. Clinical staging was
TisN0M0 (Stage 0). Patient followed up for 11 months without recurrence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>). </p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clinical aspect of the patient&#xB4;s longitudinal melanonychia</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0268-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Dermatoscopic examination of the patient&#xB4;s longitudinal melanonychia</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0268-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histopathology showing atypical melanocytes not confined to basement membrane with
pagetoid spread. No dermal invasion.(HEx40)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0268-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clinical appearance after eleven months of follow-up without signs of
recurrence</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0268-g04"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Nail apparatus melanoma (NAM) is more common among Black and Asian ethnic groups with no
gender preference and is more frequent between fifth and seventh decades.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup> While
2-3% of melanomas in Caucasians are situated in the ungual apparatus, this percentage
rises to 15-20% in Afro-Caribbeans.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup>
NAM is more commonly seen on the thumb, followed by the hallux and index finger.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>NAM typically manifests as longitudinal melanonychia (LM) which can also be a clinical
manifestation of other ungual apparatus changes which cause ungual matrix melanocytic
activation. The pigmented bands due to continuous growth of the nail plaque can be seen
in ungual matrix nevi, benign melanocytic hyperplasia and inflammatory, traumatic and
iatrogenic changes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup> LM is
therefore not a specific sign for NAM, and one of the important functions of the
dermatologist is to correctly identify the suspect lesions. </p>
      <p>Clinical examination with the naked eye can reveal suggestive characteristics however,
not pathognomonic of melanoma such as non-homogeneous pigmentation with different
coloured lines, the presence of ungual plaque fissure, the proximal area wider than the
distal area (triangular), hazy lateral borders and periungual skin pigmentation
(Hutchinson&#xB4;s sign).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Levit <italic>et al</italic>. produced an aide-memoire (ABCDEF rules) to help
distinguish alarming from non-alarming melanonychis <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup>, as follows: </p>
      <p>A (<italic>age, Afro-Americans, native Americans and Asians</italic>): fifth and seventh
decades; </p>
      <p>B (<italic>nail band</italic>): colour from <italic>brown </italic>to
<italic>black</italic>, &#x2265;3mm wide, irregular borders; </p>
      <p>C (<italic>change</italic>): rapid increase in size of band and/or change in nail
morphology; </p>
      <p>D (<italic>digit involved</italic>): thumb &gt; hallux &gt; index finger, dominant hand,
only one digit; </p>
      <p>E (<italic>extension</italic>): Hutchinson&#xB4;s sign; </p>
      <p>F (<italic>family</italic>): personal or familial history of nevi dysplastic syndrome
and melanoma. </p>
      <p>Dermatoscopy is a non-invasive tool which has allowed a greater degree of diagnostic
accuracy of pigmented lesions and the identification of early melanoma compared to
visual clinical inspection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref></sup>
Dermatoscopic characteristics associated with NAM are brown bands with irregular
longitudinal lines of different colours and widths and with loss of parallel
organization. Further findings include micro-Hutchinson&#xB4;s sign, pigmentation of
periungual tissue seen with dermatoscope but not with naked eye.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref></sup> Although there is no current consensus
to dermatoscopic monitoring, Koga <italic>et al</italic>. recommend 6-monthly evaluation
of suspicious LM, with patient advised to return sooner if changes in the lesion
develop.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Hirata <italic>et al</italic>. have suggested that the use of intraoperative
dermatoscopy on the nail bed and matrix with polarized light could result in better
visualization of pigmented lesions since this examines the region of melanin production.
Although this is an invasive technique it could give the best level of diagnostic
accuracy <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup> when compared with clinical
examination, ABCDEF rules and traditional dermatoscopy. </p>
      <p>Histopathology is still the gold standard, and biopsy can be incisional or
excisional.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> Although there is no
current consensus on managing ungual melanoma <italic>in situ</italic>, surgical
excision entails the complete ungual apparatus itself, including the nail plaque, bed
and matrix.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup> The resulting defect can
be corrected with a partial or total skin graft.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup> In our case, with histopathology of melanoma <italic>in
situ</italic>, the surgical treatment chosen was the excision of the entire nail
apparatus affected, leaving the leasion to be healed by secondary intention. The shaving
biopsy had already included the entire lesion, since the histopathology of second
excision showed no more atypical melanocytes. </p>
      <p>Compared with cutaneous melanoma, where 80% of cases are diagnosed at the TNM stage I,
only 20% of NAM are diagnosed at this stage.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup> Late diagnosis decreases the possibility of curative treatment
without the need for mutilation, and increases mortality rates. Over 50% of patients die
before 5 years after diagnosis. </p>
      <p>It is not uncommon for LM to go unnoticed or ignored by patients or even by non-
specialist physicians. It remains a challenge for dermatologists. The reported case
shows an incidental diagnosis detected at the clinic of nail apparatus melanoma at an
early stage, resulting in saving the young woman&#xB4;s thumb and, possibly, her life. This
case highlights the importance of a thorough global examination of each patient,
together with the need for fuller information to be given to people about the potential
malignant nature of longitudinal melanonychia, and draws attention to the
dermatologist&#xB4;s key role in the differential diagnosis of this clinical sign.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <p>* Study conducted at the Alfredo da Matta Foundation (FUAM) - Manaus (AM),
Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial funding: None</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Canto</surname>
              <given-names>ACM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Melanoma cut&#xE2;neo: doen&#xE7;a cur&#xE1;vel? Revis&#xE3;o de literatura
e apresenta&#xE7;&#xE3;o de um organograma de investiga&#xE7;&#xE3;o e tratamento</article-title>
          <source>Rev AMRIGS</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>312</fpage>
          <lpage>316</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bishop</surname>
              <given-names>JAN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Lentigos, melanocytic naevi and melanoma</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Burns</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breathnach</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Griffiths</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Rook's textbook of dermatology</source>
          <edition>8th</edition>
          <publisher-loc>West Sussex</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>57</lpage>
          <page-range>1-54,57</page-range>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mendon&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>IRSM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kac</surname>
              <given-names>BK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spinelli</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orofino</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fran&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Melanoma do aparelho ungueal</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>575</fpage>
          <lpage>580</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Di Chiacchio</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirata</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enokihara</surname>
              <given-names>MY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Michalany</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fabbrocini</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tosti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatologists' accuracy in early diagnosis of melanoma of the nail
matrix</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>146</volume>
          <fpage>382</fpage>
          <lpage>387</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20404227</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koga</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saida</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uhara</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Key point in dermatoscopic differentiation between early nail
apparatus melanoma and benign longitudinal melanonychia</article-title>
          <source>J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21175755</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hirata</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamada</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enokihara</surname>
              <given-names>MY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Chiacchio</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enokihara</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Patterns of nail matrix and bed of longitudinal melanonychia by
intraoperative dermatoscopy</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <lpage>303</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21531039</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Braun</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baran</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le Gal</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalle</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ronger</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pandolfi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and management of nail pigmentations</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>835</fpage>
          <lpage>847</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17320240</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duarte</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Correia</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barros</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azevedo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haneke</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nail matrix melanoma in situ: conservative surgical
management</article-title>
          <source>Dermatology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>220</volume>
          <fpage>173</fpage>
          <lpage>175</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20016126</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levit</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kagen</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scher</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grossman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Altman</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The ABC rule for clinical detection of subungual
melanoma</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>269</fpage>
          <lpage>274</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10642684</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Phan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalle</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Touzet</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ronger-Savl&#xE9;</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balme</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermoscopic features of acral lentiginous melanoma in a large series
of 110 cases in a white population</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>162</volume>
          <fpage>765</fpage>
          <lpage>771</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19922528</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
