<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diagn Pathol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Diagnostic Pathology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1746-1596</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21513565</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3094260</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1746-1596-6-38</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-1596-6-38</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Placental mesenchymal dysplasia, a case of intrauterine sudden death of fetus with rupture of cirsoid periumbilical chorionic vessels</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Umazume</surname>
            <given-names>Takeshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>umatake@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Kataoka</surname>
            <given-names>Soromon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>sorokata@hakochu-hp.gr.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Kamamuta</surname>
            <given-names>Kyouko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>kyoko_0_0_kyoko@yahoo.co.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Tanuma</surname>
            <given-names>Fumie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>tanuma-f@hakochu-hp.gr.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Sumie</surname>
            <given-names>Akihiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>a.sumie@ja-hokkaidoukouseiren.or.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Shirogane</surname>
            <given-names>Toru</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>shirogane-t@hakochu-hp.gr.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>Kudou</surname>
            <given-names>Takayuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>moukokai@hakochu-hp.gr.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A8">
          <name>
            <surname>Ikeda</surname>
            <given-names>Hitoshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>jinikeda@hakochu-hp.gr.jp</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Hakodate Central General Hospital, Honchou 33-2, Hakodate, 040-8585, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Hakodate Central General Hospital, Honchou 33-2, Hakodate, 040-8585, Japan</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <fpage>38</fpage>
      <lpage>38</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9;2011 Umazume et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Umazume et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.diagnosticpathology.org/content/6/1/38"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>We report a 32-year-old woman (1-gravid, 1-para) with a vesicular lesion in her uterus that was pointed out on ultrasound at 8 weeks' gestation. Amniocentesis at 15 weeks' gestation showed a normal female karyotype, 46XX. As the pregnancy advanced, the mole-like lesion became relatively reduced. Throughout gestation, the maternal human chorionic gonadotropin level was normal, but the serum alpha fetoprotein level rose as her pregnancy progressed. Her fetus did not exhibit any remarkable anomalies. The patient visited our hospital complaining of a diminished feeling of fetal movements at 36 weeks 5 days' gestation, and intrauterine fetal death (IUFD) was confirmed. She delivered a 2336-g female without any definite anomalies. A pathological examination led to a diagnosis of placental mesenchymal dysplasia, and androgenetic/biparental mosaicism in the placenta was identified using p57<sup>kip2 </sup>immunohistochemical staining. And it also revealed that the rupture of the cirsoid chorionic vessels had led to IUFD.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Placental mesenchymal dysplasia (PMD) is a rare placental anomaly characterized by placentomegaly and grapelike vesicles resembling molar pregnancy. The incidence of PMD is reportedly 0.02% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], with a definite preponderance of females [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Distinguishing PMD from its mimics, especially molar pregnancy is important for preventing the unnecessary termination of pregnancy. Unlike molar pregnancies, PMD usually features a normal fetus. However, PMD is distinct in that it has a high incidence of fetal growth restriction (FGR) and intrauterine fetal death (IUFD), and is associated with Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome (BWS), a condition characterized by macrosomia, visceromegaly, macroglossia, and omphalocele [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Pathologically, PMD placentas are usually large size, and show edema of stem villi with intact terminal villi and many kinds of vascular anomalies, such as cirsoid chorionic vessels, thrombosis, thickness of vessel wall, vascular stenosis, villous chorangiosis, chorioangioma and fetal thrombotic vasculopathy. Also abnormal umbilical cords, including tortuous, marked twisted cords, excessively long cords, etc. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. These vascular anomalies may lead to FGR and IUFD. Absence of trophoblastic proliferation in PMD placentas is a histological difference from partial moles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Although the pathogenesis of PMD remains unknown, androgenetic/biparental mosaicism has recently been suggested as the underlying cause of PMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The phenotypic features of PMD, including the absence of trophoblastic hyperplasia, its association with BWS, and its female preponderance, can all be explained by this novel mechanism. We report a new case of PMD without BWS, but intrauterine sudden death of the fetus without any anomaly contained FGR, at 36 weeks' gestation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 32-year old woman, gravid 1, para 1, began visiting our hospital at 4 weeks' gestation. An ultrasound performed at 8 weeks' gestation as part of a routine prenatal checkup detected a vesicular lesion in her uterus (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The maternal hCG level at 12 weeks' gestation was 100,614 mIU/mL, and this level remained normal throughout gestation. However, the patient's serum alpha-fetoprotein level increased as her pregnancy progressed, reaching 879 ng/mL at 33 weeks' gestation (2.7 multiples of the median; normal medians referenced from previous report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]). An amniocentesis performed at 15 weeks' gestation showed a normal female karyotype, 46XX. As the pregnancy advanced, the vesicular lesion decreased in size and no fetal abnormalities were detected. At 33 weeks' gestation, however, an ultrasound detected dilated chorionic vessels (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The patient visited our hospital complaining of a diminished feeling of fetal movements at 36 weeks 5 days of gestation, and IUFD was confirmed. She delivered a 2336 g female without any definite anomalies at 36 weeks 6 days of gestation. The placenta was 18 centimeters in diameter and weighed 720 g, and a long umbilical cord (about 70 cm) was found. The chorionic vessels were cirsoid, dilated and tortuous (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3a</xref>). A cross section of the placenta showed the formation of a hematoma bordering on the dilated chorionic plate vessels and vesicular changes in one-third of the parenchyma (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>). A histological examination revealed that the cirsoid dilated chorionic vessels were fragile, that a portion of the smooth muscles of the vessel had disappeared, and that the vessel wall was ruptured, causing a hemorrhage with hematoma formation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Hydropic stem villi and diminished vessels were observed in the affected lesion of the placenta. These changes were more clearly shown by immunohistochemical staining with CD34, resulting in the positive staining of vascular endothelium (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b</xref>). Although almost of the terminal villi were not affected, fetal thrombotic vasculopathy was seen in a part of the affected lesion (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5d</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Transvaginal ultrasound study</bold>. An apparently normal fetus (asterisk) and villi with multiple hypoechoic cysts (arrows) at 8 weeks' gestation. Crown-rump length is 20 millimeters. Each cyst is 2-3 millimeters in diameter.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-1596-6-38-1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Transabdominal ultrasound study</bold>. Placental parenchyma (asterisk) and dilated subchorionic vessels (arrows) at 35 weeks' gestation. These vessels are up to 2.5 centimeters in diameter.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-1596-6-38-2"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Fetal surface and cross-section of the placenta</bold>. a) Dilated and tortuous chorionic vessels and an excessively long umbilical cord. b) The formation of a hematoma bordering the dilated chorionic plate vessels and vesicular changes in the parenchyma (arrows).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-1596-6-38-3"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Merged photographs of a dilated chorionic plate vessel</bold>. The smooth muscle of the dilated chorionic plate vessel has disappeared (arrow), and the vessel wall has ruptured, producing hemorrhage and the formation of a hematoma (asterisk). (hematoxylin-eosin staining (HE), objective &#xD7;1). To view the virtual glass slides for this image please see here <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062157">http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062157</ext-link>. 
</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-1596-6-38-4"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Histopathology and immunohistochemistry of abnormal villi</bold>. a) Hydropic stem villi and diminished vessels at the affected lesion of the placenta. (HE, objective &#xD7;4). The lower left empty corner shows a cystic cavity of the hydropic stem villus. b) Decrease in both number and size of vessels by the CD34 immunohistochemical staining. (objective &#xD7;4). c) Avascular terminal villi in a part of the affected area. (HE, objective &#xD7;10). d) Scatter and disappearance of immunohistochemical CD34-positive endothelial cells in the avascular terminal villi (objective &#xD7;20). To view the virtual glass slide for image 5a please see here <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062193">http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062193</ext-link> and for image 5b here <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062232">http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062232</ext-link>. 
To view the virtual glass slide for image 5c please see here <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062263">http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062263</ext-link> and for image 5d here <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062298">http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062298</ext-link>. 
</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-1596-6-38-5"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The p57<sup>kip2 </sup>gene, which encodes a cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor, is expressed in the maternal genome, whereas the paternal allele is transcriptionally silent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Immunohistochemical staining of p57<sup>kip2 </sup>showed that some villi were composed of stromal cells that were negative for p57<sup>kip2 </sup>only in the affected lesion (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6b</xref>). Therefore, the villi of the affected lesion formed a mosaic of biparental and androgenetic cell populations. These pathological findings led to a diagnosis of PMD.</p>
      <fig id="F6" position="float">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Androgenetic/biparental mosaicism detected by p57<sup>kip2 </sup>immunohistochemical staining in the affected lesion</bold>. p57<sup>kip2</sup>-positive stromal cells indicate biparental villi in a, and no p57<sup>kip2</sup>-positive stromal cell in some villi (asterisks) suggests androgenetic villi in b. (objective &#xD7;10). To view the virtual glass slide for this image please see here <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062328">http://diagnosticpathology.slidepath.com/webViewer.php?snapshotId=1304062328</ext-link>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1746-1596-6-38-6"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The main differential diagnoses of PMD are partial hydatidiform mole, dichorionic twins of a normal fetus and complete mole, and confined placental mosaicism. When a prenatal ultrasonographic examination detects a vesicular lesion in the presence of a fetus in uterus, whether a single or twin pregnancy is present should be determined. A twin pregnancy would consist of dichorionic twins of a normal fetus and complete mole. In the present case, ultrasound appeared to reveal a single pregnancy. Unlike partial moles, the majority of PMD are diploid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In 70 - 80% of cases, the partial moles are triploid, often with 2 sets of paternal genes and 1 set of maternal genes as a result of dispermy fertilization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Cases of confined placental mosaicism involving trisomy 16 have been reported as exhibiting cystic villi on ultrasound, but these cases can be diagnosed accurately by karyotyping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. In the present case, an amniocentesis performed at 15 weeks' gestation showed a normal female karyotype, 46XX. The characteristic laboratory test for PMD includes an increased level of maternal serum AFP. The increase in the surface transfer area as a result of the increased placental volume and the increased number of vessels within the stem villi is thought to lead to an increased transfer of AFP into the maternal circulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. On the other hand, unlike with moles, the level of hCG in patients with PMD is normal to slightly increased throughout gestation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. In this case, although the maternal hCG level was normal throughout gestation, the serum AFP level increased as her pregnancy progressed. These prenatal findings suggested a diagnosis of PMD.</p>
      <p>The placenta is usually extremely large for the gestational age and the umbilical cord is relatively long in cases with PMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The gross placental findings for PMD vary with gestational age. To our knowledge, no previous report has detected a vesicular lesion in a patient with PMD prior to 13 weeks' gestation. In the present case, a vesicular lesion was detected at 8 weeks' gestation. Thus, the morphological changes in the villi appear to begin early during gestation. During the third trimester, the chorionic plate vessels in a PMD placenta are aneurysmally dilated and tortuous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. However, in cases terminated before 20 weeks of gestation, the chorionic plate vessels are not dilated, and the normal and abnormal areas are not clearly delineated, suggesting that the vascular malformations develop progressively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. As the pregnancy advances, tangled congested vessels grossly resembling gray-white or dark-red wormlike structures may be identified within the parenchyma and are often most prominent in the subchorionic plate region near the fetal surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. An ultrasound performed at 33 weeks' gestation seemingly detected this finding (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p>
      <p>Although morphologic gross findings of PMD placentas are so often mimicked by features of partial hydatidiform moles, PMD placentas are markedly enlarged and macroscopic vascular anomalies such as cirsoid dilated chorionic vessels with or without thrombi and umbilical cord anomalies like a long umbilical cord that were observed in our case are often co-existence in PMD placentas, but they are not usual in molar pregnancies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Microscopically, PMD placentas typically reveal large stem villi with hydropic swelling and cistern formation interspersed with unaffected terminal villi. Similarly, mixture of hydropic villi with cistern formation and unaffected villi are also found in partial hydatidiform moles, however, trophoblastic stromal inclusions and proliferations, which are absent in PMD placentas, are also characteristic of molar pregnancies. Not only macroscopic but also microscopic vascular anomalies such as fetal thrombotic vasculopathy that was found in our case, villous chorangiosis and chorangioma, are also characteristic together hydropic villi in PMD placentas, but not in molar pregnancies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. These morphological characteristics of PMD placenta supported to diagnose our case as PMD. Immunohistochemistry using antibodies against products of paternal imprinting genes such as the antibody against p57<sup>kip2 </sup>protein is a potential marker that may prove helpful in distinguishing PMD from molar pregnancy. The immunohistochemical detection of androgenetic/biparental mosaicism in stromal cells suggests to a diagnosis of PMD, because this mosaicism is unusual in molar pregnancies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Dichorionic twin placentas with a normal fetus and complete mole may also be needed to pathologically distinguish to PMD. But, vascular anomalies seen in PMD placentas are absent in their placentas and complete moles are purely androgenetic. Spontaneous abortion with hydropic change may have vesicle formation and can also be confused with early PMD, however, the vesicles, if present, are usually small. Also, spontaneous abortion shows degenerative changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>PMD has distinct clinicopathological features. According to Truc et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], 82% of the affected fetuses are female and about 20% of cases with PMD also have BWS. Among the PMD cases without BWS, the FGR and the IUFD rate are 50% and 36%, respectively. IUFD can occur throughout gestation (before 21 weeks, 14.3%; 22~27 weeks, 23.8%; 28~33 weeks, 33.3%; after 34 weeks, 28.6%). The cause of IUFD is currently unclear and may be heterogeneous. Thrombosis of chorionic vessels and umbilical cord anomalies are thought to be likely causes of IUFD in PMD cases, and Truc et al. reported that IUFD may be explained by a potentially chronic hypoxia secondary to obstructive fetal vascular thrombosis and a decrease in maternal-fetal gas exchange as a result of an insufficient amount of normal chorionic villi and the shunting of blood from the exchange surface in chorioangiomas and dysplastic villi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. In our case, histological examination revealed that the dilated cirsoid chorionic vessels were fragile and that part of the vessel wall had ruptured, resulting in hemorrhage with hematoma formation. Although fetal thrombotic vasculopathy was found in a part of the affected lesion, this hemorrhage was thought to have led to sudden death of the fetus at the late gestational age (36 weeks 5 days) because no significant chronic hypoxic anomaly of the fetus including FGR was observed.</p>
      <p>The underlying cause of PMD is currently unknown. Recently, Kaiser-Rogers et al. proposed androgenetic/biparental mosaicism as the origin of some cases of PMD and suggested that the phenotype of androgenetic mosaicism can presumably range from mild PMD, which may not even be diagnosed, to the typical findings of a complete hydatidiform mole, depending on the extent and distribution of the androgenetic lineage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The authors hypothesized that such mosaicism arose as the result of a failure in the replication of the maternal genome prior to the first cleavage, with normal replication and segregation of the paternal genome, resulting in two types of daughter cells, one with normal biparental genes and the other with only paternal genes. Such failed division would produce a diploid/haploid mosaic embryo, and endoreduplication of the haploid paternal-only daughter cell could then occur to produce the diploid androgenetic lineage, while the female and male haploid complements would merge to form a daughter cell with normal biparental inheritance. The phenotypic features of PMD, including the preponderance of females, the absence of trophoblastic hyperplasia, and the association with BWS, can all be explained by this mechanism. Since an androgenic 46, YY cell line would be nonviable, PMD cases would show the marked female predominance. The abnormal androgenetic cells would be confined to the chorionic mesoderm, membranes, and vessels, whereas the trophoblastic cells would be normal with no evidence of androgenetic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. This feature would explain the absence of trophoblast overgrowth in PMD in contrast to complete moles, in which androgenetic cells are identified in the trophoblastic cell layer. BWS is a condition of constitutional overgrowth with genetic linkage to chromosome 11p15.5. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Insulin-like growth factor-2 is located in this lesion, and the maternal allele is normally suppressed so that only the paternal gene is expressed. Thus, the loss of 11p15.5. gene imprinting could lead to PMD in some cases.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>PMD should be included in a differential diagnosis of cystic lesions of the placenta by sonography, especially when a phenotypically normal-appearing fetus can be identified. When the prenatal characteristics of PMD, such as an elevated AFP and normal hCG level in the mother, a normal female karyotype revealed by amniocentesis, and dilated subchorionic vessels revealed by ultrasonography during the third trimester, are detected, termination of the pregnancy at an optimal time could be considered, since sudden IUFD including rupture of the cirsoid chorionic vessels might occur at any time throughout gestation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in Chief of this Journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contributions</title>
      <p>TU and SK designed the study, performed clinical investigation, and wrote most of the drafts. KK, FT, AS, TS and TK assisted the clinical investigation, and supported to prepare the manuscript. HI performed the histological and immunohistochemical evaluation, and helped rewrite the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Dr. Kanako Kubota, Department of Surgical Pathology, Hokkaido University Hospital, for performing the immunohistochemical staining of p57<sup>kip2</sup>.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Arisawa</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakayama</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Suspected involvement of the X chromosome in Placental mesenchymal dysplasia</article-title>
          <source>Cong Anomal</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>309</fpage>
          <lpage>317</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1741-4520.2002.tb00897.x</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Truc</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Julie</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carla</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Placental Mesenchymal Dysplasia is associated with high rates of intrauterine growth restriction and fetal demise. A report of 11 new cases and a review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Am J Clin Pathol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>126</volume>
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          <lpage>78</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1309/RV45HRD53YQ2YFTP</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16753607</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Parveen</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tongson-Ignacio</surname>
            <given-names>JE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fraser</surname>
            <given-names>CR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Killeen</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>KS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Placental mesenchymal dysplasia</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>131</volume>
          <fpage>131</fpage>
          <lpage>137</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17227114</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Moscoso</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jauniaux</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hustin</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Placental vascular anomaly with diffuse mesenchymal stem villous hyperplasia. A new clinico-pathological entity?</article-title>
          <source>Pathol Res Pract</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>187</volume>
          <fpage>324</fpage>
          <lpage>328</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1712473</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kaiser-Rogers</surname>
            <given-names>KA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McFadden</surname>
            <given-names>DE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Livasy</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dansereau</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jiang</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knops</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lefebvre</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rao</surname>
            <given-names>KW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Robinson</surname>
            <given-names>WP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Androgenetic/biparental mosaicism causes placental mesenchymal dysplasia</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>192</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15908568</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Natori</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tanaka</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ishimoto</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gohda</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kiyokawa</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamauchi</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miyazaki</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nozawa</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Takagi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Relation of gestational age, maternal body weight and age or serum alpha-fetoprotein and human chorionic gonadotropin at second-trimester</article-title>
          <source>Nippon Sanka Fujinka Gakkai Zasshi</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>562</fpage>
          <lpage>566</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7522264</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Matsuoka</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Edwards</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bartletta</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Grundy</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kalikin</surname>
            <given-names>LM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harper</surname>
            <given-names>JW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Elledge</surname>
            <given-names>SJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feinberg</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Imprinting of the gene encoding a human cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor, p57KIP2, on chromosome 11p15</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>3026</fpage>
          <lpage>3030</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.7.3026</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8610162</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Lokan</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chan</surname>
            <given-names>YF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Agnesta</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Placental mesenchymal dysplasia</article-title>
          <source>Pathology</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>375</fpage>
          <lpage>378</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/003130202760120571</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12190299</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Jauniaux</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kadri</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hustin</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Partial mole and triploidy: screening patients with first-trimester spontaneous abortion</article-title>
          <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>616</fpage>
          <lpage>619</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0029-7844(96)00235-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8841229</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Astner</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schwinger</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Caliebe</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jonat</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gembruch</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Sonographically detected fetal and placental abnormalities associated with trisomy 16 confined to the placenta. A case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Prenat Diagn</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1308</fpage>
          <lpage>315</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0223(199812)18:12&lt;1308::AID-PD443&gt;3.0.CO;2-H</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9885025</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Paradinas</surname>
            <given-names>FJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sebire</surname>
            <given-names>NJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fisher</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rees</surname>
            <given-names>HC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Foskett</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Seckl</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Newlands</surname>
            <given-names>ES</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Pseudo-partial moles: placental stem vessel hydrops and the association with Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome and complete moles</article-title>
          <source>Histopathology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>447</fpage>
          <lpage>454</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2559.2001.01256.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11737301</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Jauniaux</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nicolaides</surname>
            <given-names>KH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hustin</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Perinatal features associated with placental mesenchymal dysplasia</article-title>
          <source>Placenta</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>701</fpage>
          <lpage>706</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0143-4004(97)90012-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9364606</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Benirschke</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kaufmann</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baergen</surname>
            <given-names>RN</given-names>
          </name>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">Benirschke K, La Jolla, Kaufmann P, Aachen, Baergen RN</person-group>
          <article-title>Molar Pregnancy: partial hydatidiform mole</article-title>
          <source>Pathology of the Human Placenta</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <edition>5</edition>
          <publisher-name>New York: Springer Science+Business Media, Inc</publisher-name>
          <fpage>817</fpage>
          <lpage>825</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hoffner</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunn</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Esposito</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Macpherson</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Surti</surname>
            <given-names>U</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>p57<sup>KIP2 </sup>immunostaining and molecular cytogenetics: combined approach aids in diagnosis of morphologically challenging cases with molar phenotype and in detecting androgenetic cell lines in mosaic/chimeric conceptions</article-title>
          <source>Hum Pathol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>63</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.humpath.2007.05.010</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17904617</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ping</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reeve</surname>
            <given-names>AE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Law</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Young</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boehnke</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Feinberg</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Genetic linkage of Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome to 11p15.5</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>720</fpage>
          <lpage>723</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2565083</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
