<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23842117</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3942976</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13-0212</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.13-0212</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Surgery</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Note</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Computed Tomography Angiography of Situs Inversus, Portosystemic Shunt and
Multiple Vena Cava Anomalies in a Dog</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>OUI</surname>
            <given-names>Heejin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>KIM</surname>
            <given-names>Jisun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>BAE</surname>
            <given-names>Yeonho</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>OH</surname>
            <given-names>Juyeon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>PARK</surname>
            <given-names>Seungjo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>LEE</surname>
            <given-names>Gahyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>JEON</surname>
            <given-names>Sunghoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>CHOI</surname>
            <given-names>Jihye</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Chonnam National University,
Gwangju 500&#x2013;757, Korea</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Choi, J., College of Veterinary
Medicine, Chonnam National University, Yongbong-ro, Buk-gu, Gwangju, 500&#x2013;757, South Korea.
e-mail: <email xlink:href="imsono@chonnam.ac.kr">imsono@chonnam.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>75</volume>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <fpage>1525</fpage>
      <lpage>1528</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>ABSTRACT</title>
        <p>A 5-year-old Shih Tzu was presented with intermittent vomiting and anorexia.
Microhepatica and reversed position of the abdominal organs were observed on radiography.
Ultrasonographically, portosystemic shunt (PSS) was tentatively diagnosed. Computed
tomography (CT) revealed that the distended portal vein drained into the left hepatic
vein. The caudal vena cava (CdVC) split postrenally and converged at the renal level.
Cranial to this, the azygos continuation of the CdVC was confirmed. In the thorax, a
persistent left cranial vena cava (CrVC) was found along with right CrVC. This is the
first report of a dog with persistent left CrVC and multiple abdominal malformations. CT
angiography was useful in evaluating the characteristics of each vascular anomaly and
determining the required surgical correction in this complex case.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>azygos continuation of the caudal vena cava</kwd>
        <kwd>CT</kwd>
        <kwd>persistent left cranial vena cava</kwd>
        <kwd>portosystemic shunt</kwd>
        <kwd>situs inversus</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Situs inversus is a congenital condition in which the visceral position is reversed as a
mirror image. This condition is the main characteristic of Kartagener&#x2019;s syndrome with
rhinosinusitis and bronchiectasis [<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Situs inversus
without dextrocardia has been reported with congenital vascular anomalies including
portosystemic shunts (PSS) and azygos continuation of the caudal vena cava (CdVC) [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p>
    <p>The abdominal CdVC is divided into prerenal, renal, prehepatic, hepatic and posthepatic
segments derived from the supracardinal, subcardinal and vitelline veins [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The retained middle segment of the supracardinal vein,
normally regressed during normal development, plays a role as the connection between the
embryonic CdVC and azygos vein, that is, the azygos continuation of the CdVC. The developing
CdVC, usually a prehepatic CdVC, can be inappropriately connected with the caudal portion of
the vitelline vein developing into a portal branch, and this abnormal connection between the
vessels is a PSS [<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p>
    <p>Persistent left cranial vena cava (CrVC) is an uncommon congenital defect [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. During embryologic development, the caudal portion of
the left cranial cardinal vein, normally atrophied with the fusion of the left and right
cranial cardinal veins, persists, resulting in a persistent left CrVC. This condition has been
described with other congenital defects of the cardiovascular system [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p>
    <p>To the authors&#x2019; knowledge, this is the first report documenting persistent left CrVC with
congenital abdominal anomalies including situs inversus, PSS, azygos continuation of the CdVC
and split CdVC in a dog. We described the application of CT angiography for distinguishing and
comprehending these multiple vascular anomalies and situs inversus in the dog herein.</p>
    <p>A 5-year-old, neutered male Shih Tzu was presented with a 2-week history of vomiting and
anorexia. On physical examination, there were no abnormal findings including on auscultation.
The dog&#x2019;s complete blood count and serum chemistry were within the reference ranges, except
for hepatic enzymes, such as alanine aminotransferase (968 U/<italic>l</italic>; reference
range, 19&#x2013;100 U/<italic>l</italic>), gamma-glutamyl transferase (22 U/<italic>l</italic>;
reference range, 0&#x2013;6 U/<italic>l</italic>), alkaline phosphatase (280 U/<italic>l</italic>;
reference range, 15&#x2013;127 U/<italic>l</italic>) and ammonia (143 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>mol;
reference range, 0&#x2013;98 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>mol).</p>
    <p>On radiography, microhepatica and reversed position of the abdominal organs with normal
thoracic visceral position were found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Thoracic (A, B) and abdominal (C, D) radiography of the dog. There were microhepatica
and reversed positions of the stomach (s), spleen (arrow), bilateral kidneys (*) and
cecum (c) compared with the normal thoracic visceral positions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-75-1525-g001"/></fig>). Ultrasonography revealed decreased vascular size of the intrahepatic portal vein and
hepatic vein and normal echotexture of the hepatic parenchyma. A dilated, tortuous portal
branch showing an atypical portal flow signal was found in the left cranial abdomen, and PSS
was tentatively diagnosed. Apart from the vessel suspected to be a PSS, there were many
tortuous vessels, and it was challenging to determine the characteristics of the tortuous
vessels, because of concurrent situs inversus.</p>
    <p>To identify the suspicious vessels, CT angiography was performed at 30 sec after injection of
800 mg iodine/kg iohexol (Omnihexol 300, Korea United Pharm Co., Seoul, Korea) at a rate of 3
m<italic>l</italic>/sec using a power injector (Medrad Vistron CT Injector System, Medrad,
Inc., Warrendale, PA, U.S.A.). The distended portal vein showed a convoluted course from the
mid to left cranioventral abdomen and joined the left hepatic vein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Volume-rendered CT reconstruction of the dog viewed from a left ventral perspective.
The portal branch (red) showed a serpentine course and entered the left hepatic vein
(yellow).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-75-1525-g002"/></fig>). A single extrahepatic PSS was confirmed. Additionally, two separate CdVC branches
converged at the renal level, and then a single CdVC coursed dorsally and connected directly
to the azygos vein with the prehepatic CdVC being absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Volume-rendered CT reconstruction of the dog viewed from a ventral (A) and lateral (B)
perspective. Two separate branches of the prerenal caudal vena cava (blue) converged at
the renal level and then cranial to this, a single caudal vena cava (arrowhead)
connected to the azygos vein (purple) through the shunt (green) with the prehepatic
caudal vena cava being absent.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-75-1525-g003"/></fig>). The positions of the stomach, duodenum, spleen, colon, cecum and kidneys, which had
normal shapes and internal structures, were reversed. In the thorax, a left CrVC driving
caudally to the caudodorsal angle of the heart and draining into the right atrium was found
along with the right CrVC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_004">Fig. 4</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_004" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Volume-rendered CT reconstruction of the dog viewed from a dorsal perspective. The
complete type of left CrVC (long arrow) entered the right atrium along with the normal
right cranial vena cava (arrowhead).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-75-1525-g004"/></fig>). There was no other cardiovascular defect, and this was double checked with
echocardiography. On the basis of these findings, the dog was diagnosed as having situs
inversus; abdominal vascular anomalies including PSS, azygos continuation of the CdVC and
split CdVC; and a thoracic vascular anomaly, persistent left CrVC.</p>
    <p>Among these lesions, PSS was considered the cause of the clinical signs in the dog, and other
congenital malformations were determined to be incidental findings. The PSS was surgically
corrected using an ameroid constrictor, and then clinical signs and laboratory data returned
to normal.</p>
    <p>Situs inversus with rhinosinusitis and bronchiectasis are classified as Kartagener&#x2019;s syndrome
[<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In Kartagener&#x2019;s syndrome, chronic coughing and nasal
discharge are caused by defective cilia motility. Cilia dyskinesia was ruled out in this case
because there were no respiratory signs or evidence of bronchiectasis on thoracic radiography,
even though electron endoscopy was not performed. Without primary ciliary dyskinesia, situs
inversus may not lead to clinical signs. However, this condition can interfere with diagnostic
and surgical procedures that require an understanding of the anatomy of the viscera and
vascular structures like in this dog.</p>
    <p>Ultrasonography has high sensitivity and specificity as a means of detecting PSS, although it
does depends on the examiner&#x2019;s skill and experience [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].
In this case, PSS was suspected based on ultrasonography; however, the location and number of
shunts and the connected vessels could not be clarified due to visceral malposition.
Furthermore, anatomic comprehension of other tortuous vascular branches was needed.</p>
    <p>CT is an excellent tool for evaluating the morphology of anomalous vessels, as it provides
images of the transverse plane without superimposition of structures and can be used to assess
multiple complex anomalies using reconstructed three-dimensional images. CT was useful to not
only anatomically discriminate the congenital malformations but also to create a treatment
plan based on understanding the hemodynamic state among the 4 vascular anomalies in the dog.
Surgical intervention was only necessary for the PSS classified as a single extrahepatic
shunt, and other vascular abnormalities, such as azygos continuation of the CdVC, split CdVC
and persistent left CrVC, should be avoided unnecessary surgical treatment for hemodynamic
circulation.</p>
    <p>In azygos continuation of the CdVC, the shunt provides a direct route for venous return to
the heart, so that accidental ligation of the shunt can be fatal, as shown in previous case
reported in the human literature [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. One other point
claiming our attention in this anomaly is thrombosis, which can occur due to slowing blood
flow of the shunt [<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. We could define the functional shunt between the azyogos vein and renal CdVC
and rule out thrombosis, shown as a filling defect, using CT angiography.</p>
    <p>Split CdVC is the duplication of the prerenal and renal CdVC and has no clinical significance
[<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, this anomaly added complexity to the
abdominal vessel anatomy in this case.</p>
    <p>During CT scanning, persistent left CrVC was found incidentally in the dog. Persistent left
CrVC can be classified as a complete or incomplete type depending on whether distal portion of
the left CrVC atrophies [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The incomplete type of this
vessel can form a ring with the trachea and constrict the esophagus, leading to megaesophagus
[<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Moreover, the clinical significance of this
malformation can be determined based on the structure it enters. This has no clinical
significance when it enters the right atrium, unlike the case when it enters the left atrium.
The present case was a complete type of persistent left CrVC that entered the right atrium
without obstructing other structures, such as the esophagus.</p>
    <p>Coexistence of situs inversus, PSS and azygos continuation of the CdVC has been reported in 2
other dogs previously [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Persistent left CrVC has been reported in association with cardiac
defects or other types of thoracic vascular anomalies [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. A hypothesis concerning genetic factors related to
these vascular anomalies has been postulated; however, there has been no case in which
persistent left CrVC and abdominal visceral and vascular malformations were in synchrony.</p>
    <p>A lot of different types of congenital vascular malformations can simultaneously occur, and
the clinical significance of each type may be different. Moreover, if the visceral position is
reversed, it can add difficulty to understanding the characteristics of vascular anomalies.
This dog had complicated malformations including situs inversus, PSS, azygos continuation of
the CdVC, split CdVC and even persistent left CrVC. Using CT angiography, the anatomy and
function of each anomaly could be evaluated in detail, and surgical intervention was
successfully performed.</p>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pdf_001">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Fig</title>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="jvms-75-1525-s001.pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e400" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <p>This study was supported in part by the Basic Science Research Program through the National
Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and
Technology (2012R1A1A1040407), and by the Animal Medical Institute of Chonnam National
University.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1963</year>
<article-title>Persistent left cranial vena cava in
dogs: Angiocardiography, significance, and coexisting anomalies1</article-title>.
<source><italic>Vet. Radiol.</italic></source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1740-8261.1963.tb01524.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2004</year>
<article-title>Tracheal signs and associated vascular
anomalies in dogs with persistent right aortic arch</article-title>. <source><italic>J.
Vet. Intern. Med.</italic></source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>510</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>514</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2004.tb02576.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15320589</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cavrenne</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Busscher</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Billen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clercx</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snaps</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2008</year>
<article-title>Primary ciliary dyskinesia and situs
inversus in a young dog</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet. Rec.</italic></source><volume>163</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.163.2.54</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18621999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>d&#x2019;Anjou</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Penninck</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornejo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pibarot</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2004</year>
<article-title>Ultrasnonographic diagnosis of
portosystemic shunting in dogs and cats</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet. Radiol.
Ultrasound.</italic></source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>424</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>437</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1740-8261.2004.04076.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15487568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Effler</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sifers</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1951</year>
<article-title>Anomaly of the vena cava inferior;
report of fatality after ligation</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Am. Med.
Assoc.</italic></source><volume>146</volume>: <fpage>1321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1322</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1951.63670140009011g</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14850287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Fernandez del Palacio</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernal</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luis Fuentes</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1997</year>
<article-title>Persistent left cranial vena cava
associated with multiple congenital anomalies in a six-week-old puppy</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Small Anim. Pract.</italic></source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>526</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>530</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.1997.tb03311.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9403813</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Foodman</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giger</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stebbins</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1989</year>
<article-title>Kartagener&#x2019;s syndrome in an old
miniature poodle</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Small Anim.
Pract.</italic></source><volume>30</volume>: <fpage>96</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>100</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.1989.tb01508.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Garcia-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Granja</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalo Orden</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano Rabano</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>I. D.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2009</year>
<article-title>Complex cardiac congenital defects in an
adult dog: an ultrasonographic and magnetic resonance imaging study</article-title>.
<source><italic>Can. Vet. J.</italic></source><volume>50</volume>: <fpage>933</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>935</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19949552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Harder</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pharr</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tryon</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shmon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2002</year>
<article-title>Segmental aplasia of the caudal vena
cava in a dog</article-title>. <source><italic>Can. Vet. J.</italic></source><volume>43</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>368</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12001503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellenger</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Youmans</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisdall</surname><given-names>P. L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1998</year>
<article-title>Congenital interruption of the portal
vein and caudal vena cava in dogs: six case reports and a review of the
literature</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet. Surg.</italic></source><volume>27</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>215</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-950X.1998.tb00119.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9605232</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watrous</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1983</year>
<article-title>Echocardiographic features of dilated
coronary sinus in a dog with persistent left cranial vena cava</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Am. Vet. Med. Assoc.</italic></source><volume>182</volume>: <fpage>407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>408</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6833077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Jenni</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makara</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenni</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlerth</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaus</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2009</year>
<article-title>Diagnosis of pulmonary arterio-venous
fistula and persistent left cranial vena cava by 3-dimensional computed tomographic
reconstruction</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet. Intern. Med.</italic></source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>190</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>195</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2008.0228.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19175740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kayanuma</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suganuma</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2000</year>
<article-title>A canine case of partial heterotaxia
detected by radiography and ultrasound</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet. Med.
Sci.</italic></source><volume>62</volume>: <fpage>897</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>899</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.62.897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10993189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Larcher</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abadie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyers</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2006</year>
<article-title>Persistent left cranial vena cava
causing oesophageal obstruction and consequent megaoesophagus in a dog</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Comp. Pathol.</italic></source><volume>135</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>152</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcpa.2006.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16952369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Selcer</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suter</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1976</year>
<article-title>Hepatoencephalopathy associated with
situs inversus of abdominal organs and vascular anomalies in a dog</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Am. Vet. Med. Assoc.</italic></source><volume>168</volume>: <fpage>681</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>688</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1262245</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>N. D. S.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1960</year>
<article-title>Absence of the prerenal segment of the
posterior vena cava of the dog</article-title>. <source><italic>Aust. Vet.
J.</italic></source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>68</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.1960.tb03765.x</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantinescu</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1987</year>
<article-title>An uncommon right azygos vein and caudal
vena cava in a dog</article-title>. <source><italic>Anat. Histol.
Embryol.</italic></source><volume>16</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Neil</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canapp</surname><given-names>S. O.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lattimer</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2002</year>
<article-title>Kartagener&#x2019;s syndrome in a Dachshund
dog</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Am. Anim. Hosp. Assoc.</italic></source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>49</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11804314</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1968</year>
<article-title>Epidemiologic and genetic studies of
congenital heart disease in the dog</article-title>. <source><italic>Circ.
Res.</italic></source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>202</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.RES.23.2.171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5662573</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#xC5;Blad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinns</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seiler</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McConnell</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 2009</year>
<article-title>Computed tomographic and magnetic
resonance imaging features of canine segmental caudal vena cava aplasia</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Small Anim. Pract.</italic></source><volume>50</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>349</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2009.00748.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19575698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tisdall</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellenger</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1994</year>
<article-title>Congenital portosystemic shunts in
Maltese and Australian cattle dogs</article-title>. <source><italic>Aust. Vet.
J.</italic></source><volume>71</volume>: <fpage>174</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>178</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.1994.tb03382.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8080406</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tobias</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>W. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kittleson</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Komtebedde</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><year> 1993</year>
<article-title>Cor triatriatum dexter in two
dogs</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Am. Vet. Med. Assoc.</italic></source><volume>202</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>290</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8428836</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
