<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cardiovasc Ultrasound</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Cardiovascular Ultrasound</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1476-7120</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21073752</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3000834</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1476-7120-8-49</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-7120-8-49</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>An unusual case of left ventricular aneurysm in duchenne muscular dystrophy</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Du</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaozhou</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>xjoedu@yahoo.ca</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Zeglinski</surname>
            <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>mzeglinski@sbrc.ca</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Shaikh</surname>
            <given-names>Nasir</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>nshaikh@sbgh.mb.ca</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Jassal</surname>
            <given-names>Davinder S</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>djassal@sbgh.mb.ca</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Institute of Cardiovascular Sciences, St. Boniface General Hospital, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Section of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Radiology, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <fpage>49</fpage>
      <lpage>49</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9;2010 Du et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Du et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (&lt;url&gt;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0&lt;/url&gt;), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.cardiovascularultrasound.com/content/8/1/49"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD) leads to structural heart disease, including dilated cardiomyopathy, in 90% of patients &gt;18 years of age. Despite the ubiquity of cardiomyopathy associated with DMD, ventricular aneurysms in these patients have rarely been reported. We present a case of a basal inferoposterior aneurysm of the left ventricle in a 23-year-old male patient with DMD.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>Mr. W.D. is a 23-year-old male patient with DMD. He was referred for evaluation of cardiac abnormalities due to underlying DMD. He denied chest discomfort, shortness of breath, palpitations nor syncope. On physical examination, his blood pressure was 100/60 mm Hg with a heart rate of 72 beats per minute. The jugular venous pressure was within normal limits. There were normal cardiac heart sounds with no murmurs and no evidence of pedal edema. Twelve lead electrocardiography demonstrated right bundle branch block with Q waves in the inferolateral leads (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Transthoracic echocardiography (TTE) demonstrated a mildly dilated LV with an inferoposterior wall aneurysm of the left ventricle (LV) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). The overall left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) was mildly reduced at 40-45%. Due to the low risk of rupture of a true LV aneurysm, the patient was treated conservatively.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>12 Lead EKG and transthoracic echocardiography.</bold><bold>A</bold>. The ECG demonstrates right axis deviation, prominent R waves in V1, and Q waves in the inferior and lateral leads (II, III, AVF, and V4-6). <bold>B</bold>. A parasternal long axis view on transthoracic echocardiography demonstrating a true aneurysm (15 mm &#xD7; 27 mm) of the basal inferoposterior wall of the LV (arrow). RV, right ventricle; LV, left ventricle; Ao, aorta; LA, left atrium.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1476-7120-8-49-1"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD) is an x-linked dystrophinopathy that occurs in 1/3600 to 1/6000 males [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Approximately 1/3 of DMD is caused by de novo mutations, while 2/3 are inherited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. DMD presents early at the age of 2 to 3, with patients often demonstrating difficulty mobilizing, characteristic waddling gait and lumbar lordosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The diagnosis of DMD is often made by 5 years of age when the patients' physical capacities diverge markedly from their peers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The mean age for loss of ambulation is 10 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The diagnosis of DMD is often made with genetic investigations and muscle biopsy, along with the family history and the clinical presentation. Characteristic blood biomarkers such as elevated serum creatinine kinase (CK) and myoglobin are indicative, but not diagnostic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Cardiomyopathies are noted in DMD patients as young as 10 years of age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Approximately 90% of DMD patients suffer from an underlying cardiomyopathy, with dilated cardiomyopathy constituting majority of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Despite the high prevalence of cardiac disease, cardiac symptoms were reported in only 57% of DMD patients over 18 years of age, which suggests that many patients remain asymptomatic, likely due to their low physical capability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Severe dilated cardiomyopathy may lead to heart failure, which accounts for 20% of mortalities in DMD patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Cardiac involvement in DMD is caused by the progressive loss of cardiomyocytes, which is replaced with connective tissue and lipid infiltrates, creating wall motion abnormalities, reduced LVEF and conduction anomalies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The loss of cardiomyocytes also results in higher wall stress, coupled with reduced physiological adaptability of the dystrophin-deficient myocardium, leading to LV dilation and systolic dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>A screening electrocardiography (ECG) is recommended in all DMD patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The most common ECG abnormality is sinus tachycardia, with a prevalence of approximately 90% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Other ECG abnormalities include premature atrial and ventricular contractions, conduction blocks, atrial flutter or atrial fibrillation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. As the posterior wall of the LV is often most affected in DMD, patients typically present with tall R waves in V1 and deep Q waves in the inferolateral leads, as demonstrated in our patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Other common ECG features include ST depression, prolonged QT interval and increased QT dispersion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Due to the prevalence and severity of cardiac disease in DMD patients, recent guidelines recommend TTE at the age of diagnosis, followed by every 2 years until 10 years of age, and annually thereafter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Echocardiographic evidence of structural heart disease in DMD patients include LV hypertrophy, regional wall motion abnormalities, dilation of the cardiac chambers, valvular abnormalities, and LV systolic dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Furthermore, LV wall motion abnormalities progress in a set sequence in DMD patients, initially involving the posterior wall and the apex, followed by the interventricular septum and finally the anterior wall [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Despite the pervasiveness of structural heart disease in DMD patients, an isolated left ventricular aneurysm (LVA) is a rare occurrence. Ventricular aneurysm can be visualized on TTE as a dyskinetic or akinetic evagination of the ventricular wall [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Transthoracic echocardiography has a 93% sensitivity and 94% specificity for identifying LVA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>True LVA commonly result from myocardial injury, leading to thinning and fibrosis of all three layers of the myocardium, with subsequent remodelling of the ventricle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. As the incidence of rupture is low, true LVA's are managed conservatively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Indications for surgical treatment of LVA include refractory heart failure despite optimal medical therapy, intractable angina, systemic embolization, and/or incessant ventricular arrhythmias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Our case report serves as the first illustration of an asymptomatic inferoposterior aneurysm of the LV in a DMD patient in the English literature that was managed conservatively.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Despite the ubiquity of cardiomyopathy associated with DMD, ventricular aneurysms may be incidentally detected on routine non-invasive cardiac imaging.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
      <p>DMD: Duchenne muscular dystrophy; ECG: electrocardiography; LV: left ventricle; LVA: left ventricular aneurysm; LVEF: left ventricular ejection fraction; TTE: transthoracic echocardiography.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contributions</title>
      <p>XD, MZ, NS, and DJ contributed to the writing of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Note</title>
      <p>All work was preformed at the St. Boniface General Hospital, University of Manitoba 409 Tache Avenue, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada, R2H 2A6</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bushby</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Finkel</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Birnkrant</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Case</surname>
            <given-names>LE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clemens</surname>
            <given-names>PR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cripe</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kaul</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kinnett</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>McDonald</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pandya</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Poysky</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tomezsko</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Constantin</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <collab>DMD Care Considerations Working Group</collab>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and management of Duchenne muscular dystrophy, part 1: diagnosis, and pharmacological and psychosocial management</article-title>
          <source>Lancet Neurol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>93</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(09)70271-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19945913</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Finsterer</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>St&#xF6;llberger</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The heart in human dystrophinopathies</article-title>
          <source>Cardiology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>19</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000068446</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12589117</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Fayssoil</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nardi</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Orlikowski</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Annane</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cardiomyopathy in Duchenne muscular dystrophy: pathogenesis and therapeutics</article-title>
          <source>Heart Fail Rev</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>107</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10741-009-9156-8</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19943106</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Sasaki</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sakata</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kachi</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hirata</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ishihara</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ishikawa</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Sequential changes in cardiac structure and function in patients with Duchenne type muscular dystrophy: A two-dimensional echocardiographic study</article-title>
          <source>Am Heart J</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <fpage>937</fpage>
          <lpage>944</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-8703(98)70057-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9630096</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Friedman</surname>
            <given-names>BM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dunn</surname>
            <given-names>MI</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Post-infarction ventricular aneurysms</article-title>
          <source>Clin Cardiol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>505</fpage>
          <lpage>511</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/clc.4960180905</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7489606</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Flaherty</surname>
            <given-names>GT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>O'Neill</surname>
            <given-names>MN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Daly</surname>
            <given-names>KM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Folan-Curran</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>True aneurysm of the left ventricle: a case report and literature review</article-title>
          <source>Clin Anat</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>363</fpage>
          <lpage>368</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ca.1064</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11754225</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
