<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22230934</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3271029</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-7819-10-6</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7819-10-6</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Simultaneous development of adenocarcinoma and gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST) in the stomach: case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>Daigo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>yamamotd@hirakata.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Hamada</surname>
            <given-names>Yoshinori</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>yamamotd@hirakata.kmu.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsubota</surname>
            <given-names>Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>yamamotd@hirakata.kmu.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Kawakami</surname>
            <given-names>Katsuhiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>yamamotd@hirakata.kmu.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>Chizuko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref>
          <email>yamamotd@hirakata.kmu.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>Mitsuo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>yamamotd@hirakata.kmu.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Surgery, Kansai Medical University, Hirakata, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Surgery, Seiko hospital, Neyagawa, Osaka, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Seiko hospital, Neyagawa, Osaka, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Seiko hospital, Neyagawa, Osaka, Japan</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>9</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <fpage>6</fpage>
      <lpage>6</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9;2012 Yamamoto et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Yamamoto et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.wjso.com/content/10/1/6"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) and adenocarcinoma are distinct neoplasms originating from different cell layers. Approximately 20% of patients with GIST develop other cancers.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>We report a case of the coexistence of adenocarcinoma and gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST). Gastric endoscopy showed the ulcerated tumor with bleeding along the lesser curvature of the proximal stomach and a submucosal nodule that measured about 3 cm in diameter in the lower part of the stomach body. Their pathological examination showed gastric cancer (poorly differentiated diffuse adenocarcinoma) and GIST (low-risk category). Further, immunohistochemical staining for C-kit and CD34 was positive, while that for SMA and S-100 was negative.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Although it is not easy to speculate on the coexistence of adenocarcinoma and GIST, pre-and post-operative diagnoses may be essential, and such cancer development is not considered to be unusual.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>gastric cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>GIST</kwd>
        <kwd>stomach</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>In recent years, the synchronous occurrence of tumors of different histotypes arising in the same organ has been reported more frequently. Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) and adenocarcinoma are distinct neoplasms originating from different cell layers. Although adenocarcinoma constitutes the most common type of gastric tumor, the synchronous development of a GIST is relatively rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Here, we present and discuss a case of synchronous gastric cancer and GIST.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>The patient was a 67-year-old man, who had been admitted to the hospital due to melena and a hematocrit level of 20.1 %. Nasogastric intubation revealed a fresh blood clot in the stomach. Urinalysis, chest and abdominal films, and liver function tests were within normal limits, and serum creatinine was 1.2 mg/dl. Five units of packed blood cells were transfused promptly.</p>
      <p>Abdominal CT scan showed a well-defined, heterogeneous mass (3 &#xD7; 4 m) which was located in the lower part of the stomach body (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Gastric endoscopy showed the ulcerated tumor with bleeding along the lesser curvature of the proximal stomach (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) and a submucosal nodule that measured about 3 cm in diameter in the lower part of the stomach body (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). No other metastatic lesions in other organs were found on abdominal ultrasonography or the CT scan. High-grade gastrointestinal bleeding persisted, necessitating the additional transfusion of ten units of packed red blood cells. Subsequently, the patient underwent a total gastrectomy. During the operation, there was no other evidence of metastatic disease in the intra-abdominal cavity. Macroscopic examination of the total gastrectomy specimen showed Borrman type-2 tumor measuring 5 &#xD7; 6 cm and submucosal nodule measuring 3 &#xD7; 4 cm in the stomach (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). On histopathological examination, the Borrman type-2 tumor gastric tumor showed transmural infiltration by a poorly differentiated diffuse adenocarcinoma (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). There was no vascular invasion and no lymph node metastasis. Further histopathological examination of the submucosal nodule revealed GIST of the low-risk category [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], which was composed of cytologically bland spindle cells and showed a low mitotic index (&lt; 5/50HPF).</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>An abdominal computed tomography (CT) scan showing a heterogeneous mass (3 cm &#xD7; 4 cm) located in the lower part of the stomach body</bold>. The tumor is indicated with an arrow.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-10-6-1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Gastric endoscopy confirmed an ulcerated tumor with bleeding along the lesser curvature of the proximal stomach</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-10-6-2"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Gastric endoscopy showing a submucosal nodule that measured about 3 cm in diameter in the lower part of the stomach body</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-10-6-3"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Macroscopic examination of a total gastrectomy specimen showing Borrman type-2 tumor measuring 5 &#xD7; 6 cm (black arrow) and submucosal nodule measuring 3 &#xD7; 4 cm in the stomach (white arrow)</bold>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-10-6-4"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Microscopic examination of the proximal tumor in the stomach demonstrating typical histological findings of adenocarcinoma (A)</bold>. In addition, histopathological examination of the submucosal nodule revealed GIST of the low-risk category, composed of cytologically bland spindle cells with a low mitotic index (&lt; 5) (B). Immunohistochemistry indicated strong staining for CD34 (C) and C-kit (D), while negative results were observed for S-100 (E) and SMA (F).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-10-6-5"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The immunohistochemistry indicated strong staining for CD34 and C-kit, while expressions of SMA and S-100 were negative (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B-F</xref>). These findings confirmed the simultaneous development of gastric cancer and GIST. The patient was subsequently discharged without any complications.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The coexistence of adenocarcinoma and GIST is uncommon, and GIST has often been detected incidentally in the gastric mucosa or serosa, or, occasionally, intramurally, at surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Further, gastric tumors are derived from various other carcinomas and a precise pre- and post-operative diagnosis is important. However, when the GIST is submucosal or subserosal, the gastric mucosa may not be invaded, and endoscopic biopsies can be normal. In fact, in our case, the pre-operative biopsy fragments showed only adenocarcinoma, and the GIST was detected only in the resected stomach. Therefore, it may be difficult to diagnose preoperatively.</p>
      <p>Approximately 20% of patients with GIST develop other cancers and various hypotheses have been proposed regarding the simultaneous development of GIST and adenocarcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. It is not clear whether this is a simple incidental coexistence or the two lesions are connected by a causal relationship. Gene mutations may underlie tumor predisposition in patients harboring a double neoplasia. However, at present, no data are available to support such a hypothesis.</p>
      <p>GIST is the most common mesenchymal tumor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], accounting for about 0.1 to 3% of all GI tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. IHC staining, such as is for CD34, smooth muscle actin (SMA), and S100, as well as c-kit (CD117), is necessary to make an accurate diagnosis of GIST [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. It was revealed that c-kit and CD34 showed diffuse, strongly positive expressions in GIST. Rabin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] reported that 40 to 70% of GIST's were positive for CD34, 20 to 30% were positive for SMA, and 10% were positive for S100 protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Therefore, immunostaining of CD34, c-kit, SMA, and S100 is useful, and we could confirm the histological diagnosis using these markers. Accordingly, immunohistochemical as well as clinical information may be required in order to diagnose GIST appropriately. Although it is not easy to speculate on the coexistence of adenocarcinoma and GIST, pre- and post-operative diagnoses may be essential. Further the adjuvant therapy and lymphadenectomy are important. The refinement of risk stratification systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] will increase the precision of these systems for predicting recurrence, which may facilitate improvements in individual disease management.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this study and the related photos.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contributions</title>
      <p>The authors(s) wrote the original manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bircan</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Candir</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aydin</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baspinar</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Buldul</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kapucuoglu</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Karahan</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ciris</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Synchronous primary adenocarcinoma and gastrointestinal stromal tumour in the stomach. a report of two cases</article-title>
          <source>Turk J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>191</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15492920</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Rauf</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ahmad</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Muzzafar</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hussaini</surname>
            <given-names>AS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Synchronous occurrence of gastrointestinal stromal tumour and gastric adenocarcinoma. a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Pak Med Assoc</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>184</fpage>
          <lpage>186</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16711342</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>SW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>GH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hsieh</surname>
            <given-names>PP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Collision tumour of the Stomach. A case report of Mixed Stromal Tumour and Adenocarcinoma</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>332</fpage>
          <lpage>334</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004836-200210000-00010</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12352297</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Maiorana</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fante</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Maria Cesinaro</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Adriana Fano</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Synchronous occurrence of epithelial and stromal tumors in the stomach. a report of 6 cases</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>124</volume>
          <fpage>682</fpage>
          <lpage>686</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10782147</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hamada</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Okazaki</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kawakami</surname>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kanzaki</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Metastatic gastric tumor from renal cell carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Gastric Cancer</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>170</fpage>
          <lpage>173</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10120-009-0519-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19890698</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yoshida</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sumida</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ueyama</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kanematsu</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shoji</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sueoka</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tanaka</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tsubota</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kon</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Gastric Tumor from Metastasis of Breast Cancer</article-title>
          <source>Anticancer Res</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>3705</fpage>
          <lpage>3708</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20944157</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kaffes</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hollinshead</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Katelaris</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Synchronous primary adenocarcinoma, mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma and a stromal tumor in a Helicobacter pylori-infected stomach</article-title>
          <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>1033</fpage>
          <lpage>1036</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1746.2002.02649.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12167128</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Fletcher</surname>
            <given-names>CD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Berman</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Corless</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Diagnosis of gastrointestinal stromal tumors: a consensus approach</article-title>
          <source>Hum Pathol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>65</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/hupa.2002.123545</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12094370</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Pandurengan</surname>
            <given-names>RK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dumont</surname>
            <given-names>AG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Araujo</surname>
            <given-names>DM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ludwig</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ravi</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Patel</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garber</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Benjamin</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Strom</surname>
            <given-names>SS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Trent</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Survival of patients with multiple primary malignancies: a study of 783 patients with gastrointestinal stromal tumor</article-title>
          <source>Ann Oncol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>2107</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdq078</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20348145</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Pidhorecky</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cheney</surname>
            <given-names>RT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kraybill</surname>
            <given-names>WG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gibbs</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Gastrointestinal stromal tumors. current diagnosis, biologic behavior, and management</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>705</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10434-000-0705-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034250</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Rabin</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chikman</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lavy</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sandbank</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Maklakovsky</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gold-Deutch</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: a 19 year experience</article-title>
          <source>Isr Med Assoc J</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>98</fpage>
          <lpage>102</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19432038</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>FY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qi</surname>
            <given-names>JP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>FL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>AP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Clinicopathological and immunohistochemical analysis of gastrointestinal stromal tumor</article-title>
          <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>4161</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16830365</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kang Na</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jung Ra</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hwang</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Clinicopathological and Immunohistochemical Features of Gastointestinal Stromal Tumors</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Res Treat</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>143</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4143/crt.2010.42.3.135</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20948918</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Patel</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Navigating risk stratification systems for the management of patients with GIST</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1698</fpage>
          <lpage>704</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-010-1496-z</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21213058</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
