<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJO</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Korean Journal of Ophthalmology : KJO</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8942</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2092-9382</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Ophthalmological Society</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22131787</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3223717</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3341/kjo.2011.25.6.459</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Horner's Syndrome with Abducens Nerve Palsy</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>Na Hee</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lim</surname>
            <given-names>Key Hwan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sung</surname>
            <given-names>Sun Hee</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Ewha Womans University Mokdong Hospital, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Ewha Medical Research Institute, Ewha Womans University School of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Corresponding Author: Key Hwan Lim, MD. Department of Ophthalmology, Ewha Womans University Mokdong Hospital, #911-1 Mok-dong, Yangcheon-gu, Seoul 158-710, Korea. Tel: 82-2-2650-5659, Fax: 82-2-2650-4334, <email>limkh@ewha.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>25</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>459</fpage>
      <lpage>462</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2011 The Korean Ophthalmological Society</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 68-year-old male patient presented with a week of sudden diplopia. He had been diagnosed with nasopharyngeal cancer 8 months prior and had undergone chemotherapy with radiotherapy. Eight-prism diopter right esotropia in the primary position and a remarkable limitation in abduction in his right eye were observed. Other pupillary disorders and lid drooping were not found. After three weeks, the marginal reflex distance 1 was 3 mm in the right eye and 5 mm in the left eye. The pupil diameter was 2.5 mm in the right eye, and 3 mm in the left eye under room illumination. Under darkened conditions, the pupil diameter was 3.5 mm in the right eye, and 5 mm in the left eye. After topical application of 0.5% apraclonidine, improvement in the right ptosis and reversal pupillary dilatation were observed. On brain magnetic resonance imaging, enhanced lesions on the right cavernous sinus, both sphenoidal sinuses, and skull base suggested the invasion of nasopharyngeal cancer. Lesions on the cavernous sinus need to be considered in cases of abducens nerve palsy and ipsilateral Horner's syndrome.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Abducens nerve diseases</kwd>
        <kwd>Cavernous sinus</kwd>
        <kwd>Horner's syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Nasopharyngeal neoplasms</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>The cavernous sinus is a structure located near the center of the skull base, that is situated bilaterally on the medial side of both sphenoid sinuses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. It contains the oculomotor, trochlear, abducens, and the first two divisions of the trigerminal nerve as well as the oculosympathetic nerve plexus around the internal carotid artery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. These anatomical particularities are causes of solitary or combined diverse impairments of cranial nerves and postganglionic Horner's syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Tumour involvement of the cavernous sinus region due to distant metastasis or local extension has been reported in &lt;1% of cancer patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Furthermore, the brain is a rarely involved site with head and neck cancers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Nasopharyngeal carcinoma can spread through the foramen lacerum and invade the cavernous sinus, resulting in cranial nerve injuries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. In previous reports, there have been only 13 cases of combined abducens nerve palsy and ipsilateral Horner's syndrome secondary to metastatic neoplasm within the cavernous sinus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Here, we report a case with a combination of 6th nerve palsy and incomplete Horner's syndrome caused by invasive nasopharyngeal cancer in the cavernous sinus.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>We examined a 68-year-old man who had been suffering from diplopia for a week. The patient had been diagnosed with a nasopharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma 8 months prior and had received cisplantin-based chemotherapy with radiotherapy. On the first examination, 8-prism diopter right esotropia in the primary position and a remarkable limitation in abduction in his right eye were observed. Other pupillary disorders and lid drooping were not found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). After 3 weeks, the patient complained of lid drooping in the right eye. The marginal reflex distance 1 (MRD1) was 3 mm in the right eye and 5 mm in the left. In addition to right mild ptosis, anisocoric pupils with a smaller right pupil were found and the anisocoria increased in the dark. After topical application of 0.5% apraclonidine (Iopidine; Alcon, Fort Worth, TX, USA), the patient's right pupil dilated from 2.5 mm to 5 mm in bright light and the right MRD1 increased from 3 mm to 5 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Hypohydrosis and other neurologic abnormalities were not observed. Brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) revealed newly appeared gadolinium-enhanced mucosal thickening in both sphenoid sinuses combined with bony destruction of the skull base. These lesions extended to the right cavernous sinus with encasement of the internal carotid artery (ICA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The patient underwent bilateral functional endoscopic sinus surgery with biopsy. Pathology was consistent with poorly differentiated invasive squamous cell carcinoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Seven weeks later, the esotropia worsened and the limitation of abduction, anisocoria, and right ptosis persisted. No other neurologic abnormalities were found up to the last visit. The patient died of cancerous cachexia 15 months after the diagnosis of nasopharyngeal cancer.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Neither abducens nerve palsy nor Horner's syndrome provides an indication of the location of the lesion. However, when both are present, it is important to localize the site of the lesion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. When these rare clinical features are manifested, we have to consider paratrigerminal syndrome or a lesion of the posterior cavernous sinus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Sympathetic nerve fibers travel over the wall of the carotid artery and in the cavernous portion the fibers leave the ICA and accompany the abducens nerve for only a few millimeters in the posterior portion of the sinus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). Therefore, we could consider a posterior cavernous sinus lesion due to combined abducens nerve palsy. Furthermore, incomplete Horner's syndrome without anhydrosis, as in the case reported here, indicates the involvement of the periarterial sympathetic plexus at the third angulation point [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. To date, only 13 cases with this combination of symptoms secondary to metastatic neoplasm within the cavernous sinus have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Regarding the primary lesions in these cases, there were 1 small cell lung cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], 1 parotid cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], 1 breast cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], 1 gastric cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], 1 uterine cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], 3 undetermined origins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and 3 nasopharyngeal cancers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Unlike in other three nasopharyngeal cancer cases reported by Hirao et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], the cancer only invaded the 6th nerve and sympathetic fiber without involvement of the 5th nerve in this case. Malignant tumors that affect the cavernous sinus commonly result in the 5th and the 6th nerve injuries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The more medial location of the abducens nerve has been postulated as the reason for its frequent involvement when confronted with the compressive forces in a confined space or direct invasion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In this case, the nasopharyngeal cancer extended through the sphenoidal sinus demonstrated by brain MRI and positron emission tomography (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Therefore, the cancer affected only the 6th nerve without involvement the 3rd nerve, which occupies a superior position at the lateral wall of the sinus, in addition to the 4th and 5th nerve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Although autopsy was not permitted and there was a limitation of anatomical access, we suggest that tumor cells in the sphenoidal sinus had spread to the 6th nerve in the cavernous sinus, and then perineurally metastasized to the oculosympathetic nerve fibers before joining the first division of the 5th nerve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. A plausible alternative to cocaine or hydroxyamphetamine in the diagnosis of Horner's syndrome is apraclonidine, a direct &#x3B1;-receptor agonist with strong &#x3B1;2 and weak &#x3B1;1 activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. In patients with Horner's syndrome, reversal of anisocoria and improvement of ptosis occur after application of apraclonidine due to denervation supersensitivity of the &#x3B1;1 receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. With respect to the length of survival in patients with tumor invasion of the cavernous sinus region as reported in the literature, most individuals live no longer than six months and the ultimate outcome is a dismal 75% to 85% expected mortality within 2 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The patient described in this report died 5 months after the presentation of combination abducens nerve palsy with Horner's syndrome. In other words, this manifestation may be a significant predictor of survival in addition to the location of the lesion. This is the first reported case of abducens nerve palsy with Horner's syndrome due to tumor invasion into the cavernous sinus in a Korean patient. The presence of Horner's syndrome and the 6th nerve palsy should be cautiously investigated to confirm the existence of the cavernous sinus lesions.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>This paper was presented as an e-poster in 102nd Korea Ophthalmological Meeting on November 6-8, 2009 in Goyang, Korea.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saeki</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirai</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaura</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unusual cranial nerve palsy caused by cavernous sinus aneurysms. Clinical and anatomical considerations reviewed</article-title>
          <source>Surg Neurol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>143</fpage>
          <lpage>148</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10447280</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rhoton</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The cavernous sinus, the cavernous venous plexus, and the carotid collar</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <issue>4 Suppl</issue>
          <fpage>S375</fpage>
          <lpage>S410</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12234454</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ampil</surname>
              <given-names>FL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heldmann</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balfour</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Involvement of the cavernous sinus by malignant (extracranial) tumour: palliation in six cases without surgery</article-title>
          <source>J Craniomaxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>161</fpage>
          <lpage>164</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10964552</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuda</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yorinaga</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamada</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Combination of abducens nerve palsy and ipsilateral postganglionic Horner syndrome as an initial manifestation of uterine cervical cancer</article-title>
          <source>Intern Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>1457</fpage>
          <lpage>1460</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19687598</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>George</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haydar</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adams</surname>
              <given-names>WM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imaging of Horner's syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Clin Radiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>499</fpage>
          <lpage>505</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18374711</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parkinson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bernard, Mitchell, Horner syndrome and others?</article-title>
          <source>Surg Neurol</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>221</fpage>
          <lpage>223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">224518</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kano</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niranjan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kondziolka</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of palliative radiosurgery when cancer invades the cavernous sinus</article-title>
          <source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>709</fpage>
          <lpage>715</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18692328</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Curry</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Newlon</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watson</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cavernous sinus metastasis from laryngeal squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <fpage>567</fpage>
          <lpage>568</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11700465</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Djalilian</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tekin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hall</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adams</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metastatic head and neck squamous cell carcinoma to the brain</article-title>
          <source>Auris Nasus Larynx</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11772490</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuda</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishikawa</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kishiro</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Abducens nerve palsy and postganglionic Horner syndrome with or without severe headache</article-title>
          <source>Intern Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>851</fpage>
          <lpage>855</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16908941</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gutman</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levartovski</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldhammer</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sixth nerve palsy and unilateral Horner's syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmology</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>913</fpage>
          <lpage>916</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3763136</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuda</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishikawa</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asayama</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Abducens nerve palsy and Horner syndrome due to metastatic tumor in the cavernous sinus</article-title>
          <source>Intern Med</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>644</fpage>
          <lpage>646</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16020898</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Slamovits</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cahill</surname>
              <given-names>KV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sibony</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Orbital fine-needle aspiration biopsy in patients with cavernous sinus syndrome</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>1037</fpage>
          <lpage>1042</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6631497</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilhelm</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ochsner</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kopycziok</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Horner's syndrome: a retrospective analysis of 90 cases and recommendations for clinical handling</article-title>
          <source>Ger J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>96</fpage>
          <lpage>102</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1477633</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hirao</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oku</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sugasawa</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Three cases of abducens nerve palsy accompanied by Horner syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Nihon Ganka Gakkai Zasshi</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>520</fpage>
          <lpage>524</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16884072</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kurihara</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Abducens nerve palsy and ipsilateral incomplete Horner syndrome: a significant sign of locating the lesion in the posterior cavernous sinus</article-title>
          <source>Intern Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>993</fpage>
          <lpage>994</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17015998</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ozveren</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uchida</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erol</surname>
              <given-names>FS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolated abducens nerve paresis associated with incomplete Horner's syndrome caused by petrous apex fracture: case report and anatomical study</article-title>
          <source>Neurol Med Chir (Tokyo)</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>494</fpage>
          <lpage>498</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11760384</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Freedman</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topical apraclonidine in the diagnosis of suspected Horner syndrome</article-title>
          <source>J Neuroophthalmol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15937427</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Ocular movements. Right esotropia and limitation of abduction in the right eye consistent with right abducens nerve palsy were observed.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-459-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A1,B1) Before topical application of 0.5% apraclonidine in room light. Pupil right eye (OD) measured 2.5 mm (A1), pupil left eye (OS) measured 3.0 mm (B1). (A2,B2) After topical application of 0.5% apraclonidine in bright light. Pupil OD measures 5.0 mm (A2), pupil OS measured 4.0 mm (B2). Reversal of pupillary dilatation under topical application of 0.5% apraclonidine was detected. (C1,C2) Note also the improvement of the mild ptosis in the right side after topical application of 0.5% apraclonidine.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-459-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Axial T1-weighted contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance images. Ill-defined right cavernous sinus lesion extending into the sphenoidal sinus and encasement of the internal carotid were found.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-459-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A photomicrograph of the frozen biopsy during the functional endoscopic sinus surgery showing the moderately to poorly differentiated squamous cells in the right sphenoid sinus (H&amp;E, &#xD7;200).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-459-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Schematic drawing demonstrating the anatomy of the posterior portion of the cavernous sinus on the right side. Oculosympathetic nerve fibers leave the internal carotid artery, and then join the abducens nerve for a short distance in the posterior portion of the cavernous sinus (arrow). CN III = oculomotor nerve; CN IV = trochlear nerve; CN V = trigeminal nerve; ICA = internal carotid; CN VI = abducens nerve; Sym = oculosympathetic nerve.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-459-g005"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
