<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasit Vectors</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasit Vectors</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Parasites &amp; Vectors</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1756-3305</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22916686</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3469345</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1756-3305-5-178</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-5-178</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><italic>Troglostrongylus brevior</italic> and <italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic> (Strongylida: Crenosomatidae) as agents of broncho-pulmonary infestation in domestic cats</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Brianti</surname>
            <given-names>Emanuele</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>ebrianti@unime.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Gaglio</surname>
            <given-names>Gabriella</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>ggaglio@unime.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Giannetto</surname>
            <given-names>Salvatore</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>sgiannetto@unime.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Annoscia</surname>
            <given-names>Giada</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>giavin@libero.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Latrofa</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Stefania</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>stefania.latrofa@uniba.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Dantas-Torres</surname>
            <given-names>Filipe</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>filipe.vet@globo.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>Traversa</surname>
            <given-names>Donato</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref>
          <email>dtraversa@unite.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8">
          <name>
            <surname>Otranto</surname>
            <given-names>Domenico</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>domenico.otranto@uniba.it</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Dipartimento di Sanit&#xE0; Pubblica Veterinaria, Facolt&#xE0; di Medicina Veterinaria, Universit&#xE0; degli Studi di Messina, Messina, Italy</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Dipartimento di Sanit&#xE0; Pubblica e Zootecnia, Facolt&#xE0; di Medicina Veterinaria, Universit&#xE0; degli Studi di Bari, Valenzano, BA, Italy</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Departamento de Imunologia, Centro de Pesquisas Aggeu Magalh&#xE3;es, Funda&#xE7;&#xE3;o Oswaldo Cruz, Recife, PE, Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Dipartimento di Scienze Biomediche Comparate, Facolt&#xE0; di Medicina Veterinaria, Universit&#xE0; degli Studi di Teramo, Teramo, Italy</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <fpage>178</fpage>
      <lpage>178</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9;2012 Brianti et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Brianti et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.parasitesandvectors.com/content/5/1/178"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p><italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> is currently regarded as the main metastrongyloid infesting domestic cats, whereas the reports of <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp. in domestic and wild felids largely remain anecdotic. This paper reports on pulmonary infestation caused by <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior</italic> and <italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic> in two kittens and describes, for the first time, associated clinical presentations and pathological features. Morphometrical, molecular and phylogenetic analyses have also been conducted to differentiate here the examined <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> species from <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>, towards a clearer delineation of metastrongyloids affecting cats.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Two kittens were referred for respiratory distress and hospitalized with a diagnosis of severe aelurostrongylosis, based on the presence of metastrongyloid larvae in the faeces. Despite prompt treatment, kittens died within 48 hours. Both kittens were submitted to necropsy to determine the cause of death.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>At necropsy, nematode specimens were found in the trachea, bronchi and bronchioles and were associated with respiratory signs (i.e., dyspnoea, polypnea, severe coughing and nasal discharge). Morphology and measurements of adult parasites found allowed the unequivocal identification of <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic>, even if first stage larvae were rather similar to those of <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>. Briefly, <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> larvae were shorter in length and lacking the typical knob-like terminal end of <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>. Molecular and phylogenetic analyses corroborated morphological identification and provided data on mitochondrial and ribosomal DNA genes of <italic>T. brevior</italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Data presented here indicate that <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> may cause major respiratory distress in domestic cats. Consequently, these two species should be included, along with <italic>A. abstrusus,</italic> in the differential diagnosis of cat bronchopulmonary affections and treatment protocols need to be evaluated. Through research on the biology, epidemiology and control of <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp. infestations in domestic cats are advisable to implement current knowledge on these neglected metastrongyloids.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Cat</kwd>
        <kwd>Diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Italy</kwd>
        <kwd>Metastrongyloidea</kwd>
        <kwd>Molecular biology</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Nematode infestations of the cardio-pulmonary system of dogs and cats have recently gained thescientific interest of researchers and practitioners, due to the clinical severity of the conditions they cause and to their spread throughout many Europeancountries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Among them, <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> (Strongylida: Angiostrongylidae) is commonly regarded as the only metastrongyloid of domestic cats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Broncho-pulmonary infestations by <italic>A. abstrusus</italic> are widespread throughout most European countries with prevalence rates ranging from 1% to 24.4%, according to sampled populations and detection procedures (e.g., copromicroscopy or molecular detection) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Actually, other metastrongyloids have been reported as causative agents of respiratory infestation in domestic cats. For instance, <italic>Oslerus rostratus</italic> (Strongylida: Filaroididae) has been recorded to infest the pulmonary system of cats with prevalence rates up to 24% in Spain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Meanwhile, <italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic> (Strongylida: Crenosomatidae) was retrieved once at the necropsy of a domestic cat from Blantyre (Nyasaland, Malawi) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and, larvae of a yet unclassified <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> sp. have recently been identified in faeces of domestic cats from Ibiza (Spain), which exhibited respiratory disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p>
      <p>The genus <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> encompasses four nematode species (i.e., <italic> T. brevior</italic><italic> T. subcrenatus</italic><italic> T. troglostrongylus</italic> and <italic> T. wilsoni</italic>), which are commonly found in the trachea and bronchi of wild felids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Albeit scantly studied, <italic> Troglostrongylus </italic> spp. display an indirect life cycle similar to that of <italic> A. abstrusus </italic>, with terrestrial molluscs serving as intermediate hosts and small mammals (e.g., mice) as paratenic ones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Larvae of <italic> T. brevior </italic> may develop in several species of molluscs (i.e., <italic> Helicella barbesiana </italic><italic> Helicella vestalis </italic><italic> Limax flavus </italic><italic> Monacha syriaca </italic><italic> Retinella nitellina </italic> and <italic> Theba pisana </italic>), becoming infective from 8 to 40 days depending on the environmental temperature (i.e., between 22&#xB0;-27&#xB0;C and between 4&#xB0;-8&#xB0;C, respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Nonetheless, the scant scientific information available on the distribution and pathogenicity of <italic> Troglostrongylus </italic> sp. in domestic cats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] might indicate that this infestation occurs sporadically or that it is misdiagnosed with the commonest <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>.</p>
      <p>This paper reports on pulmonary infestation by <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> in two kittens and describes, for the first time, associated clinical presentations and pathological features. Additionally, morphometric, molecular and phylogenetic analyses have also been conducted to differentiate the <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> species here examined from <italic>A. abstrusus</italic> towards a clearer delineation of metastrongyloids affecting cats.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Case description</title>
        <p>A 3-month-old female privately owned kitten (case 1), and a 3-month-old female stray kitten (case 2) were referred to the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine of Messina (Sicily region, Italy) on April 2010 and June 2011. Both animals exhibited respiratory signs such as dyspnoea, polypnea, severe coughing and nasal discharge (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). In addition, case 1 had developed inappetence and lethargy in the 48 h prior to referral while case 2 was dehydrated and in poor general condition at the moment of the clinical examination. Thoracic radiographs, performed only for case 2, showed diffuse increase of radiograph density and marked bronchial pattern in diaphragmatic lobes. Leucocytosis (i.e., 26.3&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>3</sup>/&#x3BC;l in case 1, and 20.9&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10<sup>3</sup>/&#x3BC;l in case 2) was diagnosed while biochemistry was within normal limits in both cases. <italic>Toxocara cati</italic> eggs were detected at the copromicroscopy using the flotation method in case 1 and of nematode larvae, resembling those of <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>, were retrieved by the Baermann technique in both cases. Kittens were both hospitalized with a diagnosis of severe aelurostrongylosis and antiparasitic drugs (imidacloprid 10 mg/kg/moxidectin 1 mg/kg spot-on in case 1, and fenbendazole 50 mg/kg PO once every 24 h in case 2) were administered. Both kittens also underwent systemic therapy with intravenous fluids, antibiotics (amoxicillin 20 mg/kg IV twice every 24 h and enrofloxacin 5 mg/kg IV once every 24 h) and placed in an oxygen chamber but they did not show any improvement with <italic>exitus</italic> within 24-48 h after hospitalization. Animals were not enrolled in any experimental trial. Kittens were hospitalized and keep according to Animal Welfare and Good Clinical Practice (VICH GL9-GCP, 2 "Good Clinical Practice", CVMP, June 2000) guidelines. In both cases necropsy was requested and authorized by the owners.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Pathological findings and parasite identification</title>
        <p>Carcasses of both kittens were subjected to necropsy. Parasitic specimens collected from lungs were washed in saline solution and stored in 70% ethanol (case 1) and in formalin (case 2). Worms were individually mounted on slides by the glycerol-ethanol method and microscopically observed. Microscopic images and measures were taken by using a digital image processing system (AxioVision rel. 4.8, Carl Zeiss, Germany). Parasites were sexed and identified at the species level by morphometrical and morphological keys [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Slide-mounted specimens of both sexes were stored in the parasite collection of the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine of Messina. In addition, gross anatomical findings, anatomical localization of parasites, and their morphometric features were also compared with those from <italic>A. abstrusus</italic> from a road-killed stray cat (E.B. unpublished observations).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Molecular procedures and analyses</title>
        <p>The molecular identification was performed by extracting genomic DNA from two parasite specimens of case 1 using a commercial kit (DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue Kit, Qiagen, GmbH, Hilden, Germany) in accordance with the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions. Unfortunately, all attempts to extract genomic DNA from nematodes retrieved from case 2 failed, probably because the specimens were kept in formalin.</p>
        <p>A mitochondrial partial cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit 1 gene (p<italic>cox</italic>1, ~400 bp), 18S (~1700 bp) and internal transcribed spacer 2 (ITS2, ~630 bp) of ribosomal RNA gene were amplified. In particular, p<italic>cox</italic>1 was amplified by using the degenerated set of primers T<italic>cox</italic>F (5'-TGGARYTRTCTAARCCNGG-3') and T<italic>cox</italic>R (5'-GGAGGATAHACHGTYCAHC-3'), which was designed, using the criteria of Sharrocks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], on the basis of the consensus sequences obtained by the multiple alignment of sequences of Metastrongyloidea available in GenBank<sup>TM</sup> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The 18S, ITS2 and flanking sequences of the 5.8S and 28S rRNA genes were amplified by two sets of primers (NC18SF1: 5'-AAAGATTAAGCCATGCA-3' and NC5BR: 5'- GCAGGTTCACCTACAGAT-3'; D: 5'-GAGTCGATGAAGAACGCAG-3' and B: 5'-GAATTCTGGTTAGTTTCTTTTCCT-3', respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Each reaction for p<italic>cox</italic>1 and 18S consisted of 4 &#x3BC;l genomic DNA and 46 &#x3BC;l of PCR mix containing 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl, pH 8.3 and 50 mM KCl, 250 &#x3BC;M of each dNTP, 50 pmol of each primer and 1.25 U of Ampli Taq Gold (Applied Biosystems). Approximately 100 ng of genomic DNA were added to each PCR and samples without DNA were included with each batch of sample tested. The p<italic>cox</italic>1 were amplified using the following conditions: 95&#xB0;C for 10 min (first polymerase activation and denaturation); followed by 35 cycles of 95&#xB0;C for 1 min (denaturation); 48&#xB0;C for 1 min (annealing), 72&#xB0;C for 1 min (extension); and a final extension at 72&#xB0;C for 7 min. The PCR of 18S and ITS2 were carried out by 30&#x2013;40 cycles of 94&#xB0;C for 30 sec (denaturation), 72&#xB0;C for 1 min and 45 sec (extension), and annealing temperatures of 57&#x2013;58&#xB0;C for 30&#x2013;45 sec, respectively. Polymerase activation and denaturation and final extension were similar to those above. All amplicons were resolved in ethidium bromide-stained (2%) agarose (Gellyphor, Euroclone, Italy) gels and sized by comparison with markers in the Gene Ruler<sup>TM</sup> 1 kb DNA Ladder (MBI Fermentas, Vilnius, Lithuania). Gels were photographed by a digital documentation system (Gel Doc 2000, BioRad, UK). Amplicons were purified using Ultrafree-DA columns (Amicon, Millipore; Bedford, USA) and then sequenced directly using the <italic>Taq</italic> DyeDeoxyTerminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (v.2, Applied Biosystems) in an automated sequencer (ABI-PRISM 377). </p>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>GenBank</bold>
              <sup>
                <bold> TM </bold>
              </sup>
              <bold>accession numbers (AN) of the Metastrongyloidea used in the phylogenetic analyses for 18S rRNA and the internal transcribed spacer 2 (ITS2) genes</bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
            <colgroup>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="center"/>
              <col align="center"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead valign="top">
              <tr>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>DNA region</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>Species</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>Host</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Country</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>AN</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="top">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">18S<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Felis catus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ920366<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Angiostrongylus costaricensis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Sigmodon hispidus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">EF514913<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Angiostrongylus costaricensis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">DQ116748<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Angiostrongylus dujardini</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Myodes glareolus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">EF514915<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Angiostrongylus malaysiensis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Rattus tiomanicus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">EF514914<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Angiostrongylus vasorum</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Vulpes vulpes</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">EF514916<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Angiostrongylus vasorum</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Vulpes vulpes</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ920365<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Crenosoma mephitidis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Mephitis mephitis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295805<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Crenosoma</italic> sp.<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Ailurus fulgens</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">GU475120<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Crenosoma striatum</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Erinaceus europaeus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">UK<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">GU214747<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Crenosoma vulpis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Vulpes vulpes</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ920367<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Didelphostrongylus hayesi</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Didelphis virginiana</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295806<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Filaroides martis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Neovison vison</italic> (=<italic>Mustela vison</italic>)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295807<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Halocercus invaginatus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Phocoena phocoena</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295808<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Metastrongyloidea</italic> sp.<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Ailurus fulgens</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">GU475121<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Metastrongylus elongatus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ920363<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Metastrongylus salmi</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295809<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Muellerius capillaris</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Ovis aries</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295810<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Nippostrongylus brasiliensis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rattus</italic> sp.<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ920356<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Oslerus rostratus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Lynx rufus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">GU946678<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Oslerus osleri</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Canis latrans</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295812<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Otostrongylus circumlitus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Mirounga angustirostris</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295813<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Otostrongylus</italic> sp.<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>-</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">OSU81589<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Parafilaroides decorus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Zalophus californianus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295814<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Parafilaroides</italic> sp.<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">U81590<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Protostrongylus rufescens</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Ovis aries</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ920364<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Pseudalius inflexus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Phocoena phocoena</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295816<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Skrjabingylus chitwoodorum</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Mephitis mephitis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295819<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Stenurus minor</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Phocoena phocoena</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295817<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Torynurus convolutus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Phocoena phocoena</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295818<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> sp.<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Felis catus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Spain<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">GU946677<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Troglostrongylus wilsoni</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Lynx rufus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">USA<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY295820<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">ITS2<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Felis silvestris catus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Italy<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">DQ372965<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Felis silvestris catus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Italy<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">EU034168<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Angiostrongylus dujardini</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">France<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">GQ181113<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Angiostrongylus vasorum</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Canis familiaris</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Germany<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">GU045375<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Elaphostrongylus alces</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Alces alces</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Sweden<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504028<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Elaphostrongylus alces</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Alces alces</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Sweden<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504034<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Elaphostrongylus cervi</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Cervus elaphus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">New Zealand<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504032<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Elaphostrongylus cervi</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Cervus elaphus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">New Zealand<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504026<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Elaphostrongylus rangiferi</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Rangifer tarandus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY648408<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Elaphostrongylus rangiferi</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Rangifer tarandus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504027<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Elaphostrongylus rangiferi</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Rangifer tarandus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504033<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Halocercus invaginatus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>-</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">FJ787301<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Metastrongylus asymmetricus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Y08006<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Metastrongylus elongatus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Estonia<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ305377<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Metastrongylus elongatus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Estonia<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ305376<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Metastrongylus elongatus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Estonia<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AJ305381<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Metastrongylus pudendotectus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Y08008<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Muellerius capillaris</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Ovis aries</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY679527<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Muellerius capillaris</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Ovis aries</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY679528<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Nematodirus battus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>-</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">JF345079<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Otostrongylus circumlitus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Mirounga angustirostris</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF130455<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Parelaphostrongylus odocoilei</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Ovis aries</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AY648402<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Parelaphostrongylus odocoilei</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Odocoileus hemionus hemionus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504031<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Parelaphostrongylus tenuis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Odocoileus virginianus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504035<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Parelaphostrongylus tenuis</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Odocoileus virginianus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Canada<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">AF504029<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Pseudalius inflexus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>-</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">FJ767935<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Stenurus minor</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>-</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">FJ787302<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">&#xA0;</td>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>Torynurus convolutus</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <italic>-</italic>
                </td>
                <td align="left">-</td>
                <td align="left">AY464532</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p><italic>Nippostrongylus brasiliensis</italic> and <italic>Nematodirus battus</italic> were used as outgroups.</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Sequences were determined from both strands (using the same primers individually as for the PCR) and the electropherograms verified by eye. In order to ensure open reading frames, the nucleotide sequence of p<italic>cox</italic>1 was conceptually translated into amino acid sequence using the invertebrate mitochondrial code MEGA5 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Sequences for all genes were compared with those available in the GenBank&#x2122; database by Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. In order to investigate the relationships among metastrongyloids affecting wild and domestic carnivores, sequences of 18S and ITS2 were analysed with those available in GenBank<sup>TM</sup> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) and the evolutionary history was inferred using the neighbour-joining method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. The bootstrap consensus trees inferred from over 7,000 replicates were taken to represent the evolutionary history of the taxa analysed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Branches corresponding to partitions reproduced in less than 50% bootstrap were collapsed and the percentage of replicate trees in which the associated taxa clustered together in the bootstrap test was shown next to the branches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Phylogenetic analyses were conducted in MEGA5 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Sequences of <italic>Nippostrongylus brasiliensis </italic>(Strongylida: Heligmonellidae) and <italic>Nematodirus battus</italic> (Strongylida: Molineidae) were used as outgroups. The nucleotide sequences analyzed in this paper are available in the GenBank<sup>TM</sup> database under accession numbers: JX290562 (18S); JX290563 (<italic>cox</italic>1); JX290564 (ITS2).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Pathological findings</title>
        <p>In case 1, lungs were congested and swollen with multifocal areas of haemorrhages, diffused hepatisation and lobular bronchopneumonia in lobes of the right lung (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A). The cut surface was oedematous with catarrhal exudate draining from small airways and parasites were present in respiratory tracts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B-1C). Organs of abdominal cavity appeared normal.</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Gross anatomy and parasites collected at the necropsy of case 1.</bold> Lungs were congested and swollen, lobular bronchopneumonia was noticed in lobes of the right lung (<bold>A</bold>). Several parasites were present in respiratory tracts (<bold>B-C</bold>). A total of twelve slender worms (up to 13 mm length), identified as <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior</italic> (<bold>D</bold>), were collected from bronchi and bronchioles.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-5-178-1"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In case 2, lungs were diffusely congested and swollen with a large area of consolidation in the right diaphragmatic lobe (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A). Nematodes mixed with catarrhal exudate were revealed when the trachea was cut (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B). Other organs and apparatus were normal at gross examination. In both cases, the respiratory failure was identified as the cause of death.</p>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Gross anatomy and parasites collected at the necropsy of case 2.</bold> Lungs were diffusely congested and swollen with a large area of consolidation in the right diaphragmatic lobe (<bold>A</bold>). Parasites mixed with catarrhal exudate were revealed when cutting the trachea (<bold>B</bold>), A total of twenty-two whitish nematodes (up to 24 mm length), identified as <italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) were collected from the trachea and large bronchi.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-5-178-2"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Slender and whitish nematodes (12 from case 1 and 22 from case 2) were collected from bronchi, bronchioles (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>D) and from trachea and large bronchi (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C) in case 1 and 2, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Parasite identification</title>
        <p>Parasites collected from case 1 were thin and cylindroid presenting a cuticle that was inflated and thrown into folds. The oesophagus was short and club-shaped, the stoma small and weakly developed. The excretory gland was large and extending almost to the posterior extremity of the body opening, in both sexes, at the first third of the oesophagus (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A). Nine females and three males were identified. Briefly, females were 6&#x2013;13 mm in length and 0.34&#x2013;0.43 mm in width with a conical and short tail (125&#x2013;168 &#x3BC;m) and inflated cuticle (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>C; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The gravid uterus contained larvated eggs. Males were 5&#x2013;6 mm in length and 0.43 mm in width and the oesophagus was 281&#x2013;301 &#x3BC;m length (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). The caudal edge of males showed a well-developed, undivided bursa composed by a dorsal ray elongated with four apical papillae, externo-dorsal and antero-lateral rays were well separated, postero- and medio-lateral rays joined except for the distal third, ventral rays were short and fused except at their end (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>E). The spicules (0.60&#x2013;0.63 mm) were equal in length, thin and transversely striated for most of their extent with serrated edges (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>G; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). First stage larvae (L1) (339.3 &#x3BC;m in length and 18.6 &#x3BC;m in width) had a rhabditoid oesophagus, numerous intestinal cells filled with granules and pointed tail with pronounced dorsal cuticular spine and a shallower ventral one (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Morphology and measurements of adult and larval nematodes collected from case 1 were consistent with those of <italic>T. brevior</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. </p>
        <fig id="F3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Light microscope images depicting morphometrical differences of cephalic region, caudal region, male bursa and spicules between </bold><bold><italic>Troglostrongylus brevior </italic></bold><bold>(A, C, E and G) and </bold><bold><italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus </italic></bold><bold>(B, D, F and H).</bold> Scale bars&#x2009;= 100 &#x3BC;m (A-F), 50 &#x3BC;m (G-H).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-5-178-3"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="T2">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>Anatomical localization and morphometrical features of adult stages of </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>, </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>and </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic>
              </bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
            <colgroup>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead valign="top">
              <tr>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Species</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Localization</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Sex</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Length (mm)</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Width</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Oesophagus</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Tail (anus-caudal end)</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="left">
                  <bold>Spicule length</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="top">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> (Gerichter, 1949)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Pulmonary parenchyma<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Male<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x2013;6<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">54&#x2013;64<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">240&#x2013;270<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">130&#x2013;220<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Female<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">10&#x2013;10.4<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">80<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">300<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">27&#x2013;29<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">(present study)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Bronchi and bronchioles<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Male (n&#x2009;= 3)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">5&#x2013;6<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">294&#x2013;365<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">281&#x2013;301<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">600&#x2013;631<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Female (n&#x2009;= 6)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">6&#x2013;13<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">335&#x2013;430<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">272&#x2013;298<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">125&#x2013;168<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">
                  <italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">&#xA0;<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">(present study)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Trachea and bronchi<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">Male (n&#x2009;= 7)<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">9&#x2013;10<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">285&#x2013;305<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">255&#x2013;302<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">-<hr/></td>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom">613&#x2013;686<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">&#xA0;</td>
                <td align="left">&#xA0;</td>
                <td align="left">Female (n&#x2009;= 15)</td>
                <td align="left">20&#x2013;24</td>
                <td align="left">486&#x2013;542</td>
                <td align="left">283&#x2013;312</td>
                <td align="left">178&#x2013;189</td>
                <td align="left">-</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>Measurements are expressed in microns, otherwise specified.</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <fig id="F4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Light microscope images of first stage larvae (L1) of </bold><bold><italic>Troglostrongylus brevior </italic></bold><bold>(A), </bold><bold><italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus </italic></bold><bold>(B) and </bold><bold><italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus </italic></bold><bold>(C) Magnification of caudal region is provided for each species.</bold> Scale bar&#x2009;= 50 &#x3BC;m.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-5-178-4"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="T3">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>Mean measurements (microns) of first stage larvae (L1) of </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>, </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>and </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic>
              </bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
            <colgroup>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="center"/>
              <col align="center"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead valign="top">
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="2" align="left">
                  <bold>Species (number of specimens)</bold>
                </th>
                <th colspan="2" align="center" valign="bottom">
                  <bold>First stage larvae (L1)</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>Mean length</bold>
                </th>
                <th align="center">
                  <bold>Mean width</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="top">
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> (n&#x2009;= 40)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">399.1 ( &#xB1; 11.3)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">18.5 ( &#xB1; 1.2)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Troglostrongylus brevior</italic> (n&#x2009;= 40)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">339.3 ( &#xB1; 14.1)<hr/></td>
                <td align="center" valign="bottom">18.6 ( &#xB1; 1)<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left"><italic>Troglostrongylus subcrenatus</italic> (n&#x2009;= 10)</td>
                <td align="center">280.7 ( &#xB1; 17.9)</td>
                <td align="center">15.5 ( &#xB1; 1.7)</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Parasites collected from case 2 were stout and filiform nematodes of medium size with a cuticle conspicuously inflated at the anterior end. The oesophagus was club-shaped. The excretory pore opening coincided with the ventral cuticular groove at about the middle of the oesophagus length (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B). A total of 15 females and seven males were identified. Females (20&#x2013;24 mm in length and 486&#x2013;542 &#x3BC;m in width) presented a conical and bluntly pointed tail (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>D; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) with the vulva opening posterior to the middle of body and the anus at 178&#x2013;189 &#x3BC;m from the caudal end (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>D). The uteri were filled with larvated eggs. Males (9&#x2013;10 mm in length and 285&#x2013;305 &#x3BC;m in width) presented an undivided bursa composed of a single dorsal stout ray, bearing papillae at the tip and externo-dorsal rays originating independently. Postero- and medio-lateral rays were fused over half or more of the length, antero-lateral rays were single and ventral rays fused for almost their extension (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>F). The spicules (613&#x2013;686 &#x3BC;m in length) were equal in size and shape, slender and finely striated except for their distal edges. Each spicule was split into two spikes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>H). First stage larvae (280.7 &#x3BC;m in length and 15.5 &#x3BC;m in width) had a rhabditoid oesophagus and pointed tail bearing typical dorsal and ventral cuticular spines (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>B; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Morphology and measurements of adult and larval nematodes collected from case 2 were all consistent with those of <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]<italic>.</italic></p>
        <p>Morphological and morphometrical features of adult parasites collected from cases 1 and 2 are reported in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> and compared to those of <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>. In spite of the differences in anatomical localization and body size of adult parasites, first stage larvae of <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>, <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> are rather similar, except for their slightly differing body lengths and the knob-like terminal end of <italic>A. abstrusus</italic> (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p>
        <p>Adult parasites of <italic>A. abstrusus</italic> were found in respiratory bronchioles and lung parenchyma and gross lesions were characterized by the presence of small greyish subpleural nodules (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>A) containing a mass of larvae, eggs and adult parasites (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>B). Alveoli containing parasites appeared dilated with disrupted septa and encircled by eosinophilic, neutrophilis and mononuclear infiltrate (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>C).</p>
        <fig id="F5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>Sub-pleural nodules caused by </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>in the lungs of a cat (A) Histological sections (HE) showing localization of adult worms of </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>A. abstrusus </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>in the lung parenchyma (B) and in sub-pleural nodules (C) Adult worms (male and female) of </bold>
              <bold>
                <italic>A. abstrusus </italic>
              </bold>
              <bold>(D).</bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-5-178-5"/>
        </fig>
        <p>PCR amplification of each target region characterized for nematodes from case 1 resulted in amplicons ranging from ~400 bp (p<italic>cox</italic>1) to ~1700 bp (18S) and ~630 bp (ITS2). The BLAST analysis of p<italic>cox</italic>1 gene sequences showed the closest homology (91%) with that of <italic>Necator americanus</italic> (GenBank accession number: AF303151) whereas ITS2 revealed a high homology (99%, fragment of 89 bp) when compared with <italic>Angiostrongylus cantonensis</italic> and <italic>Angiostrongylus vasorum</italic> (Strongylida: Angiostrongylidae) (GenBank accession numbers: HQ540551 and GU045376, respectively). The 18S sequence here produced was identical (homology of 100%) to <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> sp. (GenBank accession number: GU946677).</p>
        <p>The phylogenetic analyses of the sequence here produced for 18S and ITS2 genes showed a close evolutionary relationship among worms of case 1 with those of <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp., <italic>Otostrongylus</italic> spp. and <italic>Crenosoma</italic> spp. (Strongylida: Crenosomatidae) with relatively strong nodal support, to the exclusion of other metastrongyloids (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>A-B). In particular, the 18S tree revealed that the nematode was close to a <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> sp. from Spain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>A).</p>
        <fig id="F6" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Phylogenetic trees based on regions of 18S (A) and ITS2 (B) ribosomal DNA sequence data, compared with those of metastrongyloids available in GenBank</bold><sup><bold>TM</bold></sup><bold>.</bold> The trees were constructed using neighbour-joining (NJ) method (7000 replicates).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-5-178-6"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This paper is the first of all reports on clinical signs and gross lesions associated with <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> infestation in two domestic kittens. The delineation between these two species of metastrongyloids and the most known <italic>A. abstrusus</italic> is pivotal for the aetiological diagnosis of helminthic broncho-pulmonary disease of cats. These two troglostrongylids have been neglected for a long time or underestimated and deserve further investigations to assess their actual geographical distribution and clinical significance, especially in young cats. Indeed, <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp. have been reported as causative agents of respiratory conditions in many species of wild felids (e.g., <italic>Lynx rufus, Panthera pardus</italic><italic>Panthera tigris</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], but their occurrence in domestic cats was considered negligible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Recently, a <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> sp. detected in domestic cats exhibiting respiratory signs renewed the scientific interest on this genus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The 18S sequences herein produced for <italic>T. brevior</italic> and those derived from the parasitic specimens recently identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] provided an <italic>a posteriori</italic> aetiological identification for the causative agents of the cases above from Spain. This evidence might suggest that <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp. are more diffuse than currently estimated and that the limited number of records of <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> infesting domestic cats could be due to the close morphological features shared among their L1s (i.e., the parasitic stage mostly used for the diagnosis) with those of <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>. On the other hand, it cannot be ruled out that troglostrongylosis in domestic cats is limited to areas where cats are more frequently exposed to intermediate and/or paratenic hosts. Furthermore, molluscs of genera (i.e., <italic>Helicella</italic> spp. <italic>Limax</italic> spp. and <italic>Theba</italic> spp.) are common in the locality where both cats reported in this paper came from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>].</p>
      <p>Accordingly, almost all data available on lungworms affecting cats are based on copromicroscopical findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], which might lead to a misdiagnosis unless a thorough morphological and morphometric analysis is undertaken. Even if not easily achievable, an accurate evaluation of morphometrical features (i.e., total length and tail morphology) of L1s may lead to a discrimination among <italic>T. brevior</italic><italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> and <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>, being larvae of <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp. shorter in length and devoid of the typical knob-like terminal end (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p>
      <p>Molecular and phylogenetic analyses presented here provide, for the first time, data on mitochondrial and ribosomal gene sequences of <italic>T. brevior</italic>, giving a dataset for its identification. Based on the analysis of the 18S gene, the aetiological cause of infestation in cats from Ibiza was <italic>T. brevior</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The phylogenetic analysis of 18S further confirms the molecular analysis, clustering <italic>T. brevior</italic> within other <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp. infecting domestic carnivores. Nonetheless, further studies should be undertaken to differentiate <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> molecularly in order to better understand their pathogenicity, biology and bionomics (including the role of different species of molluscs as intermediate hosts) and infer their potential spread throughout Europe. A molecular characterization of these two species might contribute to assessing a specific and sensitive molecular tool for the detection of both species in faeces and pharyngeal swabs, as recently validated for <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>].</p>
      <p>The greater body size of <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> in comparison with <italic>A. abstrusus</italic> and their anatomical localisation in the upper respiratory airways (i.e., bronchioles and large bronchi) also reflects differences in the presentations and severity of clinical signs they cause in cats. Indeed, both clinical cases here described exhibited severe respiratory distress and had a lethal outcome due to respiratory failure. Accordingly, most of the lung damage observed at the gross examination was associated with the presence and action of nematode specimens. This clinical picture differs from that caused by <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>, which generally induces minor signs and is reported as an often self-limiting parasite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Nonetheless, the clinical presentation caused by <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp. and <italic>A. abstrusus</italic> may overlap in simultaneously infested animals, thus making any definitive aetiological diagnosis based on respiratory signs difficult.</p>
      <p><italic>Troglostrongylus brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> share similar biology with <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>, all involving mollusc intermediate hosts in their life cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] and thus, most likely, occupying the same ecological niches and occurring simultaneously in a given host population, as confirmed by co-infestation in the same cat population from Ibiza [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Due to their capacity of developing to the infective stage under different climatic conditions in many species of intermediate hosts, troglostrongylids may have a potential broader distribution than currently believed. Indeed, larvae of <italic>T. brevior</italic> show the highest resistance in the environment, developing to the infective stage at low temperatures (i.e., 4-8&#xB0;C in 40 days) but not <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>, even when kept up to 7 months at the same conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Under optimal conditions (i.e., 22-27&#xB0;C) <italic>T. brevior</italic> displays the shortest development time (i.e., 8 days) known for any metastrongyloid species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], suggesting that this species may potentially express a higher parasitic pressure for feline populations than <italic>A. abstrusus</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Data presented here indicate that <italic>T. brevior</italic> and <italic>T. subcrenatus</italic> may occur in domestic cats causing overt respiratory disease. Moreover, these two species should be included, along with <italic>A. abstrusus,</italic> in the differential diagnosis of bronchopulmonary affections in cats. Although the delineation of L1s among metastrongyloids is achievable using morphometrical criteria, molecular biology tools should be considered and implemented toward enhancing current knowledge on the biology, epidemiology and control of <italic>Troglostrongylus</italic> spp. infestations in domestic cats.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interest</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>EB conceived the study, documented clinical cases, described parasites and drafted the manuscript. GG and SG collected parasites, performed the morphological identification and revised the drafts of the manuscript. GA and MSL carried out the molecular genetic studies, sequence alignment and phylogenetic analyses, and drafted the manuscript. DT and FDT revised the drafts of manuscript. DO participated in molecular genetic and phylogenetic studies and revised and implemented the drafts of manuscript. All authors read and approved the final version of manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 1</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Dyspnoea caused by </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior </italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>Movie shows severe inspiratory and expiratory dyspnoea associated with </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior </italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>infestation.</bold>
          </p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1756-3305-5-178-S1.wmv" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="x-ms-wmv">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional file 2</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Respiratory symptoms caused by </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic>Troglostrongylus brevior </italic>
            </bold>
            <bold>Movie shows respiratory symptoms (coughing and dyspnoea) observed in a kitten infested by </bold>
            <bold>
              <italic> Troglostrongylus brevior.</italic>
            </bold>
          </p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1756-3305-5-178-S2.wmv" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="x-ms-wmv">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Traversa</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Guglielmini</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Feline aelurostrongylosis and canine angiostrongylosis: a challenging diagnosis for two emerging verminous pneumonia infections</article-title>
          <source>Vet Parasitol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>157</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>174</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2008.07.020</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775603</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Traversa</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Di Cesare</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Conboy</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Canine and feline cardiopulmonary parasitic nematodes in Europe: emerging and underestimated</article-title>
          <source>Parasit Vectors</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>62</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-3-62</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20653938</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Di Cesare</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Castagna</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Meloni</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Milillo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Latrofa</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Otranto</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Traversa</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Canine and feline infections by cardiopulmonary nematodes in central and southern Italy</article-title>
          <source>Parasitol Res</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-011-2405-5</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Anderson</surname>
            <given-names>RC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Nematode Parasites of Vertebrates</article-title>
          <source>Their Development and Transmission</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <edition>2</edition>
          <publisher-name>New York: CABI Publishing</publisher-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Bowman</surname>
            <given-names>DD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hendrix</surname>
            <given-names>CM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lindsay</surname>
            <given-names>DS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barr</surname>
            <given-names>SC</given-names>
          </name>
          <source>Feline Clinical Parasitology</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <publisher-name>Ames: Iowa State University Press</publisher-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mir&#xF3;</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Montoya</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jim&#xE9;nez</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Frisuelos</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Mateo</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fuentes</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Prevalence of antibodies to <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> and intestinal parasites in stray, farm and household cats in Spain</article-title>
          <source>Vet Parasitol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>126</volume>
          <fpage>249</fpage>
          <lpage>255</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2004.08.015</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15567588</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Payo-Puente</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Botelho-Dinis</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carvaja Urue&#xF1;a</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Payo-Puente</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gonzalo-Orden</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rojo-Vazquez</surname>
            <given-names>FA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Prevalence study of the lungworm <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> in stray cats of Portugal</article-title>
          <source>J Feline Med Surg</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>242</fpage>
          <lpage>246</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfms.2007.12.002</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18262453</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Traversa</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lia</surname>
            <given-names>RP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iorio</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boari</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Paradies</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Capelli</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Avolio</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Otranto</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and risk factors of <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> (Nematoda, Strongylida) infection in cats from Italy</article-title>
          <source>Vet Parasitol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>153</volume>
          <fpage>182</fpage>
          <lpage>186</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2008.01.024</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18308472</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Taubert</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pantchev</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vrhovec</surname>
            <given-names>MG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bauer</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hermosilla</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Lungworm infections (<italic>Angiostrongylus vasorum, Crenosoma vulpis, Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic>) in dogs and cats in Germany and Denmark in 2003&#x2013;2007</article-title>
          <source>Vet Parasitol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>159</volume>
          <fpage>175</fpage>
          <lpage>180</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2008.10.005</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19019555</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mircean</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Titilincu</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vasile</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Prevalence of endoparasites in household cat (<italic>Felis catus</italic>) populations from Transylvania (Romania) and association with risk factors</article-title>
          <source>Vet Parasitol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>171</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2010.03.005</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20381250</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Barutzki</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schaper</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Results of parasitological examinations of faecal samples from cats and dogs in Germany between 2003 and 2010</article-title>
          <source>Parasitol Res</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-011-2402-8</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Knaus</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kusi</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rapti</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xhaxhiu</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Winter</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Visser</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rehbein</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Endoparasites of cats from the Tirana area and the first report on <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> (Railliet, 1898) in Albania</article-title>
          <source>Wien Klin Wochenschr</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>123</volume>
          <fpage>31</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00508-011-1588-1</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21633814</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Juste</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garcia</surname>
            <given-names>AL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Menc&#xEC;a</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Mixed infestation of a domestic cat by <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> and Oslerus rostratus</article-title>
          <source>Angew Parasitol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>56</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1590596</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mill&#xE1;n</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Casanova</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>High prevalence of helminth parasites in feral cats in Majorca Island (Spain)</article-title>
          <source>Parasitol Res</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>188</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-009-1647-y</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19841943</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Fitzsimmons</surname>
            <given-names>WM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>Bronchostrongylus subcrenatus</italic> (Raillet &amp; Henry, 1913) a new parasite recorded from the domestic cat</article-title>
          <source>Vet Rec</source>
          <year>1961</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>102</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Jefferies</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Vrhovec</surname>
            <given-names>MG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wallner</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Catalan</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus and Troglostrongylus sp. (Nematoda: Metastrongyloidea) infections in cats inhabiting Ibiza, Spain</article-title>
          <source>Vet Parasitol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>173</volume>
          <fpage>344</fpage>
          <lpage>348</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2010.06.032</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20674179</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Gerichter</surname>
            <given-names>CB</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Studies on nematodes parasitic in the lungs of felidae in Palestine</article-title>
          <source>Parasitology</source>
          <year>1949</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>251</fpage>
          <lpage>262</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000083827</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18112008</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Sarmiento</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stough</surname>
            <given-names>BD</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Troglostrongylus wilsoni (Stough, 1953) n.comb. (Nematoda: Metastrongylidae) from the lungs of the bobcat, Lynx rufus rufus</article-title>
          <source>J Parasitol</source>
          <year>1956</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3274620</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13295891</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Watson</surname>
            <given-names>TG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nettles</surname>
            <given-names>VF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Davidson</surname>
            <given-names>WR</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Endoparasites and selected infectious agents in bobcats (<italic>Felis rufus</italic>) from West Virginia and Georgia</article-title>
          <source>J Wildl Dis</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>547</fpage>
          <lpage>554</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6802988</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>JD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Addison</surname>
            <given-names>EM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Joachim</surname>
            <given-names>DG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>LM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Quinn</surname>
            <given-names>NWS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Helminth parasites of Canada lynx (<italic>Felis canadensis</italic>) from northern Ontario</article-title>
          <source>Can J Zool</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>358</fpage>
          <lpage>364</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/z86-057</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Reichard</surname>
            <given-names>MV</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Caudell</surname>
            <given-names>DL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kocan</surname>
            <given-names>AA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Survey on helminth lung parasites of bobcats (<italic>Lynx rufus</italic>) from Alabama, Kansas, New Mexico, Oklahoma, and Virginia</article-title>
          <source>U.S.A. Comp Parasitol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>88</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1654/4086</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Soulsby</surname>
            <given-names>EJL</given-names>
          </name>
          <source>Helminths, Arthropods and Protozoa of Domesticated Animals</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <edition>7</edition>
          <publisher-name>London: Baill&#xE8;re Tindall</publisher-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Skryabin</surname>
            <given-names>KI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shikhobalova</surname>
            <given-names>NP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Schulz</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Popova</surname>
            <given-names>TI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Boev</surname>
            <given-names>SN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Delyamure</surname>
            <given-names>SL</given-names>
          </name>
          <source>Key to Parasitic Nematodes</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <publisher-name>Koln: E.J. BRILL</publisher-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharrocks</surname>
            <given-names>AD</given-names>
          </name>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">Griffin HG, Griffin AM</person-group>
          <article-title>The design of primers for PCR</article-title>
          <source>PCR Technology</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <publisher-name>London: Current Innovations. CRC Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Patterson-Kane</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gibbons</surname>
            <given-names>LM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jefferies</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Morgan</surname>
            <given-names>ER</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wenzlow</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Redrobe</surname>
            <given-names>SP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Pneumonia from <italic>Angiostrongylus vasorum</italic> infection in a red panda (<italic>Ailurus fulgens fulgens</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>J Vet Diagn Invest</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>270</fpage>
          <lpage>273</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/104063870902100219</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19286513</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Otranto</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tarsitano</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Traversa</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Giangaspero</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>De Luca</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Puccini</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Differentiation among three species of bovine <italic>Thelazia</italic> (Nematoda: Thelaziidae) by polymerase chain reaction-restriction fragment length polymorphism of the first internal transcribed spacer ITS-1 (rDNA)</article-title>
          <source>Int J Parasitol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>1693</fpage>
          <lpage>1698</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0020-7519(01)00279-X</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11730798</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tamura</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peterson</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Peterson</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stecher</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nei</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>2731</fpage>
          <lpage>2739</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msr121</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Altschul</surname>
            <given-names>SF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Madden</surname>
            <given-names>TL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sch&#xE4;ffer</surname>
            <given-names>AA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Z</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Miller</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lipman</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>3389</fpage>
          <lpage>3402</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.17.3389</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Saitou</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nei</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>406</fpage>
          <lpage>425</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Felsenstein</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap</article-title>
          <source>Evolution</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>791</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2408678</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Fitzsimmons</surname>
            <given-names>WM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>On a redescription of the male of Troglostrongylus subcrenatus (Raillet &amp; Henry, 1913) n. comb., from the domestic cat and the synonymy of Bronchostrongylus Cameron, 1931 with Troglostrongylus Vevers, 1923</article-title>
          <source>J Helminthol</source>
          <year>1964</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022149X00033538</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
          <name>
            <surname>Cossignani</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cossignani</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <source>Atlante delle conchiglie terrestri e dulciacquicole italiane</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <publisher-name>Ancona (Italia): L&#x2019;informatore Piceno</publisher-name>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Traversa</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Di Cesare</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Milillo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iorio</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Otranto</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic> in a feline colony from central Italy: clinical features diagnostic procedures and molecular characterization</article-title>
          <source>Parasitol Res</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>1191</fpage>
          <lpage>1196</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-008-1115-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18651179</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Pennisi</surname>
            <given-names>MG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Niutta</surname>
            <given-names>PP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Giannetto</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Lung worm disease in cats caused by <italic>Aelurostrongylus abstrusus</italic></article-title>
          <source>Tijdschr Diergeneeskd</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>263</fpage>
          <lpage>266</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7754502</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
