<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Otorhinolaryngologica Italica</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0392-100X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1827-675X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pacini Editore SpA</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21253286</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3008149</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title xml:lang="en">
					Radionecrosis of the larynx:
Case report and review of the literature
				</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="it">
          <trans-title>Radionecrosi della laringe: Case report e revisione della letteratura</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>CUKUROVA</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>CETINKAYA</surname>
            <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department of ENT, Tepecik Medical Training Hospital, Izmir;</aff>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Department of ENT, Ataturk Government Hospital,
Antalya, Turkey</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">
Address for correspondence: Dr. E.A. Cetinkaya, Antalya Atat&#xFC;rk
Devlet Hastanesi KBB Klinigi, Antalya, Turkey 07040. Fax: +90
242 3343373. E-mail: <email xlink:href="drerdemcetinkaya@gmail.com">drerdemcetinkaya@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>30</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <elocation-id>205</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Copyright by Societ&#xE0; Italiana di Otorinolaringologia e Chirurgia Cervico-Facciale</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way. For details, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>SUMMARY</title>
        <p>Aim of the present report is to describe a case of radionecrosis related to radiotherapy of the larynx and to review the literature. A review
was made of the hospital chart, surgery report, imaging studies and pathological findings of a 51-year-old male patient came to our attention.
Results indicated that radionecrosis often requires total laryngectomy. It is very rare, but morbidity and mortality rates are high. The
interval between conclusion of radiation therapy and development of radionecrosis ranges from 3 to 12 months. In this report, a case of
radionecrosis is presented which has been managed using the organ sparing strategy. In conclusion, the larynx may be spared when radionecrosis
occurs but more investigations are required in order to define the most appropriate treatment.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="it">
        <title>RIASSUNTO</title>
        <p>Scopo di questo studio &#xE8; la descrizione di un caso di radionecrosi della laringe conseguente a radioterapia ed una revisione della letteratura
sull&#x2019;argomento. A questo scopo &#xE8; stata effettuata una revisione della cartella clinica, del report chirurgico, delle indagini strumentali
e degli esami istologici di un uomo di 51 anni, giunto alla nostra attenzione. I risultati indicano che la radionecrosi della laringe spesso
richiede la laringectomia totale, in quanto, pur essendo un evento raro, presenta elevata morbidit&#xE0; e mortalit&#xE0;. Il periodo intercorso tra la
fine della radioterapia e lo sviluppo di radionecrosi &#xE8; in genere variabile tra i 3 e i 12 mesi. In questo articolo viene riportato un caso di
radionecrosi della laringe che &#xE8; stato trattato utilizzando una strategia conservativa. In conclusione, &#xE8; possibile risparmiare la laringe in
caso di radionecrosi ma occorrono maggiori dati per la definizione del trattamento pi&#xF9; appropriato.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>KEY WORDS</title>
        <kwd>Larynx</kwd>
        <kwd>Malignant tumours</kwd>
        <kwd>Radiotherapy</kwd>
        <kwd>Radionecrosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Laryngocutaneous fistula reconstruction</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Radiation has been used for treatment of laryngeal carcinomas
for more than 60 years. With the advances in
radiation technology and current trends of treating advanced-
stage laryngeal tumours with organ sparing protocols,
external-beam radiation has become the treatment
modality of choice for certain stages of squamous cell
carcinoma (SCC). However, it should be borne in mind
that every method has its complications, like its indication.
There are several complications encountered during
radiotherapy such as laryngeal oedema, skin damage,
perichondritis and cartilage necrosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01"><sup>1</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Permanent histological effects can occur within the soft
tissues of the neck with radiation doses as low as 12 Gray
(Gy). In 1979, Chandler proposed a grading system for
laryngeal radionecrosis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table I</xref>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02"><sup>2</sup></xref>. There is a direct relationship
between the number of rads delivered and the
severity of the subsequent radiation reaction. Grade I and II are expected as side-effects of radiation and do not require
aggressive treatment except humidification, voice
restraint, need to refrain from active or passive smoking
and using N-acetylcysteine, etc.. Grade III and IV reactions
are more severe, have less favourable outcomes, and
are considered as major complications that usually require
surgery. Although chondronecrosis of the larynx is
a very rare complication in otorhinolaryngology, the incidence
increases daily due to more frequent use of chemotherapy
and radiotherapy. If chondronecrosis occurs, it
can result in serious sequelae or even in death, and it is
known that there is no chance of recovery <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01"><sup>1</sup></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04"><sup>4</sup></xref>. The most
frequent cause of chondronecrosis is radiotherapy but also
recurrent perichondritis, long- or short-term intubations,
infection, trauma, tracheotomy, and neoplasia can be included
among the causes. The incidence is related to tumour
grade as well as the radiotherapy dosage. The case
is described of a 51-year-old white male with laryngeal
carcinoma treated by radiotherapy.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table I.</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Chandler classification for laryngeal radionecrosis.</title>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th style="background-color:#999999" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <th style="background-color:#999999" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptoms</th>
              <th style="background-color:#999999" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signs</th>
              <th style="background-color:#999999" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade I</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slight hoarseness, slight dryness</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slight oedema, telengiectasis</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptomatic care: humidification, anti-reflux therapy, smoking cessation</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade II</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate hoarseness, moderate dryness</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade III</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe hoarseness with dyspnoea,
moderate odynophagia and dysphagia</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe impairment of vocal cord mobility or
fixation of one cord, marked oedema, skin changes</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptomatic care + steroids, antibiotics
Tracheotomy or laryngectomy, if necessary</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade IV</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory, distress, severe odynophagia,
weight loss dehydration</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fistula, fetororis, fixation of skin to larynx, airway
obstruction, fever</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tracheotomy and/or laryngectomy</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 51-year-old male patient came to our attention, in March
1999, complaining of hoarseness for 7 months. At the direct
laryngoscopic examination of the patient, a mass was
detected completely attacking the left vocal cord, filling
the ventricule, expanding to the anterior commissure and
causing fixation of the left cord. The specimen, taken at
direct laryngoscopy, under general anaesthesia, was defined as epidermoid carcinoma. In the light of these data,
the patient was accepted as T3N0MX. Surgery was offered
primarily, but the patient chose radiotherapy.</p>
      <p>In this treatment, 2 daily dosages of 36 Gy fractions (total
72 Gy), with Co-60 tele therapy, to the primary tumour
site, were applied + bilateral neck, daily 2 Gy dosage, total
60 Gy + supraclavicular region, daily 2 Gy dosage, total
60 Gy were applied. With the 42 Gy, <italic>medulla spinalis</italic> is
preserved and, during radiotherapy, oral cavity, skull base
and bilateral lung apex were preserved. At the end of the
treatment, there were no major side-effects except grade
II mouth dryness, grade I radiodermatitis and hoarseness.
Increasing dyspnoea and difficulty in swallowing developed
2 months after the radiotherapy, consequently immediate
tracheotomy was performed. Examination of the
patient showed a widespread mass and/or oedema in the
larynx and fixation in both cords and arytenoids. Halitosis
and pain upon palpation of the neck were also observed.
These findings were considered as a recurrence and a
punch biopsy was taken. There was no carcinoma, only
necrotic and fibrotic findings were found upon pathological
investigation. Necrosis of the thyroid framework and
adjacent soft tissue was revealed at Computed Tomography
(CT) scan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Disrigidity of the thyroid cartilage
and oedema of the mucosa led us to a diagnosis of radionecrosis
of the larynx and total laryngectomy was offered.
However, the patient refused the surgical treatment, and
therefore symptomatic treatment was applied. A feeding
tube was placed; treatment with ciproflaxacine, multivitamins
(A, B and E), corticosteroids, non-steroidal antiin
"ammatory drug and intravenous liquid replacement
with isotonic solutions were administered. The patient
was discharged at his request and followed as an outpatient.
After two years, he was admitted to the hospital with
a laryngo-cutaneous fistula at the middle line of the neck.
At the endoscopic examination, the orifice of the fistula, inside the larynx, was observed just under the petiole.
Both cords and the arytenoids were normal. Furthermore,
there was no local tumour recurrence according to endoscopic
and microscopic larynx examination and control
biopsies. At the CT scan, a defect was identified at the
centre of the thyroid lamina. Magnetic Resonance Imaging
(MRI) showed normal findings except for a fistula.
There were no problems at the cricoids and epiglottis cartilage.
Therefore, laryngeal reconstruction was planned
under general anaesthesia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) and the patient was
operated via apron flap incision on October 5<sup>th</sup>, 2001. A tracheotomy was performed through the 4th-5th rings of the
trachea. The thyroid cartilage was closed with the pulldown
method by the epiglottis, and the skin defect was
closed with turnover platysma myocutaneous flaps after
wide local excision. Airway stabilization was provided by
placing a silicone T tube for 8 weeks. One week later, a
flap feeding disturbance occurred. The repaired cartilage
had healed on the inner side of the fistula but the skin flap
was ulcerated and the size of the wound had become larger
than at the beginning. Meanwhile, we applied mitomycin
C and daily scraping. There were no wound closures. The
part of the skin presenting necrosis and the tracheotomy
were reconstructed by pectoral myocutaneous flap after 8
weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The flap was functionally adequate, both
in the reconstruction of the tracheotomy and for repair of
the large skin defect. On the 29th post-operative month, no
local recurrence or distant metastasis have been seen yet.
No concomitant chemotherapy was used.</p>
      <fig id="F1" fig-type="Halftone" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Laryngostoma due to radionecrosis.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-30-205-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" fig-type="Halftone" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Pre-operative aspect of the laryngostoma.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-30-205-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" fig-type="Halftone" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Results after myocutaneous flap reconstruction.</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-30-205-g003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The first report dates back to the 1940s when Stone conducted
a series of clinical studies using an early cyclotron
for the radiotherapy treatment at Berkeley. A total of 249
patients were treated, and about half of these patients had
head neck tumours <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Radiation therapies for SCC of the
larynx have become increasingly safe and effective over
the last 20 years. This is the consequence of the attempts
to spare anatomy and function without compromising tumour
control that have been developed. The incidence of
severe reactions following 50-60 Gy had decreased from
5-12%, in the 1970s, to approximately 1%, in the 1990s.
Radiotherapy induces a hypoxic environment by stimulating
reactive fibrosis and end-arteritis of blood vessels, as
well as obliteration and fibrosis of the lymphatic system.
Oedema develops secondary to increased permeability
and decreased lymphatic drainage, which leads to further
reduction of the nutrient supply <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Major late complications, due to radiotherapy, typically
occur following a latent period of approximately 3 months because of the long-standing hypo-vascularity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06"><sup>6</sup></xref>. Laryngeal
oedema is the most frequently encountered complication,
and, at the same time, the first symptom of chondronecrosis
and this might cause false or late diagnosis. The rate
of clearance of the oedema is related to radiation dose,
volume of tissue radiated, addition of neck dissection
and size and extent of the original lesion. The most common
complication, persistent laryngeal oedema, occurs in
13.7% of patients who receive a dose less than 70 Gy but
rises to 46.2% with doses of 70 Gy or more.</p>
      <p>Of the patients undergoing radiotherapy, 1-5% may develop
radiation-induced chondronecrosis. Risk factors for
development of chondronecrosis include use of alcohol
and tobacco (most significant), tumour invasion, post-operative
infection, trauma, and the radiation technique. Intact
perichondrium can tolerate large doses of radiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>.
The cartilaginous framework becomes defective and unstable
in a patient with laryngeal chondronecrosis. This
alters the airway size, mobility and structure. Patients may
present clinically with any of the following: dysphagia,
odinophagia, hoarseness, stridor, dyspnoea, respiratory
obstruction, recurrent aspiration, fever, weight loss, and
dehydration. Most patients become symptomatic within
the first 3 months after radiotherapy. However, there are
case reports of patients presenting necrosis 25, 44 and
even 50 years after radiotherapy because of fibrosis and
endarteritis continuing with time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06"><sup>6</sup></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07"><sup>7</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>The typical patient with radiation-induced chondronecrosis
initially develops symptoms of hoarseness and breathiness.
The arytenoid cartilages are involved most frequently
when chondronecrosis occurred in association with radiotherapy.
The crico-arytenoid joint is usually affected, and
the arytenoids may become partially fixed without complete
rotation or medial sliding motion along the cricoid.
Due to this limited mobility, the ability to fully abduct
or adduct the vocal folds may be impaired. Without full
abduction, mild stridor or exercise intolerance may occur
and become progressive. Incomplete vocal fold closure
causes breathiness and potential for aspiration. The
usual course is to have greater difficulty with liquids than
with solids, but progressive dysphagia may occur. The accessory
laryngeal muscle activity may become impaired
due to fibrosis, and thus, the normal laryngeal elevation
needed for swallowing fails, leading to an unprotected airway.
If an individual has recurrent aspiration secondary
to poor swallowing function, pneumonia and respiratory
compromise can occur. Recurrent pneumonia is a definitive
indication for laryngectomy<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>The diagnosis of radiation necrosis is made on clinical
presentation and examination. Although radio-imaging is
often part of the work-up, both CT and MRI are not helpful
in distinguishing between radio-necrosis and recurrent
tumour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07"><sup>7</sup></xref>. It has been suggested that Positron Emission
Tomography (PET) scanning may be beneficial in identifying
occult malignancy in this situation. PET, according to
McGuirt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08"><sup>8</sup></xref>, has proved reliable, with the ability to differentiate tumour from radiation effect in more than 80% of
cases. The resolution of PET, however, is 6 mm. Therefore,
microscopic deposits of cancer may not be seen, and larger
deposits may be masked by pooled saliva <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>The most common treatment modality of the laryngeal radionecrosis
is total laryngectomy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03"><sup>3</sup></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04"><sup>4</sup></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06"><sup>6</sup></xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07"><sup>7</sup></xref>. Also the common
opinion was the medical management offering only temporarily,
symptomatic relief, which further requires surgical
treatment for late stage reactions (Grade III and IV).
Medical treatment options are limited and include antibiotics
anti-reflux agents, corticosteroids, humidification,
feeding tube and sputum for culture and sensitivity.
Hyperbaric oxygen in radionecrosis is another proposed
treatment modality. Ferguson et al. reported that signs
and symptoms of radionecrosis were dramatically improved
in 7/8 patients (Grade III and IV), with hyperbaric
oxygen therapy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09"><sup>9</sup></xref>. Filntisis et al. reported that 13 (72.2%)
of the 18 patients (2 had grade III and 16 had grade IV
radionecrosis), showed a major improvement after hyperbaric
oxygen therapy, and none of them required total laryngectomy
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><sup>10</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>Surgical treatment of the grade III and IV patients is still
a diagnostic and therapeutic dilemma. There is no clear
evidence of how aseptic necroses start and what limits
the necrosis. If airway obstruction is present, surgical
management may start with a tracheotomy. At the same
time, laryngeal endoscopy and biopsy is indicated to rule
out the malignancy. Due to essential principles, necrotic
tissue must be excised to promote healing. Therefore, if the effected laryngeal cartilages were removed, necrosis
should stop and the larynx should heal. Instead of
doing total laryngectomy primarily, removing necrotic
cartilage and allowing secondary wound healing may result
in a return of the progress. But these theories must
be justified with more clinical and animal experiences.
At the second stage, a myocutaneous flap from a nonradiated
site should be used for closing the fistula because
long-standing hypovascularity of the skin impairs
the healing process. The <italic>pectoralis major</italic> flap is widely
accepted on account of its versatility in head and neck
cancer reconstructions. It is supplied by the thoraco-acromial
artery, with additional circulation provided by the
lateral thoracic artery <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11"><sup>11</sup></xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S4">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Although total laryngectomy has been considered mandatory
for the treatment of radionecrosis, we saw that it could be
reconstructed without total laryngectomy. In spite of this
case report, we cannot offer medical therapy. Progressivism
and malignancy of the radionecrosis, which are considered
as the causes of total laryngectomy, must be investigated
again. Also radiated larynx and anterior neck defects may
both be reconstructed functionally. Salvage surgery, after
radiation failures, may be performed with an adequate technique
and flaps. Vascularised tissue transfer and vascularised
muscle transfer are both useful reconstruction methods for
the treatment of necrosed tissues.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rowley</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walsh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McShane</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chondroradionecrosis
of the larynx: Still a diagnostic dilemma</article-title>
          <source>J Laryngol Otol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>218</fpage>
          <lpage>220</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7745338</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chandler</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Radiation fibrosis and necrosis of the larynx</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>509</fpage>
          <lpage>514</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">475247</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oppenheimer</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krespi</surname>
              <given-names>YP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Einhorn</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management
of laryngeal radionecrosis: animal and clinical experience</article-title>
          <source>Head Neck</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>252</fpage>
          <lpage>256</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2722502</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Perez</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thorstad</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Halperin</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perez</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brady</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unusual nonepithelial tumors of
the head and the neck</article-title>
          <source>Principles and practice of radiation oncology</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <edition>5th Edition</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams and
Wilkins</publisher-name>
          <fpage>996</fpage>
          <lpage>1034</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stone</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neutron therapy and specific ionization</article-title>
          <source>Am J
Roentgenol</source>
          <year>1948</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>771</fpage>
          <lpage>771</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takiguchi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okamura</surname>
              <given-names>HO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kitamura</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Late laryngotracheal
cartilage necrosis with external fistula 44 years after
radiotherapy</article-title>
          <source>J Laryngol Otol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>658</fpage>
          <lpage>659</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12956925</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzgerald</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koch</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Delayed radionecrosis of the larynx</article-title>
          <source>Am J Otolaryngol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          <lpage>249</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10442778</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McGuirt</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greven</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
              <suffix>3rd</suffix>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>PET scanning
in head and neck oncology: a review</article-title>
          <source>Head Neck</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>208</fpage>
          <lpage>215</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9570626</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferguson</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hudson</surname>
              <given-names>WR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farmer</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hyperbaric oxygen
therapy for laryngeal radionecrosis</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3813371</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Filntisis</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moon</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kraft</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Laryngeal radionecrosis
and hyperbaric oxygen therapy: report of 18 cases
and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>554</fpage>
          <lpage>562</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10855566</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dedivitis</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guimaraes</surname>
              <given-names>AV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pectoralis major musculocutaneous
flap in head and neck cancer reconstruction</article-title>
          <source>World
J Surg</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11898036</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
