<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Gastroenterol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJG</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology : Official Journal of the Saudi Gastroenterology Association</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1319-3767</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-4049</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616420</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3003220</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SJG-16-218</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1319-3767.65196</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Synchronous Adenocarcinoma and Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor in the Stomach</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Narasimhamurthy</surname>
            <given-names>Mohana S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vallachira</surname>
            <given-names>Gopinathan P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mahadev</surname>
            <given-names>Praveen S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001">Department of Pathology, Sudharma Metropolis, Gastrosurgery, Palakkad District Hospital</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Mohana S. N, Sudharma Metropolis, Thrissur-680 022, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="mohansn@yahoo.com">mohansn@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>218</fpage>
      <lpage>220</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>In recent years, the synchronous occurrence of tumors of different histotypes arising in the same organ has been reported more frequently in the literature. In the stomach, adenocarcinoma has been described with coexisting primary rhabdomyosarcoma, carcinoid, and low-grade B-cell lymphoma of mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue. The simultaneous development of adenocarcinoma and gastric mesenchymal tumor has been documented rarely. We report one such case. A 65-year-old male was diagnosed with a proximal gastric adenocarcinoma and underwent subtotal gastrectomy. Subsequent histopathological examination revealed the presence of another tumor at the gastric antrum. This was a gastrointestinal stromal tumor of low risk category (GIST). The literature has only a few previous reports of this very rare association. It is not known whether this synchronicity is incidental or there is a causative factor inducing the development of tumors of different histotypes in the same organ. Pathologists, oncologists and surgeons should be aware of this interesting condition.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Adenocarcinoma</kwd>
        <kwd>stromal tumor</kwd>
        <kwd>synchronus</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Adenocarcinoma is the most common histological type of gastric tumor. It may coexist with another synchronous tumor of different histological type in a different part of the stomach. Gastric adenocarcinoma may coexist most commonly with lymphoma and less commonly with carcinoid and gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST).[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref>] Rarely, cells of different histological types may intermix and form a collision tumor in the stomach.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT3">3</xref>] We present here the very rare combination of a synchronous proximal gastric adenocarcinoma and a GIST.</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases" id="sec1-1">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 65-year-old gentleman presented with a five month history of dyspeptic symptoms, and weight loss. Endoscopy showed ulceration along the lesser curvature of the proximal stomach. Multiple mucosal biopsies were obtained from ulcerated areas and histopathology revealed a poorly differentiated adenocarcinoma. Subsequently, the patient underwent an elective subtotal gastrectomy.</p>
      <sec id="sec2-1">
        <title>Pathological findings</title>
        <p>Macroscopic examination of subtotal gastrectomy specimen showed firm texture of the proximal stomach and an excavating ulcerative growth measuring 40&#xD7;30&#xD7;12mm along the lesser curvature. Interestingly, a nodule of firm white tissue measuring 25 mm diameter, was present adjacent to the ulcerated area. Microscopically, the ulcerated area showed glands and sheets of neoplastic cells which had reached the serosal surface [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>]. Histological examination of adjacent nodule revealed GIST of low risk category [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>], which was composed of cytologically bland spindle cells that were demonstrated by immunohistochemistry to be uniformly positive for CD117 [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>]. Histological assessment of malignancy in GIST is based on tumor size and mitotic count and is classified into four categories as shown in the following <xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="F0001" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>H and E stained, &#xD7;40 section shows cytologically bland spindle cells in fascicles</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="SJG-16-218-g001"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F0002" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Section from stomach nodule showing glands and sheets of neoplastic cells, H and E, &#xD7;40</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="SJG-16-218-g002"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F0003" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Section from stomach nodule showing diffuse positivity for CD117 of spindle cells, Immunohistochemistry, &#xD7;40</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="SJG-16-218-g003"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="T0001" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Risk Stratification of GIST</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk category</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size (cm)</th>
                <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitotic count (per 50hpf)</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 2</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-5</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;5</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-10</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-10</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;10</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">any</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;10</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>In our case, GIST tumor size was 2.5 cm and mitotic count was less than 5/50hpf. Applying these criteria, GIST was classified into low risk category as mentioned above.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussions" id="sec1-2">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GISTs) are rare mesenchymal neoplasms of the digestive tract. Synchronous occurrence of a gastrointestinal stromal tumor with a tumor of different histogenesis is very rare and has been documented in the literature mainly in case reports. There are only a few previous reports of simultaneous adenocarcinoma and GIST in the stomach.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT4">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT6">6</xref>]</p>
      <p>In most of the reported cases of synchronous gastric adenocarcinoma and GIST, the preoperative biopsy fragments showed only adenocarcinoma. GISTs were detected only following laparotomy and examination of the resected specimens. In our case the total gastrectomy was performed for the proximal gastric adenocarcinoma and a small GIST was found incidentally with the histopathological examination of the specimen.</p>
      <p>The simultaneous finding of epithelial and stromal gastric tumors raises the question of whether such an occurrence is a simple incidental association or the two lesions are connected by a causal relationship. The suggestion that the stomach harboring a leiomyosarcoma may have a tendency to develop malignant epithelial lesions was put forward by Tada <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT5">5</xref>] Various hypotheses have been proposed regarding the simultaneous development of GIST and adenocarcinoma. Coincidence alone could easily account for such an association, particularly in countries that exhibit high incidence rates of gastric cancer, such as Japan. The possibility that gene mutations might underlie tumor predisposition in patients harboring a double gastric neoplasia cannot be theoretically discarded. Evidence of familial disease was derived in only one case.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT5">5</xref>] At present, however, no data are available to support such a hypothesis.</p>
      <p>An interesting hypothesis is that a single carcinogenic agent might interact with two neighboring tissues, inducing the development of tumors of different histotypes in the same organ. Experimental evidence for this possibility has been provided. <italic>N</italic>-methyl- <italic>N</italic>&#x2019;-nitro-<italic>N</italic>-nitrosoguanidine induces the development of gastric adenocarcinomas after oral administration in rats.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT7">7</xref>] However, when the same compound is combined with agents that alter the gastric mucosal barrier, such as aspirin or stress, leiomyosarcomas develop in conjunction with epithelial tumors.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT8">8</xref>] Equally compelling, although also experimental, are reports on the induction of gastric tumors in rats after 9,10-dimethyl-1,2-benzanthracene (DMBA) injection. Whereas administration of DMBA alone induces the development of adenocarcinomas, treatment with DMBA and cellophane plate causes mainly the induction of gastric sarcomas.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT9">9</xref>]</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="CIT1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goteri</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ranaldi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rezai</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baccarini</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bearzi</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synchronous mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma and adenocarcinoma of the stomach</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>505</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9158673</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsieh</surname>
              <given-names>PP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Collision tumour of the stomach: A case report of mixed stromal tumour and adenocarcinoma</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>332</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12352297</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sailors</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>French</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The unique simultaneous occurrence of granular cell tumour, gastrointestinal stromal tumour and gastric adenocarcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>129</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15628896</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katsoulis</surname>
              <given-names>IE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bossi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richman</surname>
              <given-names>PI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Livingstone</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Collision of adenocarcinoma and gastrointestinal stromal tumour (GIST) in the stomach: Report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Int Semin Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17222335</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maiorana</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fante</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maria Cesinaro</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andriana Fano</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synchronous occurrence of epithelial and stromal tumours in the stomach: A report of 6 cases</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>124</volume>
          <fpage>682</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10782147</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bircan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Candir</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aydin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baspinar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buldul</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kapucuoglu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synchronous primary adenocarcinoma and gastrointestinal stromal tumour in the stomach: A report of two cases</article-title>
          <source>Turk J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15492920</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sugimura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujimura</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baba</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tumor production in the glandular stomach and alimentary tract of the rat by N-methyl-N&#x2019;-nitro-N-nitrosoguanidine</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Res</source>
          <year>1970</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>65</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5458974</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geller</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horowitz</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toth</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Werther</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Experimental models for gastric leiomyosarcoma: The effects of N-methyl-N&#x2019;-nitro-N-nitrosoguanidine in combination with stress, aspirin, or sodium taurocholate</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>1088</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6692300</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shitkov</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Talalaeva</surname>
              <given-names>AV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gastric sarcomas induced in rats by DMBA and cellophane</article-title>
          <source>Vopr Onkol</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>62</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">113935</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
