<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJO</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Korean Journal of Ophthalmology : KJO</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8942</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2092-9382</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Ophthalmological Society</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21976944</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3178771</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3341/kjo.2011.25.5.349</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Case of <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> Keratitis Effectively Treated with Moxifloxacin</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Son</surname>
            <given-names>Sung Whan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Hyung Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Seo</surname>
            <given-names>Jeong Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Ophthalmology, Sahm Yook Medical Center, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Reprint requests to Jeong Won Seo, MD. Department of Ophthalmology, Sahm Yook Medical Center, #29-1 Hwigyeong 2-dong, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul 130-711, Korea. Tel: 82-2-2210-3554, Fax: 82-2-2246-8085, <email>virgo901@hanmail.net</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>25</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>349</fpage>
      <lpage>351</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2011 The Korean Ophthalmological Society</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 70-year-old man with a long history of diabetes mellitus presented to our hospital (Department of Ophthalmology, Sahm Yook Medical Center, Seoul, Korea) complaining of severe ocular pain and visual disturbance in his left eye that had started three days prior to admission. A round 3.7 &#xD7; 5.0 mm dense central stromal infiltrate with an overlying epithelial defect was noted on slit-lamp examination. Following corneal scrapings and culture, topical 0.5% moxifloxacin and 0.5% tobramycin were administered hourly. A few days later, <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> was isolated in a bacterial culture from a corneal specimen. According to the results of susceptibility tests, topical 0.5% moxifloxacin was given every hour and 0.5% tobramycin was stopped. The patient's clinical features improved steadily with treatment. The corneal epithelium healed rapidly, and the infiltrate resolved within four weeks of the initiation of treatment. The patient's best corrected visual acuity improved from hand motion to 20 / 25.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Keratitis</kwd>
        <kwd>Moxifloxacin</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic> (<italic>S. maltophilia</italic>) is a non-fermentative, gram-negative bacillus that has assumed an increasingly important role as a nosocomial pathogen in immune compromised patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Treatment of <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> infections is also complicated by the fact that isolates are resistant to many broad-spectrum agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Ophthalmologic syndromes, including conjunctivitis, keratitis, dacrocystitis and pre-septal cellulitis, may be caused by <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> keratitis is associated with very poor prognoses because of its resistance to many broad-spectrum antibiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. We describe a case of <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> keratitis that was effectively treated with topical moxifloxacin (fourth-generation fluoroquinolone) monotherapy.</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 70-year-old male presented to our hospital (Department of Ophthalmology, Sahm Yook Medical Center, Seoul, Korea) with a three-day history of left eye pain and decreased vision. He had a long history of diabetes mellitus that was controlled with oral anti-hyperglycemic agents. The patient suffered from bilateral proliferative diabetic retinopathy and had undergone pan retinal photocoagulation several times since March 1995. At age 60 he had undergone phacoemulsifications with intraocular lens implantation for the treatment of senile cataracts in both eyes.</p>
      <p>On presentation, the patient's visual acuity was hand motion in the left eye. Slit lamp examination revealed a heavily edematous cornea and a round 3.7 &#xD7; 5.0 mm dense central stromal infiltrate with an overlying epithelial defect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Anterior chamber cells 3+ and ciliary injection were also observed.</p>
      <p>After scrapings were collected from the lesion for smears and cultures, the patient was treated hourly with 0.5% moxifloxacin and 0.5% tobramycin. Four days after the initiation of treatment, heavy growth of <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> was observed in culture. The isolated bacteria were sensitive to ciprofloxacin, sulfamethoxazole-trimethoprim, levofloxacin, and moxifloxacin, but were resistant to all aminoglycosides and <italic>B</italic>-lactams (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). According to the results of susceptibility tests, topical 0.5% moxifloxacin was given every hour and 0.5% tobramycin was stopped.</p>
      <p>The patient's corneal epithelium healed in two weeks after the initiation of treatment. After the epithelium had healed, moxifloxacin was administered four times per day. The corneal infiltrate resolved within four weeks. However, mild opacity remained in the posterior stroma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The patient's best corrected visual acuity improved from hand motion to 20 / 25. His infectious keratitis was controlled and had not recurred at the one-year follow-up examination.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><italic>S. maltophilia</italic> is a motile, non-fermentative, oxidase-negative, aerobic, Gram-negative bacillus that is widespread in the environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. It is an opportunistic pathogen believed to have limited pathogenicity unless it is associated with nosocomial infections of immune compromised patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> is a seldom-reported pathogen in lens care systems or ocular infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. However, reports of postoperative and post-traumatic <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> ocular infections are increasing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The reasons underlying this emergence are complex, but may be related to the improved laboratory isolation techniques and enhanced reporting. Treatment of <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> infections is complicated by the fact that isolates are often resistant to many broad-spectrum antibiotic agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>You et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] reported the treatment results and prognoses of 10 cases of <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> keratitis in 2007 after one time applications of levofloxacin ophthalmic solution as a first line treatment of choice before culture results. They then added fortified tobramycin and cefazolin if corneal ulcers were large and centrally located of the cornea. Patients also underwent surgical treatment when there was no response to medication. The final visual acuity in three cases that had no co-infections was worse than hand motion.</p>
      <p>Fourth-generation fluoroquinolones (moxifloxacin and gatifloxacin) show an enhanced spectrum of activity against Gram-positive bacteria and comparable activity to second- and third-generation fluoroquinolones (ciprofloxacin and levofloxacin) against Gram-negative bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. New ocular antibiotic formulations with improved potency, such as moxifloxacin ophthalmic solution 0.5% (Vigamox&#xAE;; Alcon Laboratories, Fort Worth, TX, USA) or gatifloxacin ophthalmic solution 0.3% (Zymar&#xAE;; Allergan, Irvine, CA, USA) are currently available and have been shown to inhibit growth of organisms resistant to second- and third-generation fluoroquinolones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Several <italic>in vitro</italic> susceptibility studies, demonstrate that moxifloxacin is more active than earlier generation fluoroquinolones (ciprofloxacin, ofloxacin, and levofloxacin), especially against <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. For these reasons, we chose moxifloxacin monotherapy for treatment of <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> keratitis, even though antibiotic sensitivity was equal for both levofloxacin and moxifloxacin.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, we report the case of a patient who was diagnosed with <italic>S. maltophilia</italic> keratitis and effectively treated with moxifloxacin monotherapy. Unlike most previously-reported cases, which had poor prognoses, in our patient moxifloxacin monotherapy led to a good visual outcome.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khardori</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elting</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nosocomial infections due to Xanthomonas maltophilia (Pseudomonas maltophilia) in patients with cancer</article-title>
          <source>Rev Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>997</fpage>
          <lpage>1003</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2267495</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spencer</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The emergence of epidemic, multiple-antibiotic-resistant Stenotrophomonas (Xanthomonas) maltophilia and Burkholderia (Pseudomonas) cepacia</article-title>
          <source>J Hosp Infect</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>Suppl</issue>
          <fpage>453</fpage>
          <lpage>464</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7560984</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zuravleff</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>VL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Infections caused by Pseudomonas maltophilia with emphasis on bacteremia: case reports and a review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Rev Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>1236</fpage>
          <lpage>1246</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7156659</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>You</surname>
              <given-names>IC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>YG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical aspect and prognosis of stenotrophomonas (Xanthomonas) maltophilia keratitis</article-title>
          <source>J Korean Ophthalmol Soc</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>889</fpage>
          <lpage>897</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Palleroni</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bradbury</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stenotrophomonas, a new bacterial genus for Xanthomonas maltophilia (Hugh 1980) Swings et al. 1983</article-title>
          <source>Int J Syst Bacteriol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>606</fpage>
          <lpage>609</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8347518</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Senol</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia: the significance and role as a nosocomial pathogen</article-title>
          <source>J Hosp Infect</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15142709</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bottone</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madayag</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qureshi</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acanthamoeba keratitis: synergy between amebic and bacterial cocontaminants in contact lens care systems as a prelude to infection</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>2447</fpage>
          <lpage>2450</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1401013</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsiao</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia keratitis and scleritis</article-title>
          <source>Chang Gung Med J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>142</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15945320</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bauernfeind</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison of the antibacterial activities of the quinolones Bay 12-8039, gatifloxacin (AM 1155), trovafloxacin, clinafloxacin, levofloxacin and ciprofloxacin</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>639</fpage>
          <lpage>651</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9421311</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mather</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karenchak</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Romanowski</surname>
              <given-names>EG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kowalski</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fourth generation fluoroquinolones: new weapons in the arsenal of ophthalmic antibiotics</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>463</fpage>
          <lpage>466</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11931779</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) Photograph of the cornea shows an approximately 3.7&#xD7;5.0 mm epithelial defect and infiltrated stromal lesion at the time of admission. (B) Photograph of the cornea shows healed epithelium with mild posterior stromal opacity after four weeks of treatment.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-349-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Results of antimicrobial sensitivity tests</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-349-i001"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>MIC = minimal inhibitory concentration; R = resistant; S = sensitive.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
