<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Orthop Surg Traumatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Orthop Surg Traumatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>European Journal of Orthopaedic Surgery &amp; Traumatology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1633-8065</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-1068</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Paris</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23412183</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3825641</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1050</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00590-012-1050-8</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Up-to date Review and Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome in a 11-year-old girl due to penetrating glass injury to the thoracic spine</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Komarowska</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Debek</surname>
            <given-names>W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wojnar</surname>
            <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>hedgehog2@tlen.pl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hermanowicz</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rogalski</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Pediatric Surgery, Medical University of Bialystok, Bialystok, Poland </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Pediatric Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Medical University of Bialystok, Bialystok, Poland </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>23</volume>
      <issue>Suppl 2</issue>
      <fpage>141</fpage>
      <lpage>143</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Injuries in children are one of the most frequent causes of high morbidity and mortality, and they present a challenge to the treating physician. Fortunately, spinal trauma in pediatric patient is relatively rare. Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome is a rare form of incomplete spinal cord injury consisting of ipsilateral upper motor neuron paralysis (hemiplegia) and loss of proprioception with contralateral pain and temperature sensation deficits resulting from hemisection or lateral injury to the spinal cord. A 11-year-old girl was admitted to our Pediatric Trauma Emergency Department after she had suffered a penetrating back injury. Neurological examination demonstrated left lower extremity paresis and moderate spastic paralysis of the right lower extremity. The examination showed loss of temperature sensation contralateral to and below the lesion. The examination of the pain sensation was difficult because the patient was in pain shock, but it was diminished on the side opposite to the damage. Multislice spiral computed tomography (MSCT) demonstrated a triangular foreign body in spinal canal at the level of the Th11&#x2013;Th12. After a Th<sub>11</sub>&#x2013;L<sub>2</sub> laminectomy and retrieval of foreign bodies, dura repair was performed. Patient was discharged from the hospital with partial recovery. Operative decompression of the neural elements in case of spinal canal compromise is the treatment of choice. Indication for surgical intervention in existing cerebrospinal fluid fistula includes closure of the dura and reducing neural elements compression and lowering the risk of infectious complications by removing bone or foreign body fragments. Patients with Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome have good prognosis for functional recovery.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Spinal cord injury</kwd>
        <kwd>Stab wound</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag France 2013</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Injuries in children are one of the most frequent causes of high morbidity and mortality, and they present a challenge to the treating physician. Fortunately, spinal trauma in pediatric patient is relatively rare. Our knowledge about the differences between pediatric and adult spinal column and spinal cord injuries remains still incomplete; therefore, each case provides us with valuable new information. All types of spinal cord injuries are present in children population as in adults. Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome, first described in 1846 by Charles-Edouard Brown-S&#xE9;quard [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], is a rare form of incomplete spinal cord injury consisting of ipsilateral upper motor neuron paralysis (hemiplegia) and loss of proprioception with contralateral pain and temperature sensation deficits resulting from hemisection or lateral injury to the spinal cord. Typically, it occurs in young males aged 15&#x2013;50&#xA0;years old after penetrating trauma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. There are very few cases of Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome after a penetrating trauma to the spine in children reported in literature. In this population, motor vehicle accidents or other blunt traumas are the most common causes of spinal injury. We present a case of Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome after a stab wound to the thoracic region from broken glass window.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 11-year-old girl, with slight degree of mental retardation, was admitted to our Pediatric Trauma Emergency Department after she had suffered a penetrating back injury. She was running in her house when she suddenly bumped to the glass door. She has not lost consciousness.</p>
      <p>On examination at admission, she was in logical contact. She was 15 points in Glasgow Coma Scale. The vital signs were heart rate 84&#xA0;beats/min, blood pressure 100/70&#xA0;mmHg, respiratory rate 20 breaths/min and temperature 36.6&#xA0;&#xB0;C. Physical examination revealed a linear 1.5-cm-long stab wound in the low left paraspinal thoracic region (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Stab wound in the <italic>left</italic> thoracic region of the back</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="590_2012_1050_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>There was no foreign body seen over the skin surface. Bleeding was minimal, but cerebrospinal fluid leakage from the wound was observed. No other injuries were diagnosed. Neurological examination demonstrated left-side lower extremity paresis and moderate spastic paralysis on the other lower extremity. Bilateral positive Babinski sign was observed. An exact sensory examination was not possible because of slight mental retardation, but loss of temperature sensation contralateral to and below the lesion was noticed. The examination of the pain was difficult because the patient was in pain shock, but it was diminished on the side opposite to the damage. Rectal sphincter muscle tone was normal. The urogenital examination was normal. There were no abnormalities in laboratory tests.</p>
      <p>Multislice spiral computed tomography (MSCT) demonstrated a triangular foreign body inside the spinal canal (26&#xA0;mm&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;11&#xA0;mm&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;6&#xA0;mm) at the level of the Th<sub>11</sub>&#x2013;Th<sub>12</sub> and several small fragments of the glass in the paraspinal muscles on the left side (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Steroids were not used, and standard perioperative antibiotic prophylactics were administered. The patient was immediately taken to the operating theatre. The wound was explored. A Th<sub>11</sub>&#x2013;L<sub>2</sub> laminectomy was performed. Intraoperatively the 2-cm-long laceration of the dura was diagnosed, and the spinal cord was also injured.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>CT scan Th11&#x2013;Th12. A piece of glass window penetrating to the spinal canal</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="590_2012_1050_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      <p>After the foreign bodies retrieval (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), dura laceration repair was performed. There were no signs of the cerebrospinal leakage after the dura closure. Postoperative course was uncomplicated. The girl stayed in Pediatric Surgery Department for 16&#xA0;days. The rehabilitation started in the 3rd day after the surgery.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Removed pieces of the glass window</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="590_2012_1050_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>At the discharge date, she was partially recovered. The wound healed uneventfully. Muscle strength was rated according to 0&#x2013;5 Lovett score [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] as follows:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>1/5: muscle flicker, but no movement</p></list-item><list-item><p>2/5: movement possible, but not against gravity</p></list-item><list-item><p>3/5: movement possible against gravity, but not against resistance by the examiner</p></list-item><list-item><p>4/5: movement possible against some resistance by the examiner</p></list-item><list-item><p>5/5: normal muscle strength.</p></list-item></list></p>
      <p>Partial paresis in the left lower limb (3/5 in the Lovett score) and slight paresis of the right lower limb (4/5 in the Lovett score) were present. Positive bilateral Babinski sign was still present. The girl was ambulating with assistance of the walker.</p>
      <p>She was discharged from the Pediatric Surgery Department and referred to the Rehabilitation Ward.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome is a result of disruption of the descending lateral corticospinal tracts and the ascending lateral spinothalamic tracts, which cross within one or two levels on the dorsal root entrance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Clinically, they result in an ipsilateral to injury loss of position and vibration sensation as well as paralysis and hyperesthesias and contralateral loss of pain and temperature sensation. Light touch sensation is typically not affected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Spinal injury is an uncommon source of morbidity in children. The most common cause of spine injury is motor vehicle accident, falls and sports-related accidents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Far less common is penetrating injury to the spine, with the stab wounds and gunshot traumas being the most common reasons in adults. Only about 3&#xA0;% of traumatic spinal cord injury ends up with Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome; however, a pure form of this syndrome occurs rarely and therefore the term &#x2018;Brown-S&#xE9;quard-plus&#x2019; syndrome is used when additional neurological findings are present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Several cases of such Brown-S&#xE9;quard-plus syndrome have been reported in adult literature, most of them caused by penetrating trauma and rarely by blunt trauma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Reports concerning children population are very infrequent.</p>
      <p>Treatment for this disease should be the same as for other acute spinal cord injuries. Indication for surgical intervention in existing cerebrospinal fluid fistula includes closure of the dura and reducing neural elements compression and lowering the risk of infectious complications by removing bone or foreign body fragments or hematoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. However, severe neurological deficits remaining unchanged from the time of injury rarely improve after decompressive surgery.</p>
      <p>Randomized prospective trials in adults (NASCIS 3) suggest that patients with motor impairment may benefit from high-dose steroids administration within 8&#xA0;h of an injury, but their role is controversial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. There are no randomized, prospective trials concerning steroid use in spinal cord injury in children population. Steroid use is even more controversial in penetrating injury due to increased risk of infections leading to prolonged hospital stay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]; nevertheless, some authors advocate treatment with methylprednisolone succinate in scheme as in adult.</p>
      <p>In many cases of spinal cord injuries, different types of loss of motor, sensory and autonomic functions below the level of lesion are observed. Patients with Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome have relative good prognosis for functional recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors of this article would like to give special thanks to Agnieszka Stewart for her invaluable editorial assistance.</p>
      <sec id="d30e364">
        <title>Conflict of interest</title>
        <p>None of the authors of the above manuscript has declared any conflict of interest within the last 3&#xA0;years which may arise from being named as an author on the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="d30e369">
        <title>Open Access</title>
        <p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rengachary</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guthikonda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Charles Edouard Brown-s&#xE9;quard: an eccentric genius</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>954</fpage>
          <lpage>964</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/01.neu.0000318182.87664.1f</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18496202</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Henderson</surname>
              <given-names>SO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoffner</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brown-sequard syndrome due to isolated blunt trauma</article-title>
          <source>J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>847</fpage>
          <lpage>850</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0736-4679(98)00096-1</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9848698</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lovett</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>EG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Certain aspects of infantile paralysis with a description of a method for muscle testing</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <year>1916</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>729</fpage>
          <lpage>733</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1916.02580360031009</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miranda</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gomez</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alday</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramos</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome after blunt cervical trauma: clinical and radiological correlations</article-title>
          <source>Eur Spine J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1165</fpage>
          <lpage>1170</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00586-007-0345-7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17394028</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cirak</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ziegfeld</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Knight</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Avellino</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paidas</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spinal injuries in children</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr Surg</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>607</fpage>
          <lpage>612</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2003.12.011</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15065038</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hagen</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eide</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elgen</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Traumatic spinal cord injury among children and adolescents; a cohort study in western Norway</article-title>
          <source>Spinal Cord</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>981</fpage>
          <lpage>985</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sc.2011.42</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21556012</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McKinley</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meade</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brooke</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Incidence and outcomes of spinal cord injury clinical syndromes</article-title>
          <source>J Spinal Cord Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>215</fpage>
          <lpage>224</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17684887</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grubenhof</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brent</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case report: Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome resulting from a ski injury in a 7-year-old male</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Pediatr</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>341</fpage>
          <lpage>344</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOP.0b013e3282ff62d6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18475106</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jia</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuan</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brown-S&#xE9;quard syndrome due to penetrating injury by an iron fence point</article-title>
          <source>Spinal Cord</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>582</fpage>
          <lpage>584</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sc.2009.174</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20010907</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Issaivanan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nhlane</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rizvi</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shukla</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baldauf</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brown-S&#xE9;quard-plus syndrome because of penetrating trauma in children</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Neurol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2010.03.016</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20682206</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bracken</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shepard</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holford</surname>
              <given-names>TR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Administration of methylprednisolone for 24 or 48 hours or tirilazad mesylate for 48 hours in the treatment of acute spinal cord injury. Results of the Third National Acute Spinal Cord Injury Randomized Controlled Trial. National acute spinal cord injury study</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <fpage>1597</fpage>
          <lpage>1604</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1997.03540440031029</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9168289</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pettiford</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bikhchandani</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ostlie</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A review: the role of high dose methylprednisolone in spinal cord trauma in children</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Surg Int</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>287</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00383-011-3012-3</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21994079</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McKinley</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meade</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Incidence and outcomes of spinal cord injury clinical syndromes</article-title>
          <source>J Spinal Cord Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>215</fpage>
          <lpage>224</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17684887</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
