<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24346910</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3875981</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20132137</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Congenital agminated melanocytic nevus - case report<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref>
</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Nevo melanoc&#xED;tico cong&#xEA;nito agminado - relato de caso</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>da Rocha</surname>
            <given-names>Camila Roos Mariano</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grazziotin</surname>
            <given-names>Tha&#xED;s Corsetti</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rey</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Carolina Widholzer</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Luzzatto</surname>
            <given-names>Laura</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bonamigo</surname>
            <given-names>Renan Rangel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Medical resident of Dermatology at Hospital Federal da Lagoa - Rio de
Janeiro (RJ), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> MD, Dermatologist. Masters in Pathology. Universidade Federal de
Ci&#xEA;ncias da Sa&#xFA;de de Porto Alegre (UFCSPA) - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> MD, Pathologist - Dermatology Service at Universidade Federal de
Ci&#xEA;ncias da Sa&#xFA;de de Porto Alegre (UFCSPA) - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> MD, PhD, Head of Dermatology Service at Universidade Federal de
Ci&#xEA;ncias da Sa&#xFA;de de Porto Alegre (UFCSPA) - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing address:</bold> Tha&#xED;s Corsetti Grazziotin, Rua Sarmento Leite, 245,
90050-170 - Porto Alegre - RS, Brazil. E-mail: <email>tcgrazziotin@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>6 Suppl 1</issue>
      <fpage>170</fpage>
      <lpage>172</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Agminated nevus is a cluster group of melanocytic nevi confined to a localized area
of the body. There are many pigmented lesions described in the literature as
agminated, such as blue nevi, multiple lentigines and Spitz nevi, but only a few
cases of congenital agminated melanocytic nevi have been described. We report a case
of a male child who presented with congenital agminated nevi, emphasizing the
importance of physical examination, dermoscopy, histopathological evaluation,
differential diagnosis and follow up to rule out the possibility of dysplastic or
malignant changes.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>Nevo agminado &#xE9; um conjunto de les&#xF5;es melanoc&#xED;ticas confinadas a uma &#xE1;rea do corpo.
Existem muitas les&#xF5;es descritas na literatura como agminada s, como nevos azuis,
lentigos m&#xFA;ltiplos, nevo de Spitz, mas existem poucos casos de nevos melanoc&#xED;ticos
agminados cong&#xEA;nitos descritos. Relatamos o caso de um paciente do sexo masculino que
se apresentou com um nevo agminado cong&#xEA;nito, enfatizando a import&#xE2;ncia do exame
f&#xED;sico, dermatoscopia, avalia&#xE7;&#xE3;o histol&#xF3;gica, diagn&#xF3;stico diferencial e seguimento
para descartar a possibilidade de altera&#xE7;&#xF5;es displ&#xE1;sicas ou malignas.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Clusterin</kwd>
        <kwd>Nevus</kwd>
        <kwd>Nevus, intradermal</kwd>
        <kwd>Nevus, Pigmented</kwd>
        <kwd>Skin and Connective Tissue Diseases</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Agminated nevi are infrequent pigmented lesions. 'Agminated' is derived from the Latin
word 'agmen', meaning 'aggregation' and refers to a clustered or circumscribed grouping
of lesions confined to a localized area of the body. It should be distinguished from
other forms of segmental distribution lacking a definite clustering.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Pigmented lesions that have been described in the literature as agminated include blue
nevi, multiple lentigines, Spitz nevi, congenital melanocytic nevi, acquired melanocytic
nevi, and lesions within nevi spili.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup> No hyperpigmented lesions described as
agminated include xanthogranuloma, angiofibromas and neurilemomas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Most cases reported in the literature corresponded to Spitz or blue nevi, with only few
descriptions of melanocytic congenital agminated nevi. Only a few cases of congenital
agminated melanocytic nevi have been described in literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup> One of these
cases presented with a "blaschkoid" pattern following Blaschko lines on the
abdomen.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>The main differential diagnosis is nevus spilus. This nevus commonly appears during late
infancy or early childhood, leading to the belief that they are a type of congenital
nevus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup> A tan lentiginous background patch on which more darkly
pigmented macules and papules are distributed characterizes the lesion. The nevus
spillus usually presents as lentigo simplex on the histological analysis whereas
agminated nevus generally shows a junctional or compound melanocytic nevus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>The association of melanoma with agminated nevus was initially described by Marghoob
<italic>et al</italic>, in a patient with atypical mole syndrome, a pre-existent
melanoma and a dysplastic agminated nevus on the arm that first appeared during
puberty.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup> Later were described
two cases of melanoma arising directly from agminated melanocytic lesions. The first
one, published by Corradin <italic>et al</italic>, described the development of an
invasive melanoma in an acquired agminated nevus that appeared after thermal and solar
burn.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup> Most recently Rezze
<italic>et al</italic> reported the case of a patient affected by atypical mole
syndrome and with personal history of melanoma who presented an agminated nevus on the
anterior chest since puberty.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref></sup> Some
nevi within the agminated lesion presented clinical and dermoscopic criteria of atypic
nevus. The whole lesion was excised and the histopathological analysis showed an
<italic>in situ </italic>melanoma, some areas of severe dysplasia and other areas
corresponding to junctional, intradermal and compound nevi. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A nine-year-old male patient, phototype V, student, was referred to the dermatology
clinic for evaluation of multiple pigmented lesions on his left thigh. He was
accompanied by his father, who informed that the child had had a cluster of melanocytic
lesions since birth. The cluster increased in size following the growth of the patient
and the minor lesions became somewhat closer together over the years. The family
background of skin cancer was negative. The father has a history of congenital nevi on
the face and left lumbar region. The patient presented epilepsy and was in treatment
with carbamazepine, imipramine and risperidone. </p>
      <p>On physical examination, the patient had a cluster of approximately 20 maculopapular,
lightly palpable blackened lesions of different sizes on the anterior part of his left
thigh, forming a cluster of nevi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). The diameter of the total lesion was 9.2cm
x 7.6cm. The largest isolated lesion measured 2.6 cm x 1.3cm. Dermoscopy revealed
predominantly homogeneous pattern with diffuse brownish areas, regular network at the
periphery and numerous regularly distributed small dots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>). No background pigmentation was noted on clinical or dermoscopic
examination between lesions.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Multiple pigmented lesions on the left thigh</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0170-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Detail of the melanocytic lesions within the area of biopsy</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0170-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Dermoscopy revealed predominantly homogeneous pattern with diffuse brownish areas,
regular network at the periphery and numerous regularly distributed small dots</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0170-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <p>A single lesion was excised for histological evaluation with a 2 mm border of normal
skin. The histopathological findings revealed an intradermal melanocytic nevus without
histological melanocytic hyperplasia or hyperpigmentation in clinically normal
peripheral skin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">5</xref>). </p>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histopathology revealed intradermal melanocytic nevus without melanocytic
hyperplasia in the peripheral skin between the nevi</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0170-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A higher magnification reveals nevus cell nests along the papillary dermis</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0170-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Considering the clinical and histopathological diagnosis of the lesion and treatment
limitations due to the size of the total lesion, it was decided to keep dermoscopic
monitoring of the patient every 4 months. It has enhanced to the family the importance
of sun protection and guidance for the observation of changes such as modification of
color, palpation (such as nodularity), shape and rapid growth. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Agminated nevus is a rare lesion and its incidence is unknown. In this case the patient
has a congenital agminated nevus, a rare condition. </p>
      <p>The patient presented a cluster of melanocytic lesions in the anterior part of the left
thigh. There were no dysplastic or malignant changes on clinical examination, dermoscopy
or histology. It can be differentiated from nevus Spillus by the absence of brown
macular background in the clinical examination and histopathology. </p>
      <p>The association between epilepsy and agminated melanocytic nevus is to the best of our
knowledge not found in the literature. There is an established relationship between big
and giant congenital melanocytic nevi with neurocutaneous melanosis, in which the
occurrence of epilepsy is common. In this case there was no suspicion of indication for
investigation for cutaneous melanosis. </p>
      <p>The decision to follow or excise this particular and rare presentation of compound nevus
should be individualized. We decided to monitor the patient since the lesion was large
and without atypical clinical, dermoscopic and histological findings. Long-term
follow-up is recommended due to the possibility of malignant transformation, even if
this probability is at the moment not exactly defined.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <p>* Work performed at the Dermatology Service of the Health Sciences Federal University
of Porto Alegre (UFCSPA) - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial funding: None</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES </title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Happle</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Segmental lesions are not always agminated</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>838</fpage>
          <lpage>838</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12056974</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Micali</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nasca</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Innocenzi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lembo</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Agminated lentiginosis: case report and review of the
literature</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dermatol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>241</fpage>
          <lpage>245</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7971559</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Menni</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Betti</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boccardi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gualandri</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Both unilateral naevus achromicus and congenital agminated Spitz naevi
in a checkerboard mosaic pattern</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>144</volume>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>188</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11167706</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brunner</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vardarman</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Megahed</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruzicka</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Congenital agminated segmental naevi</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>315</fpage>
          <lpage>316</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7547407</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Betti</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inselvini</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palvarini</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crosti</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title> Agminated intradermal Spitz nevi arising on an unusual speckled
lentiginous nevus with localized lentiginosis: a continuum?</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermatopathol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>524</fpage>
          <lpage>527</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9335246</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marghoob</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blum</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nossa</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Busam</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sachs</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halpern</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Agminated atypical (dysplastic) nevi: case report and review of the
literature</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>917</fpage>
          <lpage>920</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11453811</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mart&#xED;n</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinazo</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Monteagudo</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garc&#xED;a</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jord&#xE1;</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Congenital agminated nevi on the trunk</article-title>
          <source>Int J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>942</fpage>
          <lpage>943</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14636187</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cabanillas Gonz&#xE1;les</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Monteagudo</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de las Heras</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cacharr&#xF3;n</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unilateral agminated melanocytic nevi</article-title>
          <source>Dermatology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>218</volume>
          <fpage>387</fpage>
          <lpage>388</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18974631</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corradin</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alaibac</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fortina</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of malignant melanoma arising from an acquired melanocytic
naevus</article-title>
          <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>432</fpage>
          <lpage>433</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17721654</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rezze</surname>
              <given-names>GG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leon</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neves</surname>
              <given-names>RI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molina</surname>
              <given-names>GC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carraro</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary cutaneous melanoma arising in agminated melanocytic nevi:
CDKN2A and CDK4 mutation screening</article-title>
          <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>98</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21710107</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
