<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJO</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Korean Journal of Ophthalmology : KJO</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8942</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2092-9382</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Ophthalmological Society</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21655050</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3102828</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3341/kjo.2011.25.3.214</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Acute-Onset Bilateral Myopia and Ciliochoroidal Effusion Induced by Hydrochlorothiazide</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Roh</surname>
            <given-names>Young-Rae</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Woo</surname>
            <given-names>Se Joon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Kyu Hyung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seongnam, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Corresponding Author: Se Joon Woo, MD. Department of Ophthalmology, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital, #300 Gumi-dong, Bundanggu, Seongnam 463-707, Korea. Tel: 82-31-787-7377, Fax: 82-31-787-4057, <email>sejoon1@hanmail.net</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>25</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>214</fpage>
      <lpage>217</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2011 The Korean Ophthalmological Society</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The authors experienced two cases of hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ)-induced acute-onset bilateral myopia and shallowing of the anterior chambers. Two middle-aged women taking HCTZ, a sulfa derivative, visited our clinic complaining of acute bilateral visual deterioration. Both had good visual acuity without corrective lenses before taking HCTZ. A complete ophthalmologic examination revealed bilateral myopic shift, intraocular pressure elevation, shallowing of the anterior chambers, choroidal effusions, radiating retinal folds, and conjunctival chemosis. Approximately one week after HCTZ discontinuance, all ocular changes disappeared completely. Physicians should be aware of the adverse ocular effects of HCTZ and should manage patients accordingly.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Angle closure</kwd>
        <kwd>Ciliochoroidal effusion</kwd>
        <kwd>Drug-induced myopia</kwd>
        <kwd>Hydrochlorothiazide</kwd>
        <kwd>Myopia</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Sulfa-derivative drugs, such as topiramate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], sulfamethoxazole, sulfasalazine, indapamide, and acetazolamide have been reported to cause acute bilateral myopia and angle closure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ) is a first-line diuretic drug of the thiazide class that acts by lowering peripheral vascular resistance and inhibiting the ability of the kidneys to retain water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. HCTZ is a sulfa derivative and has been reported to provoke acute myopic shift and bilateral acute angle closure glaucoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. We are unaware of any previous reports of HCTZ-induced acute myopic shift and intraocular pressure (IOP) elevation in Korea. Here, we relate the cases of two patients who presented with acute-onset bilateral myopia and ciliochoroidal effusion secondary to HCTZ and describe the clinical features of HCTZ-induced myopia.</p>
    <sec sec-type="cases">
      <title>Case Reports</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 1</title>
        <p>A 45-year-old woman presented with acute bilateral visual deterioration with duration of one day. Her visual acuities had previously been good without corrective lenses. She had been taking fluoxetine, magnesium hydroxide, and HCTZ for one month to reduce her weight. She had visited another local ophthalmic clinic on the day of symptom onset, and had been told that the IOPs of the right and left eyes were 37 and 41 mmHg, respectively. She was prescribed topical IOP-lowering drugs, namely, Cosopt&#xAE; (dorzolamide hydrochloride-timolol maleate) and Xalatan&#xAE; (latanoprost), and oral Diamox&#xAE; (acetazolamide). Her uncorrected visual acuities (UCVAs) were 0.15 (20 / 150), oculus dexter (OD) and 0.1 (20 / 200), oculus sinister (OS). Automated refraction revealed bilateral myopia with spherical equivalents of -3.0 diopters (D), OD and -3.6 D, OS. Degree of myopia was unchanged by cycloplegic refraction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). After correcting measured refractive errors, she could see 1.0 (20 / 20) with either eye. Her IOPs were 12 mmHg, OD and 14 mmHg OS by Goldmann applanation tonometry. An anterior segment examination revealed conjunctival chemosis and injection, shallow anterior chambers, and narrow angles in both eyes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A and 1B</xref>), and a funduscopic examination revealed bilateral choroidal effusions in the 360o periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>) and radiating retinal folds in the macula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). She was diagnosed as having drug-induced myopia and asked to discontinue drugs including HCTZ. Ten days later, she reported that her vision had recovered and that all ocular changes had disappeared (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). At this time, her UCVAs were 0.8 (20 / 25), OD and 0.6 (20 / 33), OS and she had a best-corrected visual acuity (BCVA) of 1.0 (20 / 20) in both eyes. Myopia had been reduced to the prior refractive state (spherical equivalent of -0.75D, oculi unitas).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 2</title>
        <p>A 40-year-old woman presented with bilateral visual acuity deterioration, which had started 9 hours before presentation. She also had good visual acuities without corrective lenses before the episode. She had been prescribed ginexin, spironolactone, and HCTZ at the local clinic of internal medicine to cure edematous changes of the lower extremities. Her UCVAs were 0.08 (20 / 250), OD and 0.06 (20 / 300), OS. Automated refraction revealed bilateral myopia with spherical equivalents of -4.5 D, OD and -5.25 D, OS and degree of myopia was unchanged by cycloplegic refraction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). After correcting measured refractive errors, she could see 1.2 (20 / 16), OD and 1.0 (20 / 20), OS. Her IOPs were 15 mmHg, OD and 16 mmHg, OS by Goldmann applanation tonometry. Anterior segment examinations revealed conjunctival chemosis, shallow anterior chambers, and narrow angles in both eyes. She was also diagnosed as having drug-induced myopia and recommended to discontinue all three drugs. Nine days after the discontinuance of medications, her UCVAs were 0.8 (20 / 25), OD and 0.6 (20 / 30), OS and myopia had been reduced to the prior refractive state (spherical equivalent of -0.75 D, OD and -1.25 D, OS). An anterior segment examination revealed that the conjunctival chemosis had disappeared and that the anterior chambers were of normal depth.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Both of our patients showed 2 to 4 diopters of transient myopia after HCTZ intake (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Because HCTZ was the only drug taken by both patients and all ocular signs and symptoms disappeared after cessation of this drug, we concluded that HCTZ was responsible for the acute ocular signs and symptoms. Many reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] have been issued on the clinical characteristics of sulfa drug-induced acute ocular changes. In this report, we show photographs of choroidal effusion, radiating retinal folds, and conjunctival chemosis, which have not been previously presented.</p>
      <p>The mechanism of acute myopic shift has been suggested to involve ciliochoroidal effusion and an anterior rotation of the ciliary body. Myopic shift occurs due to the anterior migration of the iris-lens diaphragm, which increases focal length. The resulting configuration has a significantly shallower anterior chamber and appositionally closes the angle of both eyes, which precipitates a glaucomatous crisis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The pathophysiology of ciliochoroidal effusion is considered to be driven by an idiosyncratic reaction, and some researchers have suggested that prostaglandins are involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p>
      <p>The differential diagnoses should include ciliary muscle spasm and primary angle closure glaucoma. Ciliary muscle spasm occurs as a manifestation of iridocyclitis, but it may also be induced by some drugs like anticholinesterase. The diagnosis of the patient can be confirmed by cycloplegic refraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In our case studies, refractive errors, as determined by cycloplegic refraction, were similar to those detected by manifest refraction, which allowed us to rule out a ciliary muscle spasm. Furthermore, because primary angle-closure glaucoma seldom develops bilaterally, the differential diagnosis is relatively easy. Other clinical manifestations, such as choroidal effusion, retinal folds, and conjunctival chemosis can also aid in establishing the differential diagnosis.</p>
      <p>Treatment of drug-induced myopia requires the prompt withdrawal of the offending agent, though discontinuation of medication should be conducted in consultation with an internist to reduce the likelihood of systemic side effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. A previous report also noted that laser iridotomy is not helpful, since the event is not due to a pupillary block [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Whenever a case of bilateral acute myopic shift with shallow anterior chambers and IOP elevation is encountered, drug-induced myopia from ciliochoroidal effusion should be suspected and treated properly.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>The authors were partly supported by grant no. 11-2008-002 from the Seoul National University Bundang Hospital Research Fund.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sankar</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasquale</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grosskreutz</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Uveal effusion and secondary angle-closure glaucoma associated with topiramate use</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>1210</fpage>
          <lpage>1211</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483094</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guier</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Elevated intraocular pressure and myopic shift linked to topiramate use</article-title>
          <source>Optom Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>1070</fpage>
          <lpage>1073</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18091300</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tripathi</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tripathi</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Drug-induced ocular disorders</article-title>
          <source>Drug Saf</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>127</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18217789</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beermann</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groschinsky-Grind</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Absorption, metabolism, and excretion of hydrochlorothiazide</article-title>
          <source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>5 Pt 1</issue>
          <fpage>531</fpage>
          <lpage>537</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1277708</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geanon</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perkins</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bilateral acute angle-closure glaucoma associated with drug sensitivity to hydrochlorothiazide</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>1231</fpage>
          <lpage>1232</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7575249</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boentert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aretz</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ludemann</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute myopia and angle-closure glaucoma induced by topiramate</article-title>
          <source>Neurology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>1306</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14610152</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rhee</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldberg</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parrish</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bilateral angle-closure glaucoma and ciliary body swelling from topiramate</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>1721</fpage>
          <lpage>1723</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11709030</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Craig</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ong</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Louis</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wells</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanism of topiramate-induced acute-onset myopia and angle closure glaucoma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          <lpage>195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14700673</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fraunfelder</surname>
              <given-names>FW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fraunfelder</surname>
              <given-names>FT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keates</surname>
              <given-names>EU</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topiramate-associated acute, bilateral, secondary angle-closure glaucoma</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>109</fpage>
          <lpage>111</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14711721</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kerimoglu</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tokgoz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozturk</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topiramate-induced acute-onset myopia and central corneal thickening: Pentacam Scheimpflug imaging findings</article-title>
          <source>Can J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>222</fpage>
          <lpage>223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19491971</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krieg</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schipper</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Drug-induced ciliary body oedema: a new theory</article-title>
          <source>Eye (Lond)</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>Pt 1</issue>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>126</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8763317</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desai</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramchandani</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhopale</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramchandani</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute myopia and angle closure caused by topiramate, a drug used for prophylaxis of migraine</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>195</fpage>
          <lpage>197</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16921218</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Ocular features at initial presentation (case 1). Anterior segment photographs of right (A) and left (B) eyes showing conjunctival chemosis and injection. (C) A fundus photograph of the right eye showing thin radiating retinal folds around the macula. (D) A photograph of the peripheral retina of the left eye showing ora serrata and an atrophic retinal hole (white arrow). The visibility of the ora serrata indicates choroidal effusion.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-214-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Ocular features after the cessation of hydrochlorothiazide (case 1). Anterior segment photographs of the right (A) and left (B) eyes revealing no conjunctival chemosis. (C) A fundus photograph of the right eye showing a normal macular appearance. (D) The ora serrata is no longer visible in this photograph of the peripheral retina of the left eye, but it can be inferred by the barrier laser markings around the atrophic hole.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-214-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Clinical and biometric parameters at presentation and after HCTZ cessation</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjo-25-214-i001"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>HCTZ = hydrochlorothiazide; VA = visual acuity; IOP = intraocular pressure; R = right eye; L = left eye.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
