<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Emerging Infect. Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23735117</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3713828</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">12-1607</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1906.121607</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letters to the Editor</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type">
          <subject>Letter</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><italic>Shewanella haliotis</italic> Associated with Severe Soft Tissue Infection, Thailand, 2012</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Shewanella haliotis</italic> Infection</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Poovorawan</surname>
            <given-names>Kittiyod</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chatsuwan</surname>
            <given-names>Tanittha</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lakananurak</surname>
            <given-names>Narisorn</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chansaenroj</surname>
            <given-names>Jira</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Komolmit</surname>
            <given-names>Piyawat</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Poovorawan</surname>
            <given-names>Yong</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: Yong Poovorawan, Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Department of Pediatrics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok 10330 Thailand; email: <email xlink:href="Yong.P@chula.ac.th">Yong.P@chula.ac.th</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>1019</fpage>
      <lpage>1021</lpage>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords: </title>
        <kwd>Shewanella haliotis</kwd>
        <kwd>liver transplant</kwd>
        <kwd>soft tissue infection</kwd>
        <kwd>septic shock</kwd>
        <kwd>bacilli</kwd>
        <kwd>bacteria</kwd>
        <kwd>antibiotic</kwd>
        <kwd>antibacterial</kwd>
        <kwd>antimicrobial</kwd>
        <kwd>immunocompromised</kwd>
        <kwd>immune compromised</kwd>
        <kwd>tropical</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><bold>To the Editor:</bold> Marine bacteria of the family <italic>Shewanellaceae</italic>, genus <italic>Shewanella</italic>, are gram-negative, motile bacilli that grow aerobically or anaerobically and produce hydrogen sulfide (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Organisms belonging to a <italic>Shewanella</italic> species were first isolated in 1931 by Derby and Hammer from dairy products and classified as <italic>Achromobacter putrefaciens</italic> (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>). Members of <italic>Shewanella</italic> species usually are found in marine environments in warm climates or during summer in temperate climates (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). In humans, most <italic>Shewanella</italic> species infections occur in skin and soft tissues (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>). One species (<italic>S. algae</italic>) and possibly a second (<italic>S. putrefaciens</italic>) have been isolated from human samples on multiple occasions (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>). A third species, <italic>S. haliotis</italic>, was implicated in human infections during 2010 (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><italic>6</italic></xref>) and <italic>S. xiamenensis</italic> was reported as the fourth infectious species among humans during 2011 (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>). <italic>S. haliotis</italic> is a novel bacterial species that was isolated from the gut microflora of abalones (<italic>Haliotis discus hannai</italic>) in 2007 (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>). We report the second description, to our knowledge, of <italic>S. haliotis</italic> involved in human disease.</p>
    <p>In September 2012, a 52-year-old woman, living in Bangkok, Thailand, was hospitalized after experiencing drowsiness for 2 hours. She had a low-grade fever, chills, and swelling, erythema, and tenderness in her left leg. During the previous week, she had handled fresh seafood in a market and had eaten cooked mackerel. She denied having eaten uncooked food or wading into flooded areas or the sea. She had undergone orthotopic liver transplantation 6 months previously to excise hepatocellular carcinoma related to Child-Pugh class C hepatitis C cirrhosis; since that procedure, she had been under treatment with immunosupressive drugs. She also had diabetes, hypertension, and nephrotic syndrome. Physical examination revealed that in addition to above-named symptoms, multiple blisters were noted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>, panel A). Her oral temperature was 37.8&#xB0;C, blood pressure 80/40 mm Hg, pulse was 110 bpm, and respiratory rate was 24 breaths/minute. A complete blood count showed a leukocyte count of 2,250 cells/&#x3BC;L (91.2% neutrophils). Despite adequate rehydration, monitored by central venous pressure, the patient required norepinephrine to stabilize her vital signs. The clinical diagnosis of her condition was septic shock with suspected necrotizing fasciitis. </p>
    <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
      <label>Figure</label>
      <caption>
        <p><italic>Shewanella haliotis</italic> severe soft tissue infection of woman in Thailand, 2012. The patient sought treatment for painful erythematous swelling of the left leg. A) Arrow indicates affected area. B) Postsurgical fasciotomy wound with necrotic tissue.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="12-1607-F"/>
    </fig>
    <p>After tissue and blood samples were collected and submitted for microbiological analysis, shock resuscitation and an emergency fasciotomy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>, panel B) were performed, and antimicrobial drug treatment with meropenem and vancomycin was started. Surgeons did not confirm the suspected necrotizing fasciitis. Two sets of blood cultures and fluid culture sampled from the left leg identified <italic>S. algae</italic> by conventional biochemical methods. The MICs of antimicrobial drugs were determined by Etest (bioM&#xE9;rieux, Solna, Sweden). This strain was susceptible to ciprofloxacin (0.25 mg/L), piperacillin-tazobactam (1.0 mg/L), ceftriaxone (1.0 mg/L), and meropenem (0.38 mg/L). The patient had fever for the first 2 days of hospitalization. After 2 weeks of treatment, the antimicrobial drug was switched to oral ciprofloxacin; treatment was continued after dressing and debridement of the fasciotomy wound.</p>
    <p>The organism produced yellowish-brown mucoid colonies on sheep blood agar and chocolate agar after 18 hours of incubation at 35<sup>&#xB0;</sup>C under CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere. MacConkey agar showed non&#x2013;lactose-fermenting colonies that were oxidase-positive, motile, and produced hydrogen sulfide on triple sugar iron agar. Growth at 42<sup>o</sup>C with 6.5% NaCl suggested that this organism was <italic>S. algae</italic>. Because phylogenetically related <italic>Shewanella</italic> species may be misidentified by routine biochemical tests, the strain was confirmed by using 16S rRNA gene sequencing.</p>
    <p>Molecular characterization of 16S rRNA gene sequencing was performed by using PCR with <italic>Shewanella</italic> species consensus primers (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Technical Appendix</xref> Table) and direct sequencing from PCR product (JX968803). Phylogenetic analysis of the 16S rRNA gene sequence showed clustering with <italic>S. haliotis</italic> (NR_044134<sup>T</sup>) and 99.9% similarity and 1 base difference (online Technical Appendix Figure). By using BLAST (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>) analysis, JX968803 showed the closest match (99.9%; 1 base difference) with <italic>Alteromonadaceae bacterium</italic> PH39 (AF513471).</p>
    <p>The strain was confirmed as <italic>S. haliotis</italic> by using additional biochemical tests and API 20 NE System (bioM&#xE9;rieux, Durham, NC, USA). It was positive for ornithine decarboxylase, gelatinase, reduction of nitrates to nitrites, tolerance to 6% NaCl, and assimilation of caprate and malate, but negative for citrate utilization, arginine dihydrolase, lysine decarboxylase, urease, indole production, assimilation of mannose, glucose, arabinose, mannitol, maltose, adipate, and acidification of glucose. This strain was resistant to polymyxin B (300 &#xB5;g/disc). </p>
    <p>More than 50 species of <italic>Shewanella</italic> have been reported. The route of <italic>Shewanella</italic> infection is associated with direct contact with the organism through seawater or ingestion of raw seafood (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>). Japan reported 1 case of <italic>S. haliotis</italic> infection in an elderly patient in whom <italic>Vibrio vulnificus</italic> infection was initially suspected (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><italic>6</italic></xref>), and various clinical manifestations of <italic>S. algae</italic> infection have been reported (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Community- and hospital-acquired infection with <italic>Shewanella</italic> species from contaminated medical devices have also been reported (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>). <italic>S. haliotis</italic> and <italic>S. algae</italic> are closely related organisms; discriminating between them on the basis of biochemical tests is difficult. Molecular characterization of 16S rRNA gene sequencing can be used to differentiate the 2 species. In summary, this case suggests that immune-compromised persons in tropical climates could be susceptible to <italic>S. haliotis</italic> soft tissue infection in the absence of typical exposures.</p>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
      <caption>
        <title>Technical Appendix</title>
        <p>Specific <italic>Shewanella</italic> consensus primer sets for 16S rRNA gene sequencing and phylogenetic analysis. </p>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="12-1607-Techapp-s1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e326" position="anchor"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="citation">
        <p><italic>Suggested citation for this article:</italic> Poovorawan K, Chatsuwan T, Lakananurak N, Chansaenroj J, Komolmit P, Poovorawan Y. <italic>Shewanella haliotis</italic> associated with severe soft tissue infection, Thailand, 2012 [letter]. Emerg Infect Dis [Internet]. 2013 Jun [date cited]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid1906.121607">http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid1906.121607</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank the staff of the Gastroenterology Unit, Department of Medicine, Liver Transplant Unit, Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University and Hospital, and the Thai Red Cross Society. We also thank Petra Hirsch for reviewing the manuscript.</p>
      <p>This work was supported by the Higher Education Research Promotion and National Research University Project of Thailand, Office of the Higher Education Commission (HR1155), Thailand Research Fund (DPG5480002), Center of Excellence in Clinical Virology, Chulalongkorn University, Integrated Innovation Academic Center , Chulalongkorn University Centenary Academic Development Project (CU56-HR01), and King Chulalongkorn Memorial Hospital. </p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ivanova</surname>
<given-names>EP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flavier</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships among marine <italic>Alteromonas</italic>-like proteobacteria: emended description of the family <italic>Alteromonadaceae</italic> and proposal of <italic>Pseudoalteromonadaceae</italic> fam. nov., <italic>Colwelliaceae</italic> fam. nov., <italic>Shewanellaceae</italic> fam. nov., <italic>Moritellaceae</italic> fam. nov., <italic>Ferrimonadaceae</italic> fam. nov., <italic>Idiomarinaceae</italic> fam. nov. and <italic>Psychromonadaceae</italic> fam. nov.</article-title>
<source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1773</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.02997-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15388743</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Derby</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammer</surname>
<given-names>BW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bacteriology of butter. IV. Bacteriological studies on surface taint butter.</article-title>
<source>Iowa Agric Exp Station Res Bull.</source>
<year>1931</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>416</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Holt</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gahrn-Hansen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruun</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic>Shewanella algae</italic> and <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic>: clinical and microbiological characteristics.</article-title>
<source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2005.01108.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15819859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goyal</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaur</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thakur</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Human soft tissue infection by the emerging pathogen <italic>Shewanella algae.</italic></article-title>
<source>J Infect Dev Ctries</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3855/jidc.1436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21537075</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Janda</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbott</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The genus <italic>Shewanella</italic>: from the briny depths below to human pathogen.</article-title>
<source>Crit Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21</lpage> and. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/1040841X.2012.726209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23043419</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tadera</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimonaka</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohkusu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morii</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimohana</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Michinaka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>
<article-title>A case report of <italic>Shewanella haliotis</italic> showing a phlegmonous inflammation of right lower leg with sepsis</article-title>
<comment>[in Japanese]</comment>
<source>JSCM</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zong</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nosocomial peripancreatic infection associated with <italic>Shewanella xiamenensis.</italic></article-title>
<source>J Med Microbiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>1387</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.031625-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baik</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>GH</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>
<article-title><italic>Shewanella haliotis</italic> sp. nov., isolated from the gut microflora of abalone, <italic>Haliotis discus hannai.</italic></article-title>
<source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>2926</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.65257-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048751</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Myung</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>SI</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Primary <italic>Shewanella algae</italic> bacteremia mimicking <italic>Vibrio</italic> septicemia.</article-title>
<source>J Korean Med Sci</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1192</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2009.24.6.1192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19949681</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Oh</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kum</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Choe</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oh</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Outbreak of <italic>Shewanella algae</italic> and <italic>Shewanella putrefaciens</italic> infections caused by a shared measuring cup in a general surgery unit in Korea.</article-title>
<source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>742</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/589903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18631115</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
