<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24346871</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3875992</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20132187</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Biological agents: investigation into leprosy and other infectious
diseases before indication<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref>
</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Agentes biol&#xF3;gicos: pesquisa de hansen&#xED;ase e outras doen&#xE7;as infecciosas
antes da indica&#xE7;&#xE3;o</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ant&#xF4;nio</surname>
            <given-names>Jo&#xE3;o Roberto</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Soubhia</surname>
            <given-names>Rosa Maria Cordeiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Paschoal</surname>
            <given-names>Vania Del Arco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Amarante</surname>
            <given-names>Carolina Forte</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Travolo</surname>
            <given-names>Ana Regina Franchi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff05">5</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Professor Emeritus and Doctor at the State Medical School of S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9;
do Rio Preto (FAMERP) - Head of Dermatology at the State Medical School of S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do
Rio Preto and the Dermatology Department of the Base Hospital of S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto -
S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto (SP), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> PhD in Health Sciences - Adjunct Professor of Dermatology at the State
Medical School of S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto (FAMERP) - S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto (SP),
Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> PhD in Health Sciences - Adjunct Professor in the Department of Health
Nursing at the State Medical School of S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto (FAMERP) - S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio
Preto (SP), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> Resident Doctor - Resident at the Medical Clinic at the Base Hospital
of the Regional Medical School Foundation (FUNFARME) - S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto (SP),
Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff05"><label>5</label> Dermatologist - Specialist in Dermatology - Residency in Dermatology
from the Base Hospital of the Regional Medical School Foundation (FUNFARME) - S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9;
do Rio Preto (SP), Brazil.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing address:</bold> Jo&#xE3;o Roberto Ant&#xF4;nio, Avenida Brigadeiro Faria Lima,
5416 - Vila S&#xE3;o Pedro, 15090000 - S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto - SP, Brazil. E-mail:
<email>dr.joao@terra.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>6 Suppl 1</issue>
      <fpage>23</fpage>
      <lpage>25</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Biological agents are widely used for various immune-mediated diseases, with
remarkable effectiveness in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis (RA), psoriasis,
psoriatic arthritis, ankylosing spondylitis and Crohn's disease. However, attention
needs to be drawn to the adverse effects of these therapies and the risk of
reactivating underlying granulomatous infectious diseases such as tuberculosis,
leprosy, syphilis, leishmaniasis, among others. The objective of this paper is to
describe a case of leprosy in a patient with RA using anti-TNF alfa, demonstrating
the need for systematic investigation of skin lesions suggestive of leprosy in
patients who require rheumatoid arthritis therapeutic treatment, especially in
endemic regions like Brazil.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>Os agentes biol&#xF3;gicos s&#xE3;o amplamente utilizados em diversas doen&#xE7;as imuno-mediadas,
com marcante efic&#xE1;cia no tratamento da Artrite Reumat&#xF3;ide (AR), Psor&#xED;ase, Artrite
Psori&#xE1;tica, Espondilite Anquilosante e Doen&#xE7;a de Crohn. No entanto, deve-se atentar
quanto aos efeitos adversos de tais terap&#xEA;uticas, como o risco de reativar doen&#xE7;as
infecciosas granulomatosas latentes, como a tuberculose, hansen&#xED;ase, s&#xED;filis,
leishmaniose, entre outras. O objetivo deste artigo &#xE9; descrever um caso de hansen&#xED;ase
em paciente portador de AR em uso de terapia anti-TNF alfa, mostrando, assim, a
necessidade de investiga&#xE7;&#xE3;o sistematizada de les&#xF5;es cut&#xE2;neas sugestivas de hansen&#xED;ase
em pacientes com indica&#xE7;&#xE3;o de terapia anti-TNF alfa, especialmente, em regi&#xF5;es
end&#xEA;micas como o Brasil.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Rheumatoid arthritis</kwd>
        <kwd>Exposure to biological agents</kwd>
        <kwd>Leprosy</kwd>
        <kwd>Tumor necrosis factor-alpha</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>The Tumor Necrosis Factor (TNF) is a proinflammatory cytokine that has a key function in
various autoimmune diseases, such as rheumatoid arthritis (RA), psoriasis, psoriatic
arthritis, ankylosing spondylitis and Crohn's disease. It plays an important role in
human immune response to infections.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup> As regards infectious diseases, it
encourages the release of other inflammatory cytokines, particularly interleukins IL-1,
IL-6 and IL-8, and stimulates the output of protease, thus participating in the
formation and maintenance of granulomas, a component of intracellular
pathogen-defence.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Biological disease modifying drugs (DMDs) are indicated for patients who experience
persistence of the disease, though treatment involves at least two schemes with
synthetic DMDs, of which at least one is the combination of DMDs. The following
biological DMDs have been approved by the National Health Surveillance Agency (ANVISA)
for use in Brazil: anti-TNF &#x3B1;, B-lymphocyte depletor, T-lymphocyte costimulation blocker
and interleukin-6 (IL-6) receptor blocker.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>At present, three anti-TNF a agents are used to treat certain autoimmune diseases:
infliximab, etanercept and adalimumab.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup> Infliximab is a
chimerical IgG monoclonal antibody, made up of 75% human protein and 25% mouse protein,
the portion of which contains the binding site for TNF. This biological agent
contributes through the death of cells expressing TNF on the surface via an Ac cytotoxic
mechanism and dependent complement, disrupting granulomas, which can cause reactivation
of latent granulomatous infections like tuberculosis and leprosy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>
<italic>Mycobacterium leprae </italic>causes a chronic infectious disease that presents
clinically as a spectrum of symptoms associated with immune response. There are two
polar clinical presentations: the tuberculoid form, represented by well-organized
granulomas with few microbacteria; and the lepromatous form, characterized by
less-organized lesions and a higher number of bacilli. There are also intermediary
clinical forms, the dimorphous forms, with immunological instability and clinical
characteristics from both polar forms. The clinical presentation is polymorphic, varying
from skin alterations with areas of diminished sensitiveness and hypopigmentation, to
more serious neural lesions or involvement of other organs, including bones and
joints.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Male patient, aged 49, white, mason, from the municipality of Auriflama, State of S&#xE3;o
Paulo, Brazil. The patient underwent follow-up in the rheumatology department at the
Base Hospital of S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto, diagnosed with rheumatoid arthritis 15 years
ago, refractory to conventional treatments. Therapy was initiated using infliximab and,
after four doses of this anti-TNF a biological agent, with a total dose of 1600mg,
during the physical exam, erythematous plaques were discovered in the dorsal region and
the left forearm, with respective diameters of 8 and 5cm; and erythematous violaceous
plaques in the left thigh, with diameters of 4 x 6cm, and diminished sensitivity in
these lesions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). The patient experienced increases in the number and diameter of
the erythematous violaceous plaques in the midsection and limbs. The patient presented
positive family epidemiology for leprosy.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous lesion in the dorsal region</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0023-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous violaceous plaque in left thigh</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0023-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The biopsy of the cutaneous lesions on the back and left thigh revealed borderline
leprosy, with a tendency toward the lepromatous pole, with whole, resistant alcohol-acid
resistant bacilli (particularly in nerves), a lymph smear (AARB) and positive Mitsuda
test, with a diameter of 11mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>). The
clinical classification, following the result of the Mitsuda test, was reactional
tuberculoid leprosy and the patient developed a clinical, downgrading reverse reaction,
similar anatomopathologically to dimorphous leprosy. The anti-TNF therapy was
interrupted and a specific treatment for leprosy was started with multibacillary
polychemotherapy (PCT/MB/WHO), presenting significant improvement in the clinical
leprosy. </p>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Mitsuda test: 11mm</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-06-s1-0023-g03"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Leprosy is a granulomatous, chronic, infectious disease of the skin and peripheral
nerves caused by <italic>Mycobacterium leprae</italic>, and is transmitted through
contact with contagious carriers on the part of susceptible individuals. In Brazil, the
disease is endemic.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Infliximab, an anti-TNF biological agent, is indicated for patients with rheumatoid
arthritis, in order to reduce signs and symptoms, prevent structural joint damage and
promote improvement of physical capacities in individuals with the active form of the
disease, which does not respond to conventional therapeutic options.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Since TNF-&#x3B1; is a modulator of cell immune response, there is a risk of opportunist
infections through suppression of endogenous TNF-a, an important cytokine for the
formation of granulomas. Thus, the risk of latent tuberculosis and other infections
needs to be evaluated, along with that of leprosy, before beginning treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>The patient in question underwent four applications of this biological agent, with a
total dose of 1600mg. He was diagnosed with leprosy and, taking into account the
symptoms, anatomopathology and immunology (Mitsuda 11mm), the specific diagnosis was
downgrading hansenic reverse reaction tuberculoid leprosy (positive AARB in the biopsy
with dimorphous characteristics), which occurred due to immunosuppression with
infliximab. In the literature, two cases have been described of patients who developed
leprosy after taking anti-TNF-a drugs; two with infliximab and two with
adalimumab.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>Recently, the introduction of biological agents as an alternative to conventional
treatments for autoimmune diseases has brought about positive therapeutic responses,
with improvements in quality of life and the psychological wellbeing of patients in
treatment. However, the development of opportunist infections or reactivation of latent
granulamatous infections, such as leprosy and tuberculosis, highlight the need for
careful indication of treatment. </p>
      <p>This study demonstrates the possibility of leprosy developing in patients using
infliximab, and recommends systematized investigation into this pathology through
epidemiological research, neurocutaneous exams and, if necessary, lymph smear testing
following the protocol for the indication of biological agents, especially in endemic
countries.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <p>* Study carried out at the Outpatient Service of the Dermatology Department of the
Base Hospital at the State Medical School of S&#xE3;o Jos&#xE9; do Rio Preto, S&#xE3;o Paulo.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial support: None.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interests: None.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES </title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Consenso 2012 da Sociedade Brasileira de Reumatologia
para o tratamento da artrite reumatoide</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras Reumatol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>152</fpage>
          <lpage>174</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22460407</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wallis</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Broder</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanson</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beenhouwer</surname>
              <given-names>DO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Granulomatous infectious diseases associated with tumor necrosis
factor antagonists</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>1261</fpage>
          <lpage>1265</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15127338</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Winthrop</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Risk and prevention of tuberculosis and other serious opportunistic
infections associated with the inhibition of tumor necrosis factor</article-title>
          <source>Nat Clin Pract Rheumatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>602</fpage>
          <lpage>610</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17075599</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Freitas</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machado</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrigueti</surname>
              <given-names>FV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reis</surname>
              <given-names>ET</given-names>
              <suffix>Neto</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinheiro</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Hansen&#xED;ase virchowiana associada ao uso de inibidor do
fator de necrose tumoral alfa</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras Reumatol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>333</fpage>
          <lpage>339</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21125169</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Faleiro</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ara&#xFA;jo</surname>
              <given-names>LHR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varavallo</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">A Terapia Anti-TNF-&#x3B1; na Artrite
Reumat&#xF3;ide</article-title>
          <source>Semina Cienc Biol Saude</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oberstein</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kromo</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tozman</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Type I reaction of Hansen's disease with exposure to Adalimumabe: A
case report</article-title>
          <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>1040</fpage>
          <lpage>1043</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18576299</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Munk</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anding</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schettini</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaufmann</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Soluble tumor necrosis factor alpha receptors in Sera from Leprosy
patients</article-title>
          <source>Infect Immun</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>423</fpage>
          <lpage>425</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9864247</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scollard</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joyce</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gillis</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of Leprosy and type 1 reactions after treatment with
Infliximab: A report of 2 cases</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>e19</fpage>
          <lpage>e22</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16779736</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
