<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Ophthalmology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2415</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23855887</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3737109</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2415-13-34</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2415-13-34</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Tear lipid layer deficiency associated with incomplete blinking: A case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Kawashima</surname>
            <given-names>Motoko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>motoko-k@a3.keio.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsubota</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>tsubota@z3.keio.jp</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>MGD Clinic, Keio University School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Keio University School of Medicine, 35 Shinanomachi, Shinjuku, Tokyo 160-8582, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Minamiaoyama Eye Clinic, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <fpage>34</fpage>
      <lpage>34</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 Kawashima and Tsubota; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Kawashima and Tsubota; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2415/13/34"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Meibomian gland obstruction induces hyposecretion of tear film lipids, which results in lipid layer deficiency and evaporative dry eye. Unfortunately, the importance of blinking in meibomian gland dysfunction has been largely overlooked, and it is not known whether incomplete blinking causes tear lipid deficiency, even in the unobstructed meibomian glands.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 38-year-old woman suffering from foreign body sensations in her eyes was examined. The cornea was clear and tear secretion was normal. Lid margin abnormalities were not observed and the meibum was clear. However, the lipid layer was very thin, and the patient was given a diagnosis of incomplete blinking. The patient was made aware of her condition and asked to blink consciously and completely. After that, an immediate increase in lipid flow was observed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Tear lipid layer deficiency can occur with incomplete blinking, even though meibomian gland structures are intact. This case highlights the importance of complete blinking.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Lipid layer</kwd>
        <kwd>Blink</kwd>
        <kwd>Meibomian gland</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Dry eye disease (DED) is a common, yet complex condition that is most often caused by meibomian gland dysfunction (MGD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Meibomian gland obstruction and gland drop out contribute hyposecretion of tear film lipids, which results in lipid layer deficiency and evaporative DED [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Recently developed noncontact meibography allows physicians to clearly and noninvasively observe meibomian gland morphology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Subjective ocular symptoms, lid margin abnormalities by slit lamp examination, diagnostic meibomian gland expression and meibomian gland structure observations by meibography are necessary for diagnosing obstructive MGD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Unfortunately, the importance of blinking in MGD has been largely overlooked, and little has been reported on tear lipid deficiency caused by incomplete blinking even in the unobstructed meibomian glands.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 38-year-old woman with a 15-year history of disposable contact lens (CL) use presented to our clinic, complaining of a foreign body sensation in her eyes. She also had&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;8&#xA0;hours/day of visual display terminal (VDT) exposure. Her symptom score on the Standard Patient Evaluation for Eye Dryness questionnaire (score range 0&#x2013;28; for those with the score of &#x2267;6, further DED examinations are recommended.) was 8. On slit lamp examination performed 4&#xA0;hours after CL removal, the cornea was clear and no fluorescein staining was observed. Tear film break-up time was 4&#xA0;seconds in the right eye and tear secretion volume measured by the Schirmer I test was 25&#xA0;mm. Lid margin abnormalities, such as irregular lid margin, vascular engorgement, plugged meibomian gland orifices, and mucocutaneous junction displacement, were not observed. Clear meibum was easily expressed and noncontact meibography showed no loss of meibomian glands in either the upper or lower lids (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Measurements and observations in the left eye were similar to those of the right eye. Neither eye met the diagnostic criteria for DED or MGD.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Normal upper and lower lid margin and meibography findings.</bold> Normal meibomian gland structures are visible.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1471-2415-13-34-1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The LipiView Ocular Surface Interferometer&#xAE; (TearScience, Inc., Morrisville, North Carolina) is a non-invasive instrument that captures live digital images of the tear film, measures its lipid content, and assesses blink dynamics. The LipiView evaluates lipid layer thickness through an Interference Color Unit score (normal average ICU score is &#x2265;75). Surprisingly, even without CL use, this patient&#x2019;s average Interference Color Unit score was 24, indicative of a very thin lipid layer.</p>
      <p>The LipiView examination also revealed that the patient&#x2019;s incomplete blink rate was abnormally high (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A). The patient was made aware of this anomaly and its significance and was asked to blink consciously and completely. LipiView examination was immediately performed again and a significant increase in lipid flow was observed (Figure&#xA0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B).</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>LipiViewresults before (A) and after (B) complete blinking from a 38-year old woman, complaining of foreign body sensation.</bold> Average Interference Color Unit (ICU) score was 24 before blinking and 43 immediately after blinking (normal average ICU score is &#x2265;75).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1471-2415-13-34-2"/>
      </fig>
      <sec>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <p>This case suggests that tear lipid layer deficiency can occur with incomplete blinking, even though meibomian gland structures are intact. We agree with previous reports that suggest that blinking efficiency affects the ocular surface health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. An incomplete blink leads to inadequate lipid distribution (thin lipid layer) as well as consequent exposure over the inferior ocular surface, which may increase evaporation. In agreement with Korb et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] who reported that forceful blinking leads to significant increases in lipid layer thickness, this case demonstrates that conscious and complete blinking can also improve meibomian gland lipid flow. It also suggests that proper blinking is important in lipid layer maintenance through augmentation of meibomian gland lipid expression and lipid spreading across the tear film. Further, McMonnies CW suggested that lubricant eye drop instillation combined with blink efficiency exercises may increase the therapeutic benefit to ocular surface epithelium with the potential to improve tear distribution so that DED symptoms are alleviated and/or prevented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p>
        <p>During work at a VDT, both the blink rate and the number of complete blinks are decreased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The recent marked increase in VDT exposure has also resulted in a marked increase in the number of DED patients. Furthermore, long-term CL use weakens the Muller&#x2019;s muscle, which can lead to blink deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Therefore, more attention should be more attention should be given to blinking status, even in patients with no clinical findings for MGD (e.g., meibomian gland dropout, meibomian orifice obstructions). Although MGD mostly affects older people, lipid deficiency can occur in younger patients. In fact, lipid deficiency with no meibomian gland obstruction is estimated to be widespread in younger patients, especially those using CL and having a high VDT exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. In addition to current treatments, improving the blink quality and quantity may be useful in treating DED.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Tear lipid layer deficiency can occur with incomplete blinking, even though meibomian gland structures are intact. This case highlights the importance of complete blinking.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>VDT: Visual display terminal; MGD: Meibomian gland dysfunction; DED: Dry eye disease; CL: Contact lens; ICU: Interference color unit.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>MK conceived of the study, performed the examination and drafted the manuscript. KT helped to draft the manuscript. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Pre-publication history</title>
      <p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p>
      <p>
        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2415/13/34/prepub">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2415/13/34/prepub</ext-link>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Mr. Tomoo Obayashi, Dr. Takeshi Ide, Dr. Sachiko Inoue, and Dr. Reiko Arita for technical assistance and advice.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Financial support</title>
      <p>No financial support was received for this submission.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Lemp</surname>
            <given-names>MA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Crews</surname>
            <given-names>LA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bron</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Foulks</surname>
            <given-names>GN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sullivan</surname>
            <given-names>BD</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Distribution of aqueous-deficient and evaporative dry eye in a clinic-based patient cohort: a retrospective study</article-title>
          <source>Cornea</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>472</fpage>
          <lpage>478</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ICO.0b013e318225415a</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22378109</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tomlinson</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bron</surname>
            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Korb</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Amano</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Paugh</surname>
            <given-names>JR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Pearce</surname>
            <given-names>EI</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yee</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yokoi</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Arita</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dogru</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The international workshop on meibomian gland dysfunction: report of the diagnosis subcommittee</article-title>
          <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>2006</fpage>
          <lpage>2049</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.10-6997f</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21450918</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Arita</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Itoh</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Maeda</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Maeda</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Furuta</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fukuoka</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tomidokoro</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Amano</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Proposed diagnostic criteria for obstructive meibomian gland dysfunction</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>2058</fpage>
          <lpage>2063</lpage>
          <comment>e2051</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2009.04.037</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19744718</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>McMonnies</surname>
            <given-names>CW</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Blink efficiency: a neglected area of ocular surface disease management?</article-title>
          <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>4484</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.11-7751</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700718</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Linton</surname>
            <given-names>RG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Curnow</surname>
            <given-names>DH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Riley</surname>
            <given-names>WJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The meibomian glands: an investigation into the secretion and some aspects of the physiology</article-title>
          <source>Br J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1961</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>718</fpage>
          <lpage>723</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjo.45.11.718</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18170726</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Korb</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Baron</surname>
            <given-names>DF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Herman</surname>
            <given-names>JP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Finnemore</surname>
            <given-names>VM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Exford</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hermosa</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leahy</surname>
            <given-names>CD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Glonek</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Greiner</surname>
            <given-names>JV</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Tear film lipid layer thickness as a function of blinking</article-title>
          <source>Cornea</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>354</fpage>
          <lpage>359</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00003226-199407000-00012</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7924337</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>McMonnies</surname>
            <given-names>CW</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Incomplete blinking: exposure keratopathy, lid wiper epitheliopathy, dry eye, refractive surgery, and dry contact lenses</article-title>
          <source>Contact lens &amp; anterior eye: the journal of the British Contact Lens Association</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clae.2006.12.002</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17251052</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsubota</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nakamori</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Dry eyes and video display terminals</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>328</volume>
          <fpage>584</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8426634</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Bleyen</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hiemstra</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Devogelaere</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>van den Bosch</surname>
            <given-names>WA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wubbels</surname>
            <given-names>RJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Paridaens</surname>
            <given-names>DA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Not only hard contact lens wear but also soft contact lens wear may be associated with blepharoptosis</article-title>
          <source>Can J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>333</fpage>
          <lpage>336</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816253</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kojima</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
            <given-names>OM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wakamatsu</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tsuyama</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ogawa</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dogru</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tsubota</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The impact of contact lens wear and visual display terminal work on ocular surface and tear functions in office workers</article-title>
          <source>American journal of ophthalmology</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>152</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>933</fpage>
          <lpage>940</lpage>
          <comment>e932</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajo.2011.05.025</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21871600</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Blackie</surname>
            <given-names>CA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Korb</surname>
            <given-names>DR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knop</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bedi</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Knop</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Holland</surname>
            <given-names>EJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Nonobvious obstructive meibomian gland dysfunction</article-title>
          <source>Cornea</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1333</fpage>
          <lpage>1345</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ICO.0b013e3181d4f366</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20847669</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
