<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J. Appl. Oral. Sci.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru da Universidade de S&#xE3;o
Paulo</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24473729</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3891287</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1679-775720130249</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dental manifestations of patient with Vitamin D-resistant
rickets</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SOUZA</surname>
            <given-names>Andr&#xE9;ia Pereira</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>KOBAYASHI</surname>
            <given-names>Tatiana Yuriko</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>LOUREN&#xC7;O NETO</surname>
            <given-names>Natalino</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SILVA</surname>
            <given-names>Salete Moura Bonif&#xE1;cio</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>MACHADO</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Aparecida Andrade Moreira</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>OLIVEIRA</surname>
            <given-names>Thais Marchini</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff> Bauru School of Dentistry, University of S&#xE3;o Paulo, Bauru, SP, Brazil.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding address:</bold> Thais Marchini Oliveira - Faculdade de
Odontologia de Bauru - Universidade de S&#xE3;o Paulo - Alameda Dr. Oct&#xE1;vio Pinheiro
Brisolla, 9-75 - Bauru - SP - 17012-901 - Brazil - Phone:55 14 32358218 - e-mail:
<email>marchini@usp.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>21</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>601</fpage>
      <lpage>606</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patients with Vitamin D-resistant rickets have abnormal tooth morphology such as thin
globular dentin and enlarged pulp horns that extend into the dentino-enamel junction.
Invasion of the pulp by microorganisms and toxins is inevitable. The increased
fibrotic content of the pulp, together with a reduced number of odontoblasts,
decreases the response to pulp infection. The most important oral findings are
characterized by spontaneous gingival and dental abscesses occuring without history
of trauma or caries. Radiographic examinations revealed large pulp chambers, short
roots, poorly defined lamina dura and hypoplastic alveolar ridge. These dental
abscesses are common and therefore the extraction and pulpectomy are the treatment of
choice. The purpose of this article is to report a case of Vitamin D-resistant
rickets in a 5 year-old boy, describing the dental findings and the treatment to be
performed in these cases.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Rickets</kwd>
        <kwd>Vitamin D</kwd>
        <kwd>Hypophosphatemia</kwd>
        <kwd>Dental pulp</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Vitamin D-resistant rickets (VDRR), also known as hereditary or familial
hypophosphatemia, is characterized by a metabolic disturbance which causes defective
calcification of mineralized structures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">14</xref></sup>. VDRR is well established genetically as an X-linked dominant
metabolic disorder, that may be characterized by persistent hypophosphatemia and
hyperphosphaturea associated with decreased renal tubular reabsorption of inorganic
phosphates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The prevalence rate is usually reported to be around 1:20,000<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref></sup>. In this
condition, there is deficient mineralization of bone caused by a genetic defect in renal
transepithelial transport of phosphate, which leads to a decrease in tubular
reabsorption of phosphate and persistent hypophosphatemia. The features of rickets are
the main systemic signs, but many children are not diagnosed until about 2-3 years of
age. The metabolic disorder is treated with large doses of oral replacement of
phosphate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r04">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>These anomalies lead to discordance between the production and the rate of
mineralization of bone matrix, hence the accumulation of unmineralized matrix and poorly
mineralized bone, causing as main clinical features severe body deformities, especially
bowing of the legs, impaired growth and short stature. Radiologic findings usually
include fractures, generalized osteopenia, growth failure, in some cases
craniosynostosis may be present and arched or curve legs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">16</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Dental findings that are often characteristic include dentin defects, unusually large
pulp chambers and enlarged pulp horns, in some cases the enamel is hypoplastic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">16</xref></sup>. These dental problems
are more commonly associated with the primary than the permanent dentition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup>. The most common intraoral radiologic
findings include large pulp chambers, short roots, poorly defined lamina dura and
hypoplastic alveolar ridge<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">16</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>On histologic analysis, the dentin exhibits large tubular clefts or lacunae and the
enlarged pulp horns may extend beyond the dentino-enamel junction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r05">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup>.
The poorly formed dentin and close proximity of the pulp to the tooth surface may lead
to a rapid necrosis of the pulp with periapical complications, because the bacterial
ingress to the pulp is being facilitated, occurring spontaneous dental abscess without
history of trauma or caries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">14</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The purpose of this article is to report a case of VDRR in a 5 year-old boy, describing
dental findings and treatment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 5 year-old boy was referred to the Pediatric Dentistry Clinic with the complaint of "a
small ball that appeared in the mouth". During the anamnesis, the patient was diagnosed
as having hypophosphatemic vitamin D-resistant rickets. The child was the third twin;
however, the parents as well as the siblings, did not have the metabolic disorder. The
medicines taken by the patient were calcitriol and phosphate supplements. He presented
short stature and several skeletal abnormalities.</p>
      <p>Clinical examinations revealed fistula at the periapical region of primary maxillary
left lateral incisor without caries or trauma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure
1</xref>). The patient presented complete primary dentition and none of the teeth
examined showed evidence of caries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2A-B</xref>).
Radiographic examinations included periapical, panoramic and occlusal views showing pulp
chambers enlarged, with pulp horns extending to the dentino-enamel junction, poorly
defined lamina dura and hypoplastic alveolar ridge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 2C</xref>). The patient presented a large physiologic wear of the incisors,
geographic tongue and primary mandibular right lateral incisor (#82) and canine (#83)
with crown alteration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 3A-B</xref>). There were
areas of rarefaction around the apices of the primary maxillary right and left central
incisor (#51,61), primary maxillary right and left lateral incisor (#52,62), primary
maxillary right and left canine (#53,63) and primary maxillary right and left first
molar (#54,64), primary mandibular right and left central incisor (#81,71) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">5A-B</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clinical examinations revealed fistula at the periapical region of primary
maxillary left lateral incisor</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jaos-21-06-0601-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2A-B</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The patient presented complete primary dentition and none of the teeth examined
showed evidence of caries</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jaos-21-06-0601-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2C</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Panoramic radiography showed the initial conditions</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jaos-21-06-0601-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3A-B</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Teeth #82 and #83 fused, clinical and periapical radiography</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jaos-21-06-0601-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Periapical radiography showed areas of rarefaction around the apices of the
primary maxillary right and left central incisor</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jaos-21-06-0601-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5A-B</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Periapical radiography showed pulp chambers enlarged with pulp horns extending to
the dentino-enamel junction</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jaos-21-06-0601-g06"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Initially, two sections of management were performed. The treatment was divided into two
phases: at first, the extraction of the teeth was performed: #51, 61, 81 and 71. At the
second phase, endodontic treatment of the teeth: #52, 62, 53 and 63. These procedures
were executed with local anesthesia and rubber dam isolation. The root canals were
submitted to preparation with Kerr files and dressing with paramonoclorofenol
(Biodin&#xE2;mica LTDA, Brazil) for 48 hours. Canals were filled with zinc oxid-eugenol and
iodoform paste and restored with resin glass ionomer cement (Vitremer, 3M/ESPE,
USA).</p>
      <p>During the aforementioned treatment, primary mandibular right first molar (#84), primary
maxillary right and left first molar (#54,64) and primary mandibular left second molar
(#75) showed periapical fistula without evidence of caries or trauma in a short-term.
These teeth were extracted. However, the child was constantly sick and did not attend
the consultations. In the other teeth, the primary mandibular right second molar (#85),
lateral incisor and canine (#82,83), primary maxillary right and left second molars
(#55,65), primary mandibular left first molar and lateral incisor and canine
(#74,73,72), the choice of treatment was to open the pulp chambers and make a dressing
with formocresol (Biodin&#xE2;mica LTDA, Brazil). After a 7-day period, the dressing with
formocresol was removed and the root instrumentation was performed and filled with zinc
oxid-eugenol and iodoform paste, afterwards the teeth were restored with resin glass
ionomer cement (Vitremer, 3M/ESPE, USA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f07">Figure
6</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f07" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Panoramic radiography showed the final treatment</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jaos-21-06-0601-g07"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In order to maintain the space of primary maxillary right and left second molars and
primary mandibular right second molar, a fixed space-maintainer was made and cemented
with resin modified glass ionomer cement (Rely X, 3M/ESPE, USA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f08">Figure 7A-B</xref>). The postoperative clinic course was uneventful and
after six months of follow-up, the child did not show clinical abscesses.</p>
      <fig id="f08" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 7A-B</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Fixed space-maintainer for maxillary and mandibular</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="jaos-21-06-0601-g08"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Dental abscesses are frequently observed in VDRR, to the extent that some patients are
first diagnosed from the appearance of the spontaneous dental abscesses which are found
in the absence of caries or trauma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref></sup>. Recurrent abscess formation affecting multiple non-carious primary
teeth has been the main clinical feature in the present case. These abscesses are due to
deficiencies of dentine mineralization which result in large pulp chambers and physical
defects within dentine. In many teeth, there are channels connecting the pulp horns to
the dentino-enamel junction, and, therefore, when the enamel is lost through attrition
or caries, oral microorganisms enter the pulp through these channels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref></sup>. In the present report, the symptoms
were enlarged pulp chambers, poorly calcified dentin and multiple dental abscesses. Of
the manifestations, spontaneous dental abscesses are most characteristic of this
metabolic disorder and present difficult problems to dentists. These abscesses may be
the first sign of a metabolic disorder, such as VDRR, which causes the patient to seek
dental attention and then, subsequently, medical evaluation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref></sup>. Andersen, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref></sup> (2012) showed an increasing frequency of endodontic complications
in these patients and the number of affected teeth increase significantly with age.
These authors concluded that the need for endodontic treatment among these patients is
comprehensive<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r01">1</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The basic dental defects in vitamin D-resistant rickets seem to be manifested in dentin.
Enamel is usually reported to be normal. Spontaneous gingival and dental abscesses occur
without history of trauma or caries, and radiographic evidence of enlarged pulp chambers
with pulpal horns extending beyond the dentino-enamel junction are most important oral
findings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref></sup>. Beltes and
Zachou<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup> (2012) affirmed that
conservative endodontic treatment must be performed in all teeth with pulp necrosis and
rarefactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r02">2</xref></sup>. Both findings and
treatment are recognized in the case presented.</p>
      <p>According to some authors, the histologic examination showed the penetration of
microorganisms through the calcified structures of the enamel layer without visible
caries. The microorganisms passed through the dentino-enamel junction and invaded
dentin, which was characterized by calcospherites and large amounts of interglobular
dentin. Furthermore, microorganisms could be detected in dentinal tubules, which were
exposed to the oral cavity when enamel was removed. However, large areas of tertiary
dentin extended between such tubules and the pulp. These light microscopic results
suggest that clinical manifestations, such as pulp recrosis and periapical lesions, may
be caused by the penetration of microorganisms through microclefts of the enamel layer
as well as pathologically altered enamel microstructures of affected teeth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r07">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref></sup>. These results might explain the clinical problems related to permanent
and primary dentition. Further histologic examinations of teeth of the patient are
necessary. Patients should be informed of possible dental problems and should seek
immediate care when necessary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r08">8</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>As demonstrated in the present case, patients with VDRR have abnormal tooth morphology
as thin globular dentin and enlarged pulp horns that extend into the dentino-enamel
junction. Invasion of the pulp by microorganisms and toxins is inevitable. The increased
fibrotic content of the pulp, together with a reduced number of odontoblasts, decreases
the response to pulp infection. In this case, the spontaneous abscesses were common,
thus, the extraction and pulpectomy was the treatment of choice. Regardless, the
prognosis for spontaneously abscessed teeth in patients with VDRR has been extremely
poor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The main management strategy for the dental manifestations is the prevention of dental
abscesses by prophylactic treatment. In the patients, this may be achieved through
prophylactic pulp therapy, pulpotomy and pulpectomy, coverage of the molar teeth with
stainless steel and restoration of the teeth with composite resins and resin glass
ionomer cement<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">14</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The methodical failure of these treated teeth suggests unhealthy pulps. The general
assumption in VDRR patients that microorganisms gain access to the pulp following
physiologic attrition may not be entirely accurate. These teeth may erupt with pulpal
extensions that communicate with the oral cavity, resulting in microscopic exposures
from the time of eruption. The prophylactic pulpotomies are being performed on pulp
tissue that is not as healthy as previously believed. Perphaps, the pulps were already
infected and the existing condition continued to progress undetected. Since the pulpal
health of teeth in these patients may be suspect, a more radical treatment approach of
prophylactic pulpectomy may be more beneficial. At this time, there is insufficient
evidence to suggest that the recommendation for prophylactic pulpotomy therapy is
beneficial in preserving primary dentition in this patient population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref></sup>. Hypothesis had shown no or little
effect on dental anomalies as result of treatment with vitamin D and phosphate
supplements, therefore, this hypothesis must be explored precisely<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r06">6</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Moreover, to prevent spontaneous dental abscesses as observed in our patient, early
conservative endodontic treatment is necessary. In patients with VDRR, professional
dental care consisting of periodical examinations, topical fluoride application and the
maintenance of good oral hygiene should be performed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r09">9</xref></sup>. Thus, dentists are advised to provide information about the
dental characteristics that might first diagnose such patients and that might request
referrals to dentist as early as possible to prevent dental infections.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andersen</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beck-Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haubek</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hintze</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gj&#xF8;rup</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poulsen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Periapical and endodontic status of permanent teeth in patients with
hypophosphatemic rickets</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Rehabil</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>144</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21902707</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beltes</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zachou</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endodontic management in a patient with vitamin D-resistant
Rickets</article-title>
          <source>J Endod</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>258</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22244648</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Breen</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prophylactic dental treatment for a patient with vitamin D-resistant
rickets: report of case</article-title>
          <source>ASDC J Dent Child</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3003172</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carpenter</surname>
              <given-names>TO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>New perspectives on the biology and treatment of X-linked
hypophosphatemic rickets</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Clin North Am</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>443</fpage>
          <lpage>466</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9130929</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chaussain-Miller</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sinding</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Septier</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolikow</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldberg</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garabedian</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dentin structure in familial hypophosphatemic rickets: benefits of
vitamin D and phosphate treatment</article-title>
          <source>Oral Dis</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>482</fpage>
          <lpage>489</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17714351</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chaussain-Miller</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sinding</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolikow</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lasfargues</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Godeau</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garabedian</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dental abnormalities in patients with familial hypophosphatemic
vitamin D-resistant rickets: prevention by early treatment with 1-hydroxyvitamin
D</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>142</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>324</fpage>
          <lpage>331</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12640383</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goodman</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gelbier</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Winter</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dental problems associated with hypophosphataemic vitamin D resistant
rickets</article-title>
          <source>Int J Paediatr Dent</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9558542</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hillmann</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geurtsen</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pathohistology of undecalcified primary teeth in vitamin D-resistant
rickets: review and report of two cases</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>218</fpage>
          <lpage>224</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8863313</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Murayama</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iwatsubo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akiyama</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amano</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morisaki</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Familial hypophosphatemic vitamin D-resistant rickets: dental findings
and histologic study of teeth</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>310</fpage>
          <lpage>316</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10982952</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ozkan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ucok</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alag&#xF6;l</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dental manifestations of familial hypophosphatemic vitamin-D-resistant
rickets: report of case</article-title>
          <source>ASDC J Dent Child</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>448</fpage>
          <lpage>450</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6094631</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rabbani</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rahmani</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ziaee</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghodoosi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dental problems in hypophosphatemic rickets, a cross sectional
study</article-title>
          <source>Iran J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>531</fpage>
          <lpage>534</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23430969</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seow</surname>
              <given-names>WK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and management of unusual dental abscesses in
children</article-title>
          <source>Aust Dent J</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>156</fpage>
          <lpage>168</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14640368</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seow</surname>
              <given-names>WK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Latham</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The spectrum of dental manifestations in vitamin D-resistant rickets:
implications for management</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dent</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          <lpage>250</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3024137</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shroff</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McWhorter</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seale</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of aggressive pulp therapy in a population of vitamin
D-resistant rickets patients: a follow-up of 4 cases</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dent</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>347</fpage>
          <lpage>349</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12212880</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yasufuku</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohno</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsutsumi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ooshima</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sobue</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murakami</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dental management of familial hypophosphatemic vitamin D-resistant
rickets: report of case</article-title>
          <source>ASDC J Dent Child</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>300</fpage>
          <lpage>304</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6311883</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zambrano</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nikitakis</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez-Quevedo</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sauk</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sedano</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rivera</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Oral and dental manifestations of vitamin D-dependent rickets type I:
report of a pediatric case</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>705</fpage>
          <lpage>709</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12789152</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
