<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Emerging Infect. Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23968631</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3810915</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13-0081</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1909.130081</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letters to the Editor</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type">
          <subject>Letter</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><italic>Alaria alata</italic> Infection in European Mink</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Alaria alata</italic> Infection in Mink</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>T&#x103;b&#x103;ran</surname>
            <given-names>Flaviu</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>S&#xE1;ndor</surname>
            <given-names>Attila David</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marinov</surname>
            <given-names>Mihai</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>C&#x103;toi</surname>
            <given-names>Cornel</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mihalca</surname>
            <given-names>Andrei Daniel</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">University of Agricultural Sciences and Veterinary Medicine Cluj-Napoca, Cluj-Napoca, Romania (F. T&#x103;b&#x103;ran, A.D. S&#xE1;ndor, C. C&#x103;toi, A.D. Mihalca); </aff>
        <aff id="aff2">Danube Delta National Institute for Research and Development, Tulcea, Romania (M. Marinov)</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: Attila D. S&#xE1;ndor, Department of Parasitology and Parasitic Diseases, University of Agricultural Sciences and Veterinary Medicine, Cluj-Napoca, Calea M&#x103;n&#x103;&#x15F;tur 3-5, RO-400372, Cluj, Romania; email: <email xlink:href="adsandor@gmail.com">adsandor@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <fpage>1547</fpage>
      <lpage>1549</lpage>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords: </title>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Alaria alata</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>mesocercariae</kwd>
        <kwd>European mink</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Mustela lutreola</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>larva migrans</kwd>
        <kwd>parasites</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><bold>To the Editor</bold>. Alariosis is a reemerging zoonotic disease caused by infection with larval stages of trematodes of the genus <italic>Alaria</italic>. The trematodes are found in wildlife that inhabit wetlands, and these animals may serve as possible reservoirs for these organisms that cause human infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). The main sources for human infection are suids and frogs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). In humans, the clinical features of alariosis caused by infections with the North American species of <italic>Alaria</italic> vary from mild and asymptomatic to moderate with respiratory or cutaneous signs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2"><italic>2</italic></xref>) or neuroretinitis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3"><italic>3</italic></xref>), to severe-to-lethal anaphylactic shock caused by larva migrans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5"><italic>5</italic></xref>). The genus <italic>Alaria</italic> has 7 species; only <italic>A. alata</italic> is found naturally in Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>), a species which has not thus far been shown to be responsible for human infections.</p>
    <p><italic>A. alata</italic> infection is common in its typical definitive host (red fox, <italic>Vulpes vulpes</italic>) and in certain paratenic hosts (wild boar, <italic>Sus scrofa</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1"><italic>1</italic></xref>). However, the role of other paratenic hosts is poorly known. Among these, mustelids are reported to harbor mesocercariae of <italic>A. alata</italic> trematodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7"><italic>7</italic></xref>). The pathogenic effect of <italic>A. alata</italic> infection has been poorly studied, because most lesions described were in humans infected with other species of <italic>Alaria</italic>. Except for 2 experimental studies that described gross lesions produced by <italic>A. alata</italic> trematodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8"><italic>8</italic></xref>), to our knowledge, no data have been published concerning lesions produced by natural infection in nonhuman hosts. Our report provides a detailed description of the lesions, shown by microscopy, which suggests the pathogenic mechanisms.</p>
    <p>One adult female European mink (<italic>Mustela lutreola</italic>) was found dead during standard surveillance operations in which box traps were used; this trapping was part of biodiversity and ecology studies in the central part of the Danube delta in Romania (45&#xB0;08&#x2032;N, 29&#xB0;19&#x2032;E) in March 2010. The corpse was deep-frozen and analyzed after 3 months in the laboratory. During necropsy, multiple, well-defined, whitish nodules were observed in most muscular and subcutaneous tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>, panel A), with no evident preferential localization. We collected samples from these tissues for artificial digestion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9"><italic>9</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10"><italic>10</italic></xref>) and histologic examination, using the routine paraffin-embedding protocol and the following staining methods: hematoxylin-eosin, Masson trichrome, and Gordon and Sweet.</p>
    <p>Artificial digestion released parasites (6 larvae/5 gm tissue) with typical larval trematode structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>, panel B). By microscopy, we observed that morphologic features of these larvae were consistent with <italic>A. alata</italic> mesocercariae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6"><italic>6</italic></xref>). Histopathologic examination confirmed the presence of parasitic forms in muscle sections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>, panel C). The mesocercariae were located in the connective fibrous tissue of the perimysium or between the muscle fibers. The typical structure of muscle fibers was altered around the larvae, with inflammatory cell reactions, represented mainly by lymphocytes, macrophages, and plasma cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>, panel D). In other areas, the inflammatory reaction around the parasite was minimal or absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>, panel E). In certain histologic sections, the damaged muscular tissue was replaced by granulation tissue in various stages of development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>, panel F). The maturity of the granulation tissue differed substantially, depending on the muscular areas examined. Some lesions were found in adult connective tissue, formed by mature collagen scar fibers (type I collagen) and few inflammatory cells, whereas other lesions had reticulin fibers (type III collagen) with numerous inflammatory cells. The lesions of the subcutaneous connective tissue consisted of an inflammatory reaction (panniculitis). The inflammation was characterized by a low number of mononuclear leukocytes and fibrinous exudate and fibroplasia.</p>
    <p>The polyphasic nature of muscle and subcutaneous lesions produced by <italic>A. alata</italic> infection in its paratenic host appears to be caused by mesocercarial migration. This view is sustained by the presence of mononuclear cells that it infiltrates and by the appearance of the granulomatous tissue in various stages of maturation, which leads to muscle and subcutaneous fibroplasia. The reparatory nature of the lesions suggests that the inflammation is probably the result of direct tissue damage rather than an immune reaction targeted toward the parasitic antigens. This assumption could explain the local absence of inflammatory reaction around the parasites. The lack of inflammation was previously observed also with <italic>A. americana</italic> infection of humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4"><italic>4</italic></xref>). The structure of all mesocercariae observed by microscopy suggested that they were alive and active before the mink carcass was frozen. Because no mesocercariae were surrounded by adult connective tissue or by granulomatous inflammation, together with the multiple presences of migratory routes, the continuous mobility of the parasites through the host&#x2019;s tissues was strongly suggested.</p>
    <p>Although data on the pathologic changes caused by <italic>Alaria</italic> spp. in general, and <italic>A. alata</italic> parasites in particular, are scarce, the migration pattern and the lesions seem to be dependent on the particular parasite and host species. The reparatory nature of the lesions suggests that the inflammation is the result of direct tissue damage rather than an immune reaction targeted toward the parasitic antigens.</p>
    <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
      <label>Figure</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Lesions produced by mesocercariae of Alaria alata in European mink. A) Mesocercariae in the muscle and subcutaneous tissue produce whitish, round or slightly oval, well-defined nodules. B) Free mesocercarium after artificial digestion, showing the characteristics of A. alata mesocercarium: piriform body with anterior oral sucker (OS), acetabulum (AC) positioned in the center of the parasite, 2 pairs of large, finely granulated penetration glands (white stars), limiting the anterior part of the acetabulum, linear ducts of penetration glands (DPG) converging to the oral opening of the oral sucker and large double ceca placed posterior to the acetabulum. C) Histologic section showing an encysted mesocercarium in the muscle (parasite is surrounded by a capsule and pericystic inflammation, which extends to the surrounding muscular tissue). D) Mononuclear leucocytes (arrowheads) scattered between the fibroblastic proliferations (white arrows) and collagen deposits (black stars). Muscle fibers are atrophic due to compression (black arrows). E) Microscopic detail of the inset from panel C. Some mesocercariae (indicated by black arrow) are enclosed in a thin, pale staining capsule (white arrows). Note the lack of leukocyte response. F) Migration route of the parasite (route with center marked by the black star), followed by invasion of nonnecrotic muscle fibers by mononucleate inflammatory cells (white arrow) located mainly in the center of the migration tract and fibrous connective tissue with collagen fibers densely packed at the periphery (bright green, marked by black arrows) and more loosely in the center (pale green material, marked by arrowheads). Hematoxylin&#x2013;eosin stain (panels C, D, E); Masson trichrome (panel F); original magnifications x40 (panels B and C), x200 (panels D and F), and x400 (panel E). </p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="13-0081-F"/>
    </fig>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="citation">
        <p><italic>Suggested citation for this article</italic>: T&#x103;b&#x103;ran F, S&#xE1;ndor AD, Marinov M, C&#x103;toi C, Mihalca AD. <italic>Alaria alata</italic> infection in European mink [letter]. Emerg Infect Dis [Internet]. 2013 Sep [<italic>date cited</italic>]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid1909.130081">http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid1909.130081</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <p>The research was conducted with the support of Unitatea Executiv&#x103; pentru Finan&#x21B;area &#xCE;nv&#x103;&#x21B;&#x103;m&#xE2;ntului Superior, a Cercet&#x103;rii, Dezvolt&#x103;rii &#x219;i Inov&#x103;rii grant PCE236/2011.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>M&#xF6;hl</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grosse</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamedy</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>W&#xFC;ste</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kabelitz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>L&#xFC;cker</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Biology of <italic>Alaria</italic> spp. and human exposition risk to <italic>Alaria</italic> mesocercariae-a review.</article-title>
<source>Parasitol Res</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-009-1444-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19430816</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kramer</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eberhard</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blankenberg</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Respiratory symptoms and subcutaneous granuloma caused by mesocercariae: a case report.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>447</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8916805</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McDonald</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kazacos</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schatz</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Two cases of intraocular infection with <italic>Alaria</italic> mesocercaria (Trematoda).</article-title>
<source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>447</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>55</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8154525</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fernandes</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cullen</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ritchie</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Systemic infection with <italic>Alaria americana</italic> (Trematoda).</article-title>
<source>Can Med Assoc J</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>1111</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1878919/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1878919/</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1000445</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stuart</surname>
<given-names>PF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cullen</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ritchie</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mildon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fernandes</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Fatal human infection with mesocercariae of the trematode <italic>Alaria americana.</italic></article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>803</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1008125</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Skrjabin</surname>
<given-names>KI</given-names></string-name>, editor. Trematodes of animals and man; essentials of trematodology, vol. XVIII. Jerusalem (Israel): Program for Scientific Translations; <year>1965</year> p. 327&#x2013;43.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Anisimova</surname>
<given-names>EI</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Study on the European mink <italic>Mustela lutreola</italic> helminthocenoses in connection with the American mink <italic>M. vison</italic> expansion in the Belarus: story of the study and review of the results.</article-title>
<source>Helminthologia</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.saske.sk/pau/helminthologia/2004_4/Anisimova193.pdf">http://www.saske.sk/pau/helminthologia/2004_4/Anisimova193.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Odening</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The &#x201C;Duncker&#x2019;s muscle fluke&#x201D; can be transmitted experimentally to monkeys</article-title>
<comment>[in German]</comment>
<source>Monatsh Veterinarmed</source>. <year>1961</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gamble</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bessonov</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cuperlovic</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gajadhar</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Knapen</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noeckler</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>International Commission on Trichinellosis: recommendations on methods for the control of <italic>Trichinella</italic> in domestic and wild animals intended for human consumption.</article-title>
<source>Vet Parasitol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>40</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4017(00)00354-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11099850</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Portier</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jouet</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fert&#xE9;</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gibout</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heckmann</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boireau</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>
<article-title>New data in France on the trematode <italic>Alaria alata</italic> (Goeze, 1792) obtained during <italic>Trichinella</italic> inspections.</article-title>
<source>Parasite</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/parasite/2011183271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21894269</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
