<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21914163</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3180410</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-7819-9-103</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7819-9-103</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Hepatoid adenocarcinoma of the gallbladder</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Ellouze </surname>
            <given-names>Sameh</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>samehktari@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Slim</surname>
            <given-names>Charfi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>charfislim@gmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Ahmad</surname>
            <given-names>Guirat</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>ahmedguirat@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>Naourez</surname>
            <given-names>Gouiaa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>naourezgouiaa@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Ali</surname>
            <given-names>Amouri</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>samehktari@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>H&#xE9;la</surname>
            <given-names>Mnif</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>samehktari@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7">
          <name>
            <surname>Mariem</surname>
            <given-names>Kossentini</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>meriemksentini@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8">
          <name>
            <surname>Mohamed</surname>
            <given-names>Ben Amar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>samehktari@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9">
          <name>
            <surname>Tahia</surname>
            <given-names>Boudawara</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>tahya.sellami@rns.tn</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of pathology, Habib Bourguiba Hospital, road El Ain., 3029, Sfax, Tunisia</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of surgery, Habib Bourguiba hospital, road El Ain., 3029, Sfax, Tunisia</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of gastroenterology, Hedi Chaker hospital, road El Ain., 3029 Sfax, Tunisia</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <fpage>103</fpage>
      <lpage>103</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9;2011 Sameh et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Sameh et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.wjso.com/content/9/1/103"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hepatoid adenocarcinoma is a rare variant of extrahepatic adenocarcinoma which behaves like hepatocellular carcinoma in morphology and functionality.</p>
        <p>We present a rare case of hepatoid adenocarcinoma of the gallbladder which invades deeply the liver bed, in a 59-year-old woman. Histologically, most of the mass in the gallbladder was composed of cells with eosinophilic cytoplasm arranged in a trabecular pattern, which resembled hepatocellular carcinoma. The main differential diagnosis was hepatocellular carcinoma with invasion into the gallbladder. The gallbladder origin of the hepatoid adenocarcinoma was verified by the presence of foci of conventional adenocarcinoma, the recognition of high-grade dysplasia in the adjacent epithelium and the absence of cirrhosis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Hepatoid</kwd>
        <kwd>adenocarcinoma</kwd>
        <kwd>gallbladder</kwd>
        <kwd>histopathology</kwd>
        <kwd>liver</kwd>
        <kwd>hepathocellular carcinoma</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Hepatoid adenocarcinoma (HAC) is a variety of adenocarcinoma associated with hepatic differentiation. The most frequent site of this carcinoma is the stomach. Only a few cases of HAC of the gallbladder have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>We present a rare case of HAC of the gallbladder which, to the best of our knowledge, represents the eighth reported case in the English literature.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 59-year-old woman presented with abdominal pain and complains about general fatigue.</p>
      <p>Ultrasonography and computed tomography revealed a solid mass within the gallbladder, which infiltrates the adjacent liver without signs of cirrhosis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1a, b</xref>). Laboratory data was within normal limits. The levels of serum AFP were not assessed preoperatively. Serological tests for hepatitis B virus surface antigen and hepatitis C virus antibody were negative.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Abdominal computed tomography revealed a solid mass within the gallbladder</bold>. <bold>1a and 1b: </bold>Abdominal computed tomography revealed a solid mass within the gallbladder, and absence of liver nodules.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-9-103-1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Cholecystectomy with resection of the involved liver subsegments, and regional lymph node dissection were performed.</p>
      <p>Gross examination revealed a white and yellow solid tumor, measuring 11 &#xD7; 5 cm, occupying the body of the gallbladder and invading the liver bed.</p>
      <p>Microscopically, the tumor was composed mainly of "hepatoid cells", which were characterized by eosinophilic cytoplasm, enlarged nuclei, prominent nucleoi, and arranged in nests or proliferated in a trabecular and solid pattern. A few sporadic foci of adenocarcinoma were mixed with the hepatoid component. Bile plugs were recognized intracellularly and foci of high-grade dysplasia were observed in the gallbladder epithelium adjacent to the tumor (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The tumor invaded deeply the liver bed. None of the lymph nodes dissected at surgery showed metastasis by the tumor cells.</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Tumor cells are arranged in a trabecular and solid pattern</bold>. <bold>2a</bold>: Tumor cells are arranged in a trabecular and solid pattern and containing bile plugs (HE&#xD7;100), <bold>2b</bold>: Tumor cells have abundant eosinophilic cytoplasm, enlarged nuclei and prominent nucleoli (HE&#xD7;400). <bold>2c</bold>: Foci of well-differentiated gallbladder adenocarcinoma (HE&#xD7;400.), <bold>2d</bold>: Foci of high-grade dysplasia were observed in the gallbladder epithelium adjacent to the tumor (HE&#xD7;200)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-9-103-2"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Immunohistochemically, the carcinoma with hepatoid features was diffusely stained for &#x3B1; fetoprotein (AFP), HepPar-1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3a</xref>) and Hepatocyte-cell antibodies, but not for Keratin7, whereas the well-differentiated adenocarcinoma was immunoreactive for Keratin7 but not for AFP or Hepatocyte-cell. CD10 positivity indicated canalicular differentiation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Intracytoplasmic expression of HepPar-1</bold>. <bold>3a: </bold>Intracytoplasmic expression of HepPar-1. <bold>3b</bold>: Canalicular staining pattern for CD10.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-9-103-3"/>
      </fig>
      <p>On the basis of histologic and immunohistochemical findings, the diagnosis of HAC of the gallbladder was reported. Three months postoperatively, the patient is still alive without any further therapeutic intervention.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Hepatoid adenocarcinoma (HAC) is a rare variety of extrahepatic adenocarcinoma, consisting of foci of both adenomatous and hepatocellular differentiations which behave like hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) in morphology and functionality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>HAC was proposed as a specific type of primary gastric cancer by Ishikura et al. in 1985 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Since then, carcinomas with hepatoid differentiation have been described in a variety of anatomic locations including the lung, kidney, female reproductive tract, pancreas, and gallbladder, the stomach being the most prevalent site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Typically, an elevated level of serum alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) is detected, although normal levels have also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] and clear cell carcinomas of the gallbladder with or without hepatoid differentiation are often associated with high serum levels of AFP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. At imaging the tumor may mimic HCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>As mentioned above, HAC was named because of its characteristic histopathological features, suggesting hepatoid differentiation resembling HCC. Generally, the tumor is composed mainly of large or polygonal cells with abundant eosinophilic cytoplasm, and it proliferates in a solid or trabecular pattern, although it sometimes shows medullary proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Furthermore, some parts which show papillary or tubular structures are often observed in the lamina propriae and/or submucosal areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The recognition of bile production proves the hepatoid nature of cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Immunohistochemically, many liver specific proteins, including AFP, albumin, transferin, PIVKA (protein induced in the absence of vitamin K), and alpha-1-antitrypsin, have been detected in the tumor cell cytoplasm. Of them, AFP is generally considered important for the diagnosis. However, it is very important to note that AFP positivity is not necessarily diagnostic of HAC, because not all HAC are associated with AFP overproduction. Therefore, the diagnosis of HAC should be made essentially by the histological features of the tumor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>In addition, focal positivity with Keratin7 suggested the presence of an adenocarcinoma. CD10 positivity indicated canalicular differentiation and thus hepatocellular origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>The main differential diagnosis is HCC with invasion into the gallbladder. When HAC of the gallbladder invades the liver deeply (as in our case), differential diagnosis of these two tumours can be very difficult [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. To aid differentiation, the clinical presentation of patients is important because HCC arising in non-fibrotic liver and without risk factors, such as hepatitis virus infection, is generally rare, as is lymph node metastasis at surgery. If the intramucosal foci of adenocarcinoma are detected histologically in a surgical specimen, the gallbladder origin is confirmed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In our case, the gallbladder origin of the HAC was verified by the presence of foci of conventional adenocarcinoma but also by the recognition of high-grade dysplasia in the adjacent epithelium and the absence of cirrhosis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>We present a rare case of hepatoid adenocarcinoma of the gallbladder which invades deeply the liver bed, in a 59-year-old woman. The main differential diagnosis was hepatocellular carcinoma with invasion into the gallbladder. The gallbladder origin of the hepatoid adenocarcinoma was verified by the presence of foci of conventional adenocarcinoma, the recognition of high-grade dysplasia in the adjacent epithelium and the absence of cirrhosis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>A written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contributions</title>
      <p>SE, SC and AG formulated the manuscript, TB and NG preparated the histological figures, AA and MBA provided the clinical history and clinical figures, HM and MK participated in the design of the study. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Sakamoto</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Monobe</surname>
            <given-names>Y</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kouno</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moriya1</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sasano</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Hepatoid adenocarcinoma of the gallbladder: Case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Pathology International</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>52</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1827.2004.01578.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14674996</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Gakiopoulou</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Givalos</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liapis</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Agrogiannis</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Patsouris</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Delladetsima</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Hepatoid Adenocarcinoma of the Gallbladder</article-title>
          <source>Dig Dis Sci</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>3358</fpage>
          <lpage>3362</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-007-9807-3</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510803</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Vardaman</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Albores-Saavedra</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Clear cell carcinomas of the gallbladder and extrahepatic bile ducts</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000478-199501000-00011</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7802141</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Nakashima</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nagafuchi</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Satoh</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title>Hepatoid adenocarcinoma of the gallbladder</article-title>
          <source>J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Surg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>226</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s005340050181</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10982619</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Van Den Bos</surname>
            <given-names>IC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hussain</surname>
            <given-names>SM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dwarkasing</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <etal/>
          <article-title>Hepatoid adenocarcinoma of the gallbladder: a mimicker of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>The British Journal of Radiology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>e317</fpage>
          <lpage>e320</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1259/bjr/97773297</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18065642</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Sakamoto</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kimura</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tokumura</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ogasawara</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Moriya</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Sasano</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Hepatoid adenocarcinoma of the gallbladder</article-title>
          <source>Histopathology</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>643</fpage>
          <lpage>652</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2559.2005.02152.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16324205</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
