<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jsls</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JSLS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>JSLS : Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1086-8089</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1938-3797</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15791975</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3015542</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Reports</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A New Technique for Laparoscopic Anterior Resection for Rectal Endometriosis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Ford</surname>
            <given-names>Jolyon</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>BSc</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>English</surname>
            <given-names>James</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Miles</surname>
            <given-names>W. F. Anthony</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Giannopoulos</surname>
            <given-names>Theo</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff>Worthing &amp; Southlands Hospitals Trust, Lyndhurst Road, Worthing, West Sussex, BN11 2DH, United Kingdom.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Address reprint requests to: Jolyon Ford, BSc, <addr-line>Clinical Fellow, Worthing &amp; Southlands Hospitals Trust, Lyndhurst Road, Worthing, West Sussex, BN11 2DH, UK</addr-line>. Telephone: <phone>00 44 1903 285190</phone>, Fax: <fax>00 44 1903 285045</fax>, E-mail: <email>jolyon.ford@virgin.net</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jan-Mar</season>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>73</fpage>
      <lpage>77</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2005 by JSLS, Journal of the Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Laparoendoscopic Surgeons</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="jsls-9-1-73.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>Anterior rectal resection is sometimes necessary to treat deeply infiltrating rectovaginal endometriosis. We describe a completely laparoscopic approach as a new way of excising rectal endometriosis that can be used without opening any part of the rectum. This avoids opening the abdomen or any risk of fecal spillage.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods:</title>
          <p>The patient received preoperative oral bowel preparation. Ureteric stents (6 F) were inserted cystoscopically. The peritoneum in the ovarian fossae was opened lateral to any disease and the rectum reflected off the back of the cervix, leaving any endometriosis on the front of the rectum. The pelvic peritoneum was reflected medially, below the level of the ureters. The mesorectum was then dissected off a 6-cm length of rectum by using a Harmonic scalpel. A circular end-to-end anastomosis instrument was passed anally until the outline of the anvil was visible, inside the colon, above the diseased rectum. The anvil was detached and held by a soft grasper before the rectum was then divided above and below the disease using a laparoscopic stapling device. The tip of the anvil was pushed through the proximal end of the colon allowing reanastomosis of the rectal stump.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion:</title>
          <p>The patient was discharged after 5 days without complications.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Laparoscopy</kwd>
        <kwd>Colon resection</kwd>
        <kwd>Endometriosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Endometriosis affecting the rectum accounts for a small but significant group of women with severe pelvic pain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Perhaps because of the inadequacy of conservative or medical measures,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> many authors advocate the complete surgical removal of rectovaginal disease, even if surgery involving the rectum is required.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></sup> Surgical techniques for this are still being developed. We report herein a modification of existing techniques to enable a small anterior resection to be done without having to open either the abdomen or the rectal lumen.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>METHODS</title>
      <sec>
        <title>The Patient</title>
        <p>The patient was a 28-year-old woman with a 10-year history of pelvic pain. She had severe pain on defecation. She had 2 previous laparoscopies demonstrating endometriosis. The most recent had suggested tethering of the rectum to the back of the cervix. When filling out a visual analogue pain survey, she gave pain scores for dysmenorrhea (40/100), dyspareunia (20/100), pain on defecation (85/100), and daily pain (65/100). She had considerable impairment in her quality of life, and using the EQ-5D quality of life assessment, she gave herself a self-rated evaluation of 31 out of 100 (population mean=88.82) for the quality of her health and had a calculated health state of 0.09 out of a maximum of 1.0 (population mean=0.93).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref></sup> On examination, a tender nodular area was noted at the top of the posterior fornix of the vagina. She was extensively counseled prior to the procedure and received liquid oral bowel preparation the day before the surgery.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>The Procedure</title>
        <p>The patient received a general anesthetic, during which an epidural was sited for postoperative pain relief. She was placed in a low Lloyd-Davies position. Ureteric catheters (6 French gauge) were inserted cystoscopically to facilitate identification of the ureters. After insufflating carbon dioxide to a pressure of 18 mm Hg via an intraumbilical disposable Verress needle, the following ports were sited: A 10-mm umbilical port, through which a 10-mm laparoscope was passed, 5-mm ports in the right and left iliac fossae, lateral to the inferior epigastric vessels, and a 12-mm port with 5-mm reducer was inserted suprapubically, to the right of the midline but medial to the inferior epigastric vessels. A survey of the pelvis was performed. We found the rectum tethered to the back of the cervix and the left pelvic side wall with incomplete obliteration of the pouch of Douglas <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>)</bold>. A deep peritoneal nodule of endometriosis was found overlying the bladder. The ovaries were normal. For most of the procedure, dissection was performed using Maryland grasping forceps and Metzenbaum scissors with a single-patient use replaceable tip. Hemostasis, suction, and irrigation were achieved using a Surgiflex WAVE (ACMI, USA) and 20 watts of bipolar power.</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Cul de sac with rectum adherent to the back of the cervix.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jsls-9-1-73-g01"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The technique of opening of the peritoneum lateral to any disease and reflecting the tethered rectum off the back of the cervix has already been described and illustrated by Redwine<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> and is therefore not illustrated herein. Using this technique, the peritoneum was opened laterally on the pelvic sidewall below the level of the ureters. These incisions were joined in the midline across the back of the cervix. The tethered rectum was then reflected down, allowing dissection into the rectovaginal space and leaving any disease on the surface of the rectum. The peritoneal incisions are extended medially and again are joined at the midline by incising over the serosal surface of the rectum, proximal to the diseased area. This technique allows the en-bloc excision of any diseased peritoneum either lateral to or overlying the rectum. At this point, we had isolated a 3-cm patch of nodular endometriosis that infiltrated the muscular layer of the rectum. It was apparent that this area was too large to be excised without creating a large defect in the rectum, and a decision was made to proceed to a segmental anterior resection.</p>
        <p>The mesorectum was dissected using the Ultracision Harmonic scalpel (Ethicon, USA), exposing a 6-cm length of rectum that incorporated the diseased area <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>)</bold>. A circular end-to-end anastomosis instrument (28-mm Premier Plus CEEA, Tyco Healthcare, USA) was inserted through the anus and advanced up the rectum to a point proximal to the disease. By unscrewing the handle, the anvil of the CEEA device was made visible through the rectal wall, and the shaft was grasped by using a soft bowel grasper <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>)</bold>. The handle of the device was then removed, leaving the anvil held in place within the lumen of the rectum, proximal to the disease. An EndoGIA Universal stapling device (Tyco Healthcare, USA) was used to transect the rectum above and below the diseased area <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>)</bold>. The excised tissue was removed through the 12-mm port site with the assistance of a retrieval bag. The point of the shaft of the anvil was then pushed through the transverse staple line on the proximal end of the colon <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>)</bold>. No purse string suture was required. The CEEA device was reinserted through the anus, and the anvil reattached <bold>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>)</bold>. The device was fired, closing the anastomosis. The anastomosis was carefully examined and hemostasis secured. The deep nodule on the surface of the bladder peritoneum was excised. The ureteric catheters were removed. A 30 F rectal catheter was inserted, as well as a urinary catheter. To reduce adhesion formation, 1000 mL of Icodextrin solution (Adept, Shire Pharmaceuticals, UK) was left in the abdomen. The gas was released and the port sites closed. The estimated blood loss was 300 mL.</p>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>After identifying rectal endometriosis, the affected loop of rectum is dissected.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jsls-9-1-73-g02"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The CEEA device is inserted up the rectum; the anvil is removed and held proximal to the diseased segment before the rectal segment is excised.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jsls-9-1-73-g03"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The rectal segment is excised using the Endo-GIA stapler.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jsls-9-1-73-g04"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The point of the shaft of the anvil is pushed through the proximal end of the colon.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jsls-9-1-73-g05"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F6" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The anvil is reattached to the CEEA device before being fired and removed.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jsls-9-1-73-g06"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The patient had an uneventful postoperative course. The urinary catheter was removed after 48 hours when the urine ran clear. The rectal tube was removed after liquid stool was passed on the fourth postoperative day, and the patient was discharged on the fifth day.</p>
        <p>Histological examination of the rectum demonstrated endometriosis within the muscularis propria of the rectal wall.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Excising rectovaginal endometriosis is a technically challenging process. Almost all the methods involve separating the adherent rectum from the back of the vagina and cervix and dissecting down into the rectovaginal septum. As this is done, the disease can be left on the side of the rectum to be stripped off after the dissection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> or can be left on the vaginal side of the septum and excised vaginally.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></sup> Shaving the disease off the front of the rectum invariably thins the serosal surface, and procedures to plicate the uterosacral ligaments and lateral rectal peritoneum across the midline have been described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Where deeper involvement of the rectal muscularis or mucosa occurs, it is necessary to excise a full-thickness part of the rectum. This can be done by excising a disc of rectal wall<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></sup> or performing an anterior segmental rectal resection. Concerns about the safety of performing such aggressive surgery for benign disease have been raised. Temporary colostomy formation has been performed when the anastomosis is extremely close to the anal margin and to manage a postoperative obstruction,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></sup> but is otherwise rarely required. Clinically detectable anastomotic leaks occur after 7.3% of resections for carcinoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref></sup> but to our knowledge have not been reported after resections for endometriosis. Other risks include fistula formation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></sup> intestinal obstruction, and pelvic abscess formation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> but also appear to be very uncommon.</p>
      <p>Advances in laparoscopic techniques and equipment have allowed segmental rectal resections to be performed whilst remaining loyal to the principles of laparoscopic surgery and minimizing the need for the traditional midline laparotomy. Total laparoscopic anterior resection has been described in animal models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref></sup> and has been used extensively for benign and malignant colorectal conditions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref></sup></p>
      <p>At some points during the several described techniques, the port sites need to be enlarged or a mini-laparotomy needs to be performed to remove the specimen or insert the anvil of the circular end-to-end anastomosis device.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref></sup> Other techniques describe the use of a 33-mm port or a hand port to facilitate the reanastomosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref></sup> Most descriptions involve opening a small part of the proximal stump of sigmoid or rectum to insert the anvil into the proximal stump. At this point, the risk of fecal spillage is present, even with adequate bowel preparation, and a purse string suture is required to secure the hole in the proximal stump around the shaft of the anvil.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>Our procedure requires a maximum port size of 12 mm, does not require a mini-laparotomy or a large port for the insertion of the anvil, and prevents any risk of fecal spillage during the operation. We hope this technique will speed postoperative recovery and improve the safety of a laparoscopic anterior resection for patients with rectal endometriosis. We believe that this sort of surgery should be performed in units where sufficient colorectal surgical backup is available and where facilities are in place to ensure that meticulous follow up and audit of these procedures occurs.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartendorp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Aggressive surgical management for advanced colorectal endometriosis</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>747</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8055717</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Redwine</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic en bloc resection for the treatment of the obliterated cul de sac in endometriosis</article-title>. <source>J Reprod Med</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>695</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1432985</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedele</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanconato</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tozzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Gonadotrophin-releasing hormone agonist treatment for endometriosis of the rectovaginal septum</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>183</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1462</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120511</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parazzini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedele</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Busacca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Postsurgical medical treatment of advanced endometriosis: results of a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>171</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1205</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7977520</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busacca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Somigliana</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marinis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Calia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Post-operative GnRH analogue treatment after conservative surgery for symptomatic endometriosis stage III-IV: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Hum Reprod</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2399</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11679528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reedijk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lie</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bowel resection for intestinal endometriosis</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>41</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1158</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9749501</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kind</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Macran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>UK population norms for EQ-5D</source>. <publisher-loc>York, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centre for Health Economics at the University of York</publisher-name>; <year>1999</year>
<comment>Discussion Paper 172</comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donnez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nisolle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillerot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smets</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>CsanasRou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rectovaginal septum adenomyotic nodules: a series of 500 cases</article-title>. <source>BJOG</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1014</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1018</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubuisson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Viera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauconnier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopically assisted vaginal management of deep endometriosis infiltrating the rectovaginal septum</article-title>. <source>Acta Obstetricia et Gynaecologica Scandinavica</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>354</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Possover</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Diebolder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Plaul</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopically assisted vaginal resection of rectovaginal endometriosis</article-title>. <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>304</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10960302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Use of the CEEA stapler to avoid ultra-low segmental resection of a full-thickness rectal endometriotic nodule</article-title>. <source>J Am Assoc Gynecol Laparosc</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>312</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11342745</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Merkel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohenberger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anastomotic leakage after low rectal stapler anastomosis: significance of intraoperative anastomotic testing</article-title>. <source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12657233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verspyck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefranc</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Blondon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Treatment of bowel endometriosis: a report of six cases of colorectal endometriosis and a survey of the literature</article-title>. <source>Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9031964</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleshman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunt</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic anterior resection of the rectum using a triple stapled intracorporeal anastomosis in the pig</article-title>. <source>Surg Laparosc Endosc</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8269231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathanson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic anterior resection: a consecutive series of 84 patients</article-title>. <source>Surg Laparosc Endosc</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8743366</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regadas</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic colorectal procedures: a multicenter Brazilian experience</article-title>. <source>Surg Laparosc Endosc Percutan Tech</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>395</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10872621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitz</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopically assisted anterior resection for diverticular disease: follow-up of 100 consecutive patients</article-title>. <source>Ann Surg</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>227</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>335</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9527055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kockerling</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prospective multicenter study of the quality of oncologic resections in patients undergoing laparoscopic colorectal surgery for cancer. The Laparoscopic Colorectal Surgery Study Group</article-title>. <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>963</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9715150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milsom</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Decanini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazio</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic oncologic proctosigmoidectomy with low colorectal anastomosis in a cadaver model</article-title>. <source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1117</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7992190</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Balcos</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bubrick</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A comparative study of open. laparoscopic intracorporeal. and laparoscopic assisted low anterior resection and anastomosis in pigs</article-title>. <source>Am Surg</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>197</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7887528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shindo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotanagi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopically assisted resection of the lower rectum</article-title>. <source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>338</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8779073</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergamaschi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnaud</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Intracorporeal colorectal anastomosis following laparoscopic left colon resection</article-title>. <source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>800</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9266637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergamaschi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haugstvedt</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Marvik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Facilitating intracorporeal colorectal anastomoses</article-title>. <source>JSLS</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9876710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Idani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Narusue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Laparoscopic low anterior resection using a triple stapling technique</article-title>. <source>Surg Laparosc Endosc Percutan Tech</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>399</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10872622</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pietrabissa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moretto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Carobbi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boggi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghilli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hand-assisted laparoscopic low anterior resection: initial experience with a new procedure</article-title>. <source>Surg Endosc</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>431</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11928022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
