<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Medical Sciences</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1449-1907</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Ivyspring International Publisher</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22253560</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3258555</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7150/ijms.3989</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijmsv09p0137</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Oral and Maxillofacial Considerations in Gardner's Syndrome</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cankaya</surname>
            <given-names>Abdulkadir Burak</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="FNA_envelop">&#x2709;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Erdem</surname>
            <given-names>Mehmet Ali</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Isler</surname>
            <given-names>Sabri Cemil</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cifter</surname>
            <given-names>Muhsin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Olgac</surname>
            <given-names>Vakur</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kasapoglu</surname>
            <given-names>Cetin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oral</surname>
            <given-names>Cuneyt Korhan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">1. Istanbul University, Faculty of Dentistry, Department of Oral Surgery, Istanbul, TURKEY.</aff>
      <aff id="A2">2. Istanbul University, Faculty of Dentistry, Department of Orthodonthics, Istanbul, TURKEY.</aff>
      <aff id="A3">3. Istanbul University, Medicine Faculty, Department of Oral Pathology, Istanbul, TURKEY.</aff>
      <aff id="A4">4. Istanbul University, Faculty of Dentistry, Department of Oral Surgery, Istanbul, TURKEY.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="FNA_envelop">&#x2709; Corresponding author: Dr.A.Burak CANKAYA, Istanbul University, Faculty of Dentistry, Department of Oral Surgery, 34093, Istanbul, Turkey. Telephone: +905327654857; Fax: +902125312230; E-mail address: <email>cankaya@istanbul.edu.tr</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>Conflict of Interest: The authors have declared that no conflict of interest exists.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>7</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>137</fpage>
      <lpage>141</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Ivyspring International Publisher. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/). Reproduction is permitted for personal, noncommercial use, provided that the article is in whole, unmodified, and properly cited.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gardner's Syndrome is a variant of familial adenomatosis polyposis (FAP) with a triad consisting of polyps of the colon, multiple osteomas and surface tumors of soft and hard tissue. The intestinal polyps have a %100 risk of undergoing malignant transformation, therefore early identification of this disease is very important. There are several symptoms of Gardner's syndrome in the oral and maxillofacial surgery, which can be discovered during routine dental examination. We report a case of a 25-year old male patient with Gardner's syndrome who has not any intestinal polyps but osteomas in the mandible and jaw deformalities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Gardner's syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>jaw</kwd>
        <kwd>dental deformalities</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Gardner's syndrome (GS) is an autosomal dominant disorder localized to a small region on the long arm of chromosome 5 (5q21-22).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref> Menzel first described adenomatosis of the colon in 1721, and in 1863, Cripps discovered the heredity of colon polyposis and termed it familial adenomatosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref> Devic and Bussy in 1912 described a triad of intestinal polyps, soft tissue tumors, and multiple osteomas of the skull.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> In 1943 Fitzgerald described a case of intraosseous osteomas, abdominal desmoids, and multiple colon polyposis and defined the oral and facial aspects of the disease.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref> In the early 1950s, the syndrome was defined by Gardner. In 1962, he also discovered the dental abnormalities and skeletal alterations of these patients.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></p>
      <p>Oral and facial anomalies are commonly observed in patients affected with this disease complex, and intestinal polyps predominantly cause malignancy. Dentists should be aware that oral and facial anomalies may play an important role in the early diagnosis of GS. This article presents a case of GS and briefly reviews the oral and maxillofacial considerations of this disease.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Case</title>
        <p>A 21-year-old patient was referred to the Department of Oral Surgery at Istanbul University, Istanbul, Turkey, for the management of craniofacial manifestations of GS. Intra-oral, extra-oral, and radiological examinations were performed. The patient came to our attention due to a primarily esthetic complaint about the right angle of the mandible. An initial clinical examination showed a nodular formation that was palpable along the mesial portion of the right mandibular angle (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The oral mucosa was normal, and the regional lymph nodules were not palpable. A panoramic radiograph and an <italic>anteroposterior radiography</italic> showed the presence of multiple round radiopaque lesions in both the maxilla and mandible, multiple impacted teeth (upper right first, second premolar, upper right third molar, upper left canine, upper left first and second premolar, upper third molar, lower left canine, first and second premolar, and lower right canine, first and second premolar), and multiple odontomas, each measuring approximately 0.5 to 2 cm in diameter (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). On palpation, these lesions were hard, well limited, and non-adherent to the skin. Diffuse sclerosis could also be noted throughout the mandibular body. Neither crepitating nor clicking on mouth opening was noticed in the temporomandibular region bilaterally. Maximum mouth opening was not restricted (42 mm). No deviation of the mandible was observed, and no pain on mouth opening was evident. No trigeminal paresthesia was diagnosed, and the facial nerve function was preserved.</p>
        <p>Dental volumetric tomographic (DVT) images showed multiple osteomas of the buccal cortex of the right mandibular angle and left mandibular angle (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Additionally, in the coronal and sagittal sections of the mandible condyle, a huge osteoma that limited mouth opening was diagnosed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Cephalometrically, he showed a slightly retrusive maxilla with an ANB angle of 1&#x2DA;and a relatively normal mandibula in anterioposterior direction. His mandibular plane angle (S-N / Go-Me: 25&#x2DA;) and articular angle (S-Ar-Go: 133&#x2DA;) were reduced (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). His profile was straight due to the slightly retruded maxilla position. According to the Steiner's S line his lips were in normal position (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). The osteomas were submitted for pathologic examination. Histopathologic examination revealed that the specimens displayed a normal-appearing dense compact lamellar bone with minimal marrow spaces and rare irregular Haversian canals that did not show osteoclasts or osteoblasts (H&amp;E X100)(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Due to the dental anomalies, the osteomas in the mandible and the familial history of the patient, the patient was diagnosed as GS. Following resection of the osteomas that caused discomfort, prosthetic rehabilitation was performed.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Gardner's syndrome is inherited as an autosomal dominant disorder with an incidence ranging between 1 in 4,000 and 1 in 12,000, depending on the region.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref> GS is known to be caused by a gene mutation located at chromosome 5.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref> The patient in this study displayed a familial history of the disease; the mother and sister had both died due to GS.</p>
      <p>The intestinal polyps of the disease typically occur prior to puberty and become generalized in the 20-40-year age group. The polyps display the potential for malignant change.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> These multiple polyps can be observed at any location in the gastrointestinal tract, particularly in the distal colon, and must be completely removed due to the high rate of transformation to adenocarsinoma.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> Gastric fundic polyps occur in 90% of affected individuals, but they are not malign lesions. Duodenal polyps also occur in 90% of affected individuals. Large polyps can cause intestinal bleeding, intussusception, or intestinal blockage. They are premalignant lesions for periampullary carcinoma.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> An increased number of peptic ulcers have also been observed.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></p>
      <p>Soft-tissue lesions such as fibromas, neurofibromas, keloids, sebaceous cysts, leiomyomas, and lipomas are also observed.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref> Desmoid tumors are considered locally invasive, non-malignant, and non-encapsulated and may occur in the skin of the anterior abdominal wall or intra-abdominally. They display no malignant potential and have a slow growth pattern.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> These lesions occur in approximately 10% of patients and are three times more common in women.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref> The majority of cutaneous lesions observed in GS present as multiple epidermoid cysts on the face, scalp, and extremities. They are benign lesions that occur at an early age, around puberty.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> Other neoplasias such as papillary carcinoma, adrenal adenoma, adenocarcinoma, hepatocellular carcinoma, osteosarcoma, chondrosarcoma, osteochondroma, tiroid tumors, liver tumors, and less commonly, hypertrophy of the pigment layer of the retina have also been reported.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref></p>
      <p>Dental abnormalities are present in 30-75% and osteomas in 68-82% of GS patients. The osteotomas are generally located in the paranasal sinuses and mandible, display slow growth, and vary from a slight thickening to a large mass.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref> Osteomas predominantly affect the mandible and maxilla<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref> but can additionally affect the skull and long bones. Calvarium osteomas, maxillary osteomas, and hypercementosis also occur.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref> Osteomas are an essential component of GS, forming a slight thickening to a large mass that may affect all parts of the skeleton. The frontal bones are the most frequent osteoma site.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> Exosteoses osteomas, also called peripheral osteomas, and enosteoses osteomas can be palpable, and enostoses may be detected by routine radiography.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> In the mandible, two types of osteomas occur: central or lobulated. Centrally located osteomas are characteristically near the roots of the teeth, and lobulated types arise from the cortex and most commonly observed at the mandibular angle.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref> We saw a huge lobulated osteoma at the right condyle and many central osteomas throught both maxilla and mandible.</p>
      <p>Seventy percent of GS patients display dental anomalies such as impacted or unerupted teeth, congenitally missing teeth, supernumerary teeth, hypercementosis, dentigerous cysts, fused molar roots, long and tapered molar roots, hypodontia, compound odontomes, and multiple caries.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> Difficulties in extraction due to ankylosis have also been reported.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></p>
      <p>Our patient presented several dental abnormalities including multiple impacted teeth in the mandible and maxilla and osteomas throughout the mandible, maxilla, and both condyle and coronoid processes.</p>
      <p>Osteomas are predominantly detected by routine panoramic radiography.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref> Pain is rarely observed, and the disease is predominantly asymptomatic, but the lesions can cause facial asymmetry as a result of expansion.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref> In addition to clinical palpation, dental panoramic radiography is an effective means of detecting multiple osteomas of the jaws that are characteristic of GS. Radiologically, the lesions are radio-opaque. In our patient, radio-opacities on the angle of the mandible were observed, and several impacted teeth in all segments of the jaws were evident. Increased difficulty of tooth extraction was present due to the high density of the alveolar bone, the limited mouth opening, and the loss of the periodontal space.<sup>16 </sup>Our diagnosis was performed by CT radiographs to detect osteomas and dental anomalies.</p>
      <p>In conclusion this case demonstrated the characteristic oral and maxillofacial features of GS, but the patient displayed no signs of intestinal polyps or cutaneous lesions. We report this case due to the absence of intestinal polyps, a rare occurrence in GS patients. According to Lew, 90% of affected patients display intestinal polyps. In contrast, the oral and maxillofacial manifestations of this syndrome appear many years prior to the intestinal lesions, meaning our patient may present intestinal polyps in the future. Osteomas that limit mandibular movement or cause esthetic problems were removed, but the possibility of recurrence exists. In such situations, the maxillofacial surgeon must perform an early GS diagnosis. The patients should always be in contact with a gastroenterologist, an oncologist, and an oral surgeon</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bodmer</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Localization of the gene for familial adenomatous polyposis on chromosome 5</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1987</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>614</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3039373</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>MGP</given-names></name><article-title>Osteomas of the condyle associated with Gardner's syndrome causing limited mandibular movement</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>1999</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1004</fpage><lpage>1009</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10437730</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Toner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Gardner's syndrome&#x2014;review and report of a case</article-title><source>Oral oncology Extra</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>92</lpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Seibert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seibert</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><article-title>Gardner's syndrome. A model for correlative radiology</article-title><source>Am J Roentgenol Radium Ther Nucl Med</source><year>1973</year><volume>119</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>64</lpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Madani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Madani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Gardner's syndrome presenting with dental complaints</article-title><source>Arch Iranian Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>539</lpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wesley</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><article-title>Gardner's syndrome with bilateral osteomas of coronoid process resulting in limited opening</article-title><source>Pediatr Dent</source><year>1987</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>57</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3472187</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><article-title>Multiple composite odontomas coincidental with other tumorous conditions: Report of a case</article-title><source>J Am Dent Assoc</source><year>1943</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1408</fpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shandler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Gardner's syndrome with an unusual fibro-osseous lesion of the mandible</article-title><source>Oral Surgery Oral Medicine Oral Pathology</source><year>1980</year><volume>49</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>486</lpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Basaran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Erkan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>One of the rarest syndromes in dentistry: Gardner's syndrome</article-title><source>European Journal of Dentistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>212</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19212549</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><article-title>A case report of Gardner's syndrome with hereditary widespread osteomatous jaw lesions</article-title><source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source><year>2009</year><volume>107</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e68</fpage><lpage>72</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19157925</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jagelman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><article-title>Manifestations of familial polyposis coli</article-title><source>Cancer Genet Cytogene</source><year>1987</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>319</fpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dawlatly</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Qurain</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salih-Mahmut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Gardner's syndrome presenting with a giant osteoma</article-title><source>Ann Saudi Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>4</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17339786</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Corell</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><article-title>Gardner's syndrome</article-title><source>Arch Surg</source><year>1966</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>299</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5902856</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boffano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerbino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>The surgical management of oral and maxillofacial manifestations of Gardner's syndrome</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2549</fpage><lpage>2554</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20594634</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ramaglia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Colao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Oral and maxillofacial manifestations of Gardner's syndrome associated with growth hormone deficiency: case report and literature review</article-title><source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source><year>2007</year><volume>103</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e30</fpage><lpage>4</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17449294</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Front view of the patient's lower face.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijmsv09p0137g01"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Panoramic view of the patient presenting multiple osteomas. A particularly large lobulated osteoma is present in the right condyle and coronoid process that impacted both permanent and deciduous teeth.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijmsv09p0137g02"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Osteomas at the left mandible angulus, mental protuberance and below the mandibular notch (white arrows)</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijmsv09p0137g03"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Osteomas at the right mandible angulus and also both condyle and coronoid process deformities (black arrow)</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijmsv09p0137g04"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
      <label>Figure 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Coronal and sagittal section view of the right condyle showing large lobulated osteoma (white arrows)</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijmsv09p0137g05"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F6" position="float">
      <label>Figure 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tracing lateral cephalometric radiograph of the patient. Ricketts' analysis is illustrated. G = glabella; N = the anterior point of the intersection between the nasal and the frontal bones; Or = the lowest point of the inferior margin of the orbi; Pn = pronasale; Po = the midpoint of the upper contour of the external auditory canal; Pns = posterior nasal spine; Ans = anterior nasal spine; A = the innermost point on the contour of the premaxilla between anterior nasal spine and the incisor tooth; Pg = the most anterior point on the contour of the chin; Gn = the most anterior and inferior point on the mandibular symphysis; Me = the most inferior point on the mandibular symphsis; Go = the midpoint of the contour connecting the ramus and body of the mandible; Ba = the lowest point on the anterior margin of the foramen magnum, at the base of the clivus; Ar = the point of the intersection between the shadow of the zygomatic arch and posterior border of the mandibular ramus.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijmsv09p0137g06"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F7" position="float">
      <label>Figure 7</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Compact tissue within a loose connective tissue containing apposition and resorption lines(X100, H&amp;E).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijmsv09p0137g07"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F8" position="float">
      <label>Figure 8</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Endoscopic examination revealed an intact intestinal mucosa without any polyps.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ijmsv09p0137g08"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Measurement of the internal cranial structures</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead valign="top">
          <tr>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skeletal Measurements</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal Value</th>
            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient's Value</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNA</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNB</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANB</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A - B(OP)</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Npog-FH (Facial plane)</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S-Ar-Go</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ar-Go-Gn</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S-N/Go-Me</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S-N-Gn(Y axis)</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
