<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Appl Oral Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J. Appl. Oral. Sci.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Applied Oral Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1678-7757</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-7765</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Faculdade de Odontologia de Bauru da Universidade de S&#xE3;o
Paulo</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22230996</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3973463</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-77572011000600012</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Nasalance and nasality at experimental velopharyngeal openings in palatal
prosthesis: a case study</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>LIMA-GREGIO</surname>
            <given-names>Aveliny Mantovan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>MARINO</surname>
            <given-names>Viviane Cristina de Castro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>PEGORARO-KROOK</surname>
            <given-names>Maria In&#xEA;s</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>BARBOSA</surname>
            <given-names>Plinio Almeida</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>AFERRI</surname>
            <given-names>Homero Carneiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff05">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>DUTKA</surname>
            <given-names>Jeniffer de Cassia Rillo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff06">6</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> PhD, Researcher, Speech Prosody Studies Group, Institute of Language
Studies (IEL), Linguistics Department, UNICAMP - University of Campinas, Campinas, SP,
Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> PhD, Assistant Professor, Department of Speech-Language Pathology and
Audiology, UNESP - Univ. Estadual Paulista - Mar&#xED;lia, SP, Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> PhD, Full Professor, Department of Speech-Language Pathology and
Audiology, Bauru School of Dentistry; Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial
Anomalies (HRAC), University of S&#xE3;o Paulo, Bauru, SP, Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> PhD, Associate Professor, Linguistics Department, Institute of Language
Studies (IEL), UNICAMP - University of Campinas, Campinas, SP, Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff05"><label>5</label> DDS, Dentist, Palatal Prosthesis Department, Hospital for
Rehabilitation of Craniofacial Anomalies (HRAC), University of S&#xE3;o Paulo, Bauru, SP,
Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff06"><label>6</label> PhD, Assistant Professor, Department of Speech-Language Pathology and
Audiology, Bauru School of Dentistry; Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial
Anomalies (HRAC), University of S&#xE3;o Paulo, Bauru, SP, Brazil.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding address:</bold> Aveliny Mantovan Lima-Gregio - Rua das Opalas, 26
- Jd. S&#xE3;o Domingos - 3471-220 - Americana - SP - BRASIL - Phone: 55 19 3407-4383 -
e-mail: <email>avelinylima@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>616</fpage>
      <lpage>622</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The use of prosthetic devices for correction of velopharyngeal insufficiency (VPI) is
an alternative treatment for patients with conditions that preclude surgery and for
those individuals with a hypofunctional velopharynx (HV) with a poor prognosis for
the surgical repair of VPI. Understanding the role and measuring the outcome of
prosthetic treatment of velopharyngeal dysfunction requires the use of tools that
allow for documenting pre- and post-treatment outcomes. Experimental openings in
speech bulbs have been used for simulating VPI in studies documenting changes in
aerodynamic, acoustic and kinematics aspects of speech associated with the use of
palatal prosthetic devices. The use of nasometry to document changes in speech
associated with experimental openings in speech bulbs, however, has not been
described in the literature.</p>
        <sec>
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>This single-subject study investigated nasalance and nasality at the presence of
experimental openings drilled through the speech bulb of a patient with HV. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Material and Methods</title>
          <p>Nasometric recordings of the word "pato" were obtained under 4 velopharyngeal
conditions: no-opening (control condition), no speech bulb, speech bulb with a 20
mm<sup>2</sup> opening, and speech bulb with 30 mm<sup>2</sup> opening. Five
speech-language pathologists performed auditory-perceptual ratings while the
subject read an oral passage under all conditions. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Kruskal-Wallis test showed significant difference among conditions (p=0.0002),
with Scheff&#xE9; <italic>post hoc</italic> test indicating difference from the
no-opening condition.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The changes in nasalance observed after drilling holes of known sizes in a speech
bulb suggest that nasometry reflect changes in transfer of sound energy related to
different sizes of velopharyngeal opening.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Speech acoustics</kwd>
        <kwd>Palatal obturators</kwd>
        <kwd>Cleft palate</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Tissue insufficiency after primary repair of cleft palate (primary palatoplasty) is one
cause of velopharyngeal dysfunction (VPD), resulting in hypernasal speech<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. Palatal fistula, a well-known residual
condition that occasionally occurs after primary palatoplasty, may also result in
hypernasal speech<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. In both
conditions, the separation between the oral and nasal cavities needs to be treated
physically in order to achieve normal speech. In general, surgical procedures (such as
palatal pushback, modified sphincter pharyngoplasty, superior-based pharyngeal flap) are
generally the treatment of choice to correct VPD following primary
palatoplasty<sup><xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. Palatal fistula
that remain after primary palatoplasty have also been treated surgically. However, the
use of prosthetic treatment still remain an important alternative, particularly for
older children and adult patients who present with unsolved problems of velopharyngeal
function and/or patients with conditions that preclude surgery<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Prosthetic management of VPD generally involves the use of an acrylic appliance to cover
fistula through the palate and/or the use of a speech bulb for reducing an opening
through the velopharyngeal port. The speech bulb provides a barrier separating the oral
and nasal cavities and its success depends on functional movement of the lateral and/or
posterior pharyngeal walls which need to embrace the bulb in order for velopharyngeal
closure to be achieved<sup><xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. Dentists,
speech-language pathologists and plastic surgeons need to work as a team particularly
when the speech bulb is the treatment of choice for those individuals who learn to
produce speech without eliciting the actions of the velopharynx. The use of speech bulbs
can be an important strategy to stimulate increased pharyngeal wall function, optimizing
further surgical treatment and supplying dental needs all at the same time. Because the
speech bulb must have adequate retention and stability, must feel comfortable to the
patient, and must support and elicit residual and/or compensatory velopharyngeal muscle
function, the collaboration between the prosthodontist and the speech-language
pathologists is essential when prosthetic treatment is the alternative of choice for
management of VPD or palatal fistula.</p>
      <p>Besides the clinical use of prosthetic or combined behavioral-prosthetic management of
VDP to achieve adequate speech, prosthetic appliances have also been used in research
studies that aimed to improve our understanding of the effect of velopharyngeal openings
on speech. Our knowledge regarding this effect has been raised mostly with information
gathered from single-subject studies that experimentally manipulated the size of
velopharyngeal openings drilled into prosthetic devices<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. In most
studies in this area it is assumed that velopharyngeal openings of different sizes may
affect speech differently, with greater opening thought to have more impact on speech
than smaller opening sizes.</p>
      <p>Sapienza, et al.<sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> (1996) investigated
respiratory, laryngeal, and supralaryngeal functions associated with experimental
"fistulas". In this study, the authors described a consistent increase of nasal airflow
and decrease in intraoral pressure and vocal intensity as the sizes of the experimental
holes increased, with laryngeal and respiratory adjustments most apparent with the 30
mm<sup>2</sup> hole size as well as when no obturator was in place. Active
physiologic adjustment rather than a passive response to oronasal coupling was therefore
observed in this study.</p>
      <p>Marino, et al.<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> (2005) conducted a
study that showed physiological adjustments at presence of palatal opening. This study
investigated immediate and long-term changes in tongue movement with experimental
"fistulas" and revealed that size and location affected tongue movement direction, with
larger sizes resulting in greater changes in movement. Particularly, this study have
showed that although an immediate response (observed as soon as the experimental
"fistula" was created) can be interpreted as indicative of the subject&#xB4;s attempts to
move the tongue towards the opening (e.g. to compensate for air loss), the findings
following a sustained perturbation (observed after the subject used the obturator with
the "fistula" for five days) suggested that with time, other physiological adjustments
may help reestablish the requirements to balance air pressure and resonance. Lima-Gregio
and colleagues<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> (2010) investigated
frequency spectral aspects of vowels [a] and [&#x250;&#x303;] at different velopharyngeal openings
(10 mm<sup>2</sup>, 20 mm<sup>2</sup> and 30 mm<sup>2</sup>). Their findings revealed
that at the presence of the larger openings (20 mm<sup>2</sup> and 30 mm<sup>2</sup>)
the F2 values obtained for the oral vowel [a] were similar to the values obtained for
the nasal vowel [&#x250;&#x303;], which the authors interpreted as indicative of tongue adjustments
(posteriorization). </p>
      <p>The above studies described the use of several objective measurements including
aerodynamic, acoustic and kinematics to document changes associated to perturbations
size introduced during speech while manipulating experimental openings in palatal
obturators. Changes in nasalance measures associated to experimental openings, however,
have not been described.</p>
      <p>The relationship between nasality and nasalance has been the subject of several studies,
with data suggesting that many factors can affect these variables. Some
authors<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> reported the
possibility of variability due to sources such as equipment, test procedures, between-
and within-subjects as well as subject performance. Therefore, while investigating
nasalance scores obtained in the presence of prosthesis, one should be aware of possible
effects of this device in nasalance results. That is, because nasalance is calculated on
the basis of an acoustic ratio of nasal to total oral+nasal acoustic energy, these
scores are subject to changes in the impedance in the vocal tract which may affect
transmission of acoustic energy<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Scarsellone, et al.<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> (1999) reported
an increase in nasalance score associated to the use of maxillary dentures for 20 women.
The authors suggested that the placement of the denture altered oral cavity dimensions,
affecting acoustical impedance of the oral cavity leading to higher nasalance scores.
While statistically significant, clinically the changes in scores were minimal and the
authors argued that nasalance changes could be explained by within-subjects variability.
Based on their findings, the authors suggested the need for careful use of nasometry for
investigated speech resonance, when dealing with patients wearing any obturator (speech
bulb or palatal lifts).</p>
      <p>Some authors<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> investigated the
relationship between nasalance and palatal lift prosthesis (PLP), which is a prosthesis
indicated to elevate the entire velum to a position in the nasopharynx close to speech
function, without developing a speech bulb. Findings from this study, however, did not
agree with those reported previously<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. These authors reported that the introduction of the PLP resulted in a
consistent and significant decrease in the nasalance scores for all 43 subjects studied.
The authors commented that even though the score decreased with the PLP, still a
significant difference was found when mean nasalance with PLP was compared with
normative data. Also the instrumental findings (indicative of hypernasality) were not
consistent with perceptual measures of normal speech nasality (observed by listeners).
All participants in Tachimura, Kotani and Wada<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> (2004) study had repaired cleft palate with residual structural
abnormalities (scar tissue) and also had reduced velopharyngeal space with the lift in
place, suggesting the possibility of altered transpalatal and transvelum transfer of
acoustical energy into nasal cavity. The authors explained that, different than a
denture (that only may alter oral impedance), a lift may change oral and also pharyngeal
resonance, narrowing the velopharynx, decreasing the size of oral cavity and altering
transpalatal and transvelum acoustic transmission.</p>
      <p>Further information regarding changes in nasalance associated to the use of palatal
prosthesis is still warranted. It is unknown at this moment whether nasometric data can
be used for predicting changes in size of velopharyngeal openings. This single-subject
study, therefore, investigated nasalance and nasality at the presence of experimental
openings drilled through a speech bulb. Since the participant of this study presented
normal resonance while wearing her speech bulb prosthesis, we assumed that the
introduction of experimental holes of known sizes in the bulb would result in hypernasal
resonance and increased nasalance scores. The comparison between the nasometric measures
prior to the experimental openings to the measures obtained with the bulb with different
sizes of openings allowed us testing the hypothesis that different openings would result
in different measures of nasalance.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Participant</title>
        <p>The Ethics Committee of the Hospital for Research and Rehabilitation of Craniofacial
Anomalies approved this study, which was conducted following the principles outlined
in the Declaration of Helsinki (Ethics Committee Approval Number: 038/2004). A
17-year-old female with a cleft of the hard and soft palate served as the single
subject in this investigation. The patient remained with velopharyngeal insufficiency
(VPI) after primary correction of the cleft palate and was fitted with a speech bulb
to optimize velopharyngeal functioning during a speech bulb reduction program, since
the prognosis for successful surgical repair was poor due to limited movement at the
velopharynx.</p>
        <p>At the time of this experiment, the participant had been successfully wearing a
removable speech bulb for over 6 months and her speech (voice, articulation and
resonance) was judged to be normal by herself as well as by 5 speech-language
pathologists (SLPs), family and peers. The patient presented no laryngeal,
respiratory, otologic, audiologic or speech conditions during the study and was free
of allergies, colds and did not use nasal decongestants while the study was
conducted.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Replica of the speech bulb</title>
        <p>To create controlled openings through the speech bulb, a replica of the subject's
original prosthesis with a speech bulb was obtained as described previously<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. The subject was instructed to wear the replica during one week
before initiating data collection to adapt to any uncontrollable variances between
the replica and original prosthesis. The subject herself expressed that her speech
was not different while wearing the replica prosthesis. Additionally, nasendoscopic
evaluation was conducted by an experienced SLP while the subject produced short
phrases with pressure consonants, showing that the replica bulb was well fitted and
adapted, fostering velopharyngeal closure during adequate speech production.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Control and experimental conditions</title>
        <p>Speech samples were obtained under one control and three experimental conditions. The
control condition included data recorded while the subject was wearing the replica
with no-opening (NO) drilled through it, resulting in normal velopharyngeal function
during speech. The three experimental conditions included: (1) no prosthesis (NP),
(2) replica with a 20 mm<sup>2</sup> hole (20 mm<sup>2</sup>), and (3) replica with a
30 mm<sup>2</sup> hole (30 mm<sup>2</sup>). The holes were drilled through the
experimental speech bulbs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>) using a
standard shop drill press with a bit area size approximating 20 mm<sup>2</sup> and 30
mm<sup>2</sup>. This hole sizes were selected based on earlier research indicating
that a hole as small as 20 mm<sup>2 </sup>resulted in a substantial changes to
speech<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. In the present study, speech recordings for all
conditions (control and experimental) were obtained at the same session, in random
order.</p>
        <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Prostheses with 20 mm<sup>2</sup> (left) and 30 mm<sup>2</sup> (right) holes
drilled through the speech bulb</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jaos-19-06-0616-g01"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Nasometric assessment</title>
        <p>The Brazilian Portuguese word "pato" (meaning: duck) repeated within the carrier
phrase "Digo _____ bojudo" ("Say stuffed ____") was used as stimuli for nasometric
assessment in this study. Although nasometry is usually conducted with longer
passages, data on shorter segments has been already reported for Portuguese
speakers<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. Additionally, the
use of words and short phrases with controlled phonetic homogeneity for nasometric
assessment is frequently used at Hospital for Rehabilitation of Craniofacial
Anomalies (HRAC)<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> and also proposed
with the Snap Test<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>.</p>
        <p>A SLP, experienced with nasometry, obtained nasalance scores for the participant
using Kay Elemetrics' Nasometer (Model 6220-2, 1994)<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Calibration, data recording and calculation of
nasalance scores were done according to the procedures described in the Nasometer's
Manual, with an adaptation of the positioning of the of the Nasometric sound
separator plate. The participant practiced the production of the phrase after
instruction from the examiner and repeated the stimuli six times for each of the 4,
leading to 24 samples. Another examiner assured stable positioning of the Nasometer's
separator plate between the upper lip and nostril of the speaker. The 6 repetitions
recorded were used for calculating a mean nasalance for the word "pato". The SLP who
conducted the nasometric assessment was blinded to the different appliance
conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Perceptual ratings of speech nasality</title>
        <p>For ratings of speech nasality a standardized oral passage in Brazilian
Portuguese<sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> was used,
facilitating SLPs speech ratings of the presence or absence of hypernasality. The
text was presented in writing and the participant read it once under each of the
conditions studied. Five SLPs with at least two years of experience in rating speech
nasality across an array of patients with resonance disorders related to VPD assessed
speech nasality. The SLPs independently performed a live auditory-perceptual
evaluation of nasality while the subject read the oral passage 4 times (one for each
condition) at the same day the nasalance measures and nasoendoscopic assessment of
velopharynx were taken. Listeners were not aware of the bulb condition during
ratings. They were asked to indicate presence or absence of hypernasality in a
scoring sheet without regard to the presence of other identifiable differences such
as inappropriate nasal air emission, weak pressure consonants, or changes in pitch,
loudness, duration and prosody.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Data analysis</title>
        <p>Mean nasalance, standard deviation, minimum, and maximum were obtained for the word
"pato" under controls and experimental conditions. Kruskal-Wallis statistical test
was used to evaluate the effect of conditions on nasometric measures. Statistical
significance was set at p&lt;0.05. Scheff&#xE9; <italic>post hoc</italic> test was used
for <italic>post hoc</italic> testing. Percentage agreement between majority of five
listeners during auditory-perceptual ratings of nasality were calculated for each
condition tested.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <p>A summary of the findings of the present study for all conditions (NO, 20
mm<sup>2</sup>, 30 mm<sup>3</sup>, NP) has been presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref> including nasalance mean and standard deviation (SD),
nasalance minimum and maximum values, auditory-perceptual rating of nasality (normal or
hypernasal) and listener's agreement during perceptual ratings.</p>
      <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of findings of present study with conditions, mean nasalance scores and
Standard Deviation (SD), minimum and maximum values of nasalance, perceptual
rating of nasality and listener's agreement during perceptual ratings</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr style="background-color:#dcddde">
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Condition</bold>
</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean&#xB1;SD</bold>
</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Min-Max</bold>
</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Speech</bold>
</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>% agreement</bold>
</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44&#xB1;9</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36-58</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="background-color:#dcddde">
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 mm<sup>2</sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#xB1;2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52-58</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypernasal</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 mm<sup>2</sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56&#xB1;2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54-60</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypernasal</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="background-color:#dcddde">
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53&#xB1;5</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48-60</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypernasal</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Particularly for this study, the mean nasalance obtained with the speech bulb with no
openings (NO) was lower than the mean obtained with openings in the bulb (20
mm<sup>2</sup>, 30 mm<sup>2</sup>) and without prosthesis (NP). While the mean
nasalance with 20 mm<sup>2</sup> opening was lower than the mean with the 30
mm<sup>2</sup> opening, mean nasalance without prosthesis (NP) did not follow this
pattern of greater nasalance with greater opening.</p>
      <p>Normal speech nasality was identified by all 5 SLPs when the participant read the
standardized passage wearing the bulb with no opening (NO). Hypernasal speech was
identified by all SLPs for the 30 mm<sup>2</sup> and NP conditions and by the majority
of the SLPs (60%) for the 20 mm<sup>2</sup>. Nasometric findings agreed with listeners
ratings when hypernasality was present. For the NO condition however, the instrument
indicated hypernasality while listeners perceived normal speech nasality.</p>
      <p>Kruskal-Wallis statistical test was used to evaluate the effect of conditions on
nasometric measures revealing significant difference between conditions (p=0.0002).
Scheff&#xE9; <italic>post hoc</italic> test indicated that the difference at the 5%
significance level was between the no opening condition and all 3 experimental
conditions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>This study investigated nasalance and nasality at the presence of different experimental
openings of controlled sizes drilled through a speech bulb. The findings of this study
were compared to nasalance norms for Portuguese language<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> and to previous studies in Japanese and English languages
that investigated nasalance scores at the presence of prosthesis<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref> presents a summary
of nasalance scores for all studies involving palatal prosthesis along with nasalance
norms in the languages studied.</p>
      <table-wrap id="t02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of findings of present and previous studies for the conditions with and
without prosthesis, including number of samples, speech stimuli, nasalance scores
(mean, Standard Deviation)</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr style="background-color:#dcddde">
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Language and conditions studied</bold>
</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>N</bold>
</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Stimuli</bold>
</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean&#xB1;SD</bold>
</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portuguese norms<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single Word</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25%&#xB1;10%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="background-color:#dcddde">
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With prosthesis NO<sup>present study</sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single Word</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44%&#xB1;9%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without prosthesis NP<sup>present study</sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single Word</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53%&#xB1;5%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="background-color:#dcddde">
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese norms<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Phrases</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9%&#xB1;4%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With palatal lift<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Phrases</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17%&#xB1;8%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="background-color:#dcddde">
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without palatal lift<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Phrases</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34%&#xB1;13%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">English norms<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Phrases</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16%&#xB1;5%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr style="background-color:#dcddde">
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With dentures<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Phrases</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12%&#xB1;5%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without dentures<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>
</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral Phrases</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11%&#xB1;5%</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Even at the presence of normal resonance as indicated by listeners, the mean nasalance
obtained for this study when the participant had the prosthesis with no-openings (44%)
was much higher than normative data reported for Portuguese language<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. DiNinno, et al.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> (2001) reported mean nasalance during
word production of 25% (SD: 10%) for adult females and 21% (SD: 8%) for adult males. The
present study's mean was also higher than the proposed cut-off value of 27% used for
oral samples for Portuguese language<sup><xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. This result suggests that even at the presence of speech rated as
normal while the participant was wearing a replica of her speech bulb (with no openings)
a lack of complete velopharyngeal closure may actually still exist, leading to nasal air
emission which was not identified by the listeners but may have been pick-up by the
nasometer. Nasal air emission, therefore, may be one explanation for higher nasalance
scores found with the control condition while compared to norms.</p>
      <p>While mean nasalance found for the participant with prosthesis with no opening (NO) was
indicative of presence of hypernasality, listeners agreed 100% that nasality was normal.
This inconsistency between instrumental and perceptual findings may be partly explained
by the use of different stimuli during evaluation, since nasalance was obtained for a
single word produced within a short carrier phrase and nasality was rated during reading
of an oral passage. Tachimura, Kotani and Wada<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> (2004) also reported scores significantly above norms for a group
with the PLP, while investigating the relationship between nasalance and the use of a
palatal lift. While the introduction of the lift resulted in a significant decrease in
the nasalance scores for all subjects, the authors indicated that the scores with the
lift still were significantly greater than the norms disagreeing with their listeners'
perceptual findings of normal nasality. Instrumental and perceptual assessments in the
study of Tachimura, Kotani and Wada<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>
(2004) also used different speech stimuli, with nasality rated during conversational
speech and nasalance obtained during production of a short passage. While the authors
used a palatal lift for correction of VPI, the present study used a speech bulb
(obturator), leading to the possibility of differences in the transfer of energy and
oral/pharyngeal impedance between both studies.</p>
      <p>Considering the relationship between nasalance and changes of impedance resulting from
the introduction of the prosthesis in oral cavity and velopharynx, the findings of
increased nasalance with the speech bulb with no openings (when compared to norms)
obtained in our study agreed with those reported in the literature<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. While Scarsellone, Rochet and Wolfaardt<sup><xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> (1999) described a significant increase in nasalance
scores associated to the use of maxillary dentures, the difference between the condition
with dentures (12%) and without dentures (11%) was only 1% and the mean scores at both
condition were still under the norms published for English speakers (16%)<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Tachimura, Kotani and Wada<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> (2004) study stated that mean nasalance
scores without the lift was higher (34%) than the scores with the lift in place (17%)
for a group of patients who had their velopharyngeal inadequacy treated with palatal
lifts. These authors<sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>, however, noted
that the mean nasalance with the lift in place (17%), was a little higher than the
nasalance norms for the Japanese language<sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> (9%), speculating that an increase in speech nasalance values could
be the result of changes in transpalatal and transvelum transfer of acoustic energy.
Therefore, higher nasometric values obtained in our study could be the result, at least
in part, of changes in transpalatal and transvelum transfer of acoustic energy due to
the presence of acrylic material used in the prosthetic appliance. Future studies,
however, are still needed to investigate the effect of material and shape prosthetic
devices in nasalance scores.</p>
      <p>Many aspects of speech may change/adjust when perturbations are introduced to the speech
system during sound production<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>.
Nasometry is limited to documenting only changes in the transfer of acoustical energy.
If we interpret the immediate changes in nasalance observed after drilling holes of
known sizes as representative of linear responses to changes in size of the
velopharyngeal space, we can consider nasalance to be sensitive to changes in
velopharyngeal function related to different types of physical management (prosthetic
and surgical). But while change in mean nasalance observed while controlling the size of
the openings was linear, it showed only a 1% increase in nasalance score for the 30
mm<sup>2</sup> opening condition (56%) when compared to the 20 mm<sup>2</sup> opening
condition (55%). This change in score among these 2 conditions was smaller than the SDs
reported in this study agreeing with perceptual assessment of speech which revealed
hypernasality for both conditions. This calls for careful interpretation of these
findings. The mean nasalance obtained when no speech bulb was in place (53%) was lower
than the means found for the 2 conditions with experimental opening (55% and 56%), which
can be interpreted as suggestive of the possibility of active physiologic adjustments,
such as reported by<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. As the later
authors described respiratory, laryngeal, and supralaryngeal physiological adjustments
may take place as the conditions within the speech system changes. Future studies
monitoring presence of adjustments such as increase or decrease in respiratory support,
elevation or depression of larynx, adjustments in tongue posture or mouth opening can
further our understanding of the strategies used by the speakers when perturbations are
introduced to the speech system during sound production.</p>
      <p>While perceptually and instrumentally monitoring the outcome of physical treatment of
VPD is needed for efficacy based practice<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> the use of nasometry to
document outcome has to be done carefully. The nonlinearity of findings reported in this
study may be associated to the fact that the Nasometer captures two types of acoustic
energy - one associated with sound resonance and the other associated with noise
resulting from nasal emission<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>, and nasal air emission may not always
be audible to listeners but may be detected by the instrument. The present findings
point to the need for future studies while controlling several variables including: the
use of equal and longer speech stimuli, the use of speech bulbs made of different
material/configuration/shapes, the use of other measures of transpalatal and transvelum
transfer of acoustical energy, and the use of measures to monitor physiologic
adjustments.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>The changes in nasalance observed after drilling holes of known sizes in a speech bulb
suggest that nasometry reflect changes in transfer of sound energy related to different
sizes of velopharyngeal opening.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Bzoch</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Communicative disorders: related to cleft lip and palate</source>
          <edition>5th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Pro-Ed</publisher-name>
          <year>2004</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carvalho-Teles</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegoraro-Krook</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lauris</surname>
              <given-names>JRP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Speech evaluation with and without palatal obturator in patients
submitted to maxillectomy</article-title>
          <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>421</fpage>
          <lpage>426</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19089242</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dalston</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>The use of nasometry in the assessment and remediation of
velopharyngeal inadequacy</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Bzoch</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Communicative disorders related to cleft lip and palate</source>
          <edition>5th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Pro-Ed</publisher-name>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>495</fpage>
          <lpage>516</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Di Ninno</surname>
              <given-names>CQMS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vieira</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teles-Magalh&#xE3;es</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Padovani</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegoraro-Krook</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasalance values identification in normal Brazilian Portuguese
speakers</article-title>
          <source>Pr&#xF3;-Fono</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>71</fpage>
          <lpage>77</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Henningsson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isberg</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Influence of palatal fistulae on speech and resonance</article-title>
          <source>Folia Phoniatr (Basel)</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>191</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3666618</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karnell</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasometric discrimination of hypernasality and turbulent nasal
airflow</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>146</fpage>
          <lpage>148</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>Kay Elemetrics Corporation</collab>
          </person-group>
          <source>Instruction manual for the nasometer model 6200</source>
          <publisher-loc>Lincoln Park</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Kay Elemetrics Corporation</publisher-name>
          <year>1994</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kummer</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Velopharyngeal dysfunction (VPD) and resonance
disorders</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kummer</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Cleft palate and craniofacial anomalies: effects on speech and
resonance</source>
          <publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Singular Learning</publisher-name>
          <year>2001</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watterson</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blanton</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison of short-term and long-term variability in nasalance
scores</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>495</fpage>
          <lpage>500</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18788879</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lima-Gregio</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dutka-Souza</surname>
              <given-names>JCR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marino</surname>
              <given-names>VCC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegoraro- Krook</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barbosa</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Achados espectrais das vogais [a] e [&#x250;&#x303;] em diferentes
aberturas velofar&#xED;ngeas</article-title>
          <source>Pr&#xF3;-Fono</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>515</fpage>
          <lpage>520</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21271109</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lipira</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grames</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molter</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Govier</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kane</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Woo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Videofluoroscopic and nasendoscopic correlates of speech in
velopharyngeal dysfunction</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>550</fpage>
          <lpage>560</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20815707</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marino</surname>
              <given-names>VCC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>WN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wharton</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paulk</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dutka-Souza</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schulz</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immediate and sustained changes in tongue movement with an
experimental palatal "fistula": a case study</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>286</fpage>
          <lpage>296</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15865464</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pegoraro-Krook</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dutka-Souza</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marino</surname>
              <given-names>VC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasoendoscopy of velopharynx before and during diagnostic
therapy</article-title>
          <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>188</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19089215</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalben</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegoraro-Krook</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Speech intelligibility of patients with cleft lip and palate after
placement of speech prosthesis</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>635</fpage>
          <lpage>641</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18177184</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegoraro-Krook</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of palatal prosthesis for the treatment of velopharyngeal
dysfunction</article-title>
          <source>J Appl Oral Sci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>197</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21394393</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sapienza</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>WS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>WN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wharton</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Respiratory and laryngeal function associated with experimental
coupling of oral and nasal cavities</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>118</fpage>
          <lpage>126</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8695619</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scarsellone</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rochet</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolfaardt</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The influence of dentures on nasalance values in
speech</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10067762</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suguimoto</surname>
              <given-names>MLCP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegoraro-Krook</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasalance values of normal adults, Brazilian Portuguese
speakers</article-title>
          <source>Pr&#xF3;-Fono</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tachimura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kotani</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wada</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasalance scores in wearers of a palatal lift prosthesis in comparison
with normative data for Japanese</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>315</fpage>
          <lpage>319</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15151451</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tachimura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mori</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirata</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wada</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasalance score variation in normal adult Japanese speakers of
Mid-West Japanese dialect</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>463</fpage>
          <lpage>467</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034028</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r21">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trindade</surname>
              <given-names>IEK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Genaro</surname>
              <given-names>KF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalston</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasalance scores of normal Brazilian Portuguese
speakers</article-title>
          <source>Braz J Dysmorphol Speech Hear Disord</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>34</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r22">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Watterson</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deutsch</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasalance and nasality in low pressure and high pressure
speech</article-title>
          <source>Cleft Palate Craniofac J</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>297</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9684765</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r23">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>WN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henningsson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegoraro-Krook</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Radiographic assessment of velopharyngeal function for
speech</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Bzoch</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Communicative disorders related to cleft lip and palate</source>
          <edition>5th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Pro-Ed</publisher-name>
          <year>2004</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
