<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Intern Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J. Intern. Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJIM</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1226-3303</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2005-6648</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Association of Internal Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24648816</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3957003</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3904/kjim.2014.29.2.263</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Image of Interest</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Ciprofloxacin: an uncommon drug reaction to a commonly used drug</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Mendes-Bastos</surname>
            <given-names>Pedro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carvalho</surname>
            <given-names>Rodrigo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cunha</surname>
            <given-names>Daniela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cardoso</surname>
            <given-names>Jorge</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Dermatology and Venereology, Curry Cabral's Hospital, Central Lisbon Hospital Center, Lisbon, Portugal.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Correspondence to Pedro Mendes-Bastos, M.D. Tel: +351217924200, Fax: +351217924200, <email>pmendesbastos@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>29</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>263</fpage>
      <lpage>264</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 The Korean Association of Internal Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>An 81-year-old obese woman was admitted due to decompensated diabetes and a lower urinary tract infection. She was started on empirical antibiotic therapy with ciprofloxacin (750 mg twice daily) and insulin. Dermatological observation was required 48 hours later due to a rash that had been evolving for 24 hours. Physical examination revealed a bilateral and grossly symmetric dermatosis involving the trunk and proximal limbs, comprising a few, round, sharply demarcated erythematous plaques, some of them with a dusky, violaceous hue, central blisters, and a detached epidermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). With the exception of flexural superficial candidiasis on the axillary and inguinal folds, no other cutaneous or mucosal lesions were found. The patient recalled a previous similar rash after taking an oral antibiotic (unable to specify which antibiotic), emphasizing that some lesions recurred at the same locations. Admitting the diagnosis of a bullous fixed drug eruption (FDE) to ciprofloxacin, the drug was withdrawn and the lesions resolved with residual grayish hyperpigmentation within 2 weeks. Histopathological examination confirmed the diagnosis, revealing interface dermatitis, epidermal necrosis, scarce neutrophilic pustules, and a perivascular inflammatory infiltrate with eosinophils on the superficial dermis.</p>
    <p>FDE usually appears as solitary lesions on the genitalia and acral sites. Commonly implicated drugs include ibuprofen, naproxen, sulfonamides, and tetracyclines. The present case describes a generalized FDE, which is a less common presentation, due to ciprofloxacin, a drug rarely reported to cause FDE. The skin reaction scored 8 points on the Naranjo scale. The absence of mucosal involvement and other symptoms/signs allowed for the exclusion of erythema multiforme and Stevens-Johnson syndrome.</p>
    <p>A careful clinical history and skin examination, particularly the pattern of recurrence, are the most valuable clues to diagnose FDE. It is usually a nonserious adverse drug reaction, stopping the offending drug will result in full clinical resolution, and immunosuppressive drugs should generally be avoided. Although FDE is a T-cell-mediated drug hypersensitivity, its pathophysiology is still not fully explained (does not completely fit any of the drug reaction types proposed by World Health Organization).</p>
    <p>The typical clinical history, time course, skin findings, and histopathological aspects of the present case made rechallenge an unwise option. Patch testing in a previously involved site may be useful in confirming the responsible drug. Although planned, this was not performed because the patient was lost to follow-up.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) Full-body dermatological examination. (B) Detail of the pubic, left inguinal, and thigh regions, showing superficial flexural candidiasis (asterisks) and several round, sharply demarcated erythematous plaques with a dusky, violaceous hue, two of them with a central blister and one with a detached epidermis (arrows).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjim-29-263-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Detail of a typical lesion with central epidermal detachment on the right forearm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjim-29-263-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
