<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Gastroenterol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi J Gastroenterol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SJG</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology : Official Journal of the Saudi Gastroenterology Association</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1319-3767</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-4049</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22421724</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3326979</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SJG-18-149</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1319-3767.93826</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Image Quiz</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Massive Diffuse Intraperitoneal Multicystic Mass in An Infant</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>Sunita</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kureel</surname>
            <given-names>Shiv N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chandra</surname>
            <given-names>Naveen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Pediatric Surgery, CSMMU (Erstwhile King George's Medical University), Lucknow, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Sunita Singh, Department of Pediatric Surgery, CSMMU (Erstwhile King George's Medical University), Lucknow - 226 003, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="drsunitasingh28@gmail.com">drsunitasingh28@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Mar-Apr</season>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>18</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>149</fpage>
      <lpage>150</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Saudi Journal of Gastroenterology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>An 18-month-old boy was referred for painless progressively increasing abdominal distension, poor oral intake, and lethargy since 1 year. There was no history of fever, hematurea, or intestinal obstruction. The child was pale and had a pulse rate of 150 beats/min. The child had mild respiratory distress due to huge abdominal distension. The abdomen was tense and nontender. There was no evidence of intraperitoneal free fluid or any definitive lump. The hemogram showed anemia, other blood biochemistry test results were normal. Ultrasonography of the abdomen suggested the possibility of encysted ascites. A 64-slice contrast-enhanced computed tomography of abdomen showed diffuse intraperitoneal multicystic mass, composed of variable sizes and wall thickness cysts [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>]. The definitive organ of origin could not be identified. Bowel loops were displaced upward by the mass. Diagnostic laparoscopy showed a pale, soft, extremely friable mass composed of cysts of variable sizes arising from the dome of the bladder. The cysts were noncommunicating and had no fluid. The mass was loosely adhered to the bowel, liver, and peritoneum. The rest of the abdominal organs were normal. Complementary cystoscopy was performed to rule out intraluminal extension of tumor, which was normal.</p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A 64-slice contrast-enhanced computed tomography of abdomen (a) Coronal view demonstrating a multicystic mass with no fluid within the cysts occupying whole of the abdominal cavity and displacing bowels upward; (b) Bladder outline with both ureters are evident on posterior sections; and (c) Axial view suggesting a multicystic mass composed of cysts of variable sizes and wall thickness</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="SJG-18-149-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <sec id="sec1-1">
      <title>QUESTION</title>
      <p>Q1. What is the diagnosis?</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>ANSWER</title>
      <p>Histopathology showed myxoid stroma containing undifferentiated round to spindle cells with Cambium layer of Nicholson. Furthermore, immunohistochemistry showed the tumor cells positivity for desmin, vimentin, actin, and myoglobin. So the definitive diagnosis was botryoid rhabdomyosarcoma (RMS).</p>
      <p>Botryoid sarcoma is a variant of embryonal type RMS. It accounts for 5-10% of all RMS.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] It is the most common malignant condition of the lower genitourinary system in infancy.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>] The lesions usually abuts an epithelial surface of hollow viscera, such as that of the bladder or vagina and projects into the lumen as a multinodular excrescences of variable sizes.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>] The median age for occurrence is 4 years. The common presentation is hematurea, frequency, urgency, and other irritative voiding symptoms or it may protrude through the urethra or vagina as a hemorrhagic, friable, grape-like mass.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>] To the best of our knowledge and search of the literature this is the first case in which the urinary bladder botryoid RMS had a huge intraperitoneal component only.</p>
      <p>Clinicoradiological deferential diagnoses of diffuse multicystic intraperitoneal tumors in children are abdominal cystic lymphangioma, benign multicystic peritoneal mesothelioma, cystic adenomatoid tumor, pseudocyst, and immature cystic teratoma.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>]</p>
      <p>So the botryoid sarcoma should also be considered in the differential diagnosis of intraabdominal cystic tumors (especially of pelvic origin) even if there are no urinary symptoms in the children.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Shedoukhy</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qayyum</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Urinary bladder botryoid rhabdomyosarcoma with immature cartilage in a 24-year-old male patient: A case report</article-title>
          <source>Saudi J Kidney Dis Transpl</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>522</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17657126</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mostofi</surname>
              <given-names>FK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morse</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polypoid rhabdomyosarcoma (sarcoma botryoides) of bladder in children</article-title>
          <source>J Urol</source>
          <year>1952</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>681</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14939381</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Uz&#xFC;m</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oz&#xE7;ay</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atao&#x11F;lu</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Benign multicystic peritoneal mesothelioma</article-title>
          <source>Turk J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>138</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19530048</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
