<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pamj</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1937-8688</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21436945</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3063493</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Life Sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Medicine</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Bilateral invasive lobular breast cancer in a female teenager: a rare finding of a common disease - case report and review of literature</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>George Enownchong</surname>
            <given-names>Enow-Orock</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Obinchemti Thomas</surname>
            <given-names>Egbe</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Eric Akum</surname>
            <given-names>Achidi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Etienne Defang</surname>
            <given-names>Asonganyi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Paul</surname>
            <given-names>Ndom</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Emmanuel</surname>
            <given-names>Fongang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peter</surname>
            <given-names>Ndumbe</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Biological Sciences, University of Buea, Pathology Service, General Hospital, Yaound&#xE9;, Cameroon</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Medicine,University of Buea, South-West Region, Cameroon</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>District Hospital, Kumba, South-West region, Cameroon</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Medical Oncology service, General Hospital Yaound&#xE9;, Cameroon</aff>
      <aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Radiology service, General Hospital Yaound&#xE9;, Cameroon</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Enow-Orock George, Pathology Service, General Hospital, BP 5408, Telephone: 237-7771-6045, Yaound&#xE9;, Cameroon</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <elocation-id>2</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; Enow-Orock George et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract abstract-type="executive-summary">
        <p>Abstract Management of cancer patients in low-resource communities presents enormous challenges. Breast cancer is a public health problem in Cameroon and occurs mostly in elderly women. The predominant histological type is a duct carcinoma. Lobular carcinoma in teenagers is rare. In this report we present a case of bilateral invasive lobular carcinoma of the breast that was confirmed on biopsies in a 22-year-old female. We present this rare finding and review the pathological, clinical and radiographic challenges of the disease. Nodules in the breast from patients of any age should be submitted for histology. Public education is beneficial and should be intensified.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Key words:</title>
        <kwd>Cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>bilateral</kwd>
        <kwd>lobular</kwd>
        <kwd>carcinoma</kwd>
        <kwd>teenager</kwd>
        <kwd>rare</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="case report" id="s1">
      <title>Patient and case report</title>
      <p>IM is a 22-year-old seamstress who reported to a regional hospital following media sensitization on cancer with &#x201C;thick patches&#x201D; in both breasts noticed about a year earlier. Physical examination revealed a teenager of normal weight, with &#x201C;bumpy&#x201D; areas in both breasts. The &#x201C;bumpy&#x201D; areas were ill-defined, non-adherent and not tender &#x201C;nodularities&#x201D; in the upper-inner quadrant and the upper-outer quadrant of the right and left breasts respectively. No axillary nodes were palpated. No mammogram or echography was done. The rest of physical and investigative examinations were normal. A diagnosis of bilateral fibroadenoma was made.</p>
      <p>Pathology examination showed two specimens of 4.0cm average diameter each with greyish, poorly-delimited, firm multiple foci on sections. Microscopy on Hematoxyline and Eosine-stained slides showed lobules filled with, and dilated by multiple layers of atypical small round cells with hyperchromatic, irregular nuclei and clear cytoplasm. The stroma was invaded in &#x201C;Indian file&#x201D;. Immuno-histochemistry was not done. A diagnosis of bilateral invasive moderately-differentiated (grade II) lobular carcinoma (ILC) was made and the patient referred.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s2">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In Cameroon, breast cancer is the commonest malignancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>] that affects mainly females aged 35 to 54 years and predominantly a ductal type (70%). Invasive lobular carcinoma (ILC) in Cameroon (9.5 %) affects mainly women above 55 years and is rare in teenagers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>]. A bilateral disease in this age group as we found in our case is even rarer.</p>
      <p>It is usually difficult to diagnose ILC early due to lack of typical radiographic and clinical signs. The vague findings may be confused with benign breast changes, especially in the younger patient. Our case exemplifies the challenges of health-care in general and cancer in particular in low-resource communities. Public sensitization is important as most patients go to hospital only when in pain. It is also important that all surgical specimens, even from patients with no known risks for cancer be sent for histology. Though age is a significant risk for cancer, younger persons are increasingly becoming affected by cancers traditionally known to be peculiar to the elderly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>In their original article on lobular carcinoma, Foote and Stewart [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>] in 1941 established the term &#x201C;invasive lobular carcinoma&#x201D;. The histologic features described were an associated desmoplastic stromal reaction and linear arrangement of cells&#x2014; Indian file. Invasive lobular carcinoma (ILC) of the breast is the second most common type of primary breast cancer, accounting for 10-15% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>In a stage-matched comparison of outcomes between ILC and invasive duct carcinoma (IDC) by El Saghir et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>], the median age at presentation was 66 years for ILC and 60 years for IDC (p &lt;0.001). Christopher et al report that the proportion of breast cancers with a lobular component increased from 9.5 percent in 1987 to 15.6 percent in 1999 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>Risk factors for breast cancer have been established in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>]. Paul et al concluded that lobular carcinoma in-situ (LCIS) is associated with increased risk of subsequent invasive disease to about 7.1% at 10 years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>]. Although lobular structures are infrequent in the normal male, sporadic cases of ILC have been described in male breast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>In comparison with IDC, ILC is significantly more likely to occur in older patients, larger, bilateral, multifocal and multicentric [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Biologically ILC is more often PR+, ER+, diploid and HER-2, p53, and epidermal growth factor receptor (EPGFR) negative compared to IDC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. In some cases like ours, no risk factors are identified and physical exam may be non-specific.</p>
      <p>Ultrasound and MRI have been shown to be more sensitive than mammography for invasive cancer, but with the risk of overestimating the extent of the tumour. Combined mammography, clinical exam, and MRI are more sensitive at detecting ILC than any other individual test or combination usually a speculated mass with asymmetric density and no definable margins nor mass [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>Contrast-enhanced MRI is highly sensitive in detecting ILC and its extent, which is of value in pre-operative planning as well as the diagnosis of multifocal or contra lateral involvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. The Computer Aided Detection (CAD) system has increased the likelihood of detecting breast cancer, to about 91% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. Because of non-specific findings, infrequency of micro-calcification, and slow growth, ILC is often detected only in late stages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>] though Arpino [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>] found the five-year disease-specific survival to be significantly better for patients with ILC compared to IDC. ILC commonly metastasizes to bone, gastrointestinal tract and ovary and studies have shown that ILC is the most common extra-genital neoplasm that metastasizes to gynaecologic organs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>].</p>
      <p>To determine the value of cytology in the differential diagnosis of ductal and lobular carcinoma of the breast, de las Morenas et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>] showed that amongst various parameters, chromatin pattern (P&lt;.0001), nuclear size (P&lt;.004) and cell size (P &lt;.004) showed statistically significant differences between the two groups. Based on this study, the presence of coarsely granular chromatin, nuclear size &gt;44 microm2 and cell size &gt; 82 microm2 are the only features diagnostic of ductal versus lobular carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. ILC is more likely to be &gt;2 cm in size (43.1% vs. 32.6%, p &lt;0.001), lymph node positive (36.8% vs. 34.4%, p &lt;0.001) and ER+ (93.1% vs. 75.6%, p &lt;0.001) and may contain signet ring cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Majority are histologic grade 2 (as in this case). Fine needle aspiration cytology often does not yield much information in lobular cancer due to the sparseness of malignant cells, and wide-bore needle biopsy is more recommended.</p>
      <p>There is a bias toward treating ILC with aggressive therapy with some series indicating a 3-6 fold excess in patients receiving mastectomy compared with breast conservation therapy (BCT). In a comparative study between BCT and mastectomy for ILC, Singletary et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>] found that less invasive treatment options are becoming widely used for the disease with outcomes similar to more aggressive treatment. Due to the infiltrative growth pattern and frequent discontinuities, there is a higher incidence of resection margin involvement in ILC with more intra-surgical conversion to mastectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>].</p>
      <p>Management of cancer patients all over the world is fraught with numerous challenges. These challenges are more acute in low resource communities like ours. This case highlights the importance of public education and multidisciplinary approach in cancer care, through referrals. It also brings to light the difficulty that health professionals face in the absence of basic facilities like ultrasound, mammography and immunohistochemistry in this case.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="s3">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Cancer is a public health problem in Cameroon, and increasingly affecting younger persons. Breast cancer is the commonest cancer in Cameroon and the predominant histologic type is a ductal carcinoma. ILC is mainly a disease of elderly females, though no age is immune, even in the absence of any risk factors, as in this teenage female with bilateral disease. Management of cancer patients in low-resource communities faces many challenges; therefore public and health personnel education should be intensified. All breast nodules from patients of any age should be submitted for histology. Developing countries need to invest more resources in the health sector.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="contribution" id="s4">
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>EOGE: pathologist who analysed the biopsy specimens and reviewed the pathology literature <bold>NPaul</bold>: medical oncologist to whom patient was referred and reviewed the medical oncology literature. <bold>AED</bold>: referred the patient after biopsy to the pathologist. <bold>AEA</bold>: chemical pathologist who</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="interest" id="s5">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare no competing interests</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mbakop</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Essame-Oyono</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ngbangako</surname>
            <given-names>MC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Abondo</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Epdemiologie actuelle des cancers au Cameroun (Afrique Centrale).</article-title>
          <source>Bull Cancer.</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>1101</fpage>
          <lpage>1104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1302536</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ndom</surname>
            <given-names>p</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Essame-Oyono</surname>
            <given-names>JL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Doh</surname>
            <given-names>AS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cancer incidence in Yaounde 2004-2008: Yaound&#xE9; Cancer Registry Technical Report.</article-title>
          <source>Yaound&#xE9;: National Cancer Control Program, Cameroon.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>26</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Foote</surname>
            <given-names>FW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stewart</surname>
            <given-names>FW</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>A histologic classification of carcinoma of the breast.</article-title>
          <source>Surgery.</source>
          <year>1941</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>74</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21022022</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Jemal</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2009.</article-title>
          <source>CA Cancer J Clin.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>225</fpage>
          <lpage>249</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474385</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>El Saghir</surname>
            <given-names>NS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Khalil</surname>
            <given-names>MK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Eid</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>El Kinge</surname>
            <given-names>AR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Charafeddine</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Geara</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>et</surname>
            <given-names>al</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Trends in epidemiology and management of breast cancer in developing Arab countries: a literature and registry analysis.</article-title>
          <source>Int J Surg.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>(4)</issue>
          <fpage>225</fpage>
          <lpage>233</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660128</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Christopher</surname>
            <given-names>IL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>National Cancer Institute&#x2019;s Surveillance Epidemiology and End Results (SEER)data analysis from nine population-based US cancer registries.</article-title>
          <source>JAMA.</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>289</volume>
          <fpage>1421</fpage>
          <lpage>1424</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12636465</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Calle</surname>
            <given-names>EE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Walker-Thurmond</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Thun</surname>
            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Overweight, obesity and mortality from cancer in a prospectively studied cohort of US adults.</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med.</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <issue>(17)</issue>
          <fpage>1625</fpage>
          <lpage>16438</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12711737</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Chuba</surname>
            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hamre</surname>
            <given-names>MR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yap</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Severson</surname>
            <given-names>RK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lucas</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Shamsa</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Aref</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Bilateral risk for subsequent breast cancer after lobular carcinoma-in-situ: Analysis of Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results Data.</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol.</source>
          <year>2005 Aug 20</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>(24)</issue>
          <fpage>5534</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16110014</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Suzanne</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Russel</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kyle</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Leish</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Julie</surname>
            <given-names>RL</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Invasive lobular carcinoma of the male breast -A rare histology of an uncommon disease.</article-title>
          <source>Breast Care.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>36</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20877682</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ashikari</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huvos</surname>
            <given-names>AG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Urban</surname>
            <given-names>JA</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Infiltrating lobular carcinoma of the breast.</article-title>
          <source>Cancer.</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>110</fpage>
          <lpage>116</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4345605</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Arpino</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bardou</surname>
            <given-names>VJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Clark</surname>
            <given-names>GM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Infiltrating lobular carcinoma of the breast: tumor characteristics and clinical outcome.</article-title>
          <source>Breast Cancer Res.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>149</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Selinko</surname>
            <given-names>VL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Middleton</surname>
            <given-names>LP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Dempsey</surname>
            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Role of sonography in diagnosing and staging invasive lobular carcinoma.</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Ultrasound.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>323</fpage>
          <lpage>332</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15293298</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Berg</surname>
            <given-names>WA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gutierrez</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>NessAiver</surname>
            <given-names>MS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Carter</surname>
            <given-names>WB</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bhargavan</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lewis</surname>
            <given-names>RS</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of mammography, clinical examination, US and MR imaging in preoperative assessment of breast cancer.</article-title>
          <source>Radiology.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>233</volume>
          <fpage>830</fpage>
          <lpage>849</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15486214</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Warren Burhenne</surname>
            <given-names>LJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wood</surname>
            <given-names>SA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>D?Orsi</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Potential contribution of computer-aided detection to the sensitivity of screening mammography.</article-title>
          <source>Radiology.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>215</volume>
          <fpage>554</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10796939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Castellino</surname>
            <given-names>RA</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Roehrig</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>W</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Improved computer-aided detection (CAD) algorithms for screening mammography.</article-title>
          <source>Radiology.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>217</volume>
          <fpage>400</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Doyle</surname>
            <given-names>DJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Reliha</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Redmond</surname>
            <given-names>HP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Barry</surname>
            <given-names>JE</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Metastatic manifestations of invasive lobular breast carcinoma.</article-title>
          <source>Clinical Radiology.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>271</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15664584</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>de las Morenas</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Crespo</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Morok</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Donelly</surname>
            <given-names>MM</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Cytologic diagnosis of ductal versus lobular carcinoma of the breast.</article-title>
          <source>Cytologic diagnosis of ductal versus lobular carcinoma of the breast.</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>(5)</issue>
          <fpage>865</fpage>
          <lpage>869</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Pritt</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ashikaga</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Oppenheimer</surname>
            <given-names>RG</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Influence of breast cancer histology on the relationship between ultrasound and pathology tumor size measurements.</article-title>
          <source>Mod Pathol.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>905</fpage>
          <lpage>910</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15105809</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Singletary</surname>
            <given-names>SE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lina</surname>
            <given-names>PP</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Kirby</surname>
            <given-names>IB</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Treatment trends in early-stage invasive lobular carcinoma: a report from the National Cancer Data Base.</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>242</volume>
          <issue>(2)</issue>
          <fpage>281</fpage>
          <lpage>289</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16041220</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
