<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23793220</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3754376</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20131812</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cutaneous histoplasmosis disclosing an HIV-infection<xref ref-type="other" rid="fn03">*</xref>
</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Histoplasmose cut&#xE2;nea reveladora de infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o pelo HIV</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marques</surname>
            <given-names>Silvio Alencar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Silvares</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Regina Cavariani</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">
2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Camargo</surname>
            <given-names>Rosangela Maria Pires</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">
3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marques</surname>
            <given-names>Mariangela Esther Alencar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">
4</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Full Professor &#x2013; Department of Dermatology and Radiotherapy. Botucatu Medical School, S&#xE3;o Paulo State University (Unesp) &#x2013; Sao Paulo (SP), Brazil.
</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> Assistant Professor - Department of Dermatology and Radiotherapy. Botucatu Medical School, S&#xE3;o Paulo State University (Unesp) &#x2013; Sao Paulo (SP), Brazil.
</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> Biologist - laboratory of Mycology - Department of Dermatology and Radiotherapy. Botucatu Medical School, S&#xE3;o Paulo State University (Unesp) &#x2013; Sao Paulo (SP),
Brazil.
</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> Lecturer - Associate Professor - Department of Pathology. Botucatu Medical School, S&#xE3;o Paulo State University (Unesp) &#x2013; Sao Paulo (SP), Brazil.
</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">
MAILING ADDRESS: Silvio Alencar Marques, Distrito de Rubi&#xE3;o Junior S/N,
18618-970 - Botucatu - SP, Brazil, E-mail: <email>smarques@fmb.unesp.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>420</fpage>
      <lpage>423</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Histoplasmosis is a systemic mycosis endemic in extensive areas of the Americas. The
authors report on an urban adult male patient with uncommon oral-cutaneous lesions
proven to be histoplasmosis. Additional investigation revealed unnoticed HIV
infection with CD4+ cell count of 7/mm<sup>3</sup>. The treatment was performed with
amphotericin B, a 2065 mg total dose followed by itraconazole 200mg/daily plus
antiretroviral therapy with apparent cure. Histoplasmosis is an AIDS-defining
opportunistic disease process; therefore, its clinical diagnosis must drive full
laboratory investigation looking for unnoted HIV-infection.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>Histoplasmose &#xE9; infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o sist&#xEA;mica end&#xEA;mica em extensas &#xE1;reas do continente
Americano. Os autores relatam caso de paciente do sexo masculino, de zona urbana com
les&#xF5;es cut&#xE2;neas e mucosas incomuns de histoplasmose. Investiga&#xE7;&#xE3;o adicional posterior
revelou infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o subjacente pelo HIV com contagem de c&#xE9;lulas CD4 de 7/mm<sup>3</sup>.
O tratamento foi realizado com anfotericina B, dose total de 2065 mg, seguido por
itraconazol 200 mg/dia associado &#xE0; terap&#xEA;utica antirretroviral com cura aparente do
quadro. Histoplasmose &#xE9; enfermidade oportun&#xED;stica definidora da s&#xED;ndrome de
imunodefici&#xEA;ncia adquirida, portanto, diagn&#xF3;stico clinico de histoplasmose implica em
investiga&#xE7;&#xE3;o laboratorial de infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o subjacente pelo HIV.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Amphotericin B</kwd>
        <kwd>Histoplasmosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Histoplasmosis is a systemic mycosis caused by <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic>,
a thermo-dimorphic fungus and a soil saprophyte. It is endemic in the central southern
region of the United States of America (USA) and in Central and South America. Infection
with <italic>H. capsulatum</italic> is caused by the inhalation of conidia from nature
in endemic areas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>The majority of infected people have either no symptoms or a very mild clinical
presentation. Individuals who develop acute pulmonary histoplasmosis are usually those
exposed to heavy infection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref></sup> Some of them may present chronic cavitary pulmonary histoplasmosis,
granulomatous mediastinitis or mediastinal fibrosis later in their lives. Dissemination
of the disease is a possible event following acute infection or a later event due to the
reactivation of quiescent foci.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref></sup> It is important to consider that even with the development of cell-mediated
immunity against <italic>H. capsulatum</italic> patients may have persistent foci of
viable fungi in various organs in equilibrium with the immune response, similarly to the
situation observed in paracoccidioidomycosis, coccidioidomycosis and tuberculosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B02">2</xref></sup> The most important risk factor for dissemination of the disease has been
HIV-induced immunosuppression and, therefore, the diagnosis of cutaneous histoplasmosis
must drive attention to possible subjacent unnoticed HIV-infection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B03">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref></sup>
</p>
      <p>The authors present an atypical case of histoplasmosis associated with unnoticed
HIV-infection, which was later confirmed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>An urban 57-year-old male patient reported a cutaneous lesion on his nose. The lesion
had been initially noticed three months before. General complaints included a 3-kg
weight loss, sporadic fever and malaise. Dermatologic examination showed a crusted
ulcerated lesion surrounded by an erythematous halo on the nose and few erythematous
papular nodules on his mentum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). Oral examination revealed a sublingual atypical
ulcerated lesion suggesting a traumatic etiology. Clinical examination was unremarkable.
Microscopic examination of representative cutaneous lesions and of the oral lesion
showed chronic lymphohistiocytic inflammation with granuloma formation on the dermis.
Multiple intracellular structures were observed in the cytoplasm of histiocytes and
giant cells, which were better observed and demonstrated on especial staining, such as
Grocott-Gomori (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">4</xref>). Culture from biopsy material in Sabouraud dextrose-agar and
Mycosel&#xAE; was positive for <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histoplasmosis: shallow ulcer with irregularly shaped limits with haematic and
meliceric crusts localized on the nose</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0420-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histoplasmosis: erythematous papule and nodules with discrete central
ulceration on the chin</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0420-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histoplasmosis: histopathological examination showing lymphohistiocytic
inflammatory infiltration with fungi in the cytoplasm of histiocytes. (HE 400
X)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0420-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histoplasmosis: histopathological examination showing multiple small size
yeast-like cells. (Grocott-Gomori 1000 X)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0420-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histoplasma capsulatum: macroconidia with stalagmospores. (Cotton-blue 1000
X)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-88-0420-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Additional investigation revealed interstitial infiltration and nodules on both lungs
which were suggestive of pulmonary histoplasmosis. Serology tests were positive for HIV
infection, at that point unknown to the patient and negative for HBV and HCV. Blood
CD4<sup>+</sup> cell count was 7/mm<sup>3</sup>; CD8<sup>+</sup> cell count was
236/mm<sup>3</sup> and HIV RNA measurement performed on plasma revealed a viral load
of 241,265 copies and a log of 5.383.</p>
      <p>The patient was treated with amphotericin B deoxycholate, 2065 mg of total dose,
followed by itraconazole 200mg/daily as a maintenance treatment, with clinical
resolution of all lesions and improvement of general conditions. Anti-retroviral therapy
and nutritional support were added to treatment as well.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Histoplasmosis is one of the most common systemic mycosis in AIDS patients worldwide,
and it is particularly important as an opportunistic co-infection where it is
endemic.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref></sup> Skin lesions are refereed as uncommon in patients diagnosed in the USA,
occurring in less than 10% of cases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">
4</xref></sup> On the other hand, among cases from Latin America, skin lesions are reported to
occur in 38% to 85% of patients with histoplasmosis and AIDS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B05">5</xref></sup> These differences were thought to be a consequence basically of reporting bias
or delayed diagnosis in cases reported from Latin America, but evidence of molecular
differences in strains of <italic>H. capsulatum</italic> prevalent in the United States
and South America has recently been provided as an additional explanation for such data,
suggesting tropism of the fungus to the skin in strains from South America.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B06">6</xref></sup> Cutaneous lesions a's a primary manifestation of HIV-related diseases are not
rare, and in histoplasmosis, they are particularly evident. The cutaneous manifestations
of histoplasmosis vary from acneiform papules to plaques, ulcers and vegetating lesions,
usually in large numbers, as a consequence of the hematogenous dissemination of the
fungus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B07">7</xref></sup> However, cutaneous lesions in histoplasmosis are not diagnostic by themselves in
the immunosuppressed patient as many other infectious and non-infectious diseases share
a similar morphological pattern. Therefore, physicians must value systemic signals and
symptoms to narrow the spectrum of hypotheses. In this reported case, the mucosal lesion
did not present the granulation or hemorrhagic points usually observed in
paracoccidioidomycosis, and this favored the hypothesis of histoplasmosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B08">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B09">9</xref></sup> Disseminated histoplasmosis occurs in HIV-infected patients with a
CD4<sup>+</sup> cell count of &lt; 50/mm<sup>3</sup>, as found in most studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B01">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B04">4</xref></sup> Our patient presented with a CD4<sup>+</sup> cell count of 7/mm<sup>3</sup> and
an expressive viral load, but besides nonspecific clinical symptoms, his HIV-status was
unnoticed until the histoplasmosis diagnosis.</p>
      <p>Treatment guidelines for disseminated histoplasmosis suggest amphotericin B deoxycholate
or liposomal amphotericin B for moderate to severe disease. As a second option,
itraconazole 600mg/daily for three days followed by 400 mg/daily for 12 months.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></sup> The treatment schedule used in the present case showed to be very effective, and
the patient remains well in an outpatient follow-up basis. It is noteworthy that
maintenance therapy with itraconazole may be required for life if immunosuppression
cannot be reversed.</p>
      <p>The present case report, once again, emphasizes the role of cutaneous lesions as a
sentinel of severe systemic diseases and subjacent immunosuppression.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="other">
        <p>* Study carried out at the Department of Dermatology and Radiotherapy, Botucatu
Medical School, S&#xE3;o Paulo State University (Departamento de Dermatologia e
Radioterapia - Faculdade de Medicina de Botucatu - Universidade Estadual Paulista
"J&#xFA;lio de Mesquita Filho" - FMB-UNESP) - Botucatu (SP), Brazil</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial funding: None</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kauffman</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Histoplasmosis: a clinical and laboratory
up-date</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>132</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17223625</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nosanchuk</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gacser</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Histoplasma capsulatum at the host-pathogen
interface</article-title>
          <source>Microbes Infect</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>973</fpage>
          <lpage>977</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18672088</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>Control for Disease Control. (CDC)</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Revision of the CDC surveillance case definition for
acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. Council of State and Territorial
Epidemiologists; AIDS Program, Center for Infectious Diseases</article-title>
          <source>MMWR</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>1s</fpage>
          <lpage>15s</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wheat</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Histoplasmosis in the acquired immunodeficiency
syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Curr Top Med Mycol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9504056</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>VS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zampese</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aquino</surname>
              <given-names>VR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cestari</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldani</surname>
              <given-names>LZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mucocutaneous manifestations of disseminated
histoplasmosis in patients with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome: particular
aspects in a Latin-American population</article-title>
          <source>Clin Dermatol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>250</fpage>
          <lpage>255</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldani</surname>
              <given-names>LZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aquino</surname>
              <given-names>VR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lunardi</surname>
              <given-names>LW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>RV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Two specific strains of Histoplasma capsulatum causing
mucocutaneous manifestations of histoplasmosis: preliminary analysis of a frequent
manifestation of histoplasmosis in southern Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Mycopathologia</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>167</volume>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>186</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19112605</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Orsi</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nogueira</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chrusciak-Talhari</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferreira</surname>
              <given-names>LCL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Talhari</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Histoplasmosis and AIDS co-infection</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>1025</fpage>
          <lpage>1026</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22147050</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fungal infections of the mucous membrane</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Ther</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>244</fpage>
          <lpage>250</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lastoria</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>MEA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paracoccidioidomycosis in a patient with cervical
cancer</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>588</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21738984</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wheat</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freifeld</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kleiman</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baddley</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McKinsey</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loyd</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical practice guidelines for management of patients
with histoplasmosis: 2007 update by the Infectious Disease Society of
America</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>807</fpage>
          <lpage>725</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17806045</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
