<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Trop Med Hyg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Trop. Med. Hyg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0002-9637</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1476-1645</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23390219</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3583305</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.12-0214</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Images in Clinical Tropical Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Borderline Lepromatous Leprosy in an Italian Man</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">MASSONE AND OTHERS</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">BORDERLINE LEPROMATOUS LEPROSY</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Massone</surname>
            <given-names>Cesare</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Clapasson</surname>
            <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nunzi</surname>
            <given-names>Enrico</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AFF1">Department of Dermatology, Division of General Dermatology, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria; Unit of Social Dermatology, National Reference Center for Hansen's Disease, Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria San Martino, Genoa, Italy; Interdipartimental Centre for Hansen Disease and Tropical Dermatology, University of Genoa, Genoa, Italy</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">*Address correspondence to Cesare Massone, Department of Dermatology, Medical University of Graz, Auenbruggerplatz 8, A-8036 Graz, Austria. E-mail: <email>cesare.massone@klinikum-graz.at</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <volume>88</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>211</fpage>
      <lpage>211</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene's Re-use License which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>We report a 77-year-old man from Italy with a painful, red right eye with decreased vision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>) and multiple asymptomatic erythematous infiltrated nodules and edematous plaques on the face (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>), tongue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>), and trunk and extremities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>). Lesions appeared on his face 20 years ago and progressively enlarged and diffused on the trunk. Two of his relatives had been affected by lepromatous leprosy. A skin biopsy specimen showed a diffuse infiltrate of vacuolar macrophages engulfed with mycobacteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>) and the focal presence in the dermis of few multinucleated giant cells and a focal infiltrate of neutrophils.</p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A 77-year-old man from Italy with borderline lepromatous leprosy. Shown are a red right eye (<bold>A</bold>) and multiple asymptomatic erythematous edematous infiltrated nodules and plaques on the face (<bold>B</bold>), tongue (<bold>C</bold>), and trunk and extremities (<bold>D</bold>). <bold>E</bold>, Histopathologic analysis showing vacuolar macrophages (Virchow cells) engulfed with <italic>Mycobacterium leprae</italic> (Fite-Faraco staining, original magnification &#xD7;1,000).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="tropmed-88-211-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <p>A polymerase chain reaction identified <italic>Mycobacterium leprae</italic>. Mycobacteria were confirmed by multiple skin smears stained with Ziehl-Neelsen stain. An ophthalmologic consultation diagnosed acute right uveitis. A neurologic consultation disclosed enlargement of both ulnar nerves and sensory and motor impairment in the fourth and fifth fingers. Electroneurography confirmed involvement of both ulnar nerves, and ultrasound examination demonstrated diffuse swelling of the ulnar nerve at the elbow.</p>
    <p>According to the Ridley-Jopling classification, borderline lepromatous leprosy was diagnosed and the patient received rifampicin (600 mg/month), minocycline (100 mg/day) instead of dapsone because of anemia, and clofazimine (300 mg/month and 50 mg/day). The man was treated with prednisone (30 mg/day for 6 months with progressive tapering), thalidomide (200 mg/day for 6 weeks with progressive tapering), and topical prednisolone drops (4 times/day for 4 weeks). Treatment cured concomitant type-1 and type-2 leprosy reactions. At one-year of follow-up, the patient showed no adverse reactions to treatment, remission of skin and mucosal lesions, and improvement of leprosy reactions.</p>
    <p>During 1990&#x2013;2009, progressive reduction of 12 autochthonous leprosy cases (the most recent case in 2003) was observed in Italy with a simultaneous increase of imported leprosy cases among immigrants from leprosy-endemic areas (159 cases).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref> Fear of segregation and marginalization caused the patient to avoid medical treatment for 20 years, resulting in an advanced stage of leprosy. This presentation was unusual because patients are usually given a diagnosis at an earlier stage. Single, anesthetic, hypopigmented, asymmetrically arranged macules and a few macules characterize tuberculoid and borderline tuberculoid leprosy, respectively. Multiple, symmetrically arranged macules, nodules, and plaques characterize borderline lepromatous and early lepromatous leprosy.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="present-address">
        <p>Authors' addresses: Cesare Massone, Department of Dermatology, Division of General Dermatology, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria, E-mail: <email>cesare.massone@klinikum-graz.at</email>. Andrea Clapasson, Unit of Social Dermatology, National Reference Center for Hansen's Disease, Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria San Martino, Genoa, Italy, E-mail: <email>clpndr@yahoo.com</email>. Enrico Nunzi, Interdipartimental Centre for Hansen Disease and Tropical Dermatology, University of Genoa, Genoa, Italy, E-mail: <email>enrico.nunzi@yahoo.it</email>.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunasso</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Noto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapasson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Imported leprosy in Italy</article-title>
<source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>999</fpage>
<lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21831112</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
