<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Korean Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Korean Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JKMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Korean Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1011-8934</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1598-6357</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22787380</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3390733</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3346/jkms.2012.27.7.811</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Basic Medical Sciences</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Hypoplasia of Left Vertebral Artery with Intimal Fibromuscular Dysplasia in a Korean Woman</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hyun</surname>
            <given-names>Chang Lim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Hyun Sik</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Hyun Jo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>Sang Pil</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology, Jeju National University School of Medicine, Jeju, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Anatomy, Jeju National University School of Medicine, Jeju, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Address for Correspondence: Sang Pil Yoon, MD. Department of Anatomy, Jeju National University School of Medicine, 66 Jejudaehak-ro, Jeju 690-756, Korea. Tel: +82.64-754-3823, Fax: +82.64-725-2593, <email>spyoon@jejunu.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>27</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>811</fpage>
      <lpage>813</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2012 The Korean Academy of Medical Sciences.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We found a case of hypoplasia of vertebral artery with fibromuscular dysplasia in an 82-yr-old Korean female cadaver during a routine dissection course. In the present case, intracranial hypoplasia in left vertebral artery and bilateral origin of posterior inferior cerebellar artery at the vertebrobasilar junction were recognized. Histopathologically, left vertebral artery showed intimal type of fibromuscular dysplasia both in its extracranial and intracranial courses. These results indicate that the association of fibromuscular dysplasia and hypoplasia does exist in the vertebral artery, although the etiologies are not verified yet.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Hypoplasia</kwd>
        <kwd>Fibromuscular Dysplasia</kwd>
        <kwd>Vertebral Artery</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Hypoplasia is an elongated, tubular, homogeneous stenosis of a part of artery. Since the definition of hypoplasia is based on the macroscopic appearance of an affected vessel, it should be differentially diagnosed by histopathological characteristics. Fibromuscular dysplasia (FMD) is an uncommon, non-inflammatory, non-atherosclerotic arterial disease that can be associated with spontaneous dissection, aneurysm, or severe stenosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). FMD most commonly involves the renal artery and internal carotid artery, less commonly the vertebral artery (VA). Typically, FMD appears 'string of beads' in angiography with dissection or aneurysm and fibrous or fibromuscular thickening in the tunica media. In this report, we describe a rare case of hypoplasia in intracranial VA associated with intimal type FMD in its extracranial and intracranial courses.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE DESCRIPTION</title>
      <p>During a routine dissection at Jeju National University Medical School in 2011, a case of hypoplasia in left vertebral artery was observed in an 82-yr-old Korean woman cadaver, whose cause of death was 'unknown'. Hypoplastic VA was defined as a lumen diameter less than 2 mm in an anatomical study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>) or as with diameter less than 50% of the contralateral side in radiological study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p>
      <p>In this case, each VA originated from the subclavian artery with an external diameter of left 4.6 mm and right 5.0 mm; and entered to the foramen transversarium with a diameter of left 3.3 mm and right 5.0 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The extracranial parts of both VAs did not show macroscopic anomaly, but intracranial part of the left VA had hypoplasia with a total length of 21 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The external diameters of the intracranial parts of VAs were found to be 3.7 mm on the right side and 1.0 mm on the left side. The vertebrobasilar junction was found to be at the level of bulbopontine sulcus. The posterior inferior cerebellar artery bilaterally arose from the basilar artery 2.5 mm from the vertebrobasilar junction. The other brain vessels had no anomalies in their course or in the origin of their branches on either side.</p>
      <p>Histopathologically, FMD is heterogeneous with various degrees of collagen hyperplasia, internal elastic lamina rupture, and disorganization of the tunica media (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). For histopathological classification of FMD, tissue sections were stained with hematoxylin and eosin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A-C</xref>), Orcein for elastic fiber (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D-F</xref>), and immunohistochemistry with anti smooth muscle actin antibody for tunica media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G-I</xref>) and anti-CD31 antibody for endothelium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Compared to the right VA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A, D, G</xref>), both extracranial and intracranial left VA pathologically diagnosed as an intimal type of FMD. Left VA has long smooth narrowing of lumen with circumferential or eccentric deposition of collagen in the tunica intima and disrupted internal elastic lamina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>). The stenotic lumen was not caused by hypertrophy in medial smooth muscles. In extracranial VA, neovascularization (rectangle in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>) in the hypertrophied intimal layer was seen with immunopositivities of smooth muscles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>). But the immunoreactivity with smooth muscles was not obvious in intracranial VA as compared to the extracranial VA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2I</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>We encountered hypoplasia in left VA associated with intimal type FMD during routine dissection course. The intracranial parts of the VAs, the basilar artery and their branches together form the vertebrobasilar system (VBS). Numerous anomalies can be seen in the VBS and also observed in this study: the posterior inferior cerebellar artery originated from the basilar artery, but this variation is not uncommon (22.5%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Moreover, the rate of hypoplasia in VA shows increasing frequency due to the radiological development.</p>
      <p>In an anatomical study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>), it was reported that there is usually a difference between the external diameter of left (3.02 &#xB1; 0.81 mm) and right (2.85 &#xB1; 0.99 mm) intracranial VA. The hypoplasia of VA was observed at rates of 20.2% on the right, 14.4% on the left and 4.8% bilaterally. In radiological study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), the unilateral hypoplasia and/or aplasia of VA has been frequently reported in Koreans (about 27%, right &gt; left) without the vertebrobasilar insufficiency symptoms. Hypoplasia and aplasia of extracranial or intracranial VA is classified as follows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>); type I denotes hypoplasia showing extracranial and/or intracranial VA, type II represents hypoplasia having any invisible part, and type III denotes aplasia both extracranial and intracranial VA. According to the radiological classification, our report correspond to type Ia of hypoplasia in intracranial VA based on macroscopic results, and type Ic of hypoplasia in extracranial and intracranial VA based on microscopic findings.</p>
      <p>Due to a collagen deposition within the tunica intima, intimal type FMD often results in a concentric stenosis or long tubular lesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). It is coincided with the angiographic classification of unifocal FMD: tubular (&gt; 1 cm) or focal (&lt; 1 cm in length). These unifocal subtypes seem to be more commonly related to intimal type FMD of this report. Surprisingly, histopathologically proven involvement of the VA has not been reported to our knowledge. A few histologically confirmed cases are reported from intracranial vessels, but Kimura et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) only confirmed the medial hyperplasia type of FMD associated with aneurysm of the VA and posterior inferior cerebellar artery. Both hypoplasia and FMD in same vessel was only reported from abdominal aorta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), but there was medial hyperplasia type of FMD associated with aneurysm. This is the first report consists of hypoplasia and intimal type FMD of the VA.</p>
      <p>Luminal narrowing in hypoplasia of VA may produce ischemic stroke both by the hemodynamic effects of atherosclerotic stenosis, thromboembolism, or FMD, since FMD of the internal carotid artery is related with focal cerebral ischemia by atherosclerotic stenosis or thromobotic occlusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Ipsilateral hypoplasia of VA has a close relation to posterior inferior cerebellar artery infarction or lateral medullary infarction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>), and the diagnosis of FMD is a rare case. Furthermore, patients with posterior circulation strokes showed a higher rate of hypoplasia of VA than those with anterior circulation strokes which had similar frequency compared to that of normal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). The frequency of FMD in patients with ischemic stroke, transient ischemic attack, or subarachnoid hemorrhage is likely to be very small, since the prevalence of FMD ranged from 0.3% to 3.2% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). VA affected 7% to 19% of patients with FMD, which is less common than renal artery or internal carotid artery involvement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). However, the prevalence in the general population is not known. A report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) performed at the Mayo Clinic only suggests presumptive evidence that FMD of the internal carotid artery was detected in only 0.02% of 20244 consecutive autopsies. Therefore, intracranial FMD of the VA is indeed rare than extracranial FMD.</p>
      <p>Although the etiology is unknown, FMD can be inherited and intimal type FMD may result from arterial injuries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). It should also be remembered that deficiency of protein S is associated with progressive intracranial occlusive disease of VA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). Intracranial FMD of the VA seems to be extremely rare. But the rate of VA involvement in vertebrobasilar insufficiency was up to 26% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). Intracranial FMD corresponds to an intracranial extension of extracranial FMD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>), and it is also true in this report that hypoplasia is only seen in intracranial VA while FMD observed in both intracranial and extracranial VA.</p>
      <p>Taken together, signs and symptoms of vertebrobasilar insufficiency should be carefully evaluated since hypoplasia of VA is not uncommon even in normal adults.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Olin</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sealove</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis, management, and future developments of fibromuscular dysplasia</article-title>
          <source>J Vasc Surg</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>826</fpage>
          <lpage>836</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21236620</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Touz&#xE9;</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oppenheim</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trystram</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nokam</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasquini</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alamowitch</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herv&#xE9;</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garnier</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mousseaux</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plouin</surname>
              <given-names>PF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fibromuscular dysplasia of cervical and intracranial arteries</article-title>
          <source>Int J Stroke</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>296</fpage>
          <lpage>305</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20636713</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Songur</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonul</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozen</surname>
              <given-names>OA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kucuker</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uzun</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bas</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toktas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Variations in the intracranial vertebrobasilar system</article-title>
          <source>Surg Radiol Anat</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>264</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18253692</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Min</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transcranial Doppler ultrasonographic evaluation of vertebral artery hypoplasia and aplasia</article-title>
          <source>J Neurol Sci</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>260</volume>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17604054</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Macchi</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Porzionato</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parenti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Caro</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The course of the posterior inferior cerebellar artery may be related to its level of origin</article-title>
          <source>Surg Radiol Anat</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>60</fpage>
          <lpage>65</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14658014</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kimura</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosoda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hara</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohmura</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A very unusual case of fibromuscular dysplasia with multiple aneurysms of the vertebral artery and posterior inferior cerebellar artery</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>1108</fpage>
          <lpage>1112</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19035727</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Odero</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bozzani</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arici</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aqozzino</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hypoplasia and fibromuscular dysplasia of infrarenal abdominal aorta with downstream aneurysmmm: case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J Vasc Surg</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>1589</fpage>
          <lpage>1592</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19118740</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Venketasubramanian</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tjia</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ischaemic stroke from cerebral embolism in cephalic fibromuscular dysplasia</article-title>
          <source>Ann Acad Med Singapore</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>891</fpage>
          <lpage>894</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8839004</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kans</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoo</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huh</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>CK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ruptured right posterior inferior cerebellar artery aneurysm associated with hypoplasia of the right vertebral artery and both internal carotid arteries</article-title>
          <source>Br J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>551</fpage>
          <lpage>553</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19718546</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schievink</surname>
              <given-names>WI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bj&#xF6;rnsson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fibromuscular dysplasia of the internal carotid artery: a clinicopathological study</article-title>
          <source>Clin Neuropathol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8998851</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barinagarrementeria</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cant&#xFA; Brito</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Izaguirre</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de la Pe&#xF1;a</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Progressive intracranial occlusive disease associated with deficiency of protein S. Report of two cases</article-title>
          <source>Stroke</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1752</fpage>
          <lpage>1756</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8236353</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chiche</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bahnini</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koskas</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kieffer</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occlusive fibromuscular disease of arteries supplying the brain: results of surgical treatment</article-title>
          <source>Ann Vasc Surg</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>496</fpage>
          <lpage>504</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9302062</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Photographs of the vertebral arteries. Macroscopic hypoplasia was seen in left vertebral artery (VA), especially in the intracranial course. For histopathological classification, samples of the VA were obtained from its extracranial (VAe, <bold>A</bold>) and intracranial (VAi, <bold>B</bold>) course (arrows). Note the uncommon origin of the posterior inferior cerebellar arteries (arrowheads) from the basilar artery.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-27-811-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Fibromuscular dysplasia of the vertebral artery (VA), intimal type. Right VA (<bold>A</bold>: hematoxylin and eosin, <bold>D</bold>: Orcein, <bold>G</bold>: anti-smooth muscle actin) was stained for control. Extracranial (VAe; <bold>B</bold>, <bold>E</bold>, <bold>H</bold>) and intracranial (VAi; <bold>C</bold>, <bold>F</bold>, <bold>I</bold>) left VA had stenotic lumen, marked fibrous thickening of tunica intima (TI), and disrupted internal elastic lamina (dotted arrows in <bold>E</bold>), while hyperplasia of smooth muscles in tunica media (TM) was not observed with anti-smooth muscle actin immunostaining (<bold>I</bold>). Neovascularization (asterisks) was also seen in left VAe with anti-CD31 immunostaining (rectangle from asterisk in <bold>B</bold>). Arrows, internal elastic lamina. Original magnification &#xD7; 10 for <bold>A</bold>-<bold>C</bold>; &#xD7; 40 for <bold>D</bold>-<bold>I</bold>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="jkms-27-811-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
