<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24626664</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3938370</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20132359</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Imaging In Dermatology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Melanoma developed during pregnancy - A case report<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref>
</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mestnik</surname>
            <given-names>Natalia Cammarosano</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Afonso</surname>
            <given-names>Jo&#xE3;o Paulo Junqueira Magalh&#xE3;es</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Enokihara</surname>
            <given-names>Milvia Maria Sim&#xF5;es e Silva</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Enokihara</surname>
            <given-names>Mauro Yoshiaki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Porro</surname>
            <given-names>Adriana Maria</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff05">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hirata</surname>
            <given-names>S&#xE9;rgio Henrique</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff05">5</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Doctor Dermatologist - Specialising in Dermoscopy at the Department of
Dermatology, Paulista School of Medicine - Federal University of S&#xE3;o Paulo (EPM-UNIFESP)
- S&#xE3;o Paulo (SP), Brazil. </aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> Doctor Dermatologist - Studying post-graduation at the Department of
Dermatology, Paulista School of Medicine - Federal University of S&#xE3;o Paulo (EPM-UNIFESP)
- S&#xE3;o Paulo (SP), Brazil. </aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> MS and PhD in Pathology. - Doctor Pathologist at the Departments of
Dermatology and Pathology, Paulista School of Medicine - Federal University of S&#xE3;o Paulo
(EPM-UNIFESP) - S&#xE3;o Paulo (SP), Brazil. </aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label> MS and PhD in Dermatology. - Doctor at the Department of Dermatology,
Paulista School of Medicine - Federal University of S&#xE3;o Paulo (EPM-UNIFESP) - S&#xE3;o Paulo
(SP), Brazil. </aff>
      <aff id="aff05"><label>5</label> MS and PhD in Dermatology. - Teacher at the Department of Dermatology,
Paulista School of Medicine - Federal University of S&#xE3;o Paulo (EPM-UNIFESP) - S&#xE3;o Paulo
(SP), Brazil. </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">MAILING ADDRESS: Natalia Cammarosano Mestnik, Rua Borges Lagoa, 508,
Vila Clementino, 04038-001. S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brazil. Telephone: +55 (11) 5576-4804,
Email: <email>nataliamestnik@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jan-Feb</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>89</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>157</fpage>
      <lpage>159</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xAE;2013 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We describe a case of plantar interdigital cutaneous melanoma in a 22-year-old woman
who reported changes in a pigmented lesion during pregnancy. Diagnosis was late and
evolution unfavourable. The purpose of this report is to draw the attention of
dermatologists to the need for careful regular examination of melanocytic lesions in
pregnant women, not ignoring possible changes as always physiological.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Melanoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Neoplastic metastasis</kwd>
        <kwd>Nevi and melanomas</kwd>
        <kwd>Pigmented nevus</kwd>
        <kwd>Pregnancy</kwd>
        <kwd>Skin Neoplasm</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Cutaneous melanoma incidence has increased in the last few decades over the world,
including in Brazil.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> It is also
considered the commonest malignant tumour found during pregnancy, corresponding to 31% of
all diagnosed malignant neoplasms.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>
Recent studies have reported an approximately 3.3% incidence of melanoma during pregnancy
in women between 16 and 49 years old.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>
</p>
    <p>In the last 50 years, non-controlled studies have suggested that hormonal factors may
influence melanoma development, and consequently pregnancy may represent a higher risk of
tumour development as well as a factor for unfavourable prognosis.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Current evidence has not confirmed this.
Controlled studies have shown that, until now, oral contraceptives and hormone replacement
therapy do not increase the risk of developing melanomas, nor do endogenous hormones. For
this reason, pregnancy does not seem to influence the development or prognosis of the
disease (when corrected by tumour thickness and location factors).<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>
</p>
    <p>Another important aspect is the relationship between pregnancy and Breslow index. Breslow
thickness is the main prognosis factor in patients diagnosed with melanoma. Some studies
have suggested that women with melanoma diagnosed during pregnancy tend to present thicker
tumours. Although there is the hypothesis of the involvement of hormonal changes and growth
factors present in pregnancy, the most probable explanation would be a delay in its
diagnosis.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>
</p>
    <p>We describe a case of a 22 year old phototype II female, born and raised in S&#xE3;o Paulo who
reported a small dark brown mark in the third interdigital space of her right foot since
birth. During her first pregnancy, she noted the mark increased in size and changed colour.
At that time she was not examined for this dermatological complaint. Two years later, she
sought dermatological evaluation, at which time an incisional biopsy was performed where
the anatomical pathological findings were melanoma. At dermatological examination in our
service, she presented a blackened plaque around the surgical ulceration (location of
biopsy) in the third interdigital space of the right foot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>) and a painful palpable
hardened mass on the root of right thigh measuring approximately 8 cm. Dermoscopy revealed
a destructured lesion with areas of irregular multifocal pigmentation, coloured light
brown, dark brown, black, and grey, as well as irregularly distributed brownish spots and
globules and an amorphous grey-blue area. The centre presented a secondary scar area from a
previous biopsy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>). Review of the slide
confirmed diagnosis of superficial spreading melanoma with a nodular component, Breslow
index 6.3mm, Clark level IV, presence of ulceration with 5.5 mm extension, 13 mitoses in 10
high power fields, angiolymphatic invasion, absence of regression, and vertical growth
phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">5</xref>). Metastatic tracking in solid organs was negative. Their laboratory exams
were normal (including lactate dehydrogenase). Its stage was IIIC in line with the American
Joint Cancer Commission Staging of Melanoma.<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> The lesion was treated surgically followed by local graft and draining
of the right inguinal lymphatic chain. After 6 months, the patient evolved with cerebral
and pulmonary metastases, quickly evolving to death.</p>
    <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>FIGURE 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Blackened plaque around the surgical ulcer in the third interdigital space of the
right foot</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-01-0157-g01"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>FIGURE 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Another angle of the lesion in the third interdigital space of the right foot, which
gives a better view of the blackened area</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-01-0157-g02"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>FIGURE 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Dermoscopy showing the destructured melanocytic lesion, irregular multifocal
pigmentation with areas of light brown, dark brown, black, and grey, brown spots and
globules with irregular distribution and an amorphous grey-blue area. The centre
presents as an area of secondary scar tissue from a previous biopsy</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-01-0157-g03"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>FIGURE 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Histology: superficial disseminative melanoma with a nodular component, noting in the
epidermis adjacent to the nodule (to the right) epidermotropism until the granulosa
layer. (HE 40x)</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-01-0157-g04"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>FIGURE 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Histology: at higher magnification, note the intense nuclear atypia and mitotic
figures. (HE 400x)</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-01-0157-g05"/>
    </fig>
    <p>The relationship between pregnancy and melanocytic lesions has been discussed for many
years. During pregnancy and exogenous hormone therapy, increased pigmentation is common in
different areas of the body. Certain areas such as the mammary areole, armpits, genital
region, and scar tissue are more prone to presenting increased pigmentation.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
</p>
    <p>Although recent studies have shown that pregnancy does not seem to promote melanoma, some
works indicated that melanocytic nevi can undergo changes during pregnancy.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> For
example, Zampino et al. followed melanocytic lesions in pregnant women and showed that
during pregnancy some melanocytic nevi underwent dermoscopic changes. However, these
changes were transitory and the pigmented lesions returned to their original colour after
childbirth.<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>
</p>
    <p>Zalaudek et al. also showed that multiple dysplastic nevi (MDN) present alterations in
diameter and colouration during pregnancy.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> However, the main question is whether these alterations correspond to a
normal finding or to a condition which raises suspicion of a diagnosis of melanoma. For
this reason, pregnant women who present MDN should receive clinical and dermoscopic follow
up.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>
</p>
    <p>Probably in this case pregnancy may have precipitated the transformation of a congenital
nevus into melanoma as the patient reported noticeable growth during pregnancy of a lesion
present since birth.</p>
    <p>The main objective of this report is to alert dermatologists to the need for careful
examination of nevi and pigmented lesions during pregnancy. This case demonstrates that we
must not interpret changes in these lesions as just being physiological. A biopsy should be
immediately performed when a pigmented lesion changes dermoscopic character during
pregnancy. This action could improve the early diagnosis and prognosis of primary cutaneous
melanoma in these patients.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <label>*</label>
        <p> Work performed at the Department of Dermatology, Paulista School of Medicine -
Federal University of S&#xE3;o Paulo (EPM-UNIFESP) - S&#xE3;o Paulo (SP), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial funding: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of interest: None</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Naser</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cutaneous melanoma: a 30-year-long epidemiological study conducted in
a city in southern Brazil, from 1980-2009</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>932</fpage>
          <lpage>941</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22147033</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stensheim</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xF8;ller</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Dijk</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foss&#xE5;</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cause-specific survival for women diagnosed with cancer during
pregnancy or lactation: A registry-based cohort study</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19029418</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Driscoll</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grant-Kels</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nevi and melanoma in pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Clin</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>199</fpage>
          <lpage>204</lpage>
          <page-range>199-204, vi</page-range>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16677966</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Driscoll</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Do hormones influence melanoma? Facts and
controversies</article-title>
          <source>Clin Dermatol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>287</fpage>
          <lpage>292</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20541681</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Travers</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sober</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berwick</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mihm</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnhill</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duncan</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Increased thickness of pregnancy-associated melanoma</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>876</fpage>
          <lpage>883</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7662565</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Balch</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gershenwald</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soong</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atkins</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Byrd</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Final version of 2009 AJCC melanoma staging and
classification</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>6199</fpage>
          <lpage>6206</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19917835</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>VL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farmer</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dotters</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Focus on Primary Care: From Nevus to Neoplasm: Myths of Melanoma in
Pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Obstet Gynecol Surv</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>112</fpage>
          <lpage>119</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11832787</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gunduz</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koltan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sahin</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>E Filiz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of melanocytic naevi by dermoscopy during
pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>351</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12702085</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zampino</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corazza</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costantino</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mollica</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Virgili</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Are melanocytic nevi influenced by pregnancy? A dermoscopic
evaluation</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>1497</fpage>
          <lpage>1504</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17199661</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zalaudek</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolf</surname>
              <given-names>IH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hofmann-Wellenhof</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leinweber</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Stefani</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Argenziano</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatoscopic follow-up of a changing pigmented melanocytic skin
lesion during pregnancy: from nevus to melanoma?</article-title>
          <source>Melanoma Res</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>323</fpage>
          <lpage>325</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15305165</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
