<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann R Coll Surg Engl</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann R Coll Surg Engl</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bulletin</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Annals of The Royal College of Surgeons of England</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0035-8843</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1478-7083</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Royal College of Surgeons</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23031753</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3954272</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/003588412X13373405385692</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">385692</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Online Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Buruli ulcer in a nine-month-old boy</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="lrh">BURULI ULCER IN A NINE-MONTH-OLD BOY</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsukagoshi</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="C1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
          <email>soniatsukagoshi@yahoo.co.uk</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dehn</surname>
            <given-names>TCB</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AF0001">
          <sup>1</sup>
          <addr-line>Oxford Deanery,</addr-line>
          <country>UK</country>
        </aff>
        <aff id="AF0002">
          <sup>2</sup>
          <addr-line>Royal Berkshire NHS Foundation Trust,</addr-line>
          <country>UK</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="C1"><addr-line>CT2 in Plastic Surgery, Wexham Park Hospital, Wexham, Slough, Berkshire SL2 4HL,</addr-line><country>UK</country> E: <email>soniatsukagoshi@yahoo.co.uk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>94</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>e215</fpage>
      <lpage>e216</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 Royal College of Surgeons</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The diagnosis of Buruli ulcer should be considered in all painless undermined ulcers in the tropics. The diagnosis and treatment are a challenge in rural settings despite the well established tuberculosis programmes. Immediate commencement on rifampicin and streptomycin is essential to halt the progression of disease and to, hopefully, reverse it. Surgery is indicated in those with complex ulcers or with complications. We report the case of a nine-month-old boy presenting to visiting British surgeons in a district hospital in Uganda with multiple ulcers to the right forearm.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Tropical skin ulceration</kwd>
        <kwd>Buruli ulcer</kwd>
        <kwd>Mycobacterium ulcerans</kwd>
        <kwd>Surgery</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="ch35_sau1">
      <title>Case history</title>
      <p>A nine-month-old male baby presented to Kamuli Mission Hospital, a rural Ugandan hospital, with right forearm oedema and lethargy. He was commenced on gentamicin, metronidazole and ceftriaxone by local clinical officers. Three days after admission, he developed two blisters to the volar aspect of the wrist and forearm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig 1</xref>). Three days later, these blisters had developed into two painless undermined ulcers revealing underlying flexor muscles, with a third lesion appearing on the dorsum of the wrist.
<fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Volar lesions on day 3 showing undermined edges and slough at the base</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9407-e8-01"/></fig></p>
      <p>These were washed out and debrided under intravenous ketamine anaesthesia. The ulcers communicated subcutaneously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig 2</xref>). The flexor tendons were visible, the extensor tendons were destroyed and the wrist joint capsule was exposed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig 3</xref>). The wounds were dressed with a non-adhesive dressing and the hand was elevated in a sling. The patient was commenced on a combined rifampicin/isoniazid tablet at a dose of rifampicin 10mg/kg since no other preparations were available (including streptomycin). All other antibiotics were discontinued.
<fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Subcutaneous communication between lesions</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9407-e8-02"/></fig>
<fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Wounds on day 10, now healthy. Note the exposed wrist joint capsule.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9407-e8-03"/></fig></p>
      <p>On day 7, the patient was taken to theatre for a further washout and dressing change. Ziehl&#x2013;Neelsen and Gram stains of pus and debrided tissue were reported as negative. Further wound debridements were undertaken on day 8 and 10, by which time the ulcers had improved in appearance and the patient had recommenced normal feeding.</p>
      <p>Following family and financial discussions, the patient was transferred to a plastic surgery unit in Kampala. Additionally, he was diagnosed with osteomyelitis of the distal radius and was due to undergo a sequestrectomy before skin grafting. All three ulcers had reduced in size by 50% with conservative therapy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="ch35_sau2">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Buruli ulcers are aggressively destructive skin lesions caused by <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic>.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> First described by Sir Albert Cook in 1897, large numbers of cases were reported in the Buruli district of Uganda (now known as Nakasongola). The peak incidence occurs in those aged 5&#x2013;15 years but it can occur at any age.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1,2</sup></xref> The exact mode of transmission is unknown. However, anecdotal evidence suggests that it is an environmental pathogen in contaminated water.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> An increase in cases reported in a Rwandan refugee population settling near the Nile in the 1960s and 1970s further confirmed its waterborne transmission. Recent studies have isolated the <italic>Mycobacterium</italic> in the salivary glands of aquatic insects.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1,2</sup></xref> The disease has been reported in over 30 tropical and subtropical countries across Africa, Asia, the Americas and Australia.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p>
      <p>The initial lesion can vary from a small, firm, painless, subcutaneous nodule, a firm plaque or an oedematous lesion.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> These lesions break down, forming characteristic painless ulcers with undermined edges.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1,3</sup></xref> Nearly all occur on the limbs.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1&#x2013;3</sup></xref>
<italic>M ulcerans</italic> produces mycolactone toxin, which is responsible for the destruction of lipocytes and fibroblasts in subcutaneous tissue, leading to the ulceration and communication between lesions.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p>
      <p>The oedematous type is the most aggressive form where swelling and ulceration can occur within days. Diagnosis is principally clinical, especially with the limited resources in endemic countries. A third of nodules may heal spontaneously.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Although the overall mortality is low, extensive disease can lead to significant morbidity.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Culture, histopathology and polymerase chain reaction are usually unavailable. The Ziehl&#x2013;Neelsen stain has only 40&#x2013;43% sensitivity.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1,2</sup></xref></p>
      <p>In the reported case, the cardinal feature suggestive of Buruli ulcer was the rapid onset oedematous lesion that broke down to form multiple painless undermined ulcers with subcutaneous communications. These were responsive to rifampicin. Ziehl&#x2013;Neelsen staining was negative but this does not exclude the diagnosis.<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p>
      <p>Previously, the mainstay of management was excision with a wide margin due to the presence of mycobacteria in the surrounding tissue.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Recurrence rates following surgery alone lie between 16% and 30%.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Unfortunately, surgery is often inaccessible and many cases are left untreated with huge morbidity outcomes.</p>
      <p>The World Health Organization has categorised these ulcers according to size with advice on appropriate management.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> All are to be treated with antibiotics. Those greater than 15cm, including multiple ulcers or those with osteomyelitis, should be treated with antibiotics and surgery. An eight-week course of combination therapy of rifampicin (10mg/kg) and streptomycin (15mg/kg) is recommended to reduce the risk of resistance. Antibiotics eliminate the mycobacteria from the tissue, remove and also reduce the size of the lesion, and diminish the need for extensive surgery. Excision, skin grafting and amputation are the most common procedures required. Post-operative recurrence has been reduced to less than 2% with pre-operative antibiotics.</p>
      <p>The differential diagnoses include tropical pyomyositis, which is a primary bacterial skeletal muscle infection with abscess formation commonly affecting the hip and thigh.<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> However, in this case, the lesion was painless throughout and ulceration is not characteristic of this disease. Pyomyositis is less rapid in onset and the patient did not respond to the antistaphylococcal antibiotics. Gram staining of the collected pus was negative and it was therefore felt that this was an unlikely cause to his symptoms.</p>
      <p>Due to the limited knowledge of its transmission, there are no public health measures to control the spread.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Currently, no vaccine is available. Education of local populations has facilitated earlier diagnosis and therefore earlier treatment.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="ch35_sau3">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>The diagnosis of Buruli ulcer should be considered in all painless undermined ulcers in the tropics. The diagnosis and treatment are a challenge in rural settings despite the well established tuberculosis programmes. Immediate commencement on rifampicin and streptomycin is essential to halt the progression of disease and to, hopefully, reverse it. Surgery is indicated in those with complex ulcers or with complications.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wansbrough-Jones</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Buruli ulcer: emerging from obscurity</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>367</volume>: <fpage>1,849</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1,858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16399129</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Buruli ulcer: progress report, 2004&#x2013;2008</article-title>. <source>Wkly Epidemiol Rec</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18437758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>van der Werf</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van der Graaf</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tappero</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asiedu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mycobacterium ulcerans infection</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>1999</year>; <volume>354</volume>: <fpage>1,013</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1,018</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mitsionis</surname>
<given-names>GI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manoudis</surname>
<given-names>GN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lykissas</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name><italic>et al</italic>
<article-title>Pyomyositis in children: early diagnosis and treatment</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Surg</source><year>2009</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>2,173</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2,178</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
