<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25054752</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4148279</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20143004</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Application of platelet-rich plasma in the treatment of chronic skin
ulcer - Case report<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></sup>
</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pinto</surname>
            <given-names>Jane Marcy Neff&#xE1;</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pizani</surname>
            <given-names>Nat&#xE1;ssia Soares</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>Hye Chung</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Silva</surname>
            <given-names>Luis Augusto Knecht</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff> Universidade Federal Fluminense (UFF) - Niter&#xF3;i (RJ), Brazil.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">MAILING ADDRESS: Nat&#xE1;ssia Soares Pizani, Avenida Marques de
Paran&#xE1;, 303, t&#xE9;rreo, Setor de Dermatologia, 24030-900 - Niter&#xF3;i - RJ, Brazil.
E-mail: <email>natassia.pizani@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Jul-Aug</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Aug</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>89</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>638</fpage>
      <lpage>640</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The platelet-rich plasma (PRP) has proved promising regarding its applicability
in dermatology, especially in the healing of chronic ulcers. The autologous
platelet-rich plasma is obtained by centrifuging the blood, so that the
components are separated by density gradient. The final product is a gel rich in
growth factors that act in tissue repair by activating fibroblasts and inducing
extracellular matrix remodeling.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Platelet-rich plasma</kwd>
        <kwd>Skin ulcer</kwd>
        <kwd>Wound healing</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Cutaneous ulceration is a very common event, with current prevalence around 0.18% and
0.32%, incidence of 0.78% and a clear tendency of rising with the increasing mean
age of the population. The effects on socioeconomic costs are inevitable. Chronic
cutaneous ulcers have a great impact on patient quality of life and public health
costs in Brazil and worldwide. The European Union reserves 2% of its yearly health
budget for the treatment of such ailments.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Healing of wounds is a complex process mediated by signals of molecular interaction
involving recruiting of mesenchymal cells, proliferation and regeneration of the
extracellular matrix. The healing process is a response of innate immunity for the
restoration of tissue integrity. It is regulated by a pattern of events including
coagulation, inflammation, granulation tissue formation, epithelialization and
tissue remodeling. These events are mediated by cytokines and growth factors that
modulate such cellular activities.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>S.M.V.S., 65-year-old, female, black, retired teacher, presents cutaneous ulcers with
13 years of evolution in the medial malleolar region of right lower limb and middle
third of left lower limb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>). The
lesions arise from chronic venous insufficiency. Initially, they measured around 2
cm. However, there was progressive increase of lesion diameter since their onset.
Between the period from 2007 to 2009, she used curative dressings based on essential
fatty acids (EFA) every 15 days. Around 5 years ago, she started treatment with
hyperbaric oxygen therapy, 80 doses divided into 3 sessions, with broad and
irregular intervals, with no apparent improvement. The patient underwent lesion
biopsy which showed dense vascularized connective tissue exhibiting fibroplasia,
acute and chronic inflammatory infiltrate close to the granulation tissue and ulcer
material. From November 2012 onward she started taking regular doses of PRP on the
left lower limb lesion. Currently, a painful ulcer remains presenting granulation
tissue with irregular edges, discrete fibrinous exudate and adjacent hyperchromia.
Reepithelialization areas in the interior of the lesion were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">3</xref>). Absence of phlogistic signs. Currently using Diosmin<sup>&#xAE;</sup>,
Vasogard<sup>&#xAE;</sup>, Dermavite<sup>&#xAE;</sup>, Drenison<sup>&#xAE;</sup> cream.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Lower left limb - June/2011</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-04-0638-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Lower left limb - May/2013</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-04-0638-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Detail of lower left limb - May/2013</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-04-0638-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Obese patient, not diabetic and hypertensive undergoing regular treatment. She denied
smoking or alcohol consumption.</p>
      <p>Since the beginning of PRP regular administration there was noticeable improvement of
the lesion, observed by the increase of granulation tissue. Softening of borders can
be noticed by palpation, which may be interpreted as decrease of local fibrosis.
Currently, she presents skin patches in the interior of the ulcer, corresponding to
reepithelialization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Obtaining the PRP</title>
        <p>Platelet-rich plasma is obtained through a process that utilizes the principle of
cell separation by differential centrifugation.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> At present, there are at least 16 systems of
PRP preparation available.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
        <p>At the outpatient clinic, at every application, 20ml of blood is collected and
distributed into 5ml test tubes, containing sodium citrate solution 3.2%, which
are later centrifuged at 400G at 1500 RPM for 15 minutes, at room temperature.
Around 1.2 ml of supernatant plasma is collected per tube and associated with 5
ml of calcium chloride at 0.025mol/L. After approximately 5 minutes, the gel is
formed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">5</xref>).<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>
Later, it is applied to the wound bed and occluded with vaseline gauze and
rolled bandage. The option of associating sodium calcium chloride and forming
the platelet gel proved to be better than the intralesional PRP injection, since
it is a large and painful ulcer.</p>
        <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Centrifuged blood</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-04-0638-g04"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Collected PRP</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-04-0638-g05"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Due to life expectancy increase and, consequently, noticeable aging of the
population, it is common for prevalence of chronic cutaneous ulcers to increase,
notably when arising from atherosclerotic and microangiopathic processes. In this
respect, it is necessary to develop techniques that assist in the process of skin
healing and repair. PRP arrives as a tool which allows the application of large
amounts of growth factors, which stimulate the production of collagen and
extracellular matrix through minimum quantities of plasma. This is an important
alternative in cases where conventional treatments were not successful, such as the
one described.</p>
      <p>Glycoprotein PDGF (platelet-derived growth factor) is the first growth factor to
appear in the wound, starting the repair process of the connective tissue. Its most
important specific activities include mitogenesis, angiogenesis, and macrophage
activation.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Growth factors promote quick increase of the number of undifferentiated mesenchymal
cells at the scar site during repair and healing time. Therefore, the PRP advantage
is to accelerate the regenerative process through the quantity of growth factors
present in the platelets.</p>
      <p>Amable et al conducted a study quantifying growth factors, cytokines and chemokines
secreted by the platelet concentrate after calcium activation. High concentrations
of PDGF, epidermal growth factor (EGF) and transforming growth factor (TGF) were
secreted together with pro and anti-inflammatory cytokines like interleukin 4
(IL-4), IL-8, IL-13, IL-17, tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF&#x3B1;) and interferonalpha
(INF&#x3B1;). No cytokine was secreted before platelet activation.<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
      <p>There are, however, many possible confounding variables in studies, as much regarding
variation of patient characteristics as PRP characteristics. Thus the difficulty of
conducting standardized studies.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
As regards research, it is a still recent discovery, although very promising.</p>
      <p>The material is easily collected and processed, and the procedure of simple technical
execution, with minimum morbidity, as it is totally autologous.</p>
      <p>In spite of the advancements in cutaneous ulceration treatment, this common condition
continues to devastate the community of patients who suffer from micro and
macrovascular afflictions. The treatment with growth factors may result in shorter
healing time and limb function recovery, enhancing the quality of life of the
patient.</p>
      <p>Based on literature, we conclude that the use of PRP in dermatology, albeit recent,
constitutes a very promising technique. It is an organic preparation, non
immunoreactive, non-toxic and of low morbidity. The cost of obtaining it is
reasonably low.</p>
      <p>Finally, more studies are necessary regarding the action mechanism and
standardization of the ideal PRP preparation. Future studies should be conducted
with lengthier follow-up periods and coverage of different PRP preparations.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of Interests: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial Support: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <label>*</label>
        <p> Work performed at Hospital Universit&#xE1;rio Ant&#xF4;nio Pedro - Universidade Federal
Fluminense (HUAP-UFF) - Niter&#xF3;i (RJ), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>How to cite this article: Neff&#xE1; Pinto JM, Pizani NS, Kang HC, Knecht Silva LA.
Application of platelet-rich plasma in the treatment of chronic skin ulcer -
Case report. An Bras Dermatol. 2014;89(4):638-40.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crovetti</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martinelli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Issi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barone</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guizzardi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campanati</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Platelet gel for healing cutaneous chronic wounds</article-title>
          <source>Transfus Apher Sci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>145</fpage>
          <lpage>151</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15062754</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mazzucco</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Medici</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Serra</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panizza</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rivara</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orecchia</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The use of autologous platelet gel to treat difficult-to-heal
wounds: a pilot study</article-title>
          <source>Transfusion</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>1013</fpage>
          <lpage>1018</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15225241</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saucedo</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yaffe</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berschback</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsu</surname>
              <given-names>WK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalainov</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Platelet-Rich Plasma</article-title>
          <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>589</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22305737</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lenharo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cosso</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Fatores de crescimento: quando
usar?</article-title>
          <source>Inovations J</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marx</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carlson</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eichstaedt</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schimmele</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strauss</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Georgeff</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma: growth factor enhancement for bone
grafts</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>638</fpage>
          <lpage>646</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9638695</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amable</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carias</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teixeira</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>da Cruz Pacheco</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corr&#xEA;a do Amaral</surname>
              <given-names> RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Granjeiro</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma preparation for regenerative medicine:
optimization and quantification of cytokines and growth
factors</article-title>
          <source>Stem Cell Res Ther</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23759113</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lacci</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dardik</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Platelet-rich Plasma: support for its use in wound
healing</article-title>
          <source>Yale J Biol Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20351977</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
