<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arq. Bras. Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cardiologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0066-782X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-4170</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24522279</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4106819</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/abc.20130235</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pericardial Synovial Sarcoma: Case Report and Literature
Review</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bezerra</surname>
            <given-names>Sabrina Godoy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brand&#xE3;o</surname>
            <given-names>Andrea Ara&#xFA;jo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Albuquerque</surname>
            <given-names>Denilson Campos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Milit&#xE3;o</surname>
            <given-names>Rochelle Coppo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hadlich</surname>
            <given-names>Marcelo Souza</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Azevedo</surname>
            <given-names>Clerio Francisco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Instituto D'Or de Pesquisa e Ensino (IDOR), Rio de Janeiro, RJ</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, RJ</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> Rede Labs D'Or - Grupo Fleury, Rio de Janeiro, RJ - Brazil</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing address: Clerio Francisco Azevedo</bold> Instituto D'Or de Pesquisa e
Ensino - Rua Diniz Cordeiro 30, Botafogo. Postal Code 22281-100, Rio de Janeiro, RJ,
Brazil E-mail: <email>cleriofilho@cardiol.br </email>,
<email>clerio.azevedo@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>101</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>e103</fpage>
      <lpage>e106</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Sarcoma, Synovial / surgery</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart Neoplasms / surgery</kwd>
        <kwd>Pericardial Effusion</kwd>
        <kwd>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Pericardial synovial sarcoma is an extremely rare primary malignant tumor of the heart
and has an unclear prognosis.</p>
      <p>The purpose of this report is to describe the case of a patient with pericardial
synovial sarcoma whose initial presentation was severe pericardial effusion and dramatic
weight loss. Despite treatment, the patient died in one year. Then, we reviewed the
medical literature for the epidemiology, clinical picture, relevance of complementary
imaging tests, therapeutic conduct and prognosis of this neoplasm.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>Female patient, 29 years old, developed dyspnea on mild exertion that evolved into
orthopnea in four days; associated with mild chest pain that improved with knee-chest
position. The patient lost 11 kg in two months. She denied smoking or alcohol
consumption. The patient's mother had presented breast neoplasm.</p>
      <p>On examination, she was mildly tachypneic with a respiratory rate of 24 rpm and
decreased breath sounds in the lung bases, no adventitious sounds. The patient had
tachycardia, heart rate of 110 bpm, hypophonetic heart sounds, paradoxical pulse
characterized by a drop in blood pressure of 105 x 63 mmHg to 80 x 58 mmHg during deep
inspiration and pathological jugular venous distention at 45&#xBA;.</p>
      <p>Electrocardiogram showed signs of low ventricular voltage. Echocardiography revealed
significant pericardial effusion with signs of diastolic restriction and oval,
hyperechoic image with a diameter of 2 cm in the pericardial sac adjacent to the Left
Atrium (LA) wall, suggesting clot.</p>
      <p>The patient underwent urgent pericardial drainage with removal of 1000 mL of
serohemorrhagic fluid, which laboratory analysis showed the presence of exudate with
large amount of red blood cells. Gram-positive bacteria, Acid-Alcohol Resistant Bacilli
(AARB), neither neoplastic cells were found. Adenosine deaminase levels were normal.</p>
      <p>After ten days in hospital, during which the patient was clinically stable, she was
discharged for outpatient investigation. With a medical appointment scheduled for the
following week, the patient returned only after five months, complaining of fatigue on
mild exertion.</p>
      <p>On this occasion, the echocardiogram revealed a large hyperechoic mass in posterior
topography, extending from the LA to the middle portion of the left ventricle (LV).
Within the mass, there were oval hypoechoic images, some of which presented septa
suggestive of central necrosis.</p>
      <p>Magnetic Resonance imaging (MRI) of the heart was requested, which revealed a large
heterogeneous mass within the pericardial sac, adjacent to the free wall of the LA and
the mid-basal portion of the LV lateral wall, measuring 9.3 x 8.0 x 4.3 cm in diameter
and multiple septa inside (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>). The central
portion of the mass was hypointense on T1-weighted spin-echo sequence, hyperintense on
T2-weighted spin-echo sequence and showed no decrease in signal intensity in the fat
saturation pre-pulse sequence. The first-pass perfusion imaging revealed good
vascularization of the mass periphery and septa, and no significant central vasculature.
On late enhancement sequence, there was intense gadolinium uptake by the mass periphery
and septa and absence of gadolinium uptake by the central region. The appearance
suggested a large malignant tumor of the pericardium with multiple areas of central
necrosis, apparently without invasion of adjacent structures by the tumor.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Cardiac magnetic resonance imaging. A. Cine imaging sequence showing a large
heterogeneous tumor with multiple septa inside, located within the pericardial
sac, adjacent to the LA free wall and the mid-basal portion of the LV lateral
wall. B. First-pass perfusion sequence. Note the tumor periphery and septa
perfusion. There is no perfusion of the central region of the tumor (necrosis). C.
Delayed enhancement sequence. Note the intense gadolinium uptake by the tumor
periphery and the septa. There is no gadolinium uptake by the central region
(necrosis). RA: right atrium; RV: right ventricle; LA: left atrium; LV: left
ventricle</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-101-06-e103-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p>It was decided to refer the patient to cardiac surgery in order to achieve complete
excision of the mass for diagnosis and therapeutic purposes.</p>
      <p>During the surgery, a capsule covering the mass was found. The capsule was opened and
inside it, there was a large friable tumor with the appearance of "fish meat". It had
multiple septa and a large amount of necrotic material inside. The tumor had ill-defined
borders and was extremely attached to the heart, without cleavage plane, which prevented
its complete excision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>). Therefore, only
one partial resection of the tumor was performed.</p>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Photos of the surgery. A: Capsule covering the tumor. B: The capsule (white arrow)
was open and inside there is a large friable pericardial tumor (black arrow) with
the appearance of &#x201C;fish meat&#x201D;, imprecise borders and extremely attached to the
heart. C: Tumor fragments with multiple septa and a large amount of necrotic
material inside</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-101-06-e103-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Pathological examination showed spindle cells consistent with the diagnosis of
pericardial synovial sarcoma.</p>
      <p>Chemotherapy and radiotherapy were indicated, but the patient failed to follow treatment
from the start. She only started chemotherapy nine months later. After the second cycle,
the patient developed progressive dyspnea, fever, dry cough and significant decline in
overall condition. Admitted on an emergency, she was diagnosed with severe
community-acquired pneumonia associated with severe neutropenia. Despite the
prescription of appropriate antibiotic therapy, recombinant human granulocyte
colony-stimulating factor and the support of intensive care, the patient developed
respiratory failure and septic shock in two days and died.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Primary cardiac tumors are rare, with a reported incidence of 0.05% in a study of 12,485
autopsies. Secondary involvement of the heart and pericardium by extracardiac tumors is
twenty times more common than primary cardiac tumors. The neoplams that most often
secondarily affect the cardiac structures are the tumors of lung and breast, melanoma
and lymphoma, either by distant metastasis or by direct invasion<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Around 80% of primary cardiac tumors are benign. The atrial myxoma is the most common
one. About 20% of primary cardiac tumors are malignant. The sarcoma is the one most
frequently found, followed by mesothelioma and linphoma<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Among the cardiac sarcomas, the pericardial synovial
sarcoma is extremely rare. It originates from mesenchymal pluripotent cells and gets its
name from the histologic similarity to synovial tissue in formation<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The signs and symptoms caused by the primary cardiac sarcoma are extremely variable and
nonspecific. Clinical manifestations can be divided into four categories: systemic;
embolic; cardiac; and secondary to metastasis.</p>
      <p>The most common systemic manifestations are fever, chills, fatigue and weight loss, and
this patient showed significant weight loss of 11 kg in two months. Embolic
manifestations occur mainly in sarcomas invading the cardiac cavities, causing pulmonary
or systemic embolism. Cardiac manifestations depend on the location of the tumor:
predominantly pericardial, intramural or intracavitary. In the case of pericardial
sarcoma, the most common initial clinical picture results from massive hemorrhagic
pericardial effusion and cardiac tamponade<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. The organs most often
affected by primary cardiac sarcoma metastases are the lungs, brain and bones.</p>
      <p>Imaging methods are extremely important for the diagnosis of cardiac tumors, which are
often an incidental finding in tests performed for other reasons. In the case of
pericardial tumors, echocardiography can identify the mass and it is important for
quantifying pericardial effusion and evaluating the presence of signs of diastolic
restriction, as in the case of this patient. MRI and computer-aided tomography help
determining the location and extent of the tumor and assessing local invasion of
adjacent organs. They are also essential for surgical planning. MRI, by using multiple
techniques, is important to characterize the tumor tissue in a detailed manner, enabling
the evaluation of characteristics suggestive of malignancy<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Due to the rapid growth of malignant tumors, they may
present central necrotic areas characterized for being hypointense on T1-weighted
spin-echo sequence, hyperintense on T2-weighted spin-echo sequence and for not
presenting gadolinium uptake in the sequences of perfusion and delayed enhancement, as
demonstrated in the present pericardial sarcoma. Other characteristics suggestive of
malignancy, well demonstrated by MRI, include: involvement of more than one heart
chamber, if the tumor is attached to the heart through a large base, extracardiac
extension and presence of pericardial effusion<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The pericardial sarcoma is a highly aggressive neoplasm. Therefore, in most cases it is
not possible to perform a complete surgical resection. In a study with 24 patients, only
22.7% of resected cardiac sarcomas had free lesion edges<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. Complete surgical resection is the main impact factor in
patient survival. Adjuvant chemotherapy and radiotherapy are recommended when the
surgery is incomplete or for recurrent tumors<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. However, despite treatment, the prognosis of patients with
cardiac sarcoma is reserved, with median survival of only 25 months<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>This report described the case of a pericardial synovial sarcoma, an extremely rare
primary cardiac tumor which, despite proper treatment, has an unclear prognosis.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lam</surname>
              <given-names>KY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickens</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tumors of the heart: a 20-year experience with a review of 12,485
consecutive autopsies</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1027</fpage>
          <lpage>1031</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8215825</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burke</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>VirmaniR</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Tumors of the heart and the great vessels</chapter-title>
          <source>Atlas of tumor pathology</source>
          <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Armed Forces Institute of Pathology</publisher-name>
          <year>1996</year>
          <fpage>127</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moorjani</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peebles</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gallagher</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsang</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pericardial synovial sarcoma</article-title>
          <source>J Card Surg</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>351</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19438797</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Zwaan</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bekkers</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Garsse</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jansen</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Suylen</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary monophasic mediastinal, cardiac and pericardial synovial
sarcoma: a young man in distress</article-title>
          <source>Neth Heart J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>226</fpage>
          <lpage>228</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17612689</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luna</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ribes</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caro</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vida</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erasmus</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of cardiac tumors with magnetic resonance
imaging</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>1446</fpage>
          <lpage>1455</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15627179</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dancer</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coffey</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhai</surname>
              <given-names>QJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reardon</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayala</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinicopathologic study of 24 patients with primary cardiac sarcomas:
a 10-year single institution experience</article-title>
          <source>Hum Pathol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>933</fpage>
          <lpage>938</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18538171</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brooks</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldblum</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoder</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seethala</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pawel</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary cardiac sarcomas: a clinicopathologic analysis of a series
with follow-up information in 17 patients and emphasis on long-term
survival</article-title>
          <source>Hum Pathol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>1385</fpage>
          <lpage>1395</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18602663</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
