<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26312679</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4540513</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20153781</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Leprosy type-I reaction episode mimicking facial cellulitis-the
importance of early diagnosis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fernandes</surname>
            <given-names>Tania Rita Moreno de Oliveira</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brand&#xE3;o</surname>
            <given-names>Graziele &#xC1;quila de Souza</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Souza</surname>
            <given-names>Bruno de Castro e</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label>Universidade Federal do Vale do S&#xE3;o Francisco(Univasf) -
Petrolina (PE), Brazil.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">MAILING ADDRESS: Tania Rita Moreno de Oliveira Fernandes, Av. Jos&#xE9; de
S&#xE1; Mani&#xE7;oba, S/N - Centro, 56304-917 - Petrolina - PE, Brazil. E-mail:
<email>trmofernandes@gmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>Conflict of Interest: None.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>90</volume>
      <issue>3 Suppl 1</issue>
      <fpage>73</fpage>
      <lpage>76</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2015 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leprosy is aneasily recognizable disease due to its dermato-neurological
manifestations. It must be present in the physician&#x2019;s diagnostic repertoire,
especially for those working in endemic areas. However, leprosy reaction is not
always easily recognized by non-dermatologists, becoming one of the major problems in
the management of patients with leprosy, as it presents clinical complications
characterized by inflammatory process, accompanied by pain, malaise and sometimes the
establishment or worsening of the patient&#x2019;s disabilities. We report the case of a
patient with type-1 periorbital reaction admitted to the hospital, diagnosed and
treated as facial cellulitis, whose late diagnosis may have contributed to the
appearance or worsening of facial neuritis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Leprosy</kwd>
        <kwd>Neuritis</kwd>
        <kwd>Orbital cellulitis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Leprosy is an infectious, chronic, and communicable disease caused by
<italic>Mycobacterium leprae</italic>. It affects mainly the skin and peripheral
nerves.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Due to the ample clinical variations of the disease, the list of differential diagnoses
is quite complex, often leading to delays in its identification and subsequent
treatment.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Among the primary
challenges, those are patients who initially present with type I or type II reactional
episodes, thus requiring early diagnosis and institution of specific treatments in order
to reduce the chance of developing physical disabilities and sequelae, which may
negatively impact their social and professional lives.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>We present here the case of a patient who was primarily diagnosed with facial cellulitis
and only later diagnosed with leprosy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A sixty-seven-year-old male patient, married, born in Brejo Santo/CE, coming from
Petrolina/PE, was admitted to the emergency room with a history of pruritus and redness
in the left eye for the last 6 months. Also, 25 days prior to the admission,the patient
developed periorbital edema and an erythematous plaque on the forehead and left
periorbital region. He sought medical attention and was prescribed prednisone 60mg/day.
At the time, he also reported numbness onthe left hand, associated with a lesion similar
to the one on his face.The patient denied any systemic symptoms. Physical examination on
admission showed an erythematous-infiltrated plaque reaching the left side of the
forehead and edema on the periorbital region and nasal dorsum to the left (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>). He was admitted with a diagnosis of
periorbital cellulitis, prescribed treatment with Ampicillin + Sulbactam and laboratory
tests were requested. Upon admission he presented 13.2g/dL hemoglobin; 39.4% hematocrit;
5,900 x10<sup>9</sup>L leukocytes (67.9% neutrophils); 272,000 x10<sup>9</sup>L
platelets; 142mEq/L sodium; 5.2-mEq/Lpotassium; 19 mg/dL BUN; 1.0 mg/dL creatinine. The
patient received antibiotic treatment for 10 days without clinical improvement, hence a
CT scan was ordered and the diagnostic hypothesis was once more facial cellulitis, which
prompted a proposal for antibiotic change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figures
2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">3</xref>). Nonetheless, a sensitivity
test was performed on the plaque area and loss of thermal sensitivity was detected all
over the lesion, as well as on the hand lesion, leading to the diagnosis of borderline
tuberculoid leprosy (BTD) in reaction.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous-infiltrated plaque on the left region of the forehead, eyelids and
nasal dorsum, at diagnosis</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-03-s1-0073-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Facial CT scan: thickening with signs of enhancement by contrast on superficial
plans/soft tissues of the left periorbital region, extending to the ipsilateral
frontal region. Compatible with periorbital cellulite</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-03-s1-0073-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Thickening of theleftperiorbital region, compatible withperiorbitalcellulitis,is
observed. No signs ofbone involvementorcollections</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-03-s1-0073-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Bacilloscopy of the lesions was negative. Both lesions were biopsied and
anatomopathological results revealed periadnexal and perineural granulomatous chronic
dermatitis. With an established diagnosis of BTD in reaction, the patient was prescribed
prednisone 60 mg/day and referred to a dermatologist, who started treatment with
specific multibacillarypolychemotherapy (rifampicin, clofazimine and dapsone).
Prednisone 60mg/day was maintained, with gradual tapering off after the reaction abated
and in 15 days the patient showed improvement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure
4</xref>). Forty-five days after the treatment was started the patient presented
marked recovery, although the presence of lagophthalmos on the left side was noticed,
prompting physical therapy and close monitoring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Figure
5</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Partial regression of lesions after 15 days of treatment</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-03-s1-0073-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Regression of lesions, although with the presence of lagophthalmos, 40 days after
diagnosis</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-03-s1-0073-g05"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Reaction episodes are acute phenomena affecting skin and peripheral nerves. They may
occur before, during or after the treatment and are the leading cause of nerve damage
and disability secondary to leprosy.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Reactions might be of type I, also known as reverse reaction or type II, namely erythema
nodosum. Type I reactions present signs of acute inflammation such as pain, erythema,
infiltration and edema of pre-existing lesions; also, the appearance of new lesions,
papules and plaques (usually erythematous and adjacent to pre-existing lesions) may
occur. Lesions may be single or multiple and are oftenulcerated. <sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>
Reactions occur in dimorphic leprosy forms (DL) such as borderline tuberculoid (BT),
borderline (BB), and borderline lepromatous (BL). Type II reactions or erythema nodosum
are associated with general symptoms such as fever, painful lymphadenopathy and malaise,
manifesting as papules or painful, erythematous nodules. They occur in lepromatous (LL)
and borderline lepromatous (BL) forms. <sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In type 1 reaction, presented by the patient in this report, there are manifestations
that can mimic erysipelas, cellulitis, drug eruptions, urticaria, psoriasis,
sarcoidosis, lymphomas, sudden peripheral facial paralysis and even leprosy relapse
itself.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> The complete mechanisms
involved in its genesis are yet unknown.It is accepted, however, that it results from an
imbalance between pro-inflammatory cytokines (gamma interferon and interleukin-2,
mainly) and anti-inflammatory cytokines (especially TGF beta and interleukin
10).<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In the clinical case in question, the patient was initially diagnosed and treated as
facial cellulitis, because of the intense inflammatory process he presented, without
taking into consideration the reported paresthesia or the lesion on the left hand, which
was similar to the facial one. Due to the lack of improvement after the therapy was
introduced, bacilloscopies of the lesion and conventional sites (earlobes and elbow)
were later performed with negative results, as frequently occurs in BTD forms. Biopsies
of the lesions revealed granulomatous dermatitis with leprosy in reaction as the primary
diagnosis. The delayed diagnosis probably contributed to the neurological impairment.
Even though Brazil is a country with high levels of endemicity, many typical cases are
only diagnosed in polarized forms and after sequelae have already been
established.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In endemic areas, leprosy reaction is the first diagnosis to be suspected in cases like
this (reactive form of BT) in which the initial lesion consists of an erythematous
plaque on the innervation area of the facial nerve, resulting in neuritis (also common
in reactional states) and subsequent lagophthalmos. Among leprosy patients, those with
BT form usually developreactional states earlier and with greater neural involvement,
which requires diagnosticand therapeutic agility in order to prevent disabilities such
as those developed by ourpatient.<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>Financial Support: None.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p><bold>How to cite this article:</bold> Fernandes TRMO, Brand&#xE3;o GAB, Souza BC. Leprosy
type-I reaction episode mimicking facial cellulitis - the importance of early
diagnosisV. An Bras Dermatol. 2015;90 (3 Suppl 1): S73-6 .</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other" id="fn01">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Work performed at Universidade Federal do Vale do S&#xE3;o Francisco (Univasf) - Petrolina
(PE), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <p>Our sincere thanks to Dr. Danilo Rocha Santiago, radiologist, by gentleness in image
analysis.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Last&#xF3;ria</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morgado de Abreu</surname>
              <given-names>MAM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Leprosy: review of the epidemiological, clinical, and etiopathogenic
aspects - Part 1</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>218</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24770495</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Teixeira</surname>
              <given-names>MAG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silveira</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fran&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characteristics of leprosy reactions in paucibacillary and
multibacillary individuals attended at two REFERENCES centers in Recife,
Pernambuco</article-title>
          <source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>287</fpage>
          <lpage>292</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20563498</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Souza</surname>
              <given-names>LWF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Leprosy reactions in discharged patients following cure by multidrug
therapy</article-title>
          <source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>737</fpage>
          <lpage>739</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21181036</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Teixeira</surname>
              <given-names>LO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akamatsu</surname>
              <given-names>HT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barreto</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soares</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neural relapse in multibacillary leprosy 6 years after end of
treatment</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>305</fpage>
          <lpage>308</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22570039</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franco Edos</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferreira</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braga</surname>
              <given-names>WS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Borderline tuberculoid leprosy and type 1 leprosy reaction in a
hepatitis C patient during treatment with interferon and ribavirin</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>109</fpage>
          <lpage>112</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24346894</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barreto</surname>
              <given-names>J&#xC1;</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marinho</surname>
              <given-names>FCA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Contin</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nogueira</surname>
              <given-names>MES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rea&#xE7;&#xE3;o reversa nodular tardia simulando recidiva: A import&#xE2;ncia da
hist&#xF3;ria cl&#xED;nica e dos exames laboratoriais</article-title>
          <source>Hansen Int</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>197</fpage>
          <lpage>202</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Last&#xF3;ria</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macharelli</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Putinatti</surname>
              <given-names>MSMA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hansen&#xED;ase: realidade no seu diagn&#xF3;stico cl&#xED;nico</article-title>
          <source>Hansen Int</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>53</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Talhari</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neves</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Hansen&#xED;ase</source>
          <edition>2. ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Manaus</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Instituto Superior de Estudos da Amazonia</publisher-name>
          <year>1989</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
