<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Mol Hepatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Mol Hepatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CMH</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinical and Molecular Hepatology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2287-2728</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2287-285X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Association for the Study of the Liver</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25032187</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4099336</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3350/cmh.2014.20.2.204</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pure red-cell aplasia and autoimmune hemolytic anemia in a patient with acute hepatitis A</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>Hyo Jeong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Sinn</surname>
            <given-names>Dong Hyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>Sung Gyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>Tae Hoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeon</surname>
            <given-names>Tae Joo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Won Chang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choi</surname>
            <given-names>Won Choong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Internal Medicine, Inje University Sanggye Paik Hospital, Inje University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Corresponding author: Dong Hyun Sinn. Department of Internal Medicine, Inje University College of Medicine, Sanggye Paik Hospital, 1342 Dongil-ro, Nowon-gu, Seoul 139-707, Korea. Tel. +82-2-950-1114, Fax. +82-2-950-1955, <email>sinndhn@hanmail.net</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>20</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>204</fpage>
      <lpage>207</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 by The Korean Association for the Study of the Liver</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pure red cell aplasia (PRCA) and autoimmune hemolytic anemia (AIHA) have rarely been reported as an extrahepatic manifestation of acute hepatitis A (AHA). We report herein a case of AHA complicated by both PRCA and AIHA. A 49-year-old female with a diagnosis of AHA presented with severe anemia (hemoglobin level, 6.9 g/dL) during her clinical course. A diagnostic workup revealed AIHA and PRCA as the cause of the anemia. The patient was treated with an initial transfusion and corticosteroid therapy. Her anemia and liver function test were completely recovered by 9 months after the initial presentation. We review the clinical features and therapeutic strategies for this rare case of extrahepatic manifestation of AHA.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Hepatitis A</kwd>
        <kwd>Pure red-cell aplasia</kwd>
        <kwd>Autoimmune hemolytic anemia</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Acute hepatitis A (AHA) is usually a mild and self-limited infection, especially when infected in early childhood.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> However, rarely, AHA can be complicated by extrahepatic manifestations, such as rash, arthralgia, leukocytoclastic vasculitis, glomerulonephritis, arthritis, toxic epidermal necrolysis, myocarditis, renal failure, optic neuritis, transverse myelitis, or polyneuritis etc.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p>
      <p>Pure red cell anemia (PRCA) and autoimmune hemolytic anemia (AIHA) are another rare extrahepatic manifestation of AHA. When complicated with PRCA and AIHA, it may contribute to significantly greater morbidity and mortality in AHA.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> We experienced a case of AHA complicated by both PRCA and AIHA, and we herein report this rare extrahepatic manifestation of AHA with a review of the treatment strategies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE</title>
      <p>A 49-year old previously healthy woman admitted our hospital with a febrile sense, myalgia and nausea for 5 days. Initial laboratory findings showed marked elevation of serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) 6,122 IU/L, alanine aminotransferase (ALT) 7,451 IU/L, total bilirubin (TB) 5.1 mg/dL, and prolonged prothrombin time (PT-INR) 1.76. Complete blood count was within normal limit except for thrombocytopenia (hemoglobin (Hb) 14.8 g/dL, white blood cell (WBC) 6,790/&#xB5;L, platelet 118 &#xD7; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#xB5;L). Mean corpuscular volume (MCV) and mean corpuscular Hb (MCH) were 82.4 fL and 28.3 pg, respectively. Serologic tests revealed negative results for hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C virus antibody, and positive result for anti-hepatitis C virus IgM. Based on clinical and laboratory findings, she was diagnosed with AHA. Her symptoms and laboratory results were gradually improved during hospitalization as AST 916 IU/L, ALT 1925 IU/L, TB 9.2 mg/dL, PT-INR 1.37, and discharged after 5 days of admission. Her serum Hb level at discharge was 14.3 g/dL. Three weeks later, she re-admitted to hospital because of jaundice and a poor general condition. Laboratory examination illustrated marked elevation of TB, 32.3 mg/dL with severe anemia (Hb, 6.9 g/dL, MCV 77.4 fL, MCH 26.4 pg). At this time, there was improvement in serum AST and ALT and PT-INR levels compared to those at the time of discharge from hospital (AST 147 IU/L/L, ALT 114 IU/L, PT-INR 1.15). She had no symptoms or signs suggesting gastrointestinal bleeding (Levin tube irrigation: no signs of upper gastrointestinal bleeding, digital rectal examination: no signs of gastrointestinal bleeding). Laboratory examination revealed elevated serum lactate dehydrogenase level (1,600 IU/L), positive direct Coombs test, decreased haptoglobin level (&lt;20 mg/dL) and positive hemoglobinuria, which confirmed the presence of AIHA. However, reticulocyte count (reticulocyte 0.08%, corrected reticulocyte count 0.04%, reticulocyte production index 0.02%) was decreased, suggesting that additional causes of anemia other than AIHA may be present. Hence, bone marrow examination was conducted, which revealed normocellular marrow (cellularity 35%) and active granulopoiesis with markedly decreased erythroid cells (myeloid: erythroid=24.9:1). Hemophagocytosis and any other necrosis were not observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Based on the results of bone marrow examination, PRCA was diagnosed for the patient. Parvovirus B19 IgM and Epstein-Barr virus VCA IgM were tested to see whether these two virus co-existed, and showed negative test results.</p>
      <p>She was treated with prednisolone (1 mg/kg), but her Hb level continued to drop, and was 4.7 g/dL on 3rd day of predinisolone treatment. She received two pints of packed red blood cells (RBC), and continued corticosteroid therapy. After transfusion, her Hb level was 7.7 g/dL, and was gradually increased, reaching 10.4 g/dL two weeks later. Reticulocyte count was increased to 15.9%, and serum TB and LDH level were decreased to 19.4 mg/dL and 927 IU/L, respectively, at that time. Prednisolone was administered at dose of 1 mg/kg for 1 month, and then the dose was tapered over two months periods. Hb level was normalized (13.4 g/dL) in two months following steroid therapy. Her liver function was completely recovered with normal Hb level nine months after initial presentation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Although rare, AHA is sometimes complicated by hematopoeitc abnormalities, such as AIHA, PRCA, aplastic anemia and hemophagocytic syndrome.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> However, AHA complicated by both AIHA and PRCA is extremely rare and only a few cases have been reported worldwide (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> To our knowledge, this is the fourth case that has been reported in the literatures.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> PRCA is a syndrome characterized by a severe normocytic anemia, reticulocytopenia, and absence of erythroblasts from an otherwise normal bone marrow. It may be present as a primary hematologic disorder or secondary to various diseases like infection including parvovirus and hepatitis virus, collagen vascular disease, leukemia, lymphoma, thymoma and solid tumors.<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> A bone marrow aspirate is usually sufficient to make the diagnosis, but a biopsy may be necessary if the bone marrow smear is not optimal. The typical bone marrow examination shows almost complete absence of erythroid precursors, but normal platelet and white cell precursors.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> To achieve remission, treatment with corticosteroids, cyclophosphamide, cyclosporine A, antithymocyte globulin, splenectomy, and plasmapheresis can be considered. Cortisosteroids are the first choice and prednisone is given orally at a dose of 1 mg/kg/d usually given until remission is induced and can be tapered. In approximately 40% of patients, remission usually occurs within 4 weeks.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></p>
      <p>AIHA is a rare autoimmune condition in which autoantibodies directed toward RBC antigens lead to their accelerated destruction. The diagnosis of AIHA is usually based on the identification of anti-RBC autoantibodies by means of the direct antiglobulin test, and in most cases, reticulocytosis is accompanied.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Corticosteroids are the cornerstone of treatment and splenectomy and rituximab are both good alternatives. In cases of severe anemia, rapid transfusion can be expected to produce beneficial results, despite potential risk of alloimmunization.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p>
      <p>In our case, patient displayed both AIHA and PRCA features simultaneously. Elevated serum lactate dehydrogenase level (1,600 IU/L), positive direct Coombs test, decreased haptoglobin level (&lt;20 mg/dL) and positive hemoglobinuria confirmed the presence of AIHA, and decreased reticulocyte and marked erythroid hypoplasia in bone marrow examination confirmed the presence of PRCA. Patient was previously healthy and had no drug history, negative serology for HBV, HCV, HIV, parvovirus and Epstein-Barr virus and had no evidence of myelodysplastic syndromes, lymphoma and leukemia in bone marrow examination. We were able to rule out hemophagocytic syndrome because the patient didn't have fever, splenomegaly and bicytopenia, and there was no hemophagocytosis in bone marrow.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Based on these findings, the patient was diagnosed with PRCA and AIHA, caused by AHA.</p>
      <p>Corticosteroid is usually the initial treatment choice in both PRCA and AIHA. Hence steroid therapy can be considered initially under this circumstance. The optimal dose and duration are not known in the setting of PRCA and AIHA in AHA patients due to paucity of relevant data. However, steroid may be tried as in PRCA (at a dose of 1 mg/kg/d usually given until remission is induced and tapered), and this approach seems successful in managing PRCA and AIHA in patients with AHA. Although other measures (plasmapheresis, intravenous immunoglobulin, cyclosporine A) have been attempted one case (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), while the other cases, including our case, responded well to steroid therapy.</p>
      <p>In summary, we experienced an AHA patient complicated by both PRCA and AIHA, who was successfully treated with corticosteroids and initial transfusion.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have no conflicts to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>AHA</term>
          <def>
            <p>acute hepatitis A</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>AIHA</term>
          <def>
            <p>autoimmune hemolytic anemia</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ALT</term>
          <def>
            <p>alanine aminotransferase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>AST</term>
          <def>
            <p>aspartate aminotransferase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>Hb</term>
          <def>
            <p>hemoglobin</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MCH</term>
          <def>
            <p>mean corpuscular Hb</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MCV</term>
          <def>
            <p>mean corpuscular volume</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PRCA</term>
          <def>
            <p>pure red cell anemia</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PT</term>
          <def>
            <p>prothrombin time</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>RBC</term>
          <def>
            <p>red blood cells</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>TB</term>
          <def>
            <p>total bilirubin</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>WBC</term>
          <def>
            <p>white blood cell</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jeong</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Current status and vaccine indication for hepatitis A virus infection in Korea</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>331</fpage>
          <lpage>337</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604134</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bae</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rho</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of acute hepatitis a complicated by Guillain-Barre syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Hepatol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>228</fpage>
          <lpage>233</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17585196</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jekarl</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>CW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute hemolysis and renal failure caused by hepatitis A infection with underlying glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Lab Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>188</fpage>
          <lpage>191</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094574</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Woo</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pure red cell aplasia caused by acute hepatitis A</article-title>
          <source>Chonnam Med J</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>53</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22111059</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>DD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeon</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of hemophagocytic syndrome complicated by acute viral hepatitis A infection</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Hepatol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20375646</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>OS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical features of acute viral hepatitis A complicated with acute renal failure</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Hepatol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>166</fpage>
          <lpage>173</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17585190</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ko</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoo</surname>
              <given-names>KD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hyun</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of pleural effusion associated with acute hepatitis A</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>198</fpage>
          <lpage>202</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20357532</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Feldman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friedman</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brandt</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>hepatitis A</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Feldman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friedman</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brandt</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Sleisenger and Fordtran's Gastrointestinal and Liver Disease</source>
          <edition>9th Edition</edition>
          <publisher-loc>PA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>Vol 2</volume>
          <fpage>1282</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
              <given-names>YK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sohn</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nam</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Corticosteroid treatment of pure red cell aplasia in a patient with hepatitis A</article-title>
          <source>Acta Haematol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>128</volume>
          <fpage>60</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22627171</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jeong</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hepatitis A: clinical manifestations and management</article-title>
          <source>Intervirology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          <lpage>19</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20068336</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chehal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharara</surname>
              <given-names>AI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haidar</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haidar</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bazarbachi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute viral hepatitis A and parvovirus B19 infections complicated by pure red cell aplasia and autoimmune hemolytic anemia</article-title>
          <source>J Hepatol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>165</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12076880</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koiso</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ueki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamada</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsukamoto</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karasawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pure red cell aplasia accompanied by autoimmune hemolytic anemia in a patient with type A viral hepatitis</article-title>
          <source>Rinsho Ketsueki</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>424</fpage>
          <lpage>429</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19483404</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sawada</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirokawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujishima</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and management of acquired pure red cell aplasia</article-title>
          <source>Hematol Oncol Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>249</fpage>
          <lpage>259</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19327582</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rossert</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casadevall</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eckardt</surname>
              <given-names>KU</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anti-erythropoietin antibodies and pure red cell aplasia</article-title>
          <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>398</fpage>
          <lpage>406</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14747386</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Michel</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Classification and therapeutic approaches in autoimmune hemolytic anemia: an update</article-title>
          <source>Expert Rev Hematol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>607</fpage>
          <lpage>618</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22077525</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Henter</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horne</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arico</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Egeler</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Filipovich</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imashuku</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>HLH-2004: Diagnostic and therapeutic guidelines for hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>124</fpage>
          <lpage>131</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16937360</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Bone marrow biopsy (A) and aspiration (B) samples showing normocellular, active granulopoiesis with markedly decreased erythroid cells (hematoxylin and eosin stain, &#xD7; 400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cmh-20-204-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Summary of patients with acute hepatitis A complicated by both pure red-cell anemia and autoimmune hemolytic anemia</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cmh-20-204-i001"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>AKI, acute kidney injury; ALT, alanine transaminase; FH, fulminant hepatitis; Hb, hemoglobulin; IVIG, intravenous immunoglobulin; PDL, Prednisolone, TB, total bilirubin.</p>
          <p><sup>*</sup>Time of onset of anemia from time of onset of acute hepatitis.</p>
          <p><sup>&#x2020;</sup>Worst value recorded during the clinical course.</p>
          <p><sup>&#x2021;</sup>Year of publication.</p>
          <p><sup>&#xA7;</sup>Co-infected with Parvovirus B19.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
