<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasite</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasite</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">parasite</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Parasite</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1252-607X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1776-1042</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>EDP Sciences</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26514595</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4626621</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/parasite/2015030</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">parasite150075</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="other">10.1051/parasite/2015030</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Short Note</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Fatal <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection in the giant panda</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="fr">
          <trans-title>Infection fatale &#xE0; <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> chez le panda g&#xE9;ant</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="zh">
          <trans-title>&#x5927;&#x718A;&#x732B;&#x5F13;&#x5F62;&#x866B;&#x81F4;&#x6B7B;&#x6027;&#x611F;&#x67D3;</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ma</surname>
            <given-names>Hongyu</given-names>
          </name>
          <!--<string-name>&#x09a6c;&#x05b8f;&#x05b87;</string-name>-->
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Zedong</given-names>
          </name>
          <!--<string-name>&#x0738b;&#x06cfd;&#x04e1c;</string-name>-->
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Chengdong</given-names>
          </name>
          <!--<string-name>&#x0738b;&#x0627f;&#x04e1c;</string-name>-->
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Caiwu</given-names>
          </name>
          <!--<string-name>&#x0674e;&#x0624d;&#x06b66;</string-name>-->
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Feng</given-names>
          </name>
          <!--<string-name>&#x09b4f;&#x05cf0;</string-name>-->
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Quan</given-names>
          </name>
          <!--<string-name>&#x05218;&#x05168;</string-name>-->
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="FN1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AFF1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>
College of Life Science, Jilin Agricultural University 2888 Xincheng Street Changchun
130118 Jilin Province China
</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="AFF2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>
Key Laboratory of Jilin Province for Zoonosis Prevention and Control, Military Veterinary Institute, Academy of Military Medical Sciences Changchun China
</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="AFF3">
        <label>3</label>
        <addr-line>
China Conservation and Research Center for the Giant Panda Ya&#x2019;an China
</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="FN1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: <email>liuquan1973@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>22</volume>
      <issue-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">parasite/2015/01</issue-id>
      <elocation-id>30</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; H. Ma et al., published by EDP Sciences, 2015</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>H. Ma et al.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>
<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> can infect nearly all warm-blooded animals. We report an acute fatal <italic>T. gondii</italic> infection in the endangered giant panda (<italic>Ailuropoda melanoleuca</italic>) in a zoo in China, characterized by acute gastroenteritis and respiratory symptoms. <italic>T. gondii</italic> infection was confirmed by immunological and molecular methods. Multilocus nested PCR-RFLP revealed clonal type I at the <italic>SAG1</italic> and <italic>c29-2</italic> loci, clonal type II at the <italic>SAG2</italic>, <italic>BTUB</italic>, <italic>GRA6</italic>, <italic>c22-8</italic>, and <italic>L358</italic> loci, and clonal type III at the alternative <italic>SAG2</italic> and <italic>SAG3</italic> loci, thus, a potential new genotype of <italic>T. gondii</italic> in the giant panda. Other possible pathogens were not detected. To our knowledge, this is the first report of clinical toxoplasmosis in a giant panda.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="fr">
        <p>
<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> peut infecter presque tous les animaux &#xE0; sang chaud. Nous rapportons une infection fatale aigu&#xEB; par <italic>T. gondii</italic> chez le panda g&#xE9;ant (<italic>Ailuropoda melanoleuca</italic>), une esp&#xE8;ce en danger, dans un zoo en Chine, caract&#xE9;ris&#xE9;e par une gastro-ent&#xE9;rite aigu&#xEB; et des sympt&#xF4;mes respiratoires. L&#x2019;infection par <italic>T. gondii</italic> a &#xE9;t&#xE9; confirm&#xE9;e par des m&#xE9;thodes immunologiques et mol&#xE9;culaires. La PCR-RFLP nich&#xE9;e a r&#xE9;v&#xE9;l&#xE9; le type clonal I aux loci <italic>SAG1</italic> et <italic>c29-2</italic>, le type clonal II aux loci <italic>SAG2</italic>, <italic>BtuB</italic>, <italic>GRA6</italic>, <italic>c22-8</italic> et <italic>L358</italic>, le type clonal III aux loci alternatifs <italic>SAG2</italic> et <italic>SAG3</italic>, et donc un nouveau g&#xE9;notype potentiel de <italic>T. gondii</italic> chez le panda g&#xE9;ant. Aucun autre agent pathog&#xE8;ne n&#x2019;a &#xE9;t&#xE9; d&#xE9;tect&#xE9;. &#xC0; notre connaissance, ceci est le premier signalement de toxoplasmose clinique chez le panda g&#xE9;ant.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="zh">
        <p>&#x5F13;&#x5F62;&#x866B;&#x80FD;&#x611F;&#x67D3;&#x51E0;&#x4E4E;&#x6240;&#x6709;&#x7684;&#x6E29;&#x8840;&#x52A8;&#x7269;&#x3002;&#x672C;&#x6587;&#x62A5;&#x9053;&#x4E86;&#x4E00;&#x4F8B;&#x53D1;&#x751F;&#x5728;&#x4E2D;&#x56FD;&#x52A8;&#x7269;&#x56ED;&#x7684;&#x6FD2;&#x5371;&#x52A8;&#x7269;&#x5927;&#x718A;&#x732B;&#x6025;&#x6027;&#x81F4;&#x6B7B;&#x6027;&#x5F13;&#x5F62;&#x866B;&#x611F;&#x67D3;&#x75C5;&#x4F8B;&#xFF0C;&#x5176;&#x4E3B;&#x8981;&#x4E34;&#x5E8A;&#x7279;&#x5F81;&#x8868;&#x73B0;&#x4E3A;&#x6025;&#x6027;&#x80C3;&#x80A0;&#x708E;&#x548C;&#x547C;&#x5438;&#x7CFB;&#x7EDF;&#x75C7;&#x72B6;&#x3002;&#x5F13;&#x5F62;&#x866B;&#x611F;&#x67D3;&#x7ECF;&#x514D;&#x75AB;&#x5B66;&#x53CA;&#x5206;&#x5B50;&#x751F;&#x7269;&#x5B66;&#x65B9;&#x6CD5;&#x786E;&#x8BC1;&#x3002;&#x591A;&#x4F4D;&#x70B9;&#x5DE2;&#x5F0F;PCR&#x9650;&#x5236;&#x6027;&#x7247;&#x6BB5;&#x957F;&#x5EA6;&#x591A;&#x6001;&#x6027;&#x5206;&#x6790;&#x8868;&#x660E;&#xFF0C;&#x611F;&#x67D3;&#x5F13;&#x5F62;&#x866B;SAG1&#x548C;c29-2&#x4F4D;&#x70B9;&#x4E3A;I&#x578B;&#xFF0C;SAG2&#xFF0C;BTUB&#xFF0C;GRA6&#xFF0C;c22-8&#x548C;L358&#x4F4D;&#x70B9;&#x4E3A;II&#x578B;&#xFF0C;alternative SAG2&#x548C;SAG3&#x4F4D;&#x70B9;&#x4E3A;III&#x578B;&#xFF0C;&#x663E;&#x793A;&#x5927;&#x718A;&#x732B;&#x611F;&#x67D3;&#x5F13;&#x5F62;&#x866B;&#x53EF;&#x80FD;&#x4E3A;&#x4E00;&#x79CD;&#x65B0;&#x57FA;&#x56E0;&#x578B;&#x3002;&#x672A;&#x68C0;&#x6D4B;&#x5230;&#x53EF;&#x5BFC;&#x81F4;&#x6027;&#x80C3;&#x80A0;&#x708E;&#x548C;&#x547C;&#x5438;&#x7CFB;&#x7EDF;&#x75C7;&#x72B6;&#x7684;&#x5176;&#x5B83;&#x75C5;&#x539F;&#x4F53;&#x3002;&#x8FD9;&#x662F;&#x9996;&#x4F8B;&#x5927;&#x718A;&#x732B;&#x5F13;&#x5F62;&#x866B;&#x611F;&#x67D3;&#x75C5;&#x4F8B;&#x3002;</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Giant panda</kwd>
        <kwd>Genotype</kwd>
        <kwd>PCR</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="17"/>
        <page-count count="4"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Toxoplasmosis, caused by the obligate intracellular protozoan <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>, is an important zoonosis worldwide. It is a major public health concern, mainly because of congenital disease, infection of immunocompromised patients, and an emerging severe form of acquired toxoplasmosis in immunocompetent patients [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The lifecycle of <italic>T. gondii</italic> includes sexual multiplication within cats and asexual multiplication within nearly all warm-blooded animals, including humans [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Humans and animals become infected by eating undercooked or raw meat containing cysts, or by ingesting food or water contaminated with sporulated oocysts.</p>
      <p>The giant panda (<italic>Ailuropoda melanoleuca</italic>) is an emblematic endangered species and regarded as a national treasure and &#x201C;living fossil&#x201D; in China [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Its population is estimated at approximately 1600 in the wild, and the captive population is more than 300 [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The health of giant pandas has attracted global attention. Here, we report an acute fatal <italic>T. gondii</italic> infection in the giant panda in China.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>In February 2014, a seven-year-old giant panda named Jin Yi was found dead at Zhengzhou Zoo, Henan Province, China. The panda did not eat at noon on February 7. On February 8, the panda was found lying in the room with head buried in the abdomen. Treatment measures included intramuscular administration of cephalosporin and intravenous infusion of glucose. The animal had difficulty breathing overnight and was found dead in the morning of February 9.</p>
      <p>A complete necropsy was conducted. Severe pathologic lesions were found, localized to the gastrointestinal tract and lungs. The gastrointestinal tract contained little or no ingesta, had multifocal mucosal hemorrhage, and dry, hard-packed digesta in the duodenum. Lungs were congested and chyme blocked the respiratory tract. Histologically, macrophages containing <italic>T. gondii</italic> tachyzoites were seen in the alveoli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Other lesions included congestion in the intestinal lamina propria and submucosa, gastric epithelial necrosis, and sloughing.</p>
      <p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Many macrophages containing <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> tachyzoites (arrow) in the alveoli, and dilated capillaries (arrowhead) in the alveolar wall. Giant panda lung, hematoxylin-eosin stain.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="parasite-22-30-fig1"/><graphic specific-use="thumbnail" xlink:href="parasite-22-30-fig1_small"/></alternatives></fig>
</p>
      <p>Serum and tissue samples were collected for examination of potential pathogens that may cause hemorrhagic gastroenteritis. The animal had an antibody titer for <italic>T. gondii</italic> of 200 by the modified agglutination test [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. <italic>T. gondii</italic> DNA was detected in the liver, spleen, lungs, kidneys, and small and large intestines by nested PCR targeting the B1 gene [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The immunofluorescence assay (IFA) revealed <italic>T. gondii</italic> tachyzoites present in the lung and small intestine tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), suggesting acute orally acquired toxoplasmosis in the giant panda, probably occurring 7&#x2013;10 days before signs.</p>
      <p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Immunofluorescence assay (IFA) conducted on the frozen tissues using monoclonal antibodies against tachyzoite-specific surface antigen SAG1 showing <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> tachyzoites in the lungs of the giant panda.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="parasite-22-30-fig2"/><graphic specific-use="thumbnail" xlink:href="parasite-22-30-fig2_small"/></alternatives></fig>
</p>
      <p>The positive DNA samples were directly typed by multilocus nested PCR-RFLP (Mn-PCR-RFLP) using 10 genetic markers (<italic>SAG1, SAG2, SAG3, BTUB, GRA6, c22-8, c29-2, L358, PK1,</italic> and <italic>Apico</italic>), and the reference strains, including <italic>GT1, PTG, CTG, MAS, TgCgCa1, TgCatBr5, TgCatBr40, TgCatBr64</italic>, and <italic>TgRsCr1</italic>, were used as positive controls. The results revealed clonal type I at the <italic>SAG1</italic> and <italic>c29-2</italic> loci, clonal type II at the <italic>SAG2</italic>, <italic>BTUB</italic>, <italic>GRA6</italic>, <italic>c22-8</italic>, and <italic>L358</italic> loci, and clonal type III at the alternative <italic>SAG2</italic> and <italic>SAG3</italic> loci, showing a potential new atypical genotype of <italic>T. gondii</italic> in the giant panda. Other potential pathogens, including viruses and bacteria that cause acute gastroenteritis, or respiratory disease, were not detected. These results demonstrated that the giant panda died from acute toxoplasmosis due to a <italic>T. gondii</italic> strain of an atypical genotype.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>
<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> is considered to be one of the most successful eukaryotic pathogens, based on the number of host species and percentage of animals infected worldwide. The consequences of infection with <italic>T. gondii</italic> are associated with the host species and parasite genotypes. Primary infections in adults are mostly asymptomatic, but severe, acute, disseminated toxoplasmosis can occur in immunocompetent hosts when infected with some isolates [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Many <italic>T. gondii</italic> genotypes identified in animals and humans show high genetic diversity of <italic>T. gondii</italic> in China [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In addition to the atypical ToxoDB#9, there are several other atypical <italic>T. gondii</italic> genotypes identified in animals and humans in China 1 [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Atypical <italic>T. gondii</italic> strains have been shown to cause severe clinical disease in immunocompetent hosts [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Despite its taxonomic classification as a carnivore, the giant panda has a diet that is primarily herbivorous, almost exclusively bamboo. The panda still retains decidedly ursine teeth and will eat meat when available [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In addition to bamboo, the captive panda is given some formulated biscuits or other dietary supplements. There are a number of stray cats and small rodents in the zoo, and these animals can freely roam in the habitat of the giant panda. The infection may be obtained by consuming food or water contaminated with sporulated oocysts, or by ingestion of rodents infected with <italic>T. gondii</italic> [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Treatment of the disease should include pyrimethamine plus sulfadiazine. Avoiding consumption of raw or undercooked meat is the main measure recommended to prevent <italic>T. gondii</italic> infection [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This study was supported financially by the International Cooperative Research Project of the Giant Panda (SD0627), the Special Fund for Agro-Scientific Research in the Public Interest (201303042), and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31372430). The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Carme</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Demar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ajzenberg</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dard&#xE9;</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Severe acquired toxoplasmosis caused by wild cycle of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>, French Guiana</article-title>. <source>Emerging Infectious Diseases</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>656</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>658</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19331765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>ZW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huo</surname>
<given-names>XX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Halm-Lai</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hide</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lun</surname>
<given-names>ZR</given-names></string-name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genotyping of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> isolates from cats in different geographic regions of China</article-title>. <source>Veterinary Parasitology</source>, <volume>183</volume>, <fpage>166</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21757292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Elmore</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conrad</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patton</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindsay</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubey</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title><italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>: epidemiology, feline clinical aspects, and prevention</article-title>. <source>Trends in Parasitology</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>190</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20202907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Fernandez-Aguilar</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ajzenberg</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cabezon</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez-Lopez</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Darwich</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubey</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almeria</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Fatal toxoplasmosis associated with an atypical <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> strain in a Bennett&#x2019;s wallaby (<italic>Macropus rufogriseus</italic>) in Spain</article-title>. <source>Veterinary Parasitology</source>, <volume>196</volume>, <fpage>523</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>527</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23523164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>ZD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>XQ</given-names></string-name>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>Diagnosis of toxoplasmosis and typing of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasites &amp; Vectors</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>292</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26017718</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singla</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Vaccines against <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>: status, challenges and future directions</article-title>. <source>Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1305</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1308</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22906945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>A new genotype of <italic>Cryptosporidium</italic> from giant panda (<italic>Ailuropoda melanoleuca</italic>) in China</article-title>. <source>Parasitology International</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>454</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>458</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23810821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Montoya</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liesenfeld</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <year>2004</year>
<source>Toxoplasmosis. Lancet</source>, <volume>363</volume>, <fpage>1965</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1976</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15194258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Qian</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lv</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> strains from stray cats revealed a single genotype in Beijing, China</article-title>. <source>Veterinary Parasitology</source>, <volume>187</volume>, <fpage>408</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22326429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Shwab</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>XQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Majumdar</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pena</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gennari</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubey</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Geographical patterns of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> genetic diversity revealed by multilocus PCR-RFLP genotyping</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>, <volume>141</volume>, <fpage>453</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>461</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24477076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shwab</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>XQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubey</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Moving towards an integrated approach to molecular detection and identification of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>, <volume>137</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19765337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ge</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Prevalence and genetic characterization of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in bats in Myanmar</article-title>. <source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>3526</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23542631</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>PX</given-names></string-name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Habitat assessment of giant panda in Qingmuchuan Nature Reserve, Shaanxi Province of Northwest China</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>206</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>212</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22489501</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>XX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>YG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>XQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>First Report of genotyping of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in free-living <italic>Microtus fortis</italic> in Northeastern China</article-title>. <source>Journal of Parasitology</source>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>692</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>694</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24684624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Pseudogenization of the umami taste receptor gene Tas1r1 in the giant panda coincided with its dietary switch to bamboo</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>2669</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2673</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20573776</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Whole-genome sequencing of giant pandas provides insights into demographic history and local adaptation</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23242367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>LX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>XQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Genetic characterization of <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> isolates from pigs in China</article-title>. <source>Journal of Parasitology</source>, <volume>96</volume>, <fpage>1027</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1029</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20481661</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <notes>
      <boxed-text position="float" orientation="portrait">
        <p>
<bold>Cite this article as</bold>: Ma H, Wang Z, Wang C, Li C, Wei F &amp; Liu Q: Fatal <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection in the giant panda. Parasite, 2015, <bold>22</bold>, 30.</p>
      </boxed-text>
    </notes>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
