<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Med Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Medical Case Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1752-1947</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25495778</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4301566</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3023</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-1947-8-424</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma of the bladder: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Ziouziou</surname>
            <given-names>Imad</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>imad.ziouziou@um5s.net.ma</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Karmouni</surname>
            <given-names>Tariq</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>t.karmouni@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>El khader</surname>
            <given-names>Khalid</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>elkhader@hotmail.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Koutani</surname>
            <given-names>Abdellatif</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>koutani-ab@live.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Iben Attya Andaloussi</surname>
            <given-names>Ahmed</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>ibenattya@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Service d&#x2019;Urologie B, Ibn Sina University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Mohamed V Souissi University, Rabat, Morocco </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <elocation-id>424</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Ziouziou et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2014</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>Lymphoepitheliomas are malignant epithelial tumors of the nasopharynx characterized by an important lymphoid proliferation at histological examination. Lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma is a rare tumor of the bladder for which the therapeutic strategy is not clearly defined.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>We report the case of a 64-year-old Moroccan man who presented with macroscopic hematuria. Investigations revealed a muscle-invasive lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma of the bladder. Therefore he underwent a radical cystoprostatectomy with a good outcome.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>This case illustrates pathogenic, clinical and therapeutic features of this unusual tumor.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Bladder</kwd>
        <kwd>Lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2014</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Lymphoepitheliomas are undifferentiated malignant epithelial tumors of the nasopharynx which are recognized histologically by lymphocytic infiltration suggesting an important malignant lymphoma. Tumors of similar histological type have been described in other sites outside of the nasopharynx (lung, stomach, cervix, skin) and are known as lymphoepithelioma-like carcinomas (LELC). The primary urothelial LELC was described for the first time by Zukerberg <italic>et al.</italic> in 1991 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The LELC is a tumor that rarely reaches the urinary tract: there were only 80 cases reported in the bladder, 10 cases in the ureter, and 7 cases in the renal pelvis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>We report the case of a patient who had a muscle-invasive LELC of the bladder, and review the literature on this rare condition in order to clarify the clinical and therapeutic features.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 64-year-old Moroccan man had a history of chronic smoking and arterial hypertension treated by losartan and hydrochlorothiazide. He reported a hematuria 2 months ago with blood clots in his urine. His physical examination was normal. Ultrasounds revealed an intravesical echogenic image localized at the left-side wall of his bladder measuring 22mm&#xD7;26mm (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p>
      <p>Cystoscopic exploration revealed a solid lesion in the left wall with a large base. A transurethral resection of the bladder tumor was performed. A pathological examination revealed a proliferation of cells with large vesicular nuclei, nucleoli and high mitotic activity. These cells were either arranged in syncytial clusters or isolated within a predominant lymphoid stroma. This proliferation infiltrated (Figures&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) muscle. An immunohistochemical examination (cytokeratin positivity) confirmed the diagnosis of LELC of the bladder (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Echogenic ultrasound image at the left wall of the bladder.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13256_2014_3023_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e291"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Massive tumoral infiltration of the stroma with regular superficial urothelial mucosa: hematein and eosin</bold>
<bold>&#xD7;200.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13256_2014_3023_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e306"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Syncytial clusters of undifferentiated highly vesicular nucleolus nucleus (arrows) cells bathed in abundant lymphoid stroma (*): hematein and eosin</bold>
<bold>&#xD7;200.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13256_2014_3023_Fig3_HTML" id="d30e322"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>
<bold>Massive infiltration of muscle (arrows): hematein and eosin</bold>
<bold>&#xD7;200.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13256_2014_3023_Fig4_HTML" id="d30e337"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>
<bold>Anti-cytokeratin antibody (AE1/AE3): positivity on the coating surface (an arrow), less positivity on the tumor cells (two arrows).</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13256_2014_3023_Fig5_HTML" id="d30e349"/></fig></p>
      <p>Chest and abdominopelvic computed tomography (CT) did not show pelvic lymphadenopathy or secondary location. A radical surgery was then decided without neoadjuvant therapy.</p>
      <p>Cystoprostatectomy with Bricker diversion and lymph node dissection were performed. The postoperative course was uneventful.</p>
      <p>The pathological examination of the surgical specimen revealed no residual tumor lesion and non-invaded lymph nodes (T0 N0).</p>
      <p>After 12 months, the patient was in good condition with normal renal function, and normal chest-abdominopelvic CTs at 6 and 12 months.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>LELC of the bladder were classified as a distinct variant of urothelial carcinomas in the classification of the World Health Organization of urothelial tumors in 2004 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>The lymphoepithelial carcinoma of the nasopharynx is strongly associated with infection with the Epstein&#x2013;Barr virus (EBV). However, no risk factor is known for LELC of the bladder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]; the average age of patients was 65 years with a sex ratio (M:F) of 2:5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Gulley <italic>et al.</italic> looked for the presence of EBV in LELC of the bladder by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization techniques: none of 11 cases had viral DNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>Two cases of post-Bacillus Calmette&#x2013;Gu&#xE9;rin (BCG) therapy LELC have been reported by Gastaud <italic>et al.</italic> and Izquierdo-Garcia <italic>et al.</italic>, suggesting a role of immune system activation after the BCG therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
      <p>The clinical presentation of LELC of the bladder does not differ from that of urothelial carcinomas. It is dominated by macroscopic hematuria and irritative voiding disorders.</p>
      <p>At endoscopy, the tumor is often unifocal, small, and has a polypoid form [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Our case had the same clinical and endoscopic characteristics described in the literature.</p>
      <p>LELC is characterized in its pure form by an undifferentiated epithelial tumor with a significant lymphocytic infiltration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Amin <italic>et al.</italic> subdivided LELC &#x2013; depending on the importance of urothelial carcinoma within the tumor &#x2013; into [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]: pure LELC, predominant LELC (lymphoepithelial component greater than 50%), and focal LELC (lymphoepithelial component less than 50%).</p>
      <p>The predominance of lymphoepithelial component is a good prognostic factor. For some authors, conservative treatment can be achieved even in invasive forms because of their chemosensitivity. Conservative treatment was either endoscopic resection or partial cystectomy followed by adjuvant chemotherapy with cisplatin. Progression-free survival was 47 months as reported by Amin <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. But in this series including 11 patients, only one patient had a predominant LELC form that had chemotherapy with transurethral resection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The number of cases reported and managed by conservative treatment is very low. Most authors recommend radical cystectomy in the case of muscle infiltration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>The pathological form of our case was mixed type, in which two components coexisted: lymphoepithelial which was predominant and urothelial.</p>
      <p>We opt for radical treatment in patients with urothelial tumor infiltrating the muscle T2 with lymphoepithelial component taking into account the low level of evidence advocating conservative treatment.</p>
      <p>Our patient did not have chemotherapy neither neoadjuvant nor adjuvant.</p>
      <p>Serrano <italic>et al.</italic>
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] reported a recurrence-free survival in 87.5% of patients who had a pure form and stages T2 or T3. The prognosis of pure forms is linked to the importance of the inflammatory infiltrate and cytotoxic T lymphocytes for two reasons: early onset of symptoms causing patients to seek care, and strengthening the action of substances used in chemotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Most authors advocate the quasi-systematic use of cisplatin-based chemotherapy as adjuvant treatment after transurethral resection or cystectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. There are even some that offer BCG therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4" sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>LELC is a rare tumor of the bladder with no therapeutic consensus. Radical treatment seems most appropriate for muscle invasive urothelial tumors with LELC component, especially as literature data, advocating conservative treatment regardless of the tumor stage, has a low level of evidence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-list>
          <def-item>
            <term>BCG</term>
            <def>
              <p>Bacillus Calmette&#x2013;Gu&#xE9;rin</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
          <def-item>
            <term>CT</term>
            <def>
              <p>Computed tomography</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
          <def-item>
            <term>EBV</term>
            <def>
              <p>Epstein&#x2013;Barr virus</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
          <def-item>
            <term>LELC</term>
            <def>
              <p>lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma.</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
        </def-list>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>IZ wrote the paper. TK, KEK, AK, and AIAA contributed by correction of this paper. All the authors read and approved the revised manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zukerberg</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>NL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Young</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carcinomas of the urinary bladder simulating malignant lymphoma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>569e76</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2031529</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wen</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>MY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsai</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsai</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lymphoepithelial-like carcinoma of ureter &#x2013; a rare case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Kaohsiung J Med Sci</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>509</fpage>
          <lpage>513</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.kjms.2012.04.010</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974672</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eble</surname>
              <given-names>JNSG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Epstein</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sesterhenn</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>World Health Organization Classification of Tumours. Tumours of the Urinary System and Male Genital Organs</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <publisher-loc>Lyon</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>IARC Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>90e109</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Serrano</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Funez</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crespo</surname>
              <given-names>CV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicolas</surname>
              <given-names>VD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naranjo</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barrilero</surname>
              <given-names>&#xC1;E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carcinoma vesical linfoepiteuoma-like: revision de la literatura y aportacion de un nuevo caso</article-title>
          <source>Arch Esp Urol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>723</fpage>
          <lpage>729</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18705195</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gulley</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amin</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholls</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banks</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayala</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srigley</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eagan</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ro</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epstein-Barr Virus is detected in undifferentiated nasopharyngeal carcinoma but not in lymphoepithelial carcinoma of the urinary bladder</article-title>
          <source>Hum. Pathol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1207</fpage>
          <lpage>1214</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0046-8177(95)90195-7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7590694</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gastaud</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demailly</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guilbert</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colombat</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petit</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Le carcinome lympho&#xE9;pith&#xE9;lial de vessie. Discussion pathog&#xE9;nique</article-title>
          <source>Prog Urol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>318</fpage>
          <lpage>320</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12108352</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Izquierdo-Garcia</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia-Diez</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perez-Rosado</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saez</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suarez-Vilela</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guerreiro-Gonz&#xE1;lez</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lymphoepithelial-like carcinoma of the bladder: three cases with clinico-pathological and p53 protein expression study</article-title>
          <source>Virchows Arch</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>444</volume>
          <fpage>420</fpage>
          <lpage>425</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00428-004-1000-x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15067546</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amin</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ro</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ordonnez</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dinney</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gulley</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayala</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma of the urinary bladder</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>466</fpage>
          <lpage>473</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000478-199405000-00005</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8172321</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tamas</surname>
              <given-names>EF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schoenberg</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Epstein</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lymphoepithelial-like carcinoma of the urinary tract: a clinicopathological study of 30 pure and mixed cases</article-title>
          <source>Mod Pathol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>828</fpage>
          <lpage>834</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/modpathol.3800823</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17541442</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pantelides</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ivaz</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falconer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hazell</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Winkler</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hrouda</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayer</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lymphoepithelial-like carcinoma of the urinary bladder: A case report and review of systemic treatment options</article-title>
          <source>Urol Ann</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0974-7796.91626</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22346102</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fadare</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Renshaw</surname>
              <given-names>IL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rubin</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pleomorphic lymphoepithelioma-like carcinoma of the urinary bladder</article-title>
          <source>Int J Clin Exp Pathol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>194</fpage>
          <lpage>199</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19079656</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
