<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Cardiol Rev</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Curr Cardiol Rev</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CCR</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Current Cardiology Reviews</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1573-403X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1875-6557</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Bentham Science Publishers</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25545802</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4356724</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CCR-11-163</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1573403X1102141224145247</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title> Giant Pulmonary Artery Aneurysm Secondary To Patent Ductus Arteriosus: A Case Report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bezgin</surname>
            <given-names>Tahir</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Demircan</surname>
            <given-names>Hacer C</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kaymaz</surname>
            <given-names>Cihangir</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff><label>*</label>Kartal Ko&#x15F;uyolu Heart &amp; Research Hospital, Cardiology Clinic, 34846 Istanbul, Turkey</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label> Address correspondence to this author at the Kartal Ko&#x15F;uyolu Heart Research Hospital, Denizer Cad. 34846 Cevizli Kartal-&#x130;stanbul, Turkey; Tel: + 90 505 442 47 12; Fax: + 90 216 459 63 21; E-mail: <email xlink:href="bezgintahir3@yahoo.com">bezgintahir3@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>163</fpage>
      <lpage>166</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2015 Bentham Science Publishers</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Bentham Science Publishers</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</uri>), which permits unrestrictive use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aneurysms involving the main pulmonary artery and its branches are rare. Clinical experience is limited, and their management is not well established. We present the case of a 35-year-old male patient with dyspnea and hemoptysis in whom subsequent imaging studies revealed a giant pulmonary artery aneurysm associated with an uncorrected patent ductus arteriosus and Eisenmenger&#x2019;s syndrome. We chose to treat the patient conservatively with medical management due to the development of Eisenmenger&#x2019;s physiology while waiting for heart-lung transplantation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Aneurysms</kwd>
        <kwd>dyspnea</kwd>
        <kwd>hemoptysis</kwd>
        <kwd>pulmonary artery.</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 35-year-old male patient was presented at our outpatient clinic with dyspnea and hemoptysis. His medical history included a cardiac defect diagnosed fifteen years earlier. He did well since then. He had been lost to follow-up until recently, and no imaging study was performed for the patient until he presented with complaints. He remained active and had an acceptable quality of life. He had a history of progressive dyspnea and hemoptysis for 2 years. His physical examination revealed central cyanosis and clubbing, and there was loudness in P2 on auscultation. O2 saturation on room air was 84%. An electrocardiogram showed sinus rhythm with right bundle branch block (Fig. <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref></bold>). Chest radiography revealed cardiomegaly, severe dilation of the main pulmonary artery, and dilation of the pulmonary branch arteries (Fig. <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>). His functional capacity was NYHA class III. Hemoglobin, hematocrit and BNP values were 19 gr/dl, 58% and 986 pg/ml, respectively. Other laboratory parameters were all within normal limits. </p>
      <p>Transthoracic echocardiography showed an aneurysm of the main pulmonary artery of approximately 7.4 cm, dilation in left and right pulmonary arteries, and a turbulent flow between the pulmonary artery and descending aorta with color Doppler (Fig. <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref></bold>-<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">B</xref></bold>). Enlargement of right heart chambers and moderate tricuspid regurgitation were detected. Estimated pulmonary arterial systolic pressure was 110 mmHg. Pulmonary valve, in parasternal long axis, was seen as it were tricuspid aortic valve that was classically observed in parasternal short axis view (Fig. <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref></bold>-<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">B</xref></bold>).</p>
      <p>Contrast-enhanced, multislice computed tomography (CT) with 3 dimensional reconstruction of the patient&#x2019;s chest revealed a giant aneurysm of the pulmonary trunk with a maximum diameter of 79 mm and a patent ductus arteriosus (PDA) (Fig. <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref></bold>-<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">B</xref></bold>). Systolic and mean pulmonary arterial pressures measured during catheterization were 140 and 95 mmHg, respectively. Vasoreactivity testing with adenosine was negative. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Pulmonary artery aneurysm (PAA) is an uncommon disease of the pulmonary vasculature. The underlying causes include congenital heart diseases, pulmonary embolism, trauma, connective tissue disorders (Marfan&#x2019;s syndrome, Ehler-Danlos syndrome), systemic vasculitis, and pulmonary hypertension [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. PDA is the most frequently associated congenital anomaly, followed by ventricular and atrial septal defects [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"> 5</xref>]. Beh&#xE7;et&#x2019;s disease is the most common vasculitic cause of PAA [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>Our patient had a giant main PAA and Eisenmenger&#x2019;s syndrome secondary to PDA. PAAs have high morbidity and mortality due to the thinning of the arterial wall related to increased wall stress and eventual rupture. The formation of an aneurysm in the presence of marked pulmonary artery hypertension suggests that the mechanical stress on the vascular wall which elevates intraluminal pressures outweighs the protective deposition of connective tissue proteins, and the medial smooth muscle cell hypertrophy observed in pulmonary hypertension [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The low pressure condition is much more benign, with low risk of arterial dissection and rupture even for large dilations, which may have diameters of up to 16 cm [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"> 8</xref>]. Although the relationship between aneurysm size and risk of rupture in low-pressure pulmonary artery aneurysms is not well defined, decades without rupture have been observed in some cases [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"> 10</xref>]. In contrast, PAAs secondary to pulmonary arterial hypertension pose a significant risk for the patient; and according to Laplace&#x2019;s law, the size of these aneurysms is an important determinant of progression and rupture [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"> 12</xref>].</p>
      <p>Unfortunately, clear guidelines regarding medical vs surgical management are lacking. Treatment of the low-pressure condition is based more on right ventricular function and associated pulmonary valve stenosis or regurgitation rather than the size of the aneurysm. It is treated primarily by aneurysmorrhaphy or by allograft implantation with or without pulmonary valve replacement [<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"> 13</xref>]. However, if significant pulmonary arterial hypertension or connective tissue disease is present, which increases the risk of rupture, surgical treatment must be considered, particularly in patients with symptoms or progressive changes [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Although a heart-lung transplant is rarely the treatment of choice, it appears to be necessary in the present case with Eisenmenger&#x2019;s syndrome. Conservative treatment is advocated for asymptomatic patients without a causative cardiac lesion and pulmonary hypertension [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"> 15</xref>]. The disadvantage of conservative treatment, however, is the potential for dissection. </p>
      <p>There are many other factors to consider during the treatment decision, including the patient&#x2019;s age, life expectancy, symptoms and functional status. Minimizing the risks for rupture (i.e. pulmonary hypertension) and annual imaging studies, including CT scans, are required to watch for dilation or rupture in asymptomatic subjects. In addition, serial echocardiograms may help to monitor cardiac function and changes in pulmonary hypertension pressures [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, one must be vigilant about symptoms that portend a possible dissection and emergent surgical intervention.</p>
      <p>Our patient had a known prior diagnosis of a cardiac defect, but duration of the pulmonary artery dilation was unknown. A large PAA can cause local compressive symptoms. In many patients a chest radiograph is obtained for unrelated symptoms, which reveals vascular dilation or a hilar/mediastinal mass; and a definitive diagnosis usually requires further radiological evaluation [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Echocardiogram is a reasonable tool for initial investigation due to its ease of use, low cost and convenient accessibility [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Further non-invasive imaging studies such as CT angiography can be used if echocardiography fails to detect an intimal flap, or to provide information related to dissection [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"> 18</xref>].</p>
      <p>In conclusion, we present an adult patient with a giant pulmonary artery aneurysm secondary to untreated PDA leading to Eisenmenger&#x2019;s syndrome. The high risk of acute pulmonary artery dissection and rupture resulting from the progressive enlargement of the aneurysm with concomitant pulmonary artery thrombosis in the setting of Eisenmenger&#x2019;s syndrome dictates treatment by heart-lung transplant, which, our patient currently awaits. While waiting for the heart-lung transplantation, we initiated treatment with bosentan according to the current guidelines to improve symptoms.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <p>Declared none.</p>
    </ack>
    <sec>
      <title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title>
      <p>The authors confirm that this article content has no conflict of interest.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez-Candales</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kleiger</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aleman-Gomez</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kouchoukos</surname>
              <given-names>NT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Botney</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary artery aneurysm review and case report.</article-title>
          <source>Clin Cardiol.</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>738</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8608676</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Durieux</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bletry</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huchon</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wechsler</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chretien</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Godeau</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiple pulmonary arterial aneurysms in Behcet's disease and Hughes-Stovin syndrome.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med.</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>736</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7282759</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mastroroberto</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chello</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zofrea</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Del Negro</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Francesca</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maltese</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary artery aneurysm.</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg.</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>585</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9262632</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coard</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rupture saccular pulmonary artery aneurysm associated with persistent ductus arteriosus.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med.</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1733410</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Butto</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lucas</surname>
              <given-names>RV </given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edwards</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary arterial aneurysm. pathologic study of five cases. </article-title>
          <source>Chest.</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>237</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3802935</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hammad</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Qahtani</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Zahrani</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Huge pulmonary artery aneurysm.</article-title>
          <source>Can Respir J.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>93</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19557216</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Veldtman</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dearani</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warnes</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low pressure giant pulmonary artery aneurysms in the adult natural history and management strategies.</article-title>
          <source>Heart.</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>1067</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12923030</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiu</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Giant aneurysm of main pulmonary artery.</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>272</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8678659</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Imazio</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cecchi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giammaria</surname>
              <given-names>M </given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Main pulmonary artery aneurysm a case report and review of the literature.</article-title>
          <source>Ital Heart J.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>232</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15119508</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>CW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doherty</surname>
              <given-names>JU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kotler</surname>
              <given-names>R </given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary artery aneurysm presenting as a lung mass.</article-title>
          <source>Chest.</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>1164</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7555134</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Senbaklavaci</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaneko</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bartunek</surname>
              <given-names>A </given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rupture and dissection in pulmonary artery aneurysms incidence, cause, and treatment review and case report.</article-title>
          <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg.</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>121</volume>
          <fpage>1006</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11326255</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deterling</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clagett</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aneurysm of the pulmonary artery review of the literature and report of a case.</article-title>
          <source>Am Heart J.</source>
          <year>1947</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>471</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20266464</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kuwaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morishita</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>H </given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical repair of the pulmonary trunk aneurysm.</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>535</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11053813</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vural</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turk</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ata</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goncu</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozyazicioglu</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Idiopathic asymptomatic main pulmonary artery aneurysm surgery or conservative management&#x3BA; A case report.</article-title>
          <source>Heart Surg Form.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>E273</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>van Rens</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westermann</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Postmus</surname>
              <given-names>PE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schramel</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Untreated idiopathic aneurysm of the pulmonary artery; long-term follow-up.</article-title>
          <source>Respir Med.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>404</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10845442</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arnaoutakis</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nwakanma</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Conte</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Idiopathic pulmonary artery aneurysm treated with surgical correction and concomitant coronary artery bypass grafting.</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>273</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19559243</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deb</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zehr</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Idiopathic pulmonary artery aneurysm.</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>1500</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16181901</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khattar</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fox</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alty</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arora</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary artery dissection an emerging cardiovascular complication in surviving patients with chronicpulmonary hypertension.</article-title>
          <source>Heart.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>142</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15657218</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. (1)</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Electrocardiogram showing sinus rhytm, right bundle branch block.
</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="CCR-11-163_F1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. (2)</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Chest radiograph shows cardiomegaly, dilated main and left pulmonary artery with peripheral pruning.
</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="CCR-11-163_F2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Fig. (3)</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) An huge pulmonary artery aneurysm seen in parasternal short axis. (B) A shunt between pulmonary artery and descending aorta
seen with color Doppler.
</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="CCR-11-163_F3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Fig. (4)</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) Moderate degree tricuspit regurgitation with pulmonary arterial systolic pressure 110 mmHg and dilatation in right heart chambers.
(B) Pulmonary valve with three cusps in the parasternal long axis.
</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="CCR-11-163_F4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
      <label>Fig. (5)</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) Contrast enhanced multislice chest CT (B) three-dimensional reconstruction of it revealing diffuse aneurysmal dilatation of the
pulmonary artery and patent ductus arteriosus.
</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="CCR-11-163_F5"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
