<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Cardiovasc Disord</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Cardiovasc Disord</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Cardiovascular Disorders</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2261</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26893167</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4759963</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">228</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12872-016-0228-0</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Prostatic abscess in a patient with ST-elevation myocardial infarction: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8333-2219</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Kadoya</surname>
            <given-names>Yoshito</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+81-0771-86-0220</phone>
            <email>m03020kdy@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kenzaka</surname>
            <given-names>Tsuneaki</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>smile.kenzaka@jichi.ac.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Internal Medicine, Kyotambacho Hospital, Kyotambacho, Kyoto, Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Division of Community Medicine and Career Development, Kobe University Graduate School of Medicine, Kobe, Japan </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <elocation-id>48</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Kadoya and Kenzaka. 2016</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>In patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI), urinary tract infection is the most common infection-related complication. Prostatic abscess in a patient with STEMI is very rare.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>We report the case of a 49-year-old Japanese man who developed fever and shaking chills during hospitalization for STEMI. We initially diagnosed catheter-associated urinary tract infection. However, subsequent contrast-enhanced computed tomography revealed multiple large abscesses in his prostate. We decided to treat with antimicrobial agents alone because the patient was receiving dual-antiplatelet therapy and discontinuation is very high risk for in-stent thrombosis. The patient recovered remarkably after treatment without drainage or surgery.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Here, we described the world&#x2019;s first reported case of prostatic abscess in an immunocompetent patient with STEMI. Early removal of indwelling bladder catheters in patients with STEMI receiving dual-antiplatelet therapy is important to avoid development of prostatic abscess. Furthermore, unnecessary invasive instrumentation should be avoided or limited to diminish the risk of infections.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Prostatic abscess</kwd>
        <kwd>ST-elevation myocardial infarction</kwd>
        <kwd>Catheter-associated urinary tract infection</kwd>
        <kwd>Urinary tract infection</kwd>
        <kwd>Indwelling bladder catheter</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>The infection-related complication rate in patients hospitalized for ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) has been reported to be 16.6&#xA0;% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Urinary tract infection (UTI) is the most common infection-related complication, reported in approximately 6&#xA0;% of patients with STEMI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Risk factors associated with UTI in such patients include urinary tract catheterization and several comorbidities, such as diabetes mellitus and chronic kidney disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Here, we report a rare case of prostatic abscess in an immunocompetent patient hospitalized for STEMI.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 49-year-old Japanese man complaining of chest pain was taken by ambulance to our hospital. His medical history included surgery for inguinal hernia at 45&#xA0;years of age. He also had a history of smoking with a Brinkman index score of 300. Electrocardiography showed ST elevation in leads V2-5. Cardiac biomarkers were also elevated as following: high sensitive Troponin I, 0.067&#xA0;ng/ml (standard value: 0.00&#x2013;0.03&#xA0;ng/ml). Based on these findings, we diagnosed STEMI, and performed emergent coronary angiography, which showed occlusion of the left anterior descending artery (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a, b</xref>). Thus, we performed emergent percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). After surgery, the patient was moved to the intensive care unit with an indwelling bladder catheter, where he recovered without any acute complications.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Coronary angiogram of left coronary artery. <bold>a</bold> Right anterior oblique (RAO)-Caudal view, pre-percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI), (<bold>b</bold>) Anteroposterior (AP)-Cranial view, pre-PCI, (<bold>c</bold>) AP-Cranial view, post-PCI. Red arrows are culprit lesion</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12872_2016_228_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>Three days after PCI, the patient developed fever and shaking chills. He had a body temperature of 39.2&#xA0;&#xB0;C, blood pressure of 103/68&#xA0;mmHg, regular pulse rate of 103 beats/min, respiratory rate of 18 breaths/min, and oxygen saturation of 97&#xA0;% (without oxygen administration). His heart and breath sounds were normal, and his abdomen was soft and flat with no tenderness. There was no skin rash, and joint findings were normal. Laboratory data at onset of fever and shaking chills are shown in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Notably, he had a white blood cell count of 13,760 cells/mm<sup>3</sup>, hemoglobin level of 12.4&#xA0;g/dL, and C-reactive protein level of 8.29&#xA0;mg/dL. Cardiac enzymes were still elevated due to the STEMI, but were returning toward normal. Chest radiography showed no infiltrative shadows (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Urinary Gram staining revealed middle-sized gram-negative rods that were phagocytized by leukocytes. We initially diagnosed catheter-associated UTI. Blood and urine cultures were performed, his indwelling bladder catheter was removed, and he was initially administered intravenous (IV) cefmetazole (1&#xA0;g every 8&#xA0;h). The fever was brought down temporarily, but fever developed again at 4&#xA0;days after starting the antimicrobial agent. In addition, micturition and pain while urinating persisted. Blood and urine cultures were both positive for <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>. We suspected abscess formation, and performed contrast-enhanced computed tomography, which showed multiple large abscesses in his prostate (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Laboratory data at onset of fever and shaking chills</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Parameter</th><th>Recorded value</th><th>Standard value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>White blood cell count</td><td>13.76&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10^9 /L</td><td>4.00&#x2013;7.50&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10^9 /L</td></tr><tr><td>Hemoglobin</td><td>12.4&#xA0;g/dL</td><td>11.3&#x2013;15.2&#xA0;g/dL</td></tr><tr><td>Hematocrit</td><td>37&#xA0;%</td><td>36&#x2013;45&#xA0;%</td></tr><tr><td>Platelet</td><td>184&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10^9 /L</td><td>130&#x2013;350&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10^9 /L</td></tr><tr><td>C-reactive protein</td><td>8.29&#xA0;mg/dL</td><td>&#x2266;0.14&#xA0;mg/dL</td></tr><tr><td>Total protein</td><td>6.2&#xA0;g/dL</td><td>6.9&#x2013;8.4&#xA0;g/dL</td></tr><tr><td>Albumin</td><td>3.4&#xA0;g/dL</td><td>3.9&#x2013;5.1&#xA0;g/dL</td></tr><tr><td>Total bilirubin</td><td>0.8&#xA0;mg/dL</td><td>0.4&#x2013;1.5&#xA0;mg/dL</td></tr><tr><td>Aspartate aminotransferase</td><td>72 U/L</td><td>11&#x2013;30 U/L</td></tr><tr><td>Alanine aminotransferase</td><td>41 U/L</td><td>4&#x2013;30 U/L</td></tr><tr><td>Lactate dehydrogenase</td><td>402 U/L</td><td>109&#x2013;216 U/L</td></tr><tr><td>Alkaline phosphatase</td><td>192 U/L</td><td>107&#x2013;330 U/L</td></tr><tr><td>&#x3B3;-glutamyltranspeptidase</td><td>19 U/L</td><td>&lt;70&#xA0;IU/L</td></tr><tr><td>Creatinine</td><td>0.79&#xA0;mg/dL</td><td>0.63&#x2013;1.03&#xA0;mg/dL</td></tr><tr><td>Sodium</td><td>137&#xA0;mEq/L</td><td>136&#x2013;148&#xA0;mEq/L</td></tr><tr><td>Potassium</td><td>4.1&#xA0;mEq/L</td><td>3.6&#x2013;5.0&#xA0;mEq/L</td></tr><tr><td>Glucose</td><td>113&#xA0;mg/dl</td><td>70&#x2013;109&#xA0;mg/dl</td></tr><tr><td>B-type natriuretic peptide</td><td>107&#xA0;pg/mL</td><td>&lt;20&#xA0;pg/mL</td></tr><tr><td>Urinary protein</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>Urinary occult blood</td><td>+++</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>Urinary nitrite</td><td>+</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>Urinary white blood cell</td><td>20&#x2013;29/high-power field</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>Urinary red blood cell</td><td>50&#x2013;99/high-power field</td><td>-</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Chest radiograph, showing no infiltrative shadows</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12872_2016_228_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Contrast-enhanced computed tomography scan, revealing multiple large prostatic abscesses (red arrows). In sequence from (<bold>a</bold>) to (<bold>d</bold>), the images are sliced from the head side to the foot side</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12872_2016_228_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>After consulting a urology specialist about drainage or surgical treatment, we decided to treat with antimicrobial agents alone because the patient was receiving dual-antiplatelet therapy and discontinuation is very high risk for in-stent thrombosis. We administered IV meropenem (1&#xA0;g every 12&#xA0;h) and amikacin (200&#xA0;mg every 12&#xA0;h) for 2&#xA0;days, and then changed to levofloxacin (750&#xA0;mg per day) based on drug sensitivity. Blood cultures were negative on the 10th day after onset of fever and shaking chills, while contrast-enhanced computed tomography showed the abscess was decreasing on the 17th day. The patient was discharged on the 27th day of hospitalization. He had in total 6&#xA0;weeks of antimicrobial therapy, and showed remarkable recovery. We continue to see this patient regularly at our clinic, and he has been in good health for more than 3&#xA0;years.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We experienced a case of prostatic abscess in a patient hospitalized for STEMI. In such patients, UTI is a frequent complication, whereas prostatic abscess is very rare. To the best of our knowledge, this is the world&#x2019;s first reported case of prostatic abscess in an immunocompetent patient with STEMI.</p>
      <p>Prostatic abscess is thought to occur as a consequence of inadequately treated acute bacterial prostatitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In recent years, prostatic abscess has rarely been reported due to the widespread use of antibacterial agents. Furthermore, it has been noted that only 2.7&#xA0;% of cases of acute bacterial prostatitis will develop into prostatic abscess [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Based on the fact that acute bacterial prostatitis is diagnosed in approximately 0.5 to 2.5&#xA0;% of patients with prostate symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], we can assume that prostatic abscess accounts for a very small percentage of all UTIs.</p>
      <p>The most common pathogen associated with prostatic abscess is <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. However, unusual pathogens, such as <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, and <italic>Candida,</italic> also have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Prostatic abscess usually occurs in immunosuppressed patients with such conditions as diabetes mellitus, chronic renal failure, hemodialysis, cancer, cirrhosis, or human immunodeficiency virus infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Other predisposing factors include indwelling bladder catheter, instrumentation of the lower urinary tract, bladder outlet obstruction, and biopsy of the prostate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In the present case, the patient was not immunosuppressed. Therefore, the indwelling bladder catheter at the time of emergent PCI for STEMI was recognized as the main cause of his prostatic abscesses.</p>
      <p>Currently, drug-eluting stents are commonly used in PCI for acute myocardial infarction. Such patients should receive dual-antiplatelet therapy after drug-eluting stent implantation. In the present case, prostatic abscess drainage, which should be done in many cases, was not performed because the patient was receiving dual-antiplatelet therapy. Because patients who undergo PCI usually receive dual-antiplatelet therapy, they have a higher risk of hemorrhagic complications with drainage or surgical treatment for an abscess. Thus, it is important to avoid unnecessary indwelling bladder catheters, or to promptly remove those that are no longer required, so that patients can avoid development of prostatic abscess. Furthermore, for all the patients, unnecessary invasive instrumentation should be avoided or limited as much as possible to diminish the risk of infections.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>In conclusion, we described the world&#x2019;s first reported case of prostatic abscess in an immunocompetent patient STEMI. Such patients usually have a higher risk with drainage due to receiving dual-antiplatelet therapy. Early removal of indwelling bladder catheters is important to avoid development of prostatic abscess. Unnecessary invasive instrumentation should be avoided or limited to diminish the risk of infections.</p>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Consent</title>
        <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this Case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor of this journal.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>IV</term>
          <def>
            <p>intravenous</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PCI</term>
          <def>
            <p>percutaneous coronary intervention</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>STEMI</term>
          <def>
            <p>ST-elevation myocardial infarction</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>UTI</term>
          <def>
            <p>urinary tract infection</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>Both authors have no financial interests to disclose and no competing interest to declare.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>YK: Clinical management of the case, manuscript redaction and correction. TK: Manuscript redaction and correction. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <p>None.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nash</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strom</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pathak</surname>
              <given-names>EB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence of major infections and adverse outcomes among hospitalized ST-elevation myocardial infarction patients in Florida, 2006</article-title>
          <source>BMC Cardiovac Disord</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2261-11-69</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kravchick</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cytron</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agulansky</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ben-Dor</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute prostatitis in middle-aged men: a prospective study</article-title>
          <source>BJU Int</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>93</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1464-410X.2004.04642.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14678376</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Millan-Rodriguez</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palou</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bujons-Tur</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Musquera-Felip</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sevilla-Cecilia</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Serrallach-Orejas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute bacterial prostatitis: two different sub-categories according to a previous manipulation of the lower urinary tract</article-title>
          <source>World J Urol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00345-005-0040-4</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16437219</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Granados</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riley</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salvador</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vincente</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prostatic abscess: diagnosis and treatment</article-title>
          <source>J Urol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>148</volume>
          <fpage>80</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1613887</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weinberger</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cytron</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Servadio</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Block</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pitlik</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prostatic abscess in the antibiotic era</article-title>
          <source>Rev Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>49</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/clinids/10.2.239</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3287559</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vandover</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalawari</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prostatic abscess</article-title>
          <source>J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>e83</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jemermed.2008.08.022</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19157756</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrade</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Porto</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Filho</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vinhaes</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of prostatic abscess</article-title>
          <source>Int Braz J Urol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1677-55382003000100006</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15745464</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trauzzi</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kay</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaufman</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lowe</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of prostatic abscess in patients with human immunodeficiency syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Urology</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>629</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0090-4295(94)90176-7</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8165764</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rim</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prostatic abscess caused by community-acquired methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>
          <source>Int J Urol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>536</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1442-2042.2011.02774.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21615798</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ko</surname>
              <given-names>YT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment of prostatic abscess: value of transrectal ultrasonographically guided needle aspiration</article-title>
          <source>J Ultrasound Med</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>609</fpage>
          <lpage>17</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10972557</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
