<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <?properties manuscript?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">7603616</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">4036</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int. J. Radiat. Oncol. Biol. Phys.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International journal of radiation oncology, biology, physics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0360-3016</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1879-355X</issn>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26581148</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4708077</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2015.08.048</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">NIHMS748715</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Radiation Sensitivity and Radiation Necrosis in the Short Telomere Syndromes</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stanley</surname>
            <given-names>Susan E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>BS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rao</surname>
            <given-names>Avani Dholakia</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gable</surname>
            <given-names>Dustin L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>BS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>McGrath-Morrow</surname>
            <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">&#x2021;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Armanios</surname>
            <given-names>Mary</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">&#xA7;</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>*</label>Department of Oncology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>&#x2020;</label>Department of Radiation Oncology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>&#x2021;</label>Department of Pediatrics, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>&#xA7;</label>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Reprint requests to: Mary Armanios, MD, 1650 Orleans St, Cancer Research Bldg 1, Rm 186, Baltimore, MD 21287. Tel: (410) 502-3817; <email>marmani1@jhmi.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>93</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>1115</fpage>
      <lpage>1117</lpage>
      <!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2015.08.048-->
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p id="P1">We report radiation necrosis as the first manifestation of a germline mutation in telomerase. A 60-year-old woman presented with defective wound healing after multiple surgical explorations of the chest wall to exclude breast cancer recurrence. At age 42, she received a diagnosis of stage I estrogen receptor&#x2013;positive left breast infiltrating ductal carcinoma on routine mammography. Lumpectomy with axillary node dissection revealed T1N0 disease. Her adjuvant radiation therapy consisted of 50.4 Gy in 28 fractions followed by a 10-Gy boost in 5 fractions to the tumor bed. She did well for 12 years, when a left rib fracture was incidentally noted on imaging. This prompted multiple needle biopsies which showed atypia but no malignancy. Open surgical biopsy revealed the anterior ribs within the radiation field were replaced with soft tissue, but no malignancy was found. The postoperative course was complicated by multiple wound infections requiring surgical debridement and failed healing of skin grafts left her with an open chest wall wound (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p>
    <p id="P2">She was evaluated at our center for a second opinion. Computed tomography (CT) imaging showed fractured left ribs and chest wall abnormalities consistent with radiation necrosis. In addition, in the contralateral lung, there was basilar honeycombing characteristic of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A and B</xref>). Family history revealed 2 siblings who died from IPF and myelodysplastic syndrome, a complex pathognomonic for the diagnosis of a short telomere syndrome (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Genetic evaluation revealed a deleterious mutation in the telomerase RNA gene, <italic>TR</italic>, that was also found in her siblings (n.80, T&gt;A). The mutation predicted disruption of the essential pseudoknot domain of TR and was associated with short telomere length, below the age-adjusted 10th percentile (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Additional chest wall reconstruction was deferred given the known risk of respiratory failure after anesthesia and elective surgery in IPF patients (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). During the subsequent year, her wound improved with conservative care, but she developed worsening respiratory symptoms, and subsequently died cancer-free from end-stage lung disease.</p>
    <p id="P3">In order to test whether short telomeres may predispose to radiation sensitivity, we used a modified cell survival assay that is used in the diagnosis of double-strand break syndromes such as ataxia-telangiectasia (A-T) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). We examined lymphoblastoid cells derived from 7 other telomerase and telomere gene mutation carriers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Four of the carriers were asymptomatic, 2 had IPF, and 1 had bone marrow failure. Cells from these subjects showed significantly compromised survival compared to controls and were similarly sensitive to A-T on average (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D and E</xref>). In 3 of 7 cases (43%), the surviving fraction at 1 Gy fell at or below 21%, a threshold considered to be diagnostic of A-T in some settings (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Neither the age nor the extent of the telomere defect predicted the 1-Gy surviving fraction.</p>
    <p id="P4">Radiation sensitivity and radiation necrosis are rare complications of radiation therapy, but they are well documented in patients with defective DNA doublestrand break repair such as A-T (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The data we show here indicate that patients with short telomere syndromes are similarly sensitive to radiation. To our knowledge, this is the first report of radiation necrosis in a telomerase mutation carrier. Sensitivity to radiation in the setting of telomere length abnormalities was first documented in telomerase null mice with short telomeres (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), and our data highlight the relevance of these observations in clinical settings.</p>
    <p id="P5">Syndromes marked by short telomeres manifest as IPF, emphysema, and aplastic anemia (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Mutations in telomere and telomerase genes are the most common cause of familial pulmonary fibrosis cases, accounting for one-third of cases (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>); they also rival alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency as a risk factor for emphysema (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Short telomere syndrome patients most often present in mid-to-late adulthood and have no associated dysmorphic features. A cancer diagnosis is estimated to affect up to 10% of severe cases, such as in dyskeratosis congenita, and predominantly manifests as myelodysplasia-acute myeloid leukemia and, more rarely, squamous cell head and neck carcinomas (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). There are sparse data regarding cancer treatment outcomes in this population. After bone marrow transplantation, pulmonary fibrosis is a nearly uniform complication, and lung shielding has evolved as a standard to minimize this risk (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Awareness of this genetic diagnosis is important in clinical settings, where ionizing radiation is used such as in assessing the risk of X ray&#x2013;based imaging as a screening tool in pulmonary fibrosis, as well as in a preference for radiation-sparing regimens in hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Patients suspected of having telomere syndromes and who have a personal or family history of IPF-emphysema, especially, or myelodysplastic syndrome, should be identifiable by telomere length measurement combined with genetic testing.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack id="S1">
      <p id="P6">This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grant (RO1 CA160433), the Ataxia-Telangiectasia Children&#x2019;s Group, and Common-wealth Foundation (M.A.).</p>
      <p id="P7">We are grateful to the subjects who volunteered for this research, and Ms. Jenny Wright from the Johns Hopkins Ataxia-Telengiectasia Clinic.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="conflict">
        <p id="P8">Conflict of interest: none.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Becker-Catania</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chun</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Early diagnosis of ataxia-telangiectasia using radiosensitivity testing</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <fpage>724</fpage>
          <lpage>731</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12072877</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alder</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qi</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Syndrome complex of bone marrow failure and pulmonary fibrosis predicts germline defects in telomerase</article-title>
          <source>Blood</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>5607</fpage>
          <lpage>5611</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21436073</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghatol</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruhl</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Danoff</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Exacerbations in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis triggered by pulmonary and nonpulmonary surgery: A case series and comprehensive review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Lung</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>190</volume>
          <fpage>373</fpage>
          <lpage>380</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22543997</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A dominant mutation in human rad51 reveals its function in DNA interstrand crosslink repair independent of homologous recombination</article-title>
          <source>Mol Cell</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>478</fpage>
          <lpage>490</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26253028</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gotoff</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amirmokri</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liebner</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ataxia telangiectasia. Neoplasia, untoward response to x-irradiation, and tuberous sclerosis</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dis Child</source>
          <year>1967</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>617</fpage>
          <lpage>625</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6072741</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>KK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiler</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Telomere dysfunction impairs DNA repair and enhances sensitivity to ionizing radiation</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10973255</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stanley</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armanios</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The short and long telomere syndromes: Paired paradigms for molecular medicine</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26232116</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stanley</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Podlevsky</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Telomerase mutations in smokers with severe emphysema</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <fpage>563</fpage>
          <lpage>570</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25562321</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alter</surname>
              <given-names>BP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giri</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Savage</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cancer in dyskeratosis congenita</article-title>
          <source>Blood</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>6549</fpage>
          <lpage>6557</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19282459</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dietz</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orchard</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baker</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Disease-specific hematopoietic cell transplantation: Nonmyeloablative conditioning regimen for dyskeratosis congenita</article-title>
          <source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>98</fpage>
          <lpage>104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383216</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p id="P9">Clinical features and cell survival of cells with short telomeres after irradiation. (A) Nonhealing open, left anterior chest wall wound (arrow) after open biopsy and failed grafts. (B) Basilar honeycombing typical of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (arrows). (C) Telogram shows telomere length of mutation carriers relative to that of age-matched controls (n = 192). Telomeres were measured in peripheral blood lymphocytes by flow cytometry and fluorescence in situ hybridization. Labels indicate the mutant telomere gene in each case. Red circles refer to individuals whose lymphoblastoid cell lines were studied in vitro (D and E). (D) Dose response curve shows the surviving fraction of cells at each dose of ionizing radiation. Data are means from each group of controls, short telomeres, and ataxia telengiectasia (A-T) cells. Each cell line was assayed in quadruplicate, and the experiment was replicated independently. (E) Individual data points for each case at 1 Gy, a threshold which has been shown to be useful in the diagnosis of DNA double-strand break syndromes (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Error bars refer to standard error of the mean. *<italic>P</italic>&lt;.05, **<italic>P</italic>&lt;.01, and ***<italic>P</italic>&lt;.001, two-sided comparison of differences in surviving fractions relative to those of controls (Student <italic>t</italic> test; GraphPad Prism software). ns = nonsignificant <italic>P</italic> value.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="nihms748715f1"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
