<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26245481</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4527251</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">651</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12957-015-0651-1</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Epidermoid cyst with unusual magnetic resonance characteristics and spinal extension</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lim</surname>
            <given-names>Jaejoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>Kyunggi</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>82-31-780-5688</phone>
            <email>sandori50@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Department of Neurosurgery, Bundang CHA Medical Center, CHA University College of Medicine, Yatap-dong 59, Seongnam, 463-712 South Korea </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>7</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>7</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <elocation-id>240</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Lim and Cho. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Intracranial epidermoid cysts are generally located in the cerebellopontine and parasellar areas and appear hypo-dense on computed tomography and hypo-intense on T1-weighted magnetic resonance imaging. We report a case of an unusual epidermoid cyst of the cerebellopontine angle extending into the upper cervical canal that appeared hyper-dense on computed tomography scanning, hyper-intense on T1-weighted magnetic resonance (MR) images, and hypo-intense on T2-weighted MR images.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Epidermoid cyst</kwd>
        <kwd>Magnetic resonance image</kwd>
        <kwd>Cervical spine extension</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Epidermoid tumors represent remnants of ectodermal tissues misplaced during embryogenesis and account for approximately 0.3 to 1.8&#xA0;% of intracranial tumors. They are most common in the cerebellopontine angle and suprasellar and parasellar regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Intracranial epidermoid cysts generally appear as well-defined lobulated hypo-dense masses on computed tomography (CT) scan. On magnetic resonance (MR) studies, they typically appear hypo-intense on T1-weighted and hyper-intense on T2-weighted images [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Occasionally, they may appear hyper-dense on CT scans and hyper-intense on T1-weighted MR images [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. We report a case of epidermoid cyst which showed hyper-intensity on T1-weighted MR images with upper cervical extension.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 46-year-old man presented with tingling sensation and numbness on both lower extremities. CT showed hyper-dense masses in both cerebellopontine areas. In the preoperative MR image, a well-defined, lobulated mass with a size of about 5.6&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.7&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;6.1&#xA0;cm is seen in the pons to the medulla area with several internal septae. The mass showed hyper-intensity on T1-weighted, hypo-intensity on T2-weighted, and hypo-intensity on diffusion-weighted images. This lesion shows no gadolinium contrast enhancement. The superior portion of this cystic lesion compressed the lower portion of the pons. The inferior portion of the lesion extended to the posterior and was surrounding the medulla, extending to the C1-C2 intervertebral level (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a&#x2013;e</xref>). A grossly subtotal surgical resection was done through the minimal lateral supraorbital approach (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f&#x2013;j</xref>). In the operation field, a shiny multi-lobulated cystic mass was seen on the cerebellopontine angle (Fig&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The trigeminal nerve and seventh and eighth nerves were surrounded by the tumor. The cyst was filled with keratinous debris arranged in laminated layers. On histopathological examination, the cysts were thin-walled and lined by stratified squamous epithelium. Cystic contents included debris and keratin materials (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Based on these histopathological characteristics, the patient was diagnosed with an epidermoid cyst. The patient&#x2019;s postoperative clinical course was uneventful, and neurological symptoms were improved. After the operation, the remnant cystic mass gradually decreased. In 15-month follow-up MR images, the remnant cyst mass completely disappeared (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1k&#x2013;o</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Preoperative and postoperative MR imaging. In the preoperative MR image, a well-defined, lobulated mass with a size of about 5.6&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.7&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;6.1&#xA0;cm is seen in front of the pons to the medulla with several internal septae. The mass showed hyper-intensity on T1-weighted, hypo-intensity on T2-weighted, and hypo-intensity on diffusion-weighted images. The superior portion of this cystic lesion compresses the lower portion of the pons. The inferior portion of the lesion extends posteriorly and is surrounding the medulla, extending to the C1-C2 intervertebral level (<bold>a</bold>&#x2013;<bold>e</bold>). Postoperative MR imaging after a grossly subtotal surgical resection was done through the minimal lateral supraorbital approach (<bold>f</bold>&#x2013;<bold>j</bold>). In the 15-month follow-up MR images, the remnant cyst mass completely disappeared (<bold>k</bold>&#x2013;<bold>o</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2015_651_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Operation images. <bold>a</bold> The trigeminal nerve (V2) and the petrous bone were exposed. <bold>b</bold> ,<bold>c</bold> The tumor in the anterior cerebellopontine area was seen. <bold>d</bold> The tumor was subtotally removed</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2015_651_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Pathologic examination. The cysts were thin-walled and lined by stratified squamous epithelium. Cystic contents included debris and keratin materials (H&amp;E, &#xD7;100)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2015_651_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>Epidermoid tumors are rare congenital lesions originating from the ectoderm that constitute 0.3 to 1.8&#xA0;% of all intracranial neoplasms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Intracranial epidermoid cysts are considered to arise from epithelial inclusions at the time of neural tube closure or during formation of the secondary cerebral vesicles, and have slow growth rates resembling that of the normal epidermis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>Pathologically, epidermoid cysts have well-circumscribed, irregular, thin walls with squamous epithelium lining. The epithelium undergoes progressive desquamation and keratin breakdown; therefore, the cystic contents include tissue debris, keratin, water, and solid cholesterol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>The typical imaging appearance is homogenous non-enhanced hypo-dense on CT, hypo-intense on T1-weighted MR imaging, and hyper-intense on T2-weighted and diffusion-weighted imaging. The CT density of the epidermoid cyst is usually between &#x2212;2 and +10 Hounsfield units (HU) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. These findings could be attributed to the lipid components and cholesterol. MR signals depend on the relative composition of cholesterol and keratin of the cystic contents. Generally, cholesterol in an epidermoid is in a solid state and appears hypo-intense on T1-weighted images. However, it occasionally presents as hyper-dense lesions on CT, making the diagnosis more difficult. Atypical intracranial epidermoid cysts show a hyper-dense signal on CT and hyper-intense signal on T1-weighted imaging as has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The suggested causes of the hyper-intensity on T1-weighted images include high protein concentration, mild calcification, and paramagnetic effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. According to Ahmadi et al., a protein level of 9.0&#xA0;g or greater per 100&#xA0;mL can increase the signal intensity of the cystic fluid on T1-weighted MR images [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Nagashima et al. also examined the total protein concentration of cystic fluid (15&#xA0;g/dl) and suggested that the highly proteinaceous contents of the cyst contributed to the hyper-density [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The hyper-density could be attributed to the calcification of the keratinized debris and saponification of debris to calcium and also can be attributable to traumatic or spontaneous intracystic microbleeding, abundance of polymorphonuclear leukocytes, and deposition of ferrocalcium complex or iron-containing pigment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>The treatment of choice for epidermoid cyst is a total resection of the tumor. But sometimes total resection is impossible because of anatomical complexity. This tumor was fortunately dissected easily from the adjacent structures. But we could not remove all of the tumor because of the long distance from the surgical field, not due to tumor adhesion. So some part of the tumor was left behind at the right upper cervical level. We periodically followed up the patient, and fortunately, the remnant lesion completely disappeared.</p>
      <p>The 46-year-old man in our report suffered tingling sensation and numbness on both lower extremities. CT showed hyper-dense masses in both cerebellopontine areas which extended to the C1-C2 intervertebral level. The mass was hyper-intense on T1-weighted and hypo-intense on T2-weighted images.</p>
      <p>The cerebellopontine angle is the most common site of the epidermoid tumors, followed by the prepontine, suprasellar, and parasellar cisterns in order. It is less frequently located in the parasellar region and the medial cranial fossa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, intracranial epidermoid tumors with extension into the upper cervical spinal canal are rare. There are only five such cases reported previously (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Of the five reported cases, only one had atypical hyper-intensity on T1-weighted images and hypo-intensity on T2-weighted images with upper cervical extension. The reason for the unusual downward extension into the upper cervical canal remains unclear. One possibility is that the cistern is anatomically narrower at the lower portion than at the upper portion of the posterior fossa, which would encourage inferior extension. Another possibility is that these tumors tend to spread in the direction of the main flow of the cerebrospinal fluid at the base of the posterior fossa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Reported intracranial epidermoid tumors with extension into the spinal canal</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Author (year)</th><th>Age</th><th>Sex</th><th>Main location</th><th>Extension level</th><th>MR signal</th><th>Surgical removal</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>MacCarty et al. (1959) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td><td>24</td><td>F</td><td>Rt. CP angle</td><td>Upper cervical</td><td>N/A</td><td>Subtotal</td></tr><tr><td>Keville and Wise (1959) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>62</td><td>Not reported</td><td>Fourth ventricle</td><td>Upper cervical</td><td>N/A</td><td>Partial</td></tr><tr><td>Ishii et al. (1983) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td>53</td><td>M</td><td>Pontine</td><td>Upper cervical</td><td>N/A</td><td>Subtotal</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Hasegawa et al. (1989) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">61</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">Rt. CP angle</td><td rowspan="2">C1-C2 intervertebral level</td><td>T2W SE: hyper-intensity</td><td rowspan="2">Subtotal</td></tr><tr><td>IR: hypo-intensity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Teo et al. (2006) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">27</td><td rowspan="2">F</td><td rowspan="2">Lt. CP angle</td><td rowspan="2">C2 level</td><td>T1W SE: hyper-intensity</td><td rowspan="2">Subtotal</td></tr><tr><td>T2W SE: hypo-intensity</td></tr><tr><td>Present case</td><td>46</td><td>M</td><td>Both CP angles</td><td>C1-C2 intervertebral level</td><td/><td>Subtotal</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We report a case of epidermoid cyst that displayed hyper-intensity on T1-weighted MR images with upper cervical extension. We think the reason for the unusual downward extension into the upper cervical canal is related to the anatomical structure of the cistern and flow of the cerebrospinal fluid.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>CT</term>
          <def>
            <p>computed tomography</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MR</term>
          <def>
            <p>magnetic resonance</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>JL and KC have made substantial contributions to the conception and design of the study, acquisition of data, and analysis and interpretation of data; have been involved in the drafting of the manuscript and its critical revision for important intellectual content; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. Both authors had participated sufficiently in the work to take public responsibility for appropriate portions of the content and have given final approval of the version to be published.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; information</bold>
        </p>
        <p>JL, M.D. (first author) is a Clinical Assistant Professor at the Department of Neurosurgery, Bundang CHA Medical Center, CHA University College of Medicine, Seongnam, South Korea. KC, M.D., PhD. (corresponding author) is the Chief Professor at the Department of Neurosurgery, Bundang CHA Medical Center, CHA University College of Medicine, Seongnam, South Korea.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Acknowledgements</bold>
        </p>
        <p>Doctor Sang-Yeon Park has provided the information on histopathological examination of this case.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kato</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ujiie</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Higa</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayashi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kubo</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okada</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical presentation of intracranial epidermoids: a surgical series of 20 initial and four recurred cases</article-title>
          <source>Asian J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028741</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Toglia</surname>
              <given-names>JU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Netsky</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alexander</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epithelial (epidermoid) tumors of the cranium. Their common nature and pathogenesis</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1965</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>384</fpage>
          <lpage>93</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/jns.1965.23.4.0384</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5853888</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahktar</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delgado</surname>
              <given-names>PN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lowe</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging and proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy of intracranial epidermoid tumors</article-title>
          <source>Crit Rev Comput Tomogr</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>5&#x2013;6</issue>
          <fpage>389</fpage>
          <lpage>427</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10408370490903543</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15747577</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sirin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonul</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kahraman</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timurkaynak</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imaging of posterior fossa epidermoid tumors</article-title>
          <source>Clin Neurol Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>461</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2004.11.007</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16202818</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sui</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical, radiological, and pathological features of 24 atypical intracranial epidermoid cysts</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>611</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/2011.10.JNS111462</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22175719</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bohara</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yonezawa</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanaya</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takeshita</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sumida</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arita</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Posterior fossa epidermoid cysts presenting with unusual radiological appearances&#x2014;two case reports</article-title>
          <source>Neurol Med Chir</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2176/nmc.51.85</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Teo</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiou</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yen</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unusual magnetic resonance characteristics of a cerebellopontine angle epidermoid cyst with upper cervical spinal canal extension</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Neurosci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>781</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocn.2005.08.011</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16723231</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mishra</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panigrahi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhir</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pattajoshi</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intrinsic brainstem white epidermoid cyst: an unusual case report</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr Neurosci</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>52</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1817-1745.131487</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24891906</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Timmer</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sluzewski</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Treskes</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Rooij</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teepen</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wijnalda</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chemical analysis of an epidermoid cyst with unusual CT and MR characteristics</article-title>
          <source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1111</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9672020</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmadi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Destian</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Apuzzo</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Segall</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zee</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cystic fluid in craniopharyngiomas: MR imaging and quantitative analysis</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>182</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiology.182.3.1535894</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1535894</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagashima</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takahama</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakaguchi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dense cerebellopontine epidermoid cyst</article-title>
          <source>Surg Neurol</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>172</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0090-3019(82)90269-5</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6979107</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tekkok</surname>
              <given-names>IH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cataltepe</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saglam</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dense epidermoid cyst of the cerebellopontine angle</article-title>
          <source>Neuroradiology</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00588230</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1881546</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hasegawa</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komai</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kitabayashi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamano</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cerebellopontine angle epidermoid tumor extending into the upper cervical spinal canal&#x2014;case report</article-title>
          <source>Neurol Med Chir</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>614</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2176/nmc.29.614</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maccarty</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leavens</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Love</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kernohan</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermoid and epidermoid tumors in the central nervous system of adults</article-title>
          <source>Surg Gynecol Obstet</source>
          <year>1959</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>191</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13625066</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keville</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wise</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intracranial epidermoid and dermoid tumors</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1959</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>564</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/jns.1959.16.5.0564</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14408729</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ishii</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nariai</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mukawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inaji</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maehara</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Practical clinical use of dynamic susceptibility contrast magnetic resonance imaging for the surgical treatment of moyamoya disease</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>302</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/NEU.0000000000000266</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24335813</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
