<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24670962</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4143648</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14-0097</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.14-0097</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Pathology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Note</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Canine Case of Primary Intra-Right Atrial Paraganglioma</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>YANAGAWA</surname>
            <given-names>Hirotaka</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>HATAI</surname>
            <given-names>Hitoshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>TAODA</surname>
            <given-names>Takahiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>BOONSRIROJ</surname>
            <given-names>Hassadin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>KIMITSUKI</surname>
            <given-names>Kazunori</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>PARK</surname>
            <given-names>Chun-Ho</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>OYAMADA</surname>
            <given-names>Toshifumi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Laboratory of Veterinary Pathology, School of Veterinary
Medicine, Kitasato University, Towada, Aomori, Japan</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>Laboratory of Small Animal Surgery 2, School of Veterinary
Medicine, Kitasato University, Towada, Aomori, Japan</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Hatai H., Laboratory of Veterinary
Pathology, School of Veterinary Medicine, Kitasato University, Towada, Aomori 034&#x2013;8628,
Japan. e-mail: <email xlink:href="hatai@vmas.kitasato-u.ac.jp">hatai@vmas.kitasato-u.ac.jp</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>76</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>1051</fpage>
      <lpage>1053</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2014 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>ABSTRACT</title>
        <p>An 11-year-old mixed breed dog
was presented with signs of anorexia. Radiographic and ultrasound examinations revealed a
large mass in the heart, between the right atrium and the right ventricle. Upon gross
inspection, a multilobulated tumor arising from the right atrial wall and occupying the
right atrium was identified. Microscopical analysis demonstrated that this tumor consisted
of neoplastic cells with granular cytoplasm, which were separated into nests by fine
fibrovascular stroma and were negative for Grimelius&#x2019;s method. Immunohistochemical
examinations revealed that the neoplastic cells expressed chromogranin A, synaptophysin
and neuron specific enolase. Electron microscopy revealed that the cytoplasm of the
neoplastic cells held secretory granules. Based on these pathological findings, the tumor
was diagnosed as a paraganglioma. This report is a rare case of primary paraganglioma
deriving from the right atrium and provides a detailed characterization of its
morphological features.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>canine</kwd>
        <kwd>morphological diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>paraganglioma</kwd>
        <kwd>right atrium</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Paragangliomas originate from extra-adrenal neural crest-derived endocrine organs, known as
paraganglia, and are chromaffin-positive [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Microscopically, the tumor cells are typically
arranged in nests or packets, known as a Zellballen pattern, surrounded by sustentacular cells
[<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Immunohistochemically, they are positive for
chromogranin, synaptophysin and neuron specific enolase (NSE). Ultrastructurally, both
adrenalin- and noradrenalin-type granules are demonstrated in the cytoplasm of the neoplastic
cells [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p>
    <p>Primary neoplasms at the heart base are uncommon in domestic animals with the exception of
hemangiosarcomas, arising from the right atrium, and aortic body tumors (chemodectomas) in
dogs [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
Intracardiac paragangliomas are rare among mammals, including humans [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In this study, we describe a case of canine right atrial paraganglioma
with detailed histopathological, immunohistochemical and ultrastructural findings.</p>
    <p>An 11-year-old female mixed-breed dog was presented with depression and anorexia. On
auscultation, a heart murmur was heard. Radiographic and ultrasound examinations revealed a
large mass between the right atrium and the right ventricle with pleural and peritoneal
effusions. Respiratory clinical signs and lethargy were not observed. The dog was euthanized
after several appointments for symptomatic treatment. The clinician performed the necropsy and
found cardiac enlargement of the right side, hepatic congestion and mild splenic atrophy. The
heart, liver and spleen were fixed in 10% buffered formalin and submitted to the laboratory
for histopathology.</p>
    <p>A cardiac tumor (3.5 &#xD7; 4.5 cm diameter) protruded from the right atrial wall and almost
obstructed the right atrium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Gross findings. The mass arises from the right atrial wall. LV: left ventricle; RV:
right ventricle. Bar=1 cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1051-g001"/></fig>). The surface of the right atrial epicardium was intact, and no lesion
was observed around the right and left atria, pericardium and aorta. The cut surface of the
tumor displayed multilobular pattern with white to grey-tan color (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Cross section of the tumor. The cut surface displays a multinodular pattern with a
lobulated texture that is white to gray-tan in color. Arrowheads: right atrial wall; LA:
left atrium; LV: left ventricle. Bar=1 cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1051-g002"/></fig>). The submitted tissues, fixed in 10% buffered formalin, were routinely processed and
embedded in paraffin wax. The tissue sections (3 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m) were stained with
hematoxylin and eosin (HE), silver impregnation (Watanabe&#x2019;s method) and Grimelius&#x2019;s method.
Immunohistochemical (IHC) analyses were performed using the polymer method with EnVision+
(Dako, Glostrup, Denmark). The primary antibodies used in these experiments were as follows:
chromogranin A (Nichirei, Tokyo, Japan; prediluted), synaptophysin (Nichirei; prediluted), NSE
(Dako; prediluted), S100 protein (Nichirei; prediluted), neurofilament protein (Dako;
prediluted) and cytokeratin (Nichirei; prediluted). For transmission electron microscopy, the
formalin-fixed tissue was post-fixed in 1% buffered osmium tetroxide and embedded in an Epoxy
resin. Ultrathin sections (70 nm) were stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate and
examined with a transmission electron microscope (TEM) (H-7650, Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan).</p>
    <p>Histological analysis revealed expansive growth of the neoplasm and fine fibrovascular stroma
separating the neoplastic cells into variable sized trabeculae or nests (Zellballen pattern)
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Histological appearance. Each trabecula or nest of the neoplastic cells is divided by
fine fibrovascular septa. HE. Bar=40 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m. Inset: the occasional
neoplastic cells have giant nuclei. HE. Bar=20 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1051-g003"/></fig>). The neoplastic cells were cuboidal to polyhedral in shape and eosinophilic and had
finely granular cytoplasms. The nuclei were pale, round to oval and occasionally large in
irregular shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3</xref>, inset). Mitotic figures
were scattered throughout the tumor (0&#x2013;4/10 high power fields). Each packet of cells was
surrounded by reticulin fibers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_004">Fig. 4</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_004" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>The nests of the neoplastic cells are divided into small components by reticulin
fibers. Silver impregnation. Bar=40 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1051-g004"/></fig>). Grimelius&#x2019;s method was negative within the neoplastic cells. IHC analysis indicated
that the neoplastic cells were positive for chromogranin A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_005">Fig. 5</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_005" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Expression of chromogranin A in the cytoplasm of the neoplastic cells. IHC. Bar=40
<italic>&#xB5;</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1051-g005"/></fig>), synaptophysin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_006">Fig. 6</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_006" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Expression of synaptophysin in the cytoplasm of the neoplastic cells. IHC. Bar=40
<italic>&#xB5;</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1051-g006"/></fig>) and NSE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_007">Fig. 7</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_007" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>Expression of NSE in the cytoplasm of the neoplastic cells. IHC. Bar=40
<italic>&#xB5;</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1051-g007"/></fig>); however, there was no immunoreactivity for the other antibodies. Ultrastructurally,
the neoplastic cells contained a large number of granules measuring approximately 160&#x2013;250 nm
in diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_008">Fig. 8</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_008" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p>Ultrastructurally, the neoplastic cells contain many intracytoplasmic granules. TEM.
Bar=1 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m. Inset: each granule is covered by limiting membrane with
halo. TEM. Bar=300 <italic>n</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1051-g008"/></fig>). The cores displayed a granular texture and occasionally contained a
highly electron dense inner region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_008">Fig.
8</xref>, inset). These granules were covered by a limiting membrane with a
narrow halo. The liver and spleen did not have any tumor-related lesions and displayed nodular
hyperplasia and mild extramedullary hematopoiesis, respectively.</p>
    <p>Based on the pathological findings, this case was consistent with a tumor of neuroendocrine
origin. Neuroendocrine tumors are categorized as endodermal (epithelial) or neuroectodermal in
origin [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Endodermal tumors arise in the pituitary
gland, parathyroid gland, C-cells of the thyroid gland, pancreatic islets or the diffuse
endocrine system of luminal organs, such as the gastrointestinal tract (carcinoid), whereas
neuroectodermal tumors arise from the adrenal medulla and from paraganglia [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
Neuroendocrine tumors are characterized by the presence of intracytoplasmic hormonal secretory
granules, which are visualized using argyrophil reaction, such as Grimelius&#x2019;s methods [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Immunohistochemistry using antibodies against
chromogranin is also used to identify neuroendocrine tumors [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The paraganglia can be sympathetic or parasympathetic in nature [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The adrenal medulla is a type of sympathetic
paraganglion, whereas, typical parasympathetic paraganglia include chemoreceptors (the
carotid/aortic body), the vagal body and cells associated with the thoracic, intra-abdominal
and retroperitoneal ganglia [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In parasympathetic
paraganglia, paragangliomas are defined as arising from chromaffin cells [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Paragangliomas can be subdivided to functional or
non-functional. Chemoreceptor tumors are non-functional [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
    <p>Due to the limited clinical findings in the present case, it was not possible to determine
whether the tumor was functional or non-functional. This case was not reactive for Grimelius&#x2019;s
method, but it was positive for neuroendocrine markers on IHC. Although the cause was unknown,
several human cases of neuroendocrine neoplasms have been diagnosed by ultrastructural or
immunohistochemical evidences even though those cases were negative for argyrophil reaction
[<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
Ultrastructural figures of the intracytoplasmic granules in the present case displayed a
slightly different texture from the ones observed in paragangliomas. The electron density of
secretory granules varies considerably with the fixative used [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The heart was received intact at the laboratory three days after necropsy in
insufficient fixative. Inappropriate fixation of the submitted organ may have influenced the
ultrastructural morphology of intracytoplasmic granules. S100 protein-positive cells were not
detected in this tumor. In general, nests of the neoplastic cells in paragangliomas are
surrounded by sustentacular cells, which are positive for S100 protein [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The sustentacular cells in two cases of human metastatic
paragangliomas, however, were negative for S100 protein [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. No S100-positive cells in this tumor
may also result from inadequate fixation, or the sustentacular cells may not be involved in
this case.</p>
    <p>In the present case, the tumor developed from the right atrial wall and protruded into the
lumen without exophytic growth and involving other tissues. The aortic body is normally
located in the periadventitial tissue of the ascending aorta and pulmonary trunk within the
pericardial sac [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Therefore, most of the aortic body
chemodectomas are located on the epicardial surface of the heart base or atria [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and often involve aorta and/or atrial, interatrial septum
[<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Paraganglial cells are generally located within
the atria along the atrioventricular sulcus and near the roots of the great vessels [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Therefore,
based on the histopathological, immunohistochemical and ultrastructural findings, the case was
diagnosed as right atrial paraganglioma.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Averyt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chivers</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegal</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year>
<article-title>Shoulder mass in a 38-year-old
woman</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin. Orthop. Relat.
Res.</italic></source><volume>355</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>327</lpage>, 330&#x2013;332.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00003086-199810000-00034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9917618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boggs</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Regan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year>
<article-title>Left atrial paraganglioma in a dog:
echocardiography, surgery, and scintigraphy</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet.
Intern. Med.</italic></source><volume>12</volume>:
<fpage>109</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>115</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.1998.tb02104.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9560768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year> Benign tumors of neural or smooth muscle origin. pp.
105&#x2013;110. <italic>In</italic>: Atlas of Tumor Pathology, 3rd series, Armed Forces Institute
of Pathology, Washington, D.C.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Capen</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year> Tumors of the endocrine glands. pp. 607&#x2013;696.
<italic>In</italic>: Tumors in Domestic Animals, 4th ed. (Meuten, D. J. ed.), Blackwell,
Ames.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Jacobowitz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1967</year>
<article-title>Histochemical studies of the relationship
of chromaffin cells and adrenergic nerve fibers to the cardiac ganglia of several
species</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Pharmacol. Exp.
Ther.</italic></source><volume>158</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>240</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4169042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Maxie</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year> Cardiovascular system. pp. 1&#x2013;105. <italic>In</italic>:
Pathology of Domestic Animals, 5th ed., vol. 3 (Maxie, M. G. ed.), Saunders,
Philadelphia.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyden</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year>
<article-title>Primary small cell neuroendocrine
carcinoma of the kidney</article-title>. <source><italic>Ultrastruct.
Pathol.</italic></source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>144</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/01913129609016308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8882359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Rekhi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jambhekar</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Metastatic paraganglioma presenting as a
primary shoulder mass</article-title>. <source><italic>Skeletal
Radiol.</italic></source><volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1617</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1622</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00256-013-1651-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23722292</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>U. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasleton</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year>
<article-title>Prealbumin in the diagnosis of
bronchopulmonary carcinoid tumors</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Clin.
Pathol.</italic></source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>575</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jcp.44.7.573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1713221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tahir</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>Right atrial paraganglioma: a rare
primary cardiac neoplasm as a cause of chest pain</article-title>. <source><italic>Tex.
Heart Inst. J.</italic></source><volume>36</volume>:
<fpage>594</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>597</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20069088</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tischler</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year>
<article-title>Pheochromocytoma and extra-adrenal
paraganglioma: updates</article-title>. <source><italic>Arch. Pathol. Lab.
Med.</italic></source><volume>132</volume>: <fpage>1272</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1284</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18684026</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Tischler</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year> Paraganglia. pp. 1277&#x2013;1299. <italic>In</italic>:
Histology for Pathologist, 4th ed. (Mills, S. E. ed.), Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins,
Philadelphia.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldblum</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year> Paraganglioma. pp. 989&#x2013;1015. <italic>In</italic>:
Enzinger and Weiss&#x2019;s Soft Tissue Tumors, 5th ed. (Weiss, S. E. and Goldblum, J. R. eds.),
Elsevier, Philadelphia.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Wey</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>
<article-title>Right atrial chromaffin paraganglioma in
a dog</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet.
Cardiol.</italic></source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>464</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvc.2012.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22840732</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Wilander</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimelius</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year>
<article-title>Identification, characterization and
classification of endocrine tumors</article-title>. <source><italic>Zentralbl.
Pathol.</italic></source><volume>139</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>100</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7690247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
