<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26113920</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4469507</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-20-189</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2015.20.189.6175</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dural tear of unusual cause</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kechna</surname>
            <given-names>Hicham</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Loutid</surname>
            <given-names>Jaouad</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ouzzad</surname>
            <given-names>Omar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hanafi</surname>
            <given-names>Sidi Mohamed</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hachimi</surname>
            <given-names>Moulay Ahmed</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Anesthesia Resuscitation Pole- Military Hospital Meknes, Morroco</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Hicham Kechna, Anesthesia Resuscitation Pole- Military Hospital Meknes, Morroco</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>20</volume>
      <elocation-id>189</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Hicham Kechna et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Epidural analgesia is highly recommended in cancer anorectal surgery. In addition to the fight against pain it provides some benefit in allowing early rehabilitation of patients. One of the risks of this practice is the dural tear creating a cerebrospinal fluid leak (CSF) in the epidural space (EPD). Clinical features the typical positional headache, a procession of various more or less severe symptoms: nausea, vomiting, dizziness, visual or hearing impairment or radicular pain. We report a dural of unusual cause secondary of the obstruction of tuohy catheter by vertebral cartilage.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Headache</kwd>
        <kwd>spinal analgesia</kwd>
        <kwd>epidural anaesthesia</kwd>
        <kwd>post-dural puncture headache</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The lumbar post puncture syndrome (LPPS) occurs after a break duro subarachnoid during an epidural puncture creating a cerebrospinal fluid leak (CSF) in the epidural space (EPD). Clinical features the typical positional headache, a procession of various more or less severe symptoms: nausea, vomiting, dizziness, visual or hearing disturbances or radicular pain. The occurrences of circumstances are numerous, we report the case of a dural breach occurred when performing epidural analgesia for digestive cancer surgery of an unusual cause.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Patient and observation</title>
      <p>It is a 46 year old patient without significant medical history and normal weight, admitted to visceral surgery block for sigmoid tumor resection. Epidural analgesia was used for the management of perioperative pain. After installation and commissioning requirement in this kind of anesthetic practice, the realization of the puncture was at L2-L3 by an experienced anesthetist. After introducing the catheter 2-3 cm and removing the plastic core research epidural space using against fluid pressure was started. Bone obstacle was felt and the needle was redirected in a cephalic direction. To the failure of catheterization despite the introduction of the needle tuohy over its entire length, the latter was withdrawn for verification. It was then that we discovered the obstruction of the catheter by a piece of bone cartilage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>) dural tear was strongly suspected despite the non completion of cerebrospinal fluid through the needle. The second attempt was successful at the underlying spaced. The immediate postoperative analgesia was based on an intravenous analgesics and the epidural wasn't started until fully awake and lucid contact with the patient under the close supervision of an anesthesic nurse care even after returning to service. However, the day after surgery, the patient complained of typical post-dural puncture syndrome what motivated the execution of a blood patch. The evolution was very favorable.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Images showing the tip of cartilage responsible for the obstruction of the epidural catheter</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-20-189-g001"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0003">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The dural tear is one of the most common complications of locating the epidural space. The operator experience is a commonly recognized risk factor. so, if a frequency of about 1% is generally accepted in the research of the lumbar epidural space [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], Norris et al. [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] have reveal that the frequency can reach 2.7% when the majority of acts practiced by internal. The role of patient characteristics making it difficult to find the epidural space, especially obesity, is less straightforward. Indeed, three-quarters of cases of dural breaches occurred in the first or second attempt at identification. However, it was recently shown that the period of custody is an additional risk factor in the development of this complication. [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] After a dural tear, the majority of anesthesiologists, as was the case in our observation, search the epidural space in an intervertebral spacing or sus- underlying for epidural analgesia [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, it should be emphasized that epidural catheter should be used with caution. Indeed, a significant portion of the solution administered into the epidural space can pass into the subarachnoid space and promote the expansion of the block [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], with, in the extreme, the risk of total spinal anesthesia [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This passage is particularly important that the breach was made with a needle of large diameter [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], especially with a needle of 17 gauge. It is for this reason that epidural analgesia for our patient was started that after a complete awakening and under close supervision. Headache is the main result of the dural tear. Their frequency is 30 to 70% of cases of proven breach [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], which can often be more important in obstetric epidural analgesia due to the age of patients, the large diameter of the needle used for marking the epidural space and the role favoring any thrust forces in the expulsion phase [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. For some teams any postural headache in the aftermath of epidural analgesia should be considered and treated as a MPPC. [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] While many therapeutic approaches are proposed (rest, establishment of a lap belt, hydration, analgesics, caffeine, sumatriptan, epidural infusion of crystalloid or colloid) [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] the radical cure of PDPH is always based on achieving a epidural blood patch because the severity and nature of these debilitating headaches quickly leads to depressive manifestations of women and aggressiveness of the environment. In our case, being the circumstances of the execution, the diagnosis of dural tear was quickly adopted and bood patch immediately realized. However, for the case of dural tear proved with continued epidural analgesia using a catheter placed in a space or sus- underlying the realization of a blood preventive patch by the epidural catheter may be considered. Indeed, several studies show that preventive blood patch greatly decreases the frequency and intensity of CPPD probably [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In our case the tear was strongly suspected and the blood patch made the first complaint headaches. The incidence of epidural blood patch success of around 90%, which means that about 10% of patients had residual headaches after blood patch. In these cases, a second blood patch should be offered.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S0004">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>After accidental dural tear, analgesia may be continued by epidural (obstetrics). In case of epidural analgesia, a prophylactic blood patch seems desirable. This observation highlights the importance of greater caution in the progression of the needle tuohy and the verification of permeability of the needle every each bone contact.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="S0005">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0006">
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>The authors have read the final version of this manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harada</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dan</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extensive application of epidural anesthesia and analgesia in a university hospital: Incidence of complications related to technique</article-title>
          <source>Reg Anesth.</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <season>Jan-Feb</season>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8448096</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Norris</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leighton</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DeSimone</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Needle bevel direction and headache after inadvertent dural puncture</article-title>
          <source>Anesthesiology.</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <month>5</month>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>729</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2655500</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Norris</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grieco</surname>
              <given-names>WM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borkowski</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leighton</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arkoosh</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huffnagle</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Complications of labor analgesia: Epidural versus combined spinal epidural techniques</article-title>
          <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <month>9</month>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>529</fpage>
          <lpage>37</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8067559</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aya</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mangin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robert</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrer</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eledjam</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Increased risk of unintentional dural puncture in night-time obstetric epidural anesthesia</article-title>
          <source>Can J Anaesth.</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <month>7</month>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>665</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10442962</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berger</surname>
              <given-names>CW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crosby</surname>
              <given-names>ET</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grodecki</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>North American survey of the management of dural puncture occurring during labour epidural analgesia</article-title>
          <source>Can J Anaesth.</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <month>2</month>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>110</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9512843</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Souron</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simon</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamza</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dural taps in peridural analgesia for labor: management by French anesthesiologists in 1997</article-title>
          <source>Ann Fr Anesth R&#xE9;anim.</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <month>11</month>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>941</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10615542</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leighton</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arkoosh</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huffnagle</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huffnagle</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kinsella</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norris</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The dermatomal spread of epidural bupivacaine with and without prior intrathecal sufentanil</article-title>
          <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <month>9</month>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>526</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8780275</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Swenson</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsing Lee</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McJames</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effect of prior dural puncture on cerebrospinal fluid sufentanil concentrations in sheep after the administration of epidural sufentanil</article-title>
          <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <month>4</month>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>794</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9539604</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hodgkinson</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Total spinal block after epidural injection into an interspace adjacent to an inadvertent dural perforation</article-title>
          <source>Anesthesiology.</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <month>11</month>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>593</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7294420</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Swenson</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wisniewski</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McJames</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashburn</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pace</surname>
              <given-names>NL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effect of prior dural puncture on cisternal cerebrospinalfluid morphine concentrations in sheep after administration of lumbar epidural morphine</article-title>
          <source>Anesth Analg.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <month>9</month>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>523</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8780274</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smedstad</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C&#xE9;phal&#xE9;es post-ponction dure-m&#xE8;re: est-ce diff&#xE9;rent en obst&#xE9;trique?</article-title>
          <source>Can J Anesth.</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <month>1</month>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9466019</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Angle</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halpern</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Second stage pushing correlates with headache after unintentional dural puncture in parturients</article-title>
          <source>Can J Anesth.</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <month>9</month>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>861</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10490155</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aya</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mangin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nouvellon</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robert</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrer</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eledjam</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Br&#xE8;che durale en analg&#xE9;sie obst&#xE9;tricale: aspects &#xE9;pid&#xE9;miologiques et prise en charge th&#xE9;rapeutique</article-title>
          <source>Ann Fr Anesth R&#xE9;anim.</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <month>11</month>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>757</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11759317</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eledjam</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Viel</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aya</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mangin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Postdural puncture headache</article-title>
          <source>Cah Anesthesiol.</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>579</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8287298</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cheek</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banner</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sauter</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gutsche</surname>
              <given-names>BB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prophylactic extradural blood patch is effective</article-title>
          <source>Br J Anaesth.</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <month>9</month>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>340</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3179154</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Trivedi</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eddi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shevde</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Headache prevention following accidental dural puncture in obstetric patients</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Anesth.</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <season>Jan-Feb</season>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>42</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8442966</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
