<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25654373</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4602720</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000000360</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00360</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>7100</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Thoracolumbar Scoliosis in a Patient With Proteus Syndrome</article-title>
        <subtitle>A Case Report and Literature Review</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Zheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shen</surname>
            <given-names>Jianxiong</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Jinqian</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Polisner.</surname>
            <given-names>Stuart</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>From the Department of Orthopaedic Surgery (ZL, JS, JL), Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, China.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Correspondence: Jianxiong Shen, Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Peking, Union Medical College, Beijing 100730, China (e-mail: <email>shenjianxiong@medmail.com.cn</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>94</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <elocation-id>e360</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-94-e360.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>The Proteus syndrome (PS) is a complex and rare congenital hamartomatous condition with a wide range of malformations. Little is reported about spinal deformity associated with this syndrome.</p>
        <p>This study presents a case of scoliosis occurring in the setting of PS and explores the possible mechanisms between the 2 diseases.</p>
        <p>The patient is a 17-year-old Chinese female with scoliosis and hemihypertrophy of the right upper and lower extremity as well as exostosis of the right lower leg joint including the hip, knee, ankle, and toes. These manifestations were suggestive of PS. She underwent a posterior correction at thoracic 2-lumbar 4 (T5&#x2013;L4) levels, using the Moss-SI spinal system. At 3-month follow-ups, the patient was clinically pain free and well balanced. Plain radiographs showed solid spine fusion with no loss of deformity correction.</p>
        <p>The severity of scoliosis in PS is progressively aggravated and the correction of the extensive spinal deformities is generally difficult. Therefore, early diagnosis is required for adequate interdisciplinary treatment.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Proteus syndrome (PS) is a complex, rare, and variable disorder characterized by the patchy or segmental overgrowth of multiple tissues and organs including connective tissue nevi, epidermal nevi, vascular and lymphatic malformations, and craniofacial hyperostosis along with susceptibility to tumors.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> This syndrome was first described by Cohen and Hayden in 1979.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Dietrich et al<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> titled the disease, which has multiple, diverse, somatic manifestations, as the Greek god Proteus, who could change his form at will. The diagnostic criteria of the disease are yet to be properly established, and it may be confused with other similar syndromes such as Klippel&#x2013;Trenaunay&#x2013;Weber syndrome, neurofibromatosis, and Mafucci syndrome.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> About 200 cases of PS have been reported in the literature, and incidence of bone malformations is unknown.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> The exact cause, pathogenesis, and embryologic origin of PS remain a subject of discussion.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> There are limited reports regarding the diagnosis and management of PS with its possible resultant scoliosis. We here present a case of PS in a 17-year-old girl with unusual presentation of scoliosis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CONSENT</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient's parents on behalf of the child for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 17-year-old asylum seeker was admitted for an elective correction of her progressive scoliotic deformity. She was found to have scoliosis at age 3 by her parents. The brace therapy was initiated around 3 years of age, and the patient was compliant with the brace for 12 years, wearing it approximately 18 hours a day. There was also a history of progression of scoliosis despite brace therapy with thoracolumbosacral orthosis. Therefore, she was suggested the surgical correction for her spinal deformity. After 2 years, she was referred to the Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Beijing, China. Her plain radiographs of the spine showed that the Cobb angle of the thoracolumbar scoliosis was 100&#xB0; and the Cobb angle of compensatory thoracic curvature was 70&#xB0; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), suggesting the need for surgical correction.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Standing anteroposterior and lateral radiographs of the preoperation.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e360-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Her past medical history was only remarkable in that she underwent resection of a soft tissue mass on the right side of her anterior abdomen at the age of 7. On physical examination, she has gradually demonstrated hemihypertrophy of the right upper and lower extremity as well as exostosis of the right lower leg joint including the hip, knee, ankle, and toes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). She also showed increased thickness of the right plantar surface without cerebriform masses. For these asymmetrical deformities and joint dysfunctions, PS eventually was diagnosed. Magnetic resonance imaging revealed no evidence of any spinal cord or canal abnormalities. Computed tomography revealed no vertebral body deformities. The family history was unremarkable, and there was no parental consanguinity.</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Radiograph of the foot showing enlargement of the first tarsometatarsal and metatarsophalangeal joints, with epiphyseal osteocartilaginous exostosis. Note the same finding in the fifth metatarsophalangeal joint.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e360-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In June 2014, a posterior correction and fusion at T2&#x2013;L4 levels was performed, using the Moss-SI spinal system. The total operation time was 4 hours and 45 minutes. Total amount of blood loss was 800&#x200A;mL. During the operation, the signal of this patient was normal using intraoperative spinal cord monitoring. Postoperatively, there was no sign of renal dysfunction. Postoperative plain x-ray film demonstrated the Cobb angles of the thoracolumbar scoliosis correction from 100&#xB0; to 77&#xB0; (correction rate 33%) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Her follow-up was asymptomatic, well balanced in the sagittal and coronal planes, with solid fusion at the third postoperative month. Both the patient and her parents were satisfied with the results of the surgery.</p>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Standing anteroposterior and lateral radiographs of 4 d after operation.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e360-g003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>PS is a group of disorders marked by partial gigantism of the hands, feet, or both; plantar hyperplasia; hemangiomas; lipomas; lymphangiomas; varicosities; verrucous epidermal nevi; macrocephaly; cranial exostosis; and asymmetry of the limbs because of long bone overgrowth.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> However, there are limited reports regarding the diagnosis and management of PS with scoliosis. In the present study, we reported a case of a 17-year-old female with scoliosis.</p>
      <p>The diagnosis of PS is based on the existence of at least 4 of the major 7 criteria described by Samlaska et al<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> in 1989. The diagnostic criteria for PS are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> Despite these criteria, PS was often confused with a number of other syndromes with related disproportional skeletal enlargement including the following: hemihyperplasia syndromes, epidermal nevi (CLOVE) syndrome, type 2 segmental Cowden syndrome, neurofibromatosis, Klippel&#x2013;Trenaunay&#x2013;Weber syndrome, multiple enchondromatosis (Ollier disease and Maffucci syndrome), and Bannayan&#x2013;Zonana syndrome.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> However, each of these syndromes can be distinguished from PS by meticulous observation of these characteristics.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Scoliosis is a common manifestation of PS, which can range from one single long, gentle curve to multiple, severe curves.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> While the time of onset of scoliosis in PS is similar to that of adolescent idiopathic scoliosis, the severity and rate of progression in PS can be remarkable. There are no specific guidelines for scoliosis operations on patients with PS, but doctors must keep in mind that these PS including overgrowth of bones of the external auditory canal can cause conductive hearing loss, infection, and cholesteatomas.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>TABLE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Diagnostic Criteria for Proteus Syndrome</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e360-g004"/>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>The exact etiology, pathogenesis, and embryologic origin of PS syndrome are still not known.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> It is hypothesized to be caused by a new, mosaic, mutation acquired early in development; cells derived from the mutated cell line carry this mutation and result in affected tissues.<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> For this patient, we propose that the localized overgrowth of the right lumbar facets and pedicles were the result of hemihypertrophy based on PS, not the influence of mechanical stress.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>In conclusion, PS is a relatively new rare syndrome described in recent years. The management of patients with PS and scoliosis is challenging. However, the cause of scoliosis in PS remains to be investigated. As the number of cases increases, the etiology, clinical manifestations, and natural history of this syndrome will become clearer. The severity of scoliosis in PS is progressively aggravated, and that correction of the extensive spinal deformities is generally difficult. Considering these findings, early diagnosis and treatment is recommended.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p>The authors would like to thank their center colleagues and the devotion of the patients.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviation: PS = Proteus syndrome.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of P.R. China (Grant Number: 81272053, 81330044, 81301596, and 81401847).</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarman</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuksel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Proteus syndrome: report of a case with developmental glaucoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Korean J Ophthalmol</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>274</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24882963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomason</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramowsky</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rickets</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Proteus syndrome: three case reports with a review of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic>Fetal Pediatr Pathol</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>153</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22413928</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuzurihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A case of Proteus syndrome with severe spinal canal stenosis, scoliosis, and thoracic deformity associated with tethered cord</article-title>. <source><italic>Jpn J Radiol</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22223075</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A newly recognized hamartomatous syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic>Birth Defects Orig Artic Ser</italic></source>
<year>1979</year>; <volume>15</volume>
<issue>(5B)</issue>:<fpage>291</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">118782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Glidden</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The Proteus syndrome: CNS manifestations</article-title>. <source><italic>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</italic></source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>987</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>990</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9613526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takebayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokogushi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Scoliosis in Proteus syndrome: case report</article-title>. <source><italic>Spine</italic></source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>E395</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>398</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11568716</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kansu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozgen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Radiographic manifestations of the temporomandibular joint in a case of Proteus syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic>Dentomaxillofac Radiol</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>58444855</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22241876</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pazzaglia</surname><given-names>UE</given-names></name><name><surname>Beluffi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonaspetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Bone malformations in Proteus syndrome: an analysis of bone structural changes and their evolution during growth</article-title>. <source><italic>Pediatric radiology</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>829</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>835</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17569038</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sapp</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Kamp</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Newly delineated syndrome of congenital lipomatous overgrowth, vascular malformations, and epidermal nevi (CLOVE syndrome) in seven patients</article-title>. <source><italic>Am J Med Genet Part A</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>143A</volume>:<fpage>2944</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2958</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17963221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalhor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parvizi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Slongo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Acetabular dysplasia associated with intra-articular lipomatous lesions in proteus syndrome. A case report</article-title>. <source><italic>J Bone Joint Surg Am</italic></source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>86-A</volume>:<fpage>831</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>834</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15069153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tosi</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapp</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Assessment and management of the orthopedic and other complications of Proteus syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic>J Child Orthop</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>327</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23024722</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmetoglu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Isik</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Aynaci</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Proteus syndrome associated with liver involvement: case report</article-title>. <source><italic>Genet Couns</italic></source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12872817</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samlaska</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Proteus syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic>Arch Dermatol</italic></source>
<year>1989</year>; <volume>125</volume>:<fpage>1109</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1114</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2667470</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biesecker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The challenges of Proteus syndrome: diagnosis and management</article-title>. <source><italic>Eur J Hum Genet</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1151</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1157</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16883308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Heterozygous somatic activating AKT1 mutation in a case of Proteus syndrome with mental retardation</article-title>. <source><italic>J Dermatol</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>189</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24387135</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhagat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A severe and rapidly progressive case of proteus syndrome in a neonate who presented with unilateral hydrocephalus apart from other typical features of the proteus syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Neonatol</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>154</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24027714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farajzadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahedi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moghaddam</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A new gastrointestinal finding in Proteus syndrome: report of a case of multiple colonic hemangiomas</article-title>. <source><italic>Int J Dermatol</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16445505</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
