<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26491512</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4594980</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-21-69</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2015.21.69.7068</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Images in Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A characteristic image in Joubert syndrome: molar tooth sign</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sghir</surname>
            <given-names>Mouna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kesomtini</surname>
            <given-names>Wassia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Unit of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, University Hospital Tahar Sfar, Mahdia, Tunisia</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Mouna Sghir, Unit of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, University Hospital Tahar Sfar, Mahdia, Tunisia</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>21</volume>
      <elocation-id>69</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Mouna Sghir et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Joubert syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>molar tooth</kwd>
        <kwd>aplasia</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="S0001">
      <title>Image in medicine</title>
      <p>Joubert syndrome is a relatively rare autosomal recessive congenital disorder; it is characterized by cerebellar vermis hypoplasia or aplasia. Characteristic clinical symptoms and signs include motor and respiratory abnormalities. It is currently included in the malformation spectrum of cerebello-oculo-renal syndromes (CORS). An image known as a &#x201C;molar tooth sign&#x201D; is typically observed in cerebral magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and is characterised by a deep posterior interpeduncular fossa, thickened and elongated superior cerebellar peduncles, as well as hypoplasia or agenesis of the cerebellar vermis. We report the case of a 4-year-old male, referred to our rehabilitation unity with a history of hypotonia and delayed psychomotor development. Physical examination found macrocephaly, frontal bossing and triangular upper lip and arched palate. Ocular examination revealed a bilateral divergent squint and inability to track objects with eyes. All aspects of his development were delayed. He had a generalized hypotonia but deep tendon reflexes were normal. There were important negative signs including: Regular breathing pattern, no organomegaly and no polydactyly or syndactyly. With these findings, a brain MRI was requested, which showed the classic &#x201C;molar tooth sign&#x201D; which led to the clinical diagnosis of Joubert syndrome. In complementary studies, the audiogram revealed a bilateral sensorineural hearing loss, the ophthalmology assessment and laboratory studies were normal. We have prescribed a stander and hearing aid. A rehabilitation program was started consisting of: joint mobilization, muscle strengthening, occupational and speech therapy.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Cerebral MRI showing agenesis of cerebellar vermis causing the &#x201C;molar tooth sign&#x201D;</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-21-69-g001"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </body>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
