<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diagn Pathol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diagn Pathol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Diagnostic Pathology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1746-1596</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26022184</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4446797</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">287</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13000-015-0287-z</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Malignant neuroendocrine tumour of the appendix in childhood with loco-regional lymph node invasion</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lyons</surname>
            <given-names>Rebecca F</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>rebeccalyons@rcsi.ie</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Irfan</surname>
            <given-names>Muhammad</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>caliber48@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Waldron</surname>
            <given-names>Ronan</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>ronanwaldy@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bambury</surname>
            <given-names>Niamh</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>niamhbambury@rcsi.ie</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bennani</surname>
            <given-names>Fadel</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>fadel.bennani@hse.ie</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nemeth</surname>
            <given-names>Tamas</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>tamas.nemeth@hse.ie</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Khan</surname>
            <given-names>Waqar</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>waqar.khan2@hse.ie</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Barry</surname>
            <given-names>Kevin</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>kbarsurg@eircom.net</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Surgery, Mayo General Hospital, Saolta Hospital Group, Mayo, Ireland </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Histopathology, Mayo General Hospital, Saolta Hospital Group, Mayo, Ireland </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label/>Professor of Surgery, Discipline of Surgery, National University of Ireland, Galway, Ireland </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <elocation-id>55</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Lyons et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <title>Virtual slides</title>
        <p>The virtual slide(s) for this article can be found here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diagnosticpathology.diagnomx.eu/vs/1006600359152743">http://www.diagnosticpathology.diagnomx.eu/vs/1006600359152743</ext-link></p>
        <sec>
          <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
          <p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13000-015-0287-z) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Neuroendocrine tumours</kwd>
        <kwd>Childhood</kwd>
        <kwd>Metastatic</kwd>
        <kwd>Lymph node</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Malignant neuroendocrine tumour of the appendix is a rare finding in the paediatric population. Metastases to the loco-regional lymph nodes at time of diagnosis are very rare. The literature reviewing the treatment and follow up of such cases is not definitive regarding best practice and management guidelines vary due to the complexity and rarity of these tumours.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A twelve year old girl presented acutely to the emergency department, with a two day history of right iliac fossa pain associated with nausea and vomiting. No fevers or rigors were reported. The patient denied urinary symptoms and was pre-menstrual. She had a background of recurrent presentations to the emergency department with non specific abdominal pain in the preceding months. This girl had also been investigated by the paediatric service regarding episodes of dizziness, headaches and recurrent epistaxis. All previous investigations were normal. On this occasion, she had tenderness, localised guarding and rebound in the right iliac fossa. Her inflammatory markers were elevated, white cell count (WCC) 14.2 and a C reactive protein (CRP) of 23.4. Intravenous antibiotics were commenced and a plan for surgical intervention was made.</p>
      <p>The patient underwent an emergency uncomplicated laparoscopic appendicectomy. At the time of surgery, it was noted that the apex of the appendix was distended. (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) There were no signs of acute inflammation or purulent fluid. The base of the appendix was ligated using endoloops and the specimen was submitted for histology. The patient made an uncomplicated recovery and was discharged forty eight hours later.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Intra-operative image of the appendix at initial operation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13000_2015_287_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>Pathological examination of the appendix (measuring 60&#xA0;mm in length) demonstrated a rare case of infiltrating neuroendocrine tumour of the appendix. The tumour penetrated the mucosa, submucosa and muscularis propria with extraluminal extenstion into the mesoappendix. This tumour was well differentiated measuring 25&#xA0;mm in maximal diameter. The tumour stained positive for chromogranin, CD 56 and synaptophysin. The Ki67 proliferative index measured 15%, therefore consistent with a Grade 2 (G2) neuroendocrine tumour. A microscopic lymph node of the mesoappendix was also analysed which stained positive for chromogranin A, confirming a small metastatic deposit in the centre of the lymph node<italic>.</italic> (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) The provisional staging of pT3, N1 Mx was assigned and the patient proceeded to staging investigations. A computerised tomography (CT) scan of the thorax, abdomen and pelvis was performed demonstrating a cluster of sub-centimetre lymph nodes in the right paracolic gutter of indeterminate significance. (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) Urinary 5 HIAA testing was also completed and a normal level reported.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Highlights the histological appendix specimen with staining. <bold>A</bold>: Base of the appendix with accompanying mesoappendiceal lymph node. <bold>B</bold>: Neuroendocrine carcinoma of the appendix located at the apex with extramural extension into the mesoappendix. <bold>C</bold>: Chromogranin A, neuroendocrine marker positive. <bold>D</bold>: Mesoappendiceal lymph node showing small focus of metastatic tumour.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13000_2015_287_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>CT scan identifying the sub centimetre lymph nodes in right paracolic gutter.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13000_2015_287_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>After discussion at the gastrointestinal multidisciplinary meeting, the decision to perform a laparoscopic right hemicolectomy was made. The pathological examination of the subsequent right hemicolectomy specimen showed no evidence of residual tumour grossly or microscopically. Forty seven loco-regional lymph nodes were retrieved. Two of these lymph nodes were positive for metastatic neuroendocrine tumour. These were located at 1&#xA0;cm and 5&#xA0;cm from the appendicectomy site. All peri-ileal lymph nodes were free of disease. The immunohistochemistry profile again was positive for chromogranin, synaptophysin and CD 56. (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Shows the histological lymph node specimen with staining. <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>: Large lymph node from right hemicolectomy specimen showing metastatic tumour. <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>: Immuno staining positive for chromogranin A (C) and synaptophysin (D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13000_2015_287_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      <p>The patient is currently doing well and has been enrolled on a clinical and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) surveillance programme.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Laparoscopic appendicectomy is a common procedure in the paediatric age group. Rarely has an unexpected diagnosis of a malignant neuroendocrine tumour of the appendix been noted. Interestingly benign neuroendocrine tumours are the most common tumour of the gastrointestinal tract in children, however malignant neuroendocrine tumours are rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> highlights the key publications on malignant neuroendocrine tumours within the paediatric population. Definitive incidence reporting across the literature is lacking, with varying incidences being reported. However, Parkes et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] has been referenced widely in the literature with an incidence of 1.14 per million children. The other large study by Boxberger et al. concluded that the incidence was 1 per 100,000 children, a value that is widely referenced in the literature.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Highlights the incidence of malignant neuroendocrine tumours in the literature</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="top"><th>
<bold>Author</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Number of children in series</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Incidence reported</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td>Parkes et al. 1993 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]</td><td>40 children over 24&#xA0;years</td><td>1.14 per million children</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Pelizzo et al. 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]</td><td>10 children over 8&#xA0;years</td><td>1.14 per million children</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>D&#x2019;Aleo et al. 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>2 children</td><td>1 per 100,000 children</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>O&#x2019;Donnell et al. 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td>3 children over 9&#xA0;years</td><td>1 per 100,000 children</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Boxberger et al. 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</td><td>237 children over 5&#xA0;years</td><td>1 per 100,000 children</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Up to 90% are diagnosed incidentally after laparoscopic appendicectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Usually there is a large female predominance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. This is interesting, when one considers the recent trend in the literature looking at the conservative management of acute appendicitis in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>The presenting features of both benign and malignant neuroendocrine tumours usually follow that of acute appendicitis as highlighted in our case. The well described carcinoid syndrome of flushing, diarrhoea and cardiac disease is rarely reported within the paediatric population as this is associated with liver or retroperitoneal metastases. It is in such cases that the 5 hydroxyindoleacetic acid (5HIAA) testing is positive [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>Boxberger <italic>et. al</italic> studied neuroendocrine tumours in children over a five year period. They noted that mean age of presentation was 13&#xA0;yrs (4.5-19.5), the majority of those presented with signs of acute appendicitis and the diagnosis was made histologically. The location of the tumour similar to our case primarily was at the apex of the appendix (70%) with extension into the mesoappendix in 63%. Extension into the mesoappendix was more likely if the size of the primary tumour was over 15&#xA0;mm.</p>
      <p>It has been confirmed across the literature that site, size and grade are significant in predicting aggressive behaviour of tumours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Prognosis has been found to be directly related to tumour size. Rossi et al. questioned whether or not mesoappendiceal involvement was an indicator or poor prognosis, however their study confirmed previous studies findings, that size is the main determinant of prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p>
      <p>Decision on further operative treatment after histological confirmation of malignant neuroendocrine tumours is based on the size of the tumour. If the tumour is less than 2&#xA0;cm appendicectomy alone is the operation of choice. A low proliferative index, an apical location of the tumour, and lack of angiolymphatic or mesoappendiceal invasion are other factors that influence surgery. A right hemicolectomy is the operation of choice if the tumour is greater than 2&#xA0;cm, or if there is histological evidence of mesoappendiceal extension or location of the tumour at the base with caecal extension. However it must be noted that only 20% of resected specimens will show any residual disease.</p>
      <p>The World Health Organisation revised the classification system for neuroendocrine tumours in 2010 and places considerable emphasis on the Ki67 proliferative index. The Ki67 index is used to subdivide the neuroendocrine tumours into G1 or G2 neoplasms. If the Ki67 index is less than 3%, these are classified as G1. A Ki67 index between 3-20% classifies the tumours as G2. G3 is represented by a Ki67 greater than 20%. Ki67% has been studied as a factor for predicting metastases or recurrence. In 2013 Yamaguchi <italic>et. al</italic> investigated Ki67 as a predictive index of tumour spread. This important study reported that a Ki67 index of 2.8% or greater gave a specificity of 86.8% of having metastases or recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. When assessing Ki67 as a marker for the biologic behaviour of tumours, it must be considered that Ki67 expression varies during the disease progression. This is not fully understood at present, but literature available suggests that Ki67 expression does vary and depending on the time of measurement, Ki67 can result in the WHO classification being upgraded. This has significant implications for treatment and follow up of these patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>The presence of lymph node involvement as in our case, is rare and has been reported sporadically in 4-5% of paediatric cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. A review of 414 cases looking at neuroendocrine tumour and metastases found that only 4.1% of the cases had metastases identified. MacGillivary <italic>et. al</italic> confirmed that tumours greater than 2&#xA0;cm and mesoappendiceal invasion are associated with metastatic disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. D&#x2019;Aleo <italic>et. al</italic> suggested that a right hemicolectomy for a child with a neuroendocrine tumour of the appendix is a radical procedure as the prognosis is quite good. 5&#xA0;year survival is reported between 90-100%. There is a trend towards limited resection as an alternative option to the classic right hemicolectomy, with perhaps an ileocaecal resection deemed appropriate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>No definitive follow up has been quoted in the literature. Despite the incidence of recurrent disease being low, follow up is recommended. In general terms clinical follow up, including chromogranin A (CgA) and 5 HIAA testing is recommended. No studies have assessed the sensitivity of these biologic markers to detect metastases or local recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The ENETS guidelines recommend that if the tumour is less than 1&#xA0;cm then no specific follow up is needed. However if there is involvement of lymph nodes, long term follow up is recommended. MRI or CT is recommended in cases where the initial tumour is greater than 2&#xA0;cm, local invasion or metastatic disease are present at diagnosis. MRI should be considered in the young and in females of childbearing age due to the lower radiation doses when compared to serial CT scanning. It is recommended that these high risk patients are followed up at 6&#xA0;months and 12&#xA0;months post operatively and annually thereafter.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Consent was obtained from the patient for publication.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>RFL was involved in concept design, literature review and writing manuscript. MI, RW and NB all contributed to literature review and collection of radiological imaging. FB and TM contributed histological analysis and slide preparation. WK undertook a review of manuscript. KB was involved in concept generation, contribution to manuscript design and final review of manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pelizzo</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>La Riccia</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bouvier</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chappuis</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franchella</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>&#x2018;Carcinoid tumours of the appendix in children&#x2019;</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Surg Int</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>399</fpage>
          <lpage>402</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s003830000559</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11527175</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parkes</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muir</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>al Sheyyab</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cameron</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pincott</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raafat</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carcinoid tumours of the appendix in children 1957-1986: incidence, treatment and outcome</article-title>
          <source>Br J Surg</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>502</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.1800800433</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8495322</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boxberger</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Redlich</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boger</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leuschner</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>VonSchweinitz</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dralle</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>&#x2018;Neuroendocrine tumors of the appendix in children and adolescents</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>65</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pbc.24267</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22887869</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Minneci</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sulkowski</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nacion</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahida</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Copper</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moss</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Feasibility of Nonoperative management strategy for uncomplicated acute appendicitis in children&#x2019;</article-title>
          <source>J American College Surg</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>219</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>272</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2014.02.031</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stinner</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rothmund</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neuroendocrine tumours (carcinoids) of the appendix</article-title>
          <source>Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>729</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpg.2005.06.003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16253897</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MacGillivray</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heaton</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rushin</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Creuss</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Distant metastasis from a carcinoid tumour of the appendix less than one centimeter in size</article-title>
          <source>Surgery</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>466</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1557693</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Assadi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kubiak</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaiser</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Appendiceal Carcinoid tumours in children: does size matter?&#x2019;</article-title>
          <source>Med Pediatr Oncol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>65</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mpo.1269</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11835243</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rossi</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valli</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bertolini</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sighinolfi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Losi</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cavazza</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Does Mesoappendix infiltration predict a worse prognosis in incidental neuroendocrine tumours of the appendix? A clinicopathologic and immunohistochemical study of 15 cases</article-title>
          <source>Am J Clin Pathol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>706</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1309/199VD990LVHPTQUM</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14608896</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rutledge</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alexander</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary appendiceal malignancies: rare but important</article-title>
          <source>Surgery</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>244</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1542852</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sandor</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Modlin</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>&#x2018;A retrospective analysis of 1570 appendiceal carcinoids&#x2019;</article-title>
          <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>422</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1572-0241.1998.00422.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9517651</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujimori</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomita</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ichikawa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitomi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohno</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical validation of the gastrointestinal NET grading system: Ki67 index criteria of the WHO 2010 classification is appropriate to predict metastasis or recurrence</article-title>
          <source>Diagn Pathol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>65</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-1596-8-65</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23607525</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Singh S, Hallet J, Rowsell C, Law CH. &#x2018;Variability of Ki67 labelling index in multiple neuroendocine tumors specimens over the course of the disease.&#x2019; European Journal of Surgical Oncology, 2014;14:748.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donnell</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garstin</surname>
              <given-names>WIH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical treatment of malignant carcinoid tumours of the appendix</article-title>
          <source>Int J Clin Pract</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>431</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-1241.2006.00875.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911574</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Syracuse</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perzin</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Price</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiedel</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mesa Tejada</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carcinoid tumours of the appendix: mesoappendiceal extension and nodal metastases</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>190</volume>
          <fpage>58</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-197907000-00013</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">464679</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>D&#x2019;Aleo</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazzarechi</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruggiero</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riccardi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carcinoid tumors of the appendix in children: two case reports and review of literature</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Hematol Oncol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>347</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/088800101300312627</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11452407</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pape</surname>
              <given-names>UF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perren</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niederle</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gross</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gress</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ENETS Consensus guidelines for the management of patients with Neuroendocrine Neoplasms from the Jejuno-Ileum and the appendix including Goblet cell Carcinomas</article-title>
          <source>Neuroendocrinology</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000335629</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22262080</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
