<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25422692</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4239440</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-18-217</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2014.18.217.4645</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Duodenal perforation: an unusual complication of sickle cell anemia</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ac&#x131;payam</surname>
            <given-names>Can</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ald&#x131;&#xE7;</surname>
            <given-names>G&#xFC;liz</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ak&#xE7;ora</surname>
            <given-names>B&#xFC;lent</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>&#xC7;elikkaya</surname>
            <given-names>Mehmet Emin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>A&#x15F;kar</surname>
            <given-names>Hasan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dorum</surname>
            <given-names>Bayram Ali</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Mustafa Kemal University, School of Medicine, Department of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology, Hatay, Turkey</aff>
      <aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Mustafa Kemal University, School of Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, Hatay, Turkey</aff>
      <aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>Mustafa Kemal University, School of Medicine, Department of Pediatric Surgery, Hatay, Turkey</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Can Ac&#x131;payam, Mustafa Kemal University School of Medicine, Department of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology, Hatay, Turkey</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>18</volume>
      <elocation-id>217</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Can Ac&#x131;payam et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Duodenal perforation in childhood is a rare condition with a high mortality rate if not treated surgically. Primary gastroduodenal perforation is frequently associated with peptic ulcer and exhibits a positive family history. Helicobacter pylorus is the most significant agent. Secondary gastroduodenal perforation may be a finding of specific diseases, such as Crohn disease, or more rarely may be associated with diseases such as cystic fibrosis or sickle cell anemia. A 14-year-old boy presented with abdominal and back pain. The patient was operated on for acute abdomen and diagnosed with duodenal perforation. Helicobacter pylorus was negative. There was no risk factor to account for duodenal perforation other than sickle cell anemia. Surgical intervention was successful and without significant sequelae. Duodenal perforation is a rare entity described in patients with sickle cell anemia. To our knowledge, this is the first report of duodenal perforation in a patient sickle cell anemia.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Sickle cell anemia</kwd>
        <kwd>duodenal perforation</kwd>
        <kwd>abdominal pain</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Sickle cell disease is an inherited condition resulting from a point mutation occurring in the triplet codon of the gene for the B globin chain of hemoglobin. Abdominal pain is a frequent symptom among patients undergoing sickle cell crisis. The abdominal symptoms that may be comorbid with sickle cell crisis are generally attributed to circulatory stasis and vascular occlusion. Sickle hemoglobinopathy-related gastrointestinal disorders include cholecystitis, abdominal pain crises (potentially associated with ischemic bowel injury), paralytic ileus, splenic sequestration and acute hepatic syndromes [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Peptic ulcer disease is the main cause of gastroduodenal perforation, followed, in order, by necrotic or ulcerated malignancies, iatrogenic injuries and traumatic injuries [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Surgery represents the essential element of treatment for gastroduodenal perforation. Gastroduodenal perforation associated with peptic ulcers frequently occurs in the gastric antrum and the duodenal bulb. The most frequent and regular finding in gastroduodenal perforation is extraluminal free air. However, this may not be present, especially at the onset of symptoms [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Although there have been previous reports of ischemic bowel injury in the gastrointestinal system in patients with sickle cell anemia, we encountered no cases of gastroduodenal perforation [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Duodenal perforation is a rare finding in patients with sickle cell anemia. We report a case of a 14-year-old child with duodenal perforation associated with sickle cell anemia.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Patient and observation</title>
      <p>A 14-year-old boy with homozygous sickle cell disease presented to hospital with abdominal pain, anorexia and intermittent vomiting over the previous 4 days. The pain was severe. His medical history was significant for sickle cell anemia. He had been diagnosed with sickle cell anemia at the age of 3 and had not received regular follow-ups. The most recent painful crisis had taken place 4 years previously and he had experienced no gastric symptoms to date. He was not using hydroxyurea.</p>
      <p>At physical examination, the patient&#x2032;s temperature was 36.7 &#xB0;C, heart rate was 96 beats/min, respiratory rate 20/min and blood pressure 100/60 mmHg. Examinations of the head, ears, eyes, nose and throat were within normal limits. Respiration was normal, and cardiac examination detected no abnormalities. No organomegaly was present. We identified diffuse abdominal sensitivity to palpation and rebound tenderness.</p>
      <p>Hematological values were white blood count 66.800/mm3, hemoglobin 7.8 g/dl and platelets 1.099.000/mm3. Coagulation profile and biochemical parameters were normal. Helicobacter pylori IgG and IgM values were negative. Abdominal x-ray film revealed free air beneath the diaphragm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>). Surgical consultation was performed. Preoperative diagnosis was perforation. Manual exchange blood transfusion was performed to reduce HbS. HbS decreased to 26% and hemoglobin increased to 9.1 gr/dl after transfusion. A 2x1 cm perforation in the anterior face of the second part of the duodenum was detected at exploratory laparotomy, and primary repair was performed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>). No problem was encountered at postoperative observation, and the patient was discharged without sequelae.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Free air beneath the diaphragm at abdominal x-ray film</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-18-217-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>2x1 cm perforation in the anterior face of the second part of the duodenum in a 14-year-old child with sickle cell anemia</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-18-217-g002"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0003">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Abdominal pain frequently accompanies sickle cell pain crisis, in which vaso-occlusive or infarctive crisis often leads to acute abdominal pain associated with ischemia and infarction. Approximately 10% of patients with sickle cell anemia are admitted to hospital each year due to acute abdominal pain. Factors implicated in this pain include vertebral marrow hyperplasia or infarct with nerve root compression, mesenteric and retroperitoneal lymphadenitis with infarction, and occlusion of blood supply to ischemic or infracted abdominal organs. Polymerization of HbS under low oxygen tension leads to distorted erythrocytes with reduced deformability. This in turn results in vascular occlusion and injury. The highly complex interaction between the endothelium, plasma factors, leucocytes, and rigid sickle red cells is also a significant factor in vaso-occlusion [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>Abdominal pain is frequently observed during vaso-occlusive or infarctive crisis and may lead to acute surgical abdomen [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Pre-operative transfusions are recommended for patients with sickle cell crisis undergoing surgical procedures under general anesthesia [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Preoperative transfusion was performed in our case, and HbS was brought down 26%. Mucosal ischemia associated with the microvascular abnormalities inherent in the condition may be responsible for the increased incidence of peptic ulcer disease in sickle cell anemia [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The most common cause of duodenal perforation is peptic ulcer disease [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. One study reported peptic ulcer disease in 7.7% to 35% of patients with sickle cell anemia [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Lee et al. [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] investigated upper endoscopic and gastric acid output in 51 patients with homozygous sickle cell disease and recurrent epigastric pain. They determined 39% abnormalities in the upper gastrointestinal tract, including 18 (35%) cases with peptic ulcers [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Our patient presented with abdominal pain and was diagnosed with perforation after examinations. In contrast to the literature, he had no symptoms suggestive of peptic ulcer disease. No etiological factor other than sickle cell disease was detected. Duodenal perforation was attributed to mucosal ischemia and hypoxia resulting from 4-day vaso-occlusive crisis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S0004">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Bearing gastroduodenal perforation in mind may be life-saving in patients with sickle cell anemia presenting with abdominal and back pain, even in the absence of any previous gastric symptoms.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="S0005">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0006">
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>All the authors have contributed to in the management of the patient or writing of the manuscript. All authors have read and approve the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Woods</surname>
              <given-names>KF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Onuoha</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schade</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kutlar</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Helicobacter pylori infection in sickle cell disease</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Med Assoc.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>361</fpage>
          <lpage>365</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10946532</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Engelhardt</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pulitzer</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Etheredge</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ischemic intestinal necrosis as a cause of atypical abdominal pain in a sickle cell patient</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Med Assoc.</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1077</fpage>
          <lpage>1088</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2681800</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ilgar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>ElmalI</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nural</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of abdominal computed tomography in determining perforation findings and site in patients with gastrointestinal tract perforation</article-title>
          <source>Ulus Travma Acil Cerrahi Derg.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23588977</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldman</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Punguyire</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osei-Kwakye</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baiden</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Duodenal perforation in a 12-month old child with severe malaria</article-title>
          <source>Pan Afr Med J.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22826726</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeong</surname>
              <given-names>YY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heo</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>HK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gastrointestinal tract perforation: MDCT findings according to the perforation sites</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Radiol.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>63</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19182505</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karim</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossoff</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siddiqui</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuchs</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Multz</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fulminant ischaemic colitis with atypical clinical features complicating sickle cell disease</article-title>
          <source>Postgrad Med J.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <issue>920</issue>
          <fpage>370</fpage>
          <lpage>372</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12151697</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sheehan</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machida</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Butzner</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute pancreatitis in a child with sickle cell anemia</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Med Assoc.</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>70</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8426390</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nazem</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walker</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sickle cell crisis and the acute abdomen</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Med Assoc.</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>787</fpage>
          <lpage>788</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3531534</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thirumalai</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terry</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Serjeant</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endoscopic and gastric acid studies in homozygous sickle cell disease and upper abdominal pain</article-title>
          <source>Gut.</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>569</fpage>
          <lpage>572</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2731748</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
