<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Revista do Instituto de Medicina Tropical de S&#xE3;o Paulo</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0036-4665</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-9946</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Instituto de Medicina Tropical</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25076441</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4131826</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0036-46652014000400017</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0036-46652014000400017</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>MOLECULAR IDENTIFICATION OF <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic> IN A
SERONEGATIVE CAT SCRATCH DISEASE PATIENT WITH AIDS IN RIO DE JANEIRO,
BRAZIL</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Identifica&#xE7;&#xE3;o molecular de <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic> em
paciente com SIDA soronegativo para doen&#xE7;a da arranhadura do gato no Rio de
Janeiro, Brasil</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Favacho</surname>
            <given-names>Alexsandra R.m.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">(1)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Roger</surname>
            <given-names>Isabelle</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">(2)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Akemi</surname>
            <given-names>Amanda K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">(3)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pessoa</surname>
            <given-names>Adonai A.</given-names>
            <suffix>JR.</suffix>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">(1)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Varon</surname>
            <given-names>Andrea G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">(2)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gomes</surname>
            <given-names>Raphael</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">(1)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Godoy</surname>
            <given-names>Daniela T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">(1)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pereira</surname>
            <given-names>Sandro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">(3)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lemos</surname>
            <given-names>Elba R.s.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">(1)</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>(1)</label> Laborat&#xF3;rio de Hantaviroses e Rickettsioses, Instituto Oswaldo
Cruz (IOC)/FIOCRUZ</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>(2)</label> Instituto de Pesquisa Cl&#xED;nica Evandro Chagas (IPEC)</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>(3)</label> Laborat&#xF3;rio de Pesquisa Cl&#xED;nica em Dermatozoonoses em Animais
Dom&#xE9;sticos (LAPCLIN-DERMZOO), Instituto de Pesquisa Evandro Chagas (IPEC); FIOCRUZ,
Rio de Janeiro, RJ, <country>Brasil</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Alexsandra R.M Favacho, Laborat&#xF3;rio de Hantaviroses e
Rickettsioses (LHR), Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, FIOCRUZ, Av. Brasil 4365, Manguinhos,
21040-900 Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brasil. Tel: <phone>+55-2125621727</phone>. Fax:
<fax>+55-2125621897</fax>. E-mail: <email>afavacho@ioc.fiocruz.br</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="com">
          <p>
<bold>AUTHORS' CONTRIBUTIONS</bold> ARMF conceived and designed the study,
performed analysis and interpretation of these data, and prepared the manuscript;
DTG, SAP and ERSL participated in interpretation of data and manuscript revision;
AAP, AAK and RG carried out the laboratory tests; IR, AV and ERSL carried out the
clinical assessment; all authors read and approved the final manuscript. ARMF and
ERSL are guarantors of the paper.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p><bold>COMPETING INTERESTS</bold> None declared.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Jul-Aug</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Aug</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>56</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>363</fpage>
      <lpage>365</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p id="para1">
<italic>Bartonella henselae</italic> is associated with a wide spectrum of clinical
manifestations, including cat scratch disease, endocarditis and meningoencephalitis,
in immunocompetent and immunocompromised patients. We report the first molecularly
confirmed case of <italic>B. henselae</italic> infection in an AIDS patient in state
of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Although DNA sequence of <italic>B. henselae</italic> has
been detected by polymerase chain reaction in a lymph node biopsy, acute and
convalescent sera were nonreactive.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p id="para2">
<italic>Bartonella henselae</italic> est&#xE1; associada a um amplo espectro de
manifesta&#xE7;&#xF5;es cl&#xED;nicas, incluindo a doen&#xE7;a da arranhadura de gato, endocardite, e
meningoencefalite, em pacientes imunocompetentes e imunocomprometidos. Relatamos o
primeiro caso confirmado por m&#xE9;todo molecular de <italic>B. henselae</italic> em um
paciente com SIDA no estado do Rio de Janeiro, Brasil. Apesar da sequ&#xEA;ncia de DNA de
<italic>B. henselae</italic> ser detectada pela rea&#xE7;&#xE3;o em cadeia da polimerase em
uma bi&#xF3;psia do linfonodo, soros das fases aguda e convalescente foram n&#xE3;o
reativos.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Cat scratch disease</kwd>
        <kwd>Human immunodeficiency virus</kwd>
        <kwd>Molecular diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Rio de Janeiro</kwd>
        <kwd>Brazil</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="10"/>
        <page-count count="3"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p id="para3">
<italic>Bartonella</italic> species are small, fastidious, Gram-negative, rod-shaped
bacteria that are associated with infections in immunocompetent and immunocompromised
patients. There are more than 22 species so far described in the
<italic>Bartonella</italic> genus, with <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic>,
<italic>B. bacilliformis</italic>, and <italic>B. quintana</italic> accounting for
the majority of human cases. <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic>, the main agent of the
cat scratch disease (CSD), is also associated with a wide variability in clinical
manifestations, including Parinaud's oculoglandular syndrome, endocarditis,
meningoencephalitis, disseminated disease, and fever of unknown origin<sup><xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. Immunocompromised hosts, particularly severely immunocompromised patients
infected with HIV, are more susceptible to infection from <italic>B. henselae</italic>,
and the clinical course may be more severe<sup><xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. The transmission of <italic>B. henselae</italic> from cats to humans frequently
occurs through direct or indirect scratches, bites, or licks from infected cats and
probably from the bite of an arthropod vector, <italic>Ctenocephalides felis</italic>,
the cat flea<sup><xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p id="para4">We report the diagnosis of <italic>B. henselae</italic> infection using
molecular methods in an HIV-positive patient who was negative to the gold standard
serologic tests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p id="para5">A 34-year-old man infected with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) from the
Municipality of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, was admitted to hospital in August 2011. Upon
arrival, the patient was uncomfortable and febrile (39.5 &#xB0;C) with a cluster of warm,
red, enlarged, tender unilateral lymph nodes on the right epitrochanteric (&gt; 10 cm),
axillar, supraclavicular, periauricular, and posterior cervical chain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1</xref>). A discrete nonpruritic rash was noted on the
torso and abdomen. The patient had been scratched on the abdomen and bitten on the thumb
by his 7-month-old kitten seven days before. He also mentioned numerous fleabites prior
to the start of his symptoms and that his kitten spent most of the time outdoors in
contact with roaming cats.</p>
      <p>
<fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1 -</label><caption><title>(<bold>A</bold>) Photograph of the right epitrochlear regions showing a
diffuse erythematous skin rash. (<bold>B</bold>) Total recovery from lymph node
lesions after antibiotic treatment (azithromycin).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0036-4665-rimtsp-56-04-363-gf01"/></fig>
</p>
      <p id="para6">Diagnosis of HIV seropositivity had been made two years previously. The CD4
count was 244 cells/mm<sup>3</sup> with a viral load of 215,857 copies/mm<sup>3</sup> at
admission. Other laboratory data revealed biochemical panel and blood count within the
normal range, elevated C-reactive protein, cultures from tissue biopsy and multiple
blood cultures were sterile for aerobic and anaerobic bacteria, mycobacteria and fungi.
The patient was positive for toxoplasmosis (IgG), but the serology studies for viral
hepatitis, cytomegalovirus, and syphilis were negative.</p>
      <p id="para7">CSD was suspected, but serum samples collected on days 11 and 19 of the
illness were nonreactive to <italic>B. henselae</italic>, using a commercial kit of
indirect immunofluorescence assay (IFA) for class-specific IgG antibody
(Bion<sup>&#xAE;</sup>, USA). In addition, the serum from the patient's cat was submitted
for IFA and was <italic>B. henselae</italic> reactive (titer of 64). Histopathological
examination of the posterior cervical node revealed a granulomatous inflammation and
neutrophilic microabscesses. No organisms were observed using Gram, Ziehl-Neelson, and
Warthin-Starry silver stains. Abdominal ultrasound revealed a slightly enlarged spleen;
the chest radiograph and transthoracic echocardiography were otherwise normal.</p>
      <p id="para8">Several days later, the patient maintained moderate fever associated with an
episodic dull abdominal pain and worsening of the epitrochanteric lesion. Abdominal
ultrasound and computed tomography of the abdomen on day 19 of the illness revealed an
enlarged spleen with multiple discrete nodules and intra-abdominal lymphadenopathy. A
lymph node ultrasound detected a large nonhomogeneous subcutaneous collection on the
anterior epitrochlear region that was collected prior to antibiotic therapy and
evaluated using culture and molecular analysis.</p>
      <p id="para9">Intravenous amoxicillin-clavulanate (1 g) and oral azithromycin (500 mg) were
started empirically to cover bacterial infections associated with a cat bite and were
stopped after eight days. Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole 160/800 mg and HAART (tenofovir
300 mg, lamivudine 300 mg, and efavirenz 600 mg) were subsequently initiated on the
20<sup>th</sup> day of hospital stay with a progressive and steady rise in CD4 cell
count.</p>
      <p id="para10">DNA isolated from patient and cat serum and lymph node tissue/aspirates
patient samples were used as templates for the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assays
using genus-specific primers targeting the 16S-23S rRNA intergenic region<sup><xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>, riboflavin synthase C gene<sup><xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>, the citrate synthase gene (<italic>gltA</italic>)<sup><xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>, and &#x3B2; subunit of RNA polymerase gene (<italic>rpoB</italic>)<sup><xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. A second step was performed using species-specific primers targeting the heat
shock protein gene (<italic>hrtA</italic>)<sup><xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> following reported protocols.</p>
      <p id="para11">
<italic>B. henselae</italic> DNA sequences were only detected on the histological (lymph
node tissue) sample, while the detection in cat serum samples was not confirmed. The
amplification products were purified, and the sequencing was performed using an ABI
PRISM BigDye terminator v.3.1 cycle sequencing kit (Applied Biosystems, CA, USA). The
resulting sequences (GenBank accession no. JX028199.1) were submitted to BLASTn, and the
nucleotide sequence generated from the lymph node sample clearly demonstrated 100%
identity with the homologous gene fragment of the <italic>hrtA</italic> gene from
<italic>B. henselae</italic> Houston-1 strain, complete genome. The diagnosis of
<italic>B. henselae</italic> lymphadenitis and splenitis was confirmed; the patient's
condition improved with the treatment, and he was discharged after 31 days of
hospitalization. Azithromycin was maintained for two months. The patient remained
asymptomatic and without evidence of recurrence of disease one year after hospital
discharge.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p id="para12">
<italic>Bartonella</italic> spp. have worldwide distribution and are zoonotic agents of
public health with importance in both human and veterinary medicine<sup><xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Although bartonellosis are not notifiable diseases in Brazil, the number of
cases has been rising in the last two decades (National Rickettsial Reference Laboratory
2012, unpublished data).</p>
      <p id="para13">This study presents the first report of molecular identification of
<italic>B. henselae</italic> in lymph node tissue specimen from a patient who is HIV
positive and seronegative to <italic>Bartonella</italic> infection in Rio de Janeiro,
Brazil. Although IFA assay is considered the gold standard technique for the diagnosis
<italic>Bartonella</italic>, this patient failed to develop normal antibody response
to this agent. Serologic sensibility varies from one laboratory to another ranging from
nearly 100% to &lt; 30%, depending on the antigen used, the cut-off chosen, and the test
procedures. In addition, serological assays exhibit low specificity and cross-reactivity
can occur between <italic>Bartonella</italic> spp. and agents such as Epstein-Barr
virus, cytomegalovirus, <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> and <italic>Streptococcus
pyogenes</italic>
<sup><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Therefore, the detection of <italic>B. henselae</italic> DNA by PCR and
nucleotide sequencing in the lymph node specimen proved to be useful in the diagnosis of
infection.</p>
      <p id="para14">The possibility that the patient's cat might have been involved in zoonotic
transmission was reinforced; the patient's cat was seroreactive to <italic>B.
henselae</italic> antigens. As cats may have persistent and asymptomatic bacteremia,
they represent a potential danger of exposure for people with immunosuppressive conditions<sup><xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p id="para15">The suspicion of CSD and the appropriate empiric antibiotic treatment, even
before the molecular diagnostics, improved the clinical status of the patient. Although
no follow-up PCR was performed, the patient remained entirely asymptomatic 14 months
after the illness. There are no controlled trials of treatment for bartonellosis in
HIV-infected individuals, but antibiotic treatment for at least three months has been recommended<sup><xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. In conclusion, given the low sensitivity of the serological assays, PCR
diagnosis for <italic>B. henselae</italic> should be considered for patients with
suspected CSD even after a negative result in serology test. This way, more frequent and
appropriate diagnosis will be made, leading to a better treatment and cure.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <p id="para18">We are thankful to Dr. Jairo Dias Barreira at Universidade do Rio de Janeiro
(UNIRIO) for the taxonomic identification of the cat's arthropod. We are also grateful
for the technical assistance of Endi&#xE1; Barros de Almeida at Hantavirosis and
Rickettsiosis Laboratory, on the serological techniques. We would like to thank CNPq for
student fellowships.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p><bold>FUNDING</bold> None.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>
<bold>ETHICAL APPROVAL</bold> This study was approved by the Oswaldo Cruz
Foundation/FIOCRUZ, the Comiss&#xE3;o de &#xC9;tica em Pesquisa - CEP (CEP authorization no.
559/10).</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sims</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regnery</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goral</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of <italic>Rochalimaea henselae</italic> DNA
in specimens from cat scratch disease patients by PCR</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>942</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8027347</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Breitschwerdt</surname>
              <given-names>EB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maggi</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chomel</surname>
              <given-names>BB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lappin</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bartonellosis: an emerging infectious disease of
zoonotic importance to animals and human beings</article-title>
          <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care (San Antonio)</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20230432</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dutta</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwarzwald</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edwards</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Disseminated bartonellosis presenting as neuroretinitis
in a young adult with human immunodeficiency virus infection</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>675</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20216243</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ayers M, McClure SC, Richardson SE, Tellier R. Detection
and identification of <italic>Bartonella</italic> species pathogenic for humans by
PCR amplification targeting the riboflavin synthase gene
(<italic>ribC</italic>)</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>1069</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12624031</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lamas</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mares-Guia</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rozental</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moreira</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Favacho</surname>
              <given-names>ARM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barreira</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<italic>Bartonella</italic> spp. infection in HIV positive individuals, their pets
and ectoparasites in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: serological and molecular
study</article-title>
          <source>Acta Trop</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>137</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20206113</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maggi</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breitschwerdt</surname>
              <given-names>EB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Potential limitations of the 16S-23S rRNA intergenic
region for molecular detection of <italic>Bartonella</italic>
species</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>1171</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15750079</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Norman</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regnery</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jameson</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greene</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krause</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differentiation of <italic>Bartonella</italic>-like
isolates at the species level by PCR-restriction fragment length polymorphism in
the citrate synthase gene</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>1797</fpage>
          <lpage>803</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7545181</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Renesto</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gouvernet</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drancourt</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roux</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raoult</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Use of <italic>rpoB</italic> gene analysis for detection
and identification of <italic>Bartonella</italic> species</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>430</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158086</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Resto-Ruiz</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>BE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of host immune response in pathogenesis of
<italic>Bartonella henselae</italic>
</article-title>
          <source>DNA Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>431</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12906736</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vermeulen</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verbakel</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Notermans</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reimerink</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peeters</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of sensitivity, specificity and
cross-reactivity in <italic>Bartonella henselae</italic> serology</article-title>
          <source>J Med Microbiol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>743</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20223899</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
