<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25648207</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4427755</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14-0518</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.14-0518</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Internal Medicine</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Note</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Nonsurgical resolution of caudal mediastinal paraesophageal abscess in a
cat</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>JUNG</surname>
            <given-names>Joohyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>CHOI</surname>
            <given-names>Mincheol</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Ilsan Animal Medical Center, Daehwa-dong 2030, Ilsanseo-gu,
Goyang-si, Gyeonggi-do, 411-803, South Korea</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>Veterinary Radiology Department, College of Veterinary
Medicine and Research Institute for Veterinary Science, Seoul National University, Seoul,
151-742, South Korea</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Choi, M., Department of Veterinary
Medical Imaging, College of Veterinary Medicine, Seoul National University, Seoul 151-742,
South Korea. e-mail: <email xlink:href="mcchoi@snu.ac.kr">mcchoi@snu.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>77</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>499</fpage>
      <lpage>502</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2015 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A one-year-old, castrated male domestic short hair cat was admitted with a history of
anorexia, regurgitation and pyrexia for two days. Fever and leukocytosis were identified.
There were a large soft tissue density oval mass in the caudal mediastinum on thoracic
radiographs, a fluid-filled oval mass in the caudal mediastinum on ultrasonography, and
left-sided and ventrally displaced and compressed esophagus on esophagram. On esophageal
endoscopy, there were no esophageal abnormalities. CT findings with a fluid filled mass
with rim enhancement indicated a caudal mediastinal paraesophageal abscess. The patient
was treated with oral antibiotics, because the owner declined percutaneous drainage and
surgery. The patient was admitted on emergency with severe respiratory distress; and
ruptured abscess and deteriorated pleuropneumonia were suspected. With intensive
hospitalization care and additional antibiotic therapy, the patient had full recovery.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>caudal mediastinal paraesophageal abscess</kwd>
        <kwd>CT</kwd>
        <kwd>feline</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Caudal mediastinal paraesophageal abscess (CMPA) is an uncommon mediastinal disease in dogs
and cats, demonstrating abscess formation outside the esophagus in the caudal mediastinum.
CMPA needs nearly always surgical intervention [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. We
report nonsurgical resolution of caudal mediastinal paraesophageal abscess with antibiotics
and supportive care in a cat.</p>
    <p>A one-year-old, castrated male domestic short hair cat, weighing 5.4 kg, was admitted with a
history of anorexia, regurgitation and pyrexia for two days and decreased appetite, weight
loss and nausea for a month. On physical examination, the patient had a fever of 40.4&#xB0;C and
tachypnea. Hematological examination revealed leukocytosis (24,400/<italic>&#xB5;l</italic>).</p>
    <p>Plain thoracic radiographs showed a large soft tissue density round mass in the caudal
mediastinum, multifocal patchy alveolar infiltration in lung field and left caudal pleural
thickening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig.1.</label><caption><p>Right lateral (A) and ventrodorsal (B) thoracic plain radiographs show a soft tissue
density round mass located in the caudal mediastinum. Sternal lymph node swelling, focal
patchy alveolar infiltration and irregular left caudal pleural thickening are
identified.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-77-499-g001"/></fig>). Abdominal ultrasound revealed a fluid-filled round mass without remarkable blood
signals in the caudal mediastinum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Abdominal ultrasound demonstrates a hypoechoic cavitary oval mass filled with swirling
fluid.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-77-499-g002"/></fig>). On esophagram using barium sulfate, the esophagus was left sided displaced and
compressed by this round mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Esophagram (A; right lateral view, B; ventrodorsal view) demonstrates that the
esophagus is displaced to the left and ventrally and narrowed by the caudal mediastinal
paraesophageal mass.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-77-499-g003"/></fig>). On esophageal endoscopy, there were no esophageal abnormalities including remnant
foreign body, inflammation, perforation or fistula. To further evaluate the nature of this
round mass, CT was performed under general anesthesia. There was a fluid density round mass
with rim enhancement in the caudal mediastinal paraesophageal region. This mass compressed
esophagus. And, multifocal patchy infiltration in bilateral lung lobes, severer in the left
caudal lung lobe and irregular left caudal pleural thickening were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_004">Fig. 4</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_004" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Computed tomography indicates a hypoattenuating abscess with rim enhancement in the
caudal mediastinum (asterisks in A, B, C, D and F). The esophagus (arrows in A, C, D and
F) was compressed and displaced to the left by adjacent CMPA. There are no evidences to
support association between the esophagus and CMPA at this time. There are multifocal
patchy infiltration in bilateral lung lobes (arrowheads in C and E) and left caudal
pleural thickening (black arrows in E).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-77-499-g004"/></fig>). Therefore, based on these imaging findings, CMPA and pleuropneumonia were diagnosed
clinically, although histopathologic and bacteriologic examinations were not performed. The
patient was treated with oral antibiotics using amoxicillin and clavulanic acid 62.5mg/cat PO
twice daily for 3 days before surgery. The patient showed better clinical signs with
antibiotics, and the owner declined percutaneous drainage and surgery on the day of surgery.
On 12 days of antibiotics treatment, the patient was admitted to the emergency department with
acute respiratory distress. The patient showed tachypnea on physical examination. Body
temperature was 39.3&#xB0;C. Plain thoracic radiographs showed disappearance of the caudal
mediastinal paraesophageal mass and increased patchy alveolar infiltration and pleural
thickening in the left caudal lung lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_005">Fig. 5</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_005" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Right lateral (A) and ventrodorsal (B) thoracic radiographs show resolution of CMPA and
deterioration with left caudal pleuropneumonia when the patient is admitted on emergency
with acute respiratory distress.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-77-499-g005"/></fig>). The mass was also not identified on ultrasonography. Unfortunately, bacteriologic
examination was not performed, because there was only a small amount of pleural effusion, not
enough for thoracentesis, in the left caudal lung field. Rupture or leakage of abscess and
deteriorated pleuropneumonia were suspected, because there was no remarkable change of CMPA
and pleuropneumonia on thoracic radiographs three days ago. On hematology, there was elevated
WBC (25,600/<italic>&#xB5;l</italic>) including remarkable increases in band neutrophil cells and
toxic change in neutrophils. Other clinical chemistry results were within normal limits. The
patient was further treated with combination antibiotics using metronidazole 15 mg/kg PO twice
daily and amoxicillin and clavulanic acid 62.5 mg/cat PO twice daily with aggressive
hospitalization care. The patient had full recovery for 21 days and showed no recurrence of
abscess or pleuropneumonia. The patient is doing well without any other complications for one
year.</p>
    <p>CMPA is an uncommon disease characterized by abscess formation adjacent to the esophagus
within caudal mediastinum [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. General clinical signs of
CMPA are pyrexia, lethargy and regurgitation associated with abscess and paraesophageal mass
effect. Additionally, in the case of concurrent pulmonary infiltration or pleural effusion,
there is coughing or respiratory distress [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Main causes of CMPA are known for esophageal disorders
including perforation due to an esophageal foreign body, endoscopic trauma and inadequate
wound closure or surgical materials left within the operative field in case of esophageal
cancer surgery in human and veterinary medicine [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This patient had CMPA and pleuropneumonia
concurrently, although the etiology is poorly understood. There were no evidences associated
with esophageal abnormalities. The esophagus was only associated with clinical signs of
vomiting and anorexia, because of extrinsic compression by CMPA.</p>
    <p>The most common bacteria associated with CMPA are <italic>Nocardia sp</italic> and
<italic>Actinomyces sp</italic> in the previous veterinary studies [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, most reposts submit
no results of bacteriology, because of previous antibiotics treatment [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Unfortunately, sampling from CMPA was not performed, because the owners
were afraid of complications of percutaneous drainage.</p>
    <p>Treatment of CMPA needs mediastinal drainage with antibiotics effective against anaerobic
bacteria. CMPA has favorable prognosis after aggressive surgical drainage. As initial CMPA
drainage method, there has been surgical mediastinotomy and transdiaphragmatic abscess
omentalization [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In human, percutaneous drainage is indicated, if the patients are old and have
disseminated intravascular coagulation, immunodeficiency, malnutrition or high risk of
re-operation [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Successful management of CMPA may depend on early diagnosis followed by
aggressive surgical drainage and suitable antibiotic therapy, and correction of the underlying
predisposing conditions. Fortunately, without surgical drainage, this patient had good
prognosis, because of early diagnosis of CMPA, spontaneous rupture of mediastinal abscess,
suitable antibiotic therapy and intensive supportive care.</p>
    <p>Diagnostic imaging modalities, such as thoracic radiographs, abdominal ultrasonography,
esophagram, endoscopy and CT, were all helpful to evaluate CMPA in this patient by stages.
Plain thoracic radiographs are usually the first choice exploration in CMPA and offer rapid
information of the lung and mediastinum including the esophagus. This cat had remarkable round
widening of caudal mediastinum and suspicious pleuropneumonia. However, esophageal
abnormalities or association could not be evaluated. This mass showed homogeneous soft tissue
density without air on plain radiography. Because of no gas in the mass, abdominal
ultrasonography was helpful. On ultrasonography, caudal mediastinal widening was a hypochoic
movable fluid-filled mass with well defined wall in the caudal mediastinum. A hypoechoic mass
with heterogeneous internal echoes or septation, hyperechoic thick wall and peripheral blood
signals can be specific ultrasonographic findings of abscess [<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, the ultrasonographic
differential diagnosis includes a caudal mediastinal abscess. But, it could not also evaluate
for esophageal relations. Esophagram with barium sulfate ruled out esophageal hiatal hernia
and showed paraesophageal mass effect; left and ventral displacement of esophagus with
flattening of esophageal lumen. There was no leakage of the contrast medium between esophagus
and a caudal mediastinal mass. Endoscopy showed no abnormalities in the esophageal mucosa and
ruled out remnant esophageal foreign body or small perforation. Therefore, the association and
complement between plain thoracic radiographs, ultrasonography, esophagram and endoscopy were
necessary for diagnosing CMPA in this patient. However, above all, CT was considered the best
imaging modality of CMPA diagnosis compared with the previous imaging procedures. CT was
specific in determining the nature of fluid fillled paraesophageal mediastinal mass and
pleuropneumonia. A hypoattenuating oval mass with rim enhancement of the circumference can be
specific images of abscess on CT [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Therefore,
CT findings were conclusive for CMPA in this patient. And, CT could rule out any other
concurrent or underlying diseases. And, it helps choosing the precise surgical plan.</p>
    <p>This is the first known documentation of non-surgical resolution of CMPA and pleuropneumonia
by antibiotics in a cat. This case is unusual, because general CMPA needs surgical or
percutaneous drainage, but this patient had suspicious spontaneous rupture of abscess and
worse pleuropneumonia and overcame this condition with proper antibiotics and intensive
supportive care. CMPA may be expected with good clinical outcome with prompt treatment after
an early diagnosis, even failure of bacteriological examination and surgical drainage.
However, CMPA may be life-threatening if not recognized in time. Fever and leukocytosis may be
the most considerable evidences for abscess. And, readily available diagnostic imaging, such
as thoracic radiographs, ultrasonographs, esophagram or endoscopy, is helpful for the
diagnosis of CMPA complementally. However, CT is the critical diagnosing modality of CMPA.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishlah</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaharudin</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sathananthar</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norie</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year>. <article-title>Posterior mediastinal abscess secondary
to esophageal perforation following fish bone ingestion</article-title>.
<source><italic>Med. J. Malaysia</italic></source><volume>63</volume>:
<fpage>162</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>163</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18942310</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Arellano</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gervais</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Computed tomography-guided drainage of
mediastinal abscesses: clinical experience with 23 patients</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Vasc. Interv. Radiol.</italic></source><volume>22</volume>:
<fpage>673</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>677</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvir.2011.01.427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21439848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year>. <article-title>Use of ultrasonography and secondary
wound closure to facilitate diagnosis and treatment of a cranial mediastinal abscess in
a dog</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Am. Vet. Med.
Assoc.</italic></source><volume>203</volume>: <fpage>1293</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1295</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8253621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Brissot</surname><given-names>H. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>. <article-title>Caudal mediastinal paraesophageal
abscesses in 7 dogs</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet.
Surg.</italic></source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>286</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>291</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22150504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosemurgy</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year>. <article-title>Life-threatening acute posterior
mediastinitis due to esophageal perforation</article-title>. <source><italic>Ann.
Thorac. Surg.</italic></source><volume>49</volume>:
<fpage>979</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>983</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-4975(90)90882-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2369200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fearnside</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brain</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Omentalisation of a caudal mediastinal
abscess in a dog</article-title>. <source><italic>Aust. Vet.
J.</italic></source><volume>89</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>220</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.2011.00705.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21595642</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Gianella</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfammatter</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgener</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>. <article-title>Oesophageal and gastric endoscopic
foreign body removal: complications and follow-up of 102 dogs</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Small Anim. Pract.</italic></source><volume>50</volume>:
<fpage>649</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>654</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2009.00845.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19954441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Koutinas</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papazoglou</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saridomichelakis</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koutinas</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patsikas</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>. <article-title>Caudal mediastinal abscess due to a grass
awn (Hordeum spp) in a cat</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Feline Med.
Surg.</italic></source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>46</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/jfms.2002.0182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12547622</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Osler</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>du Preez</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year>. <article-title>Application of ultrasound in the
diagnosis and treatment of empyema and mediastinal abscess in a dog</article-title>.
<source><italic>S. Afr. Med. J.</italic></source><volume>76</volume>:
<fpage>174</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>175</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2669176</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwingenberger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year>. <article-title>Radiographic, computed tomographic, and
ultrasonographic findings with migrating intrathoracic grass awns in dogs and
cats</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet. Radiol.
Ultrasound</italic></source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>255</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1740-8261.2008.00360.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18546780</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Seiler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rytz</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaschen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>. <article-title>Radiographic diagnosis&#x2014;cavitary
mediastinal abscess</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet. Radiol.
Ultrasound</italic></source><volume>42</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>433</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1740-8261.2001.tb00965.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11678565</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sim&#xF3;n-Yarza</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Viteri-Ram&#xED;rez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#xED;a-Lallana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>. <article-title>US-guided transhepatic drainage of a
mediastinal abscess</article-title>.
<source><italic>Radiologia</italic></source><volume>56</volume>:
<fpage>e21</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22464798</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sivacolundhu</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x2019;Hara</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>. <article-title>Thoracic actinomycosis
(arcanobacteriosis) or nocardiosis causing thoracic pyogranuloma formation in three
dogs</article-title>. <source><italic>Aust. Vet.
J.</italic></source><volume>79</volume>: <fpage>398</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>402</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.2001.tb12981.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11491216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rho</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eom</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>. <article-title>CT differentiation of abscess and
non-infected fluid in the postoperative neck</article-title>. <source><italic>Acta
Radiol.</italic></source><volume>54</volume>: <fpage>48</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>53</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23091233</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
