<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJO</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24008802</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4061687</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJO-62-365</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0301-4738.116486</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Brief Communications</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Meibomian gland dysfunction in a case of ichthyosis follicularis with alopecia and photophobia syndrome</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fatima</surname>
            <given-names>Tarannum</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mathur</surname>
            <given-names>Umang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Acharya</surname>
            <given-names>Manisha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Cornea, Dr Shroff Charity Eye Hospital, Daryaganj, New Delhi, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Dr. Tarannum Fatima, D-6/2 IGIMS Shiekhpura, Patna, Bihar, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="fatimatarannum@gmail.com">fatimatarannum@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>62</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>365</fpage>
      <lpage>367</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We are reporting an interesting case of ichthyosis follicularis with alopecia and photophobia syndrome in a daughter and father from the Indian subcontinent associated with Meibomian gland dysfunction. A three-year-old female child presented with pain, redness and severe photophobia in both eyes since one month. Cutaneous examination revealed ichthyosis, absence of hair all over the body including eyebrows, scalp and angular cheilosis. Ocular examination revealed bilateral severe meibomianitis, multiple superficial punctate keratitides in right eye and corneal epithelial defect in the left eye. Other systemic features were prominent high forehead and large ears. Her father had similar symptoms. Her symptoms improved after adequate treatment of meibomian gland dysfunction. She is asymptomatic at present.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Ichthyosis follicularis</kwd>
        <kwd>alopecia and photophobia syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>meibomian gland dysfunction</kwd>
        <kwd>ocular invovement</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Ichthyosis refers to a relatively uncommon group of skin disorders characterized by the presence of excessive amounts of dry surface scales. It is regarded as a disorder of keratinization or cornification and it is due to abnormal epidermal differentiation or metabolism. The syndrome of ichthyosis follicularis with alopecia and photophobia (IFAP) syndrome was first described in 1909 by MacLeod 1909 in three boys.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Recently, we observed a daughter and father with this syndrome associated with severe Meibomian gland dysfunction (MGD) in the eyes.</p>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A three-year-old child presented with complaints of pain, watering and severe photophobia in both eyes since one month. There was history of absence of hair all over her body including eyebrows and eyelashes since birth. There was dryness, itching and scaling of skin since birth, and recurrent self-resolving angular cheilosis. There was no history of delayed milestones, deafness, diarrhea and seizures. There was no history of consanguinity in the family. Vision could not be recorded at presentation due to severe photophobia. Ocular examination revealed bilateral severe meibomianitis, multiple superficial punctate keratitides in the right eye and a large corneal epithelial defect (7 mm &#xD7; 7 mm) in the left eye [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1a</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">c</xref>]. Fundus in right eye was within normal limits and in the left eye was not visible. Cutaneous examination revealed non-cicatricial complete body alopecia with severe angular cheilosis. The palms and soles were unaffected [Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">2a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">b</xref>].</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1a</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Female child with IFAP syndrome showing angular cheilosis</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-62-365-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1b</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Figure showing corneal epithelial defect in the left eye</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-62-365-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1c</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Severe Meibomian gland dysfunction</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-62-365-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2a</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Showing total absence of hair over the scalp and eyebrows</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-62-365-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2b</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Absence of hair in the limbs</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-62-365-g005"/>
      </fig>
      <p>She was given systemic erythromycin for two weeks. Hot fomentation of eyelids, massage of lids with tetracycline eye ointment, liberal lubrication and low-dose steroid fluorometholone BID was advised for two weeks. Antibiotic eye drop tobramycin QID was added in the left eye. One week after this treatment she had improved symptomatically. The epithelial defect in the left eye had healed with minimal scarring and the punctate keratitis resolved over 4 weeks. Visual acuity at final follow-up was 20/20 in right eye and 20/60 in left eye. Meibomian gland treatment was continued. She is asymptomatic at present.</p>
      <p>The father had all the systemic features as the daughter [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 3</xref>]. Ocular examination revealed bilateral severe meibomianitis. He was started on similar treatment as his daughter.</p>
      <fig id="F6" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Father with similar features</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-62-365-g006"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Generalized ichthyosis and alopecia have been reported in very few syndromes. These are ablepharon ichthyosis, alopecia ichthyosis and pseudo-hermaphrodites, alopecia &#x2013; skeletal abnormalities &#x2013; mental retardation, deafness ichthyosis, dermotrichic syndrome, ectodermal dysplasia &#x2013; alopecia &#x2013; mental retardation syndrome, Hayden syndrome, hereditary mucoepithelial syndrome, IFAP syndrome, ichthyosis deafness, Hirschsprung disease, ichthyosis hypertrichosis hyperhidrosis syndrome, KIDS syndrome, keratosis follicularis spinosa decalvans, Sjogren &#x2013; Larson syndrome, triculodermovertebral syndrome and woodhouse syndrome. Out of these conditions, ocular involvement is primarily seen in ablepharon ichthyosis syndrome, KIDS syndrome, IFAP syndrome and keratosis follicularis spinulosa decalvans syndrome. In patients with KID syndrome, nails are often dystrophic, teeth may be small or malformed and ocular changes are usually observed during the second or third decade. In addition, there is a congenital hearing loss, palmoplantar hyperkeratosis with leather grain-like keratoderma.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Our patient was a three-year-old female. She did not have deafness, ablepharon or patchy alopecia. She had very severe photophobia, non-scarring ichthyosis, total alopecia, high forehead, large ears and angular stomatitis &#x2013; all features that has been found in cases of IFAP syndromes reported till date.</p>
      <p>Forty cases of IFAP syndrome have been reported worldwide with different clinical manifestations.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] An interesting feature of this syndrome is that patients bear a striking resemblance to each other probably due to the loss of hair and photophobia.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</p>
      <p>Ocular abnormalities are important for the diagnosis of IFAP syndrome. The ocular features that have been reported up till now are punctate keratopathy, erosion, corneal scarring, atopic keratoconjunctival inflammation, horizontal nystagmus, myopia and absence of eyebrows and eyelashes.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] The presence of MGD as the cause of tear film instability has not been noted in the previously reported cases. Embryologically, the Meibomian glands are formed by the ingrowth of the basal epithelial cells at the inner margin and the sweat glands of Moll that arise from the wall of the hair sacs.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Being ectodermal in origin these are likely to be affected. Photophobia and punctate keratitis may be due to secondary to tear film instability caused by MGD. Kamo <italic>et al</italic>. have highlighted the pilosebaceous anomaly in a three-year-old boy with IFAP syndrome.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] In our patient, both photophobia and punctate erosions resolved with treatment of MGD. Adequate treatment of MGD helped in preventing the recurrent attacks of inflammation and scarring in our patient.</p>
      <p>Mode of inheritance in IFAP syndrome is not definitely determined.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Most of the reported patients were males, and in some families milder effects were noted in possible transmitting female. Recently, a mother and daughter,[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and two unrelated female patients,[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] with an IFAP syndrome have been reported. However, there are no reports till now, which shows a father to daughter transmission like in our case, which may throw some light to the pattern of inheritance in this disease. The daughter had more severe disease as compared to the father indicating the possibility of variable penetration of the genetic abnormality. In our case it seemed likely that the inheritance was X-linked dominant with variable penetrance.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, IFAP syndrome is a rare ectodermal developmental disorder with variable manifestation. A father and daughter with this syndrome are described in this report. Ocular manifestations are an important part of this disease spectrum. MGD may be one of the contributing factors for photophobia seen in this syndrome.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Macleod</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Three cases of ichthyosis follicularis associated with baldness</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1909</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>89</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harper</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oranje</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prose</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Text book of pediatric dermatology</article-title>
          <source>IFAP syndrome</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1348</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cursiefen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schlotzer-Schrehardt</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holbach</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pfeiffer</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naumann</surname>
              <given-names>GO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ocular findings in ichthyosis follicularis, atrichia, and photophobia syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>681</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10326971</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bron</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tripathi</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tripathi</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wolff's anatomy of the eye and the orbit</article-title>
          <year>1997</year>
          <edition>8th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kamo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohyama</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kosaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amagai</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebihara</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakayama</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ichthyosis follicularis, alopecia, and photophobia syndrome: A case report and a pathological insight into pilosebaceous anomaly</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermatopathol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21242756</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martino</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D&#x2019;Eufemia</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pergola</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Finocchiaro</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Celli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giamp&#xE0;</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Child with manifestations of dermotrichic syndrome and ichthyosis follicularis-alopecia-photophobia (IFAP) syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1456297</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sato-Matsumura</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsumura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumakiri</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosokawa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ichthyosis follicularis with alopecia and photophobia in a mother and daughter</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>142</volume>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10651714</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cambiaghi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barbareschi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tadini</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ichthyosis follicularis with atrichia and photophobia (IFAP) syndrome in two unrelated female patients</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>5 Suppl</issue>
          <fpage>S156</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12004300</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
