<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Malar J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Malar. J</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Malaria Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1475-2875</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26620122</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4665899</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">959</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-015-0959-x</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Repeated <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> malaria relapses in a Peruvian sailor</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>McFarland</surname>
            <given-names>Adam P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>mcfarlaa@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sanchez</surname>
            <given-names>Juan F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>chiroque@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mercado</surname>
            <given-names>Alejandro</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>amercadonoriega@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ventocilla</surname>
            <given-names>Julio A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>julio.ventocilla@med.navy.mil</email>
            <email>julio.ventocilla@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cavalcanti</surname>
            <given-names>Sofia</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>sofiacavalcanti0484@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
            <given-names>Sofia</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>sgonzalez1907@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lescano</surname>
            <given-names>Andres G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+51 94761-9799</phone>
            <email>andres.lescano.g@upch.pe</email>
            <email>wlescano@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>School of Medicine and Health Sciences, The George Washington University, Washington, DC USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Parasitology, U.S. Naval Medical Research Unit No. 6 (NAMRU-6), Av. Venezuela Cdra. 36 S/N. Bellavista, Callao, 03 Peru </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label/>Centro Medico Naval &#x201C;Cirujano Mayor Santiago Tavara&#x201D;, Peruvian Navy, Callao, Peru </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label/>School of Public Health and Management, Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia (UPCH), Lima, Peru </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <elocation-id>478</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; McFarland et al. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Two <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> recurrences in a Peruvian sailor with weight above the 60&#xA0;kg (cap for primaquine dosage) highlight the importance of adequate radical cure weight dosage for patient treatment and control efforts, particularly within the military.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 38&#xA0;year old, 76&#xA0;kg, 1.68&#xA0;m male Peruvian sailor presented to emergency room of the Peruvian Navy hospital in Lima on February 15, 2011. The patient reported a seven day history of fever, chills, and headache without significant past medical history. He had been deployed to a military base in a malaria-endemic area called VRAEM (Valle del R&#xED;o Apur&#xED;mac, Ene y Mantaro) from March 2010 to January 2011. The patient did not receive any pre-deployment prophylactic anti-malarials. His physical examination showed 39&#xA0;&#xB0;C fever, but had no neurological or respiratory symptoms, severe malaria, jaundice, nor liver or kidney infection or failure. His platelet levels were 120,000/mm<sup>3</sup> and leukocytes at 3400 cells/&#xB5;L; all other laboratory results were in normal ranges. The patient was diagnosed with <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> (<italic>P. vivax</italic>) malaria confirmed by blood smear on February 16th, and received a regimen of 3&#xA0;days of chloroquine concurrent with 7&#xA0;days of primaquine. He received 1&#xA0;g of chloroquine on the first and second day of treatment, and 500&#xA0;mg on the third day. He received 30&#xA0;mg of primaquine daily for the entire 7&#xA0;days. The drug administration was in accordance with the Peruvian Ministry of Health standards. Treatment was provided under supervision by health professionals with complete adherence. Fever resolved by the fourth day of hospitalization. The final thick smear on day 7 was negative. The patient was discharged with no symptoms on March 18, 2011.</p>
      <p>On May 20, 2011, the patient presented again to the emergency room with a 1-week history of similar symptoms. He reported no travel to other endemic areas since the previous hospitalization. He weighed 75&#xA0;kg, had 39&#xA0;&#xB0;C fever, his platelet level was 202,000/mm<sup>3</sup>, and leukocytes at 4300 cells/&#xB5;L. The patient had antibodies to the hepatitis B core antigen, but was negative for the hepatitis B surface antigen and other infectious diseases and parasites. A thick smear performed on May 20th tested positive again for <italic>P. vivax</italic>. The patient was provided the same treatment and dose as the initial (February) episode. His fever had resolved by the fourth day of hospitalization. The final thick smear was negative.</p>
      <p>The patient returned a third time with similar symptoms in August, 2011. He reported no travel to a malaria endemic area since his previous hospitalization in May except to visit family in Pucallpa city, Peru (Ucayali department, 52 cases of <italic>P. vivax</italic> in 2011), during which he only stayed in the urban area where no malaria transmission occurs, suggesting a low chance of re-infection. A thick smear tested positive for <italic>P. vivax</italic>. The patient was prescribed primaquine for 14&#xA0;days at 30&#xA0;mg per day and was released from the hospital after fully completing treatment under the supervision of Navy health staff. Microsatellite analysis was performed using the initial (February) patient blood sample and the second recurrence (August) thick smear in order to determine the genetic relationship between episodes. The six microsatellite markers tested were identical between the two samples (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Microsatellite analysis of <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> infection strains</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Sample</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Date</th><th align="left" colspan="6">Microsatellite markers (Chromosome position, marker ID)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">3.35, v33</th><th align="left">4.2771, v28</th><th align="left">6.3, v30</th><th align="left">7.67, v25</th><th align="left">12.335, v24</th><th align="left">14.185, v23</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Initial infection</td><td align="left">Feb-11</td><td align="left">118</td><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">157</td><td align="left">101</td><td align="left">162</td><td align="left">270</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Second recurrence</td><td align="left">Aug-11</td><td align="left">118</td><td align="left">87</td><td align="left">157</td><td align="left">101</td><td align="left">162</td><td align="left">270</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The periodicity of the symptoms, the patient&#x2019;s low risk of exposure, and the homology of the molecular data suggest that his second and third episodes of malaria were a relapse of the initial infection rather than a re-infection with a new parasite.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case discussion</title>
      <p>Primaquine is currently the only FDA approved drug to prevent relapses of <italic>P. vivax</italic>, as it targets the hypnozoites latent in hepatic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Many Ministries of Health in South America recommend a maximum of 30&#xA0;mg/day for 7&#xA0;days (210&#xA0;mg total) establishing a maximum weight of 60&#xA0;kg and only a week of treatment as compliance is low for longer time periods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. It has been suggested, however, that this total dose may be at the lower edge of reasonable efficacy and minimally effective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Several studies have demonstrated failure of primaquine due to inadequate dosage compared to body weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In this case, the maximum total dose of 210&#xA0;mg recommended by the Peruvian Ministry of Health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] was not effective for this patient. The subject weighed 25&#xA0;% over the 60&#xA0;kg weight limit and therefore received low-dose regimens twice. No more relapses were observed after a 14-day full dosage treatment. This is of particular importance for the military, as personnel tend to weigh more than the weight (60&#xA0;kg) used to calculate the maximum total dosage of primaquine. Additionally, the rise of obesity in malaria endemic countries could render standard treatment recommendations ineffective. Higher doses of primaquine are used in other regions, as current Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) standards advise a maximum dosage of 0.5&#xA0;mg/kg/day capped at 60&#xA0;kg (max of 30&#xA0;mg/day) for no more than 14&#xA0;days (420&#xA0;mg total) in G6PD positive individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. However, compliance remains a critical issue. Tafenoquine, a new drug undergoing clinical evaluation, has been shown to be significantly effective in a single dose taken with chloroquine in preventing relapse of <italic>vivax</italic> malaria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Until the safety and efficacy of tafenoquine can be further determined, the adoption of CDC recommendations and larger doses of primaquine are the only options to effectively treat patients and prevent relapse as well as contribute to the elimination of the parasite in endemic areas.</p>
      <p>A key question in this case is whether the patient&#x2019;s subsequent episodes of malaria were the result of relapse of dormant hypnozoites or re-infection with a new strain. After the initial hospitalization, the patient did not travel to any areas with malaria transmission, making re-infection unlikely. Additionally, the strains from the February and August blood smears were identical based on molecular analysis. The Amazon Basin is a region of high <italic>P. vivax</italic> diversity, and homologous strains would strongly suggest relapse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. While whole genomic analysis is necessary in order to completely determine if the strains are identical and therefore exhibiting relapse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], re-infection is doubtful due to the low possibility of transmission, homologous strains between hospitalizations, and high genetic diversity among <italic>P. vivax</italic> species in this region. <italic>P. vivax</italic> exhibits geographical variation in relapse patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Historically, it has been thought that frequent relapsing strains originate from the tropics, and that strains with a long latent period originate from temperate regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, the Amazon Basin is unique in that it contains both long-latency and frequent relapsing strains, complicating attempts to characterize the predominant relapse pattern [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Recent evidence has demonstrated that the majority of relapses occur within 2&#x2013;3&#xA0;months of infection, with 70&#xA0;% of relapses occurring within 5&#xA0;months of initial infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In addition, characterizing relapse patterns in malaria-endemic areas is inherently problematic as studies cannot completely distinguish a relapse from a new infection. True periodicity of relapse can most accurately be determined in patients with single, short exposure that minimizes the chance of re-infection. Travellers, including the military, are therefore good populations to study relapse patterns. In this case, the sailor did not travel to any areas where he could have been re-infected. His recurrent parasitaemia is most likely due to the reactivation of a latent strain. The two relapses occurring 3&#xA0;months apart are most likely representative of the relapse pattern common in the Amazon Basin.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, the frequent incidence of relapse of <italic>P. vivax</italic> in South America poses an important challenge for elimination. The 60&#xA0;kg cap on patient weight and 210&#xA0;mg maximum primaquine dose recommended in Peru and other South American nations may limit the efficacy necessary for radical cure in individual patients and control in the endemic population. This becomes increasingly important during the current epidemic of obesity, as a heavier patient population could negatively impact the management of <italic>vivax</italic> malaria and potentially other diseases, as well as the effectiveness of other anti-malarial drugs. Until more effective radical cure drugs are licensed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] or alternative parameters for dosing are explored (e.g. body mass index), clinicians can better prevent relapses in <italic>vivax</italic> malaria and support malaria control by using adequate primaquine dosing by weight and increasing the number of days of treatment up to 14&#xA0;days if needed.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>AM, SC and SG evaluated and monitored the patient. APM, JFS and AGL proposed the preparation of the manuscript. JFS and APM collected the data. JAV conducted the microsatellite testing. APM wrote the first draft. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      <sec id="d30e520">
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <p>The authors would like to thank the staff of the Peruvian Naval Hospital &#x201C;Cirujano Mayor Santiago Tavara&#x201D; in Lima, Peru, for their assistance to gather the information needed for this report. Also, we would like to thank LCDR Luis Loayza, DDM, for the arrangements of all necessary coordinations.</p>
        <p>
<bold>Disclaimer</bold> The views expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the official policy or position of the Department of the Navy, Department of Defense, nor the U.S. Government.</p>
        <p>
<bold>Copyright statement</bold> Several authors of this manuscript are employees of the U.S. Government. This work was prepared as part of their duties. Title 17 U.S.C. &#xA7; 105 provides that &#x2018;Copyright protection under this title is not available for any work of the United States Government.&#x2019; Title 17 U.S.C. &#xA7; 101 defines a U.S. Government work as a work prepared by a military service member or employee of the U.S. Government as part of that person&#x2019;s official duties.</p>
        <p>
<bold>Financial support</bold> The participation of Dr. Lescano in this project is sponsored by the training grant NIH/FIC 2D43 TW007393 awarded to NAMRU-6 by the Fogarty International Center of the US National Institutes of Health. Work was partially funded by the Armed Forces Health Surveillance Center, Global Emerging Infections Surveillance and Response System (AFHSC/GEIS) of the U.S. Department of Defense.</p>
        <p>
<bold>Consent</bold> Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for the publication of this report.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar2">
        <title>Competing interests</title>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hill</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baird</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parise</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryan</surname>
              <given-names>ET</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magill</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primaquine: report from CDC expert meeting on malaria chemoprophylaxis I</article-title>
          <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>402</fpage>
          <lpage>415</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968913</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baird</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evidence and implications of mortality associated with acute <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> malaria</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>36</fpage>
          <lpage>57</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00074-12</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23297258</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministerio de Salud del Peru. Norma T&#xE9;cnica de Salud para la atenci&#xF3;n de la Malaria y Malaria Grave en el Per&#xFA;. Resoluci&#xF3;n Ministerial. 2007&#xA0;No 076-2007/MINSA.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Durand</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cabezas</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lescano</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galvez</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gutierrez</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arrospide</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Efficacy of three different regimens of primaquine for the prevention of relapses of <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> malaria in the Amazon Basin of Peru</article-title>
          <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>18</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.13-0053</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24752682</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luz</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deckers</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tauil</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Subdoses of primaquine in overweight patients and malaria vivax relapses: report of two cases in the Federal District Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>749</fpage>
          <lpage>750</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0037-86822010000600033</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21181040</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goller</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jolley</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ringwald</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Biggs</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regional differences in the response of&#xA0;<italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> malaria to primaquine as anti-relapse therapy</article-title>
          <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>207</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17297026</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwartz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regev-Yochay</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurnik</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Short Report: a consideration of primaquine dose adjustment for radical cure of&#xA0;<italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic>&#xA0;malaria</article-title>
          <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>393</fpage>
          <lpage>395</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11037784</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Llanos-Cuentas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lacerda</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rueangweerayut</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krudsood</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kochar</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tafenoquine plus chloroquine for the treatment and relapse prevention of <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> malaria (DETECTIVE): a multicentre, double-blind, randomised, phase 2b dose-selection study</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>383</volume>
          <fpage>1049</fpage>
          <lpage>1058</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)62568-4</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24360369</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCollum</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soberon</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salas</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santolalla</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Udhayakumar</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Escalante</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic variation and recurrent parasitaemia in Peruvian <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> populations</article-title>
          <source>Malar J.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-13-67</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24386898</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bright</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alenazi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shokoples</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tarning</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paganotti</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic analysis of primaquine tolerance in a patient with relapsing vivax malaria</article-title>
          <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>802</fpage>
          <lpage>805</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1905.121852</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23648098</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Battle</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karhunen</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhatt</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gething</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howes</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Golding</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Geographical variation in <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> relapse</article-title>
          <source>Malar J.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>144</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-13-144</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24731298</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krotoski</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The hypnozoite and malarial relapse</article-title>
          <source>Prog Clin Parasitol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>19</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2491691</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Determinants of relapse periodicity in <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> malaria</article-title>
          <source>Malar J.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-10-297</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21989376</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Orjuela-S&#xE1;nchez</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>da Silva</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>da Silva-Nunes</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferreira</surname>
              <given-names>MU</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Recurrent parasitemias and population dynamics of <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> polymorphisms in rural Amazonia</article-title>
          <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>961</fpage>
          <lpage>968</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2009.09-0337</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19996423</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pedro</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guaraldo</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campos</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daniel-Ribeiro</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brasil</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> malaria relapses at a travel medicine centre in Rio de Janeiro, a non-endemic area in Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Malar J.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          <lpage>251</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-11-245</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22839416</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baird</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chloroquine resistance in <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic></article-title>
          <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>4075</fpage>
          <lpage>4083</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.48.11.4075-4083.2004</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15504824</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
