<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Intern Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J. Intern. Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJIM</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Korean Journal of Internal Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1226-3303</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2005-6648</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Association of Internal Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25378982</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4219973</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3904/kjim.2014.29.6.822</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letter to the Editor</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Funtional significance of the intermediate lesion in a single coronary artery assessed by fractional flow reserve</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ha</surname>
            <given-names>Sang Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kwon</surname>
            <given-names>Se Hwan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Soo-Joong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, Kyung Hee University Medical Center, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Diagnostic Radiology, Kyung Hee University Medical Center, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Correspondence to Soo-Joong Kim, M.D. Department of Internal Medicine, Kyung Hee University Medical Center, 23 Kyungheedae-ro, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul 130-872, Korea. Tel: +82-2-958-8180, Fax: +82-2-958-8160, <email>soojoong@dreamwiz.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>29</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>822</fpage>
      <lpage>824</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 The Korean Association of Internal Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Fractional flow reserve</kwd>
        <kwd>Coronary artery anomaly</kwd>
        <kwd>Single coronary artery</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>To the Editor,</p>
    <p>Congenital coronary artery anomalies are infrequently seen during coronary angiographic study, reportedly occurring in 0.64% to 1.3% of patients [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Most patients with a congenital coronary artery anomaly are asymptomatic; in rare cases, they may present with chest pain and have myocardial ischemia or other life-threatening conditions. We present a patient with the right coronary artery (RCA) originating from the terminal branch of the left circumflex (LCx) artery who presented with chest pain and was found to have a moderate stenotic lesion in the distal LCx artery. Fractional flow reserve (FFR) allowed us to evaluate this moderate stenotic lesion in a single coronary artery, and to treat with medical therapy only.</p>
    <p>A 63-year-old man was admitted to the cardiology unit with atypical chest pain. He had hypertension as coronary heart disease risk factor. His vital signs were stable, and physical examination showed no abnormalities. A resting electrocardiogram demonstrated a convex-shaped ST-segment elevation in the precordial lead without reciprocal change. Laboratory findings including cardiac markers showed no abnormalities. Echocardiography revealed normal left ventricular morphology, no regional wall motion abnormality, and a diastolic dysfunction of relaxation abnormality. The patient underwent coronary computed tomographic (CT) angiography. It demonstrated the presence of a single coronary artery with the LCx artery continuing in the course of the RCA and minimal possibility of chronic total occlusion (CTO) of the RCA ostium with a collateral supply from the LCx artery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). It also showed 60% diameter stenosis in the distal LCx artery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
    <p>To differentiate single coronary artery from CTO of the RCA ostium and confirm the degree of stenosis in the distal LCx artery, we performed coronary angiography. Selective left coronary angiography displayed normal origin and course of the left main, LCx, and left anterior descending arteries. The LCx artery did not terminate after reaching the crux; giving rise to the posterior descending branch, it coursed in the right atrioventricular groove as if it were the RCA and ended when it reached the right sinus of Valsalva (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). There was a stenosis of 60% diameter in the distal part of the LCx proper where the RCA arose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Attempts to engage the right coronary catheter into the RCA ostium were futile, and aortography obtained in the left anterior-oblique projection displayed the absence of the ostium of the RCA in the right sinus of Valsalva (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). To decide the functional significance of the stenosis in the distal LCx artery, we performed an FFR study with a pressure wire and found that there was no critical functional stenosis (FFR, 0.9) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). The patient was discharged with medications of aspirin, statin, nitrate, and &#x3B2; blocker and free from chest pain.</p>
    <p>A single coronary artery is an extremely rare congenital anomaly characterized by a single coronary artery ostium from an aortic sinus, and is seen in only 0.024% to 0.066% of patients who undergo conventional coronary angiography [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. A single coronary artery is usually asymptomatic and has a benign course, and these patients have a normal life expectancy. The presence of a single coronary artery may bring about myocardial ischemia because of the inability to adequately sustain normal coronary circulation [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p>
    <p>FFR is a physiologic parameter that can be readily measured during the invasive procedure and can evaluate the functional significance of coronary stenosis. In particular, FFR plays an important role when making a decision for percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) of angiographically moderate stenosis and assessing accurately the functional consequences of a given coronary stenosis with unclear hemodynamic significance [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In addition, the clinical outcome of patients in whom PCI is deferred because FFR indicated no hemodynamically significant stenosis was very favorable [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In this case, FFR was a good assessment modality because the lesion of interest in the LCx artery was a part of a single coronary artery that supplied both the LCx artery and RCA territories. With FFR, we could make a decision for deferred PCI and choose medical treatment, even though coronary CT angiography and coronary angiography showed moderate stenosis in the LCx artery.</p>
    <p>In conclusion, FFR could successfully evaluate the functional significance of a moderate stenotic lesion in a single coronary artery where the RCA originated from the terminal portion of the LCx artery.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sundaram</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kreml</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imaging of coronary artery anomalies</article-title>
          <source>Radiol Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>711</fpage>
          <lpage>727</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20705168</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lipton</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barry</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Obrez</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silverman</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wexler</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolated single coronary artery: diagnosis, angiographic classification, and clinical significance</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>39</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">758666</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pijls</surname>
              <given-names>NH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Bruyne</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peels</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Measurement of fractional flow reserve to assess the functional severity of coronary-artery stenoses</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>334</volume>
          <fpage>1703</fpage>
          <lpage>1708</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8637515</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pijls</surname>
              <given-names>NH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Schaardenburgh</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manoharan</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Percutaneous coronary intervention of functionally nonsignificant stenosis: 5-year follow-up of the DEFER Study</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>2105</fpage>
          <lpage>2111</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17531660</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Coronary computed tomography (CT) angiography findings. (A, B) Volume rendering CT imaging and (C) multiplanar reformation image showed a single coronary artery in which the right coronary artery (RCA) originated from a branch of the left circumflex (LCx) artery with minimal possibility of chronic total occlusion of the RCA ostium with collateral supply from the LCx artery.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjim-29-822-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) The single coronary artery visualized in the caudal angulation. (B) The left anterior oblique caudal view of selective left coronary angiography showed a stenosis of 60% in the distal left circumflex (LCx) proper artery (arrow). (C) Aortogram showed the absence of the right coronary ostium in the right sinus of Valsalva. (D) Flow fractional reserve demonstrated no functional significance of stenosis of the distal LCx proper artery.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjim-29-822-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
