<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Postgrad Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Postgrad Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPGM</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Postgraduate Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-3859</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0972-2823</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26119439</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4943410</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JPGM-61-193</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0022-3859.159426</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinicopathological Forum</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pulmonary choriostoma in a case of tuberous sclerosis complex</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Spalgais</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gothi</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Verma</surname>
            <given-names>AK</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Pulmonary Medicine, ESI-Post Graduate Institute of Medical Sciences and Research (PGIMSR), Delhi, India</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology, ESI-Post Graduate Institute of Medical Sciences and Research (PGIMSR), Delhi, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Dipti Gothi, E-mail: <email xlink:href="diptigothi@gmail.com">diptigothi@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Sep</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>61</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>193</fpage>
      <lpage>196</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; 2015 Journal of Postgraduate Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 52 years old lady was diagnosed to have Tuberous Sclerosis Complex (TSC) on the basis of 2 major and one minor criterion. She had family history of similar complaints in her sister and two sons. There was involvement of kidney in the form of angiomyolipoma, skin in the form of facial angiofibroma and teeth with a dental pit. She had an unusual lung involvement in the form of multiple small choristomas. Choristoma was diagnosed on transbronchial lung biopsy and was present in the form of disorganised striated muscles. The reported pulmonary manifestations of TCS i.e. lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM) and multifocal micronodular pneumocyte hyperplasia (MMPH) are types of hamartomas. Hamartomas and choristomas are both types of disorganized tissue. &#x2018;Choristoma&#x2019;of lung in TSC however is not reported. Clinopathological correlation of pulmonary hamartoma and choristoma, and treatment in TSC has been discussed.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>KEY WORDS</title>
        <kwd>Tuberous sclerosis</kwd>
        <kwd>choristoma</kwd>
        <kwd>hamartoma</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec1-1">
      <title>Case Details</title>
      <p>A 52 year old lady, normotensive, non-diabetic and non-smoker was referred to pulmonary medicine department of our institute for the evaluation of pulmonary nodules. She did not have significant respiratory complaints. She did however have a history of multiple admissions in the Medicine department during the past year for year for anaemia, anasarca and hydronephrosis. She also had history of non-progressive facial lesions since early childhood and similar lesions in one of her sons. Her sister died at the age of 40 of a seizure disorder. On examination, her vital parameters were normal. There were non tender, non- progressive, pale brown, papular lesions of about 2 to 8 mm over the cheeks. There was poor orodental hygiene with one dental pit found on oral examination. Systemic examination did not reveal any significant abnormality. Dermatological consultation diagnosed the skin lesions as facial angiofibromas (adenoma sebaceum). She was also detected to have mild mental retardation on psychiatric evaluation. Ophthalmological examination was normal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>Investigations</title>
      <p>The routine biochemical and hematological investigations were normal except for iron deficiency anaemia (hemoglobin-9.8gms/dl). The computed tomography of kidney, ureter and bladder showed multiple variable sized focal masses containing macroscopic fats almost completely replacing bilateral renal parenchyma suggestive of bilateral renal angiomyolipoma [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>]. The magnetic resolution imaging (MRI) of brain was normal as was the ECG and 2D ECHO. Endocrine evaluation showed hypothyroidism with thyroid stimulating hormone of 8.3IU/ml. An ultrasonography of the neck showed a 11 mm cystic lesion with thin septation in left lobe of thyroid. Thyroid scan showed mildly increased uptake with cold area in inferior pole of left thyroid. Fine needle aspiration cytology was consistent with a benign follicular nodule. The chest radiograph showed a few calcific lesions in both upper lobes with a few nodular lesions in lower lobes. High resolution computed tomography (HRCT) chest showed multiple randomly distributed nodules of about 4 to 13 mm in size in bilateral lung fields. Some of them showed calcification in the periphery and some of them were calcified completely. In addition there were cystic change in lingular region suggestive of localized lymphangioleomyoma [Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">d</xref>]. Spirometry showed restrictive pattern with forced vital capacity (FVC) 1.56 litre (55% predicted), forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV<sub>1</sub>) 1.28 litre (53%) and FEV1/FVC-82%.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>CT of the kidney, ureter, and bladder showing multiple, variable-sized, focal masses containing fats replacing the bilateral renal parenchyma, suggestive of bilateral angiomyolipoma</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-61-193-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>One of the sons&#x2019; MRI of the brain showing cortical tuber</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-61-193-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Another son's facial angiofibroma</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-61-193-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>HRCT of the chest showing multiple, randomly distributed nodules in the bilateral lung fields with calcification; calcified nodules marked with black arrows and noncalcified nodules marked with red arrows in (a-d) and cystic changes in the lingular lobe marked with an arrow in (b)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-61-193-g004"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-3">
      <title>Pathological Findings</title>
      <p>Lung tissue from the transbronchial biopsy showed largely normal lung tissue with one small bit showing a microcyst lined by cuboidal epithelium containing abnormally formed skeletal muscle with striations in the background of normal alveolar tissue suggestive of choristoma of lung [Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">b</xref>].</p>
      <fig id="F5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Transbronchial lung biopsy with (a) Hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) stain 100&#xD7; magnification and (b) H&amp;E stain 400&#xD7; magnification showing abnormally formed skeletal muscle with striations (marked with an arrow) in the background of normal alveolar tissue</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-61-193-g005"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-4">
      <title>Clinical Diagnosis and Discussion</title>
      <p>She was diagnosed to have tuberous sclerosis on the basis of two major criteria i.e. facial angiofibroma and angiomyolipoma of kidney. On family screening, one of her sons had mild mental retardation with multiple signal alteration seen in bilateral cerebral parenchyma in a nodular pattern, predominently located in the cortical region of bilateral high frontoparietal region on MRI of brain [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>]. The other son had facial angiofibromas [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>], renal angiomyolipoma and mild mental retardation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-5">
      <title>Management</title>
      <p>The Choristoma of lung and localized lymphangiomyoma did not require treatment. The patient refused surgical removal of angiomyolipoma. She was treated with sirolimus 2 mg per day for angiomyolipoma. The patient discontinued it after 2 months due to stomatitis and vomiting. She was also given levothyroxine and iron supplements for hypothyroidism and iron deficiency anaemia respectively. Patient is now on regular follow up for the last two years without disease progression. A comparative HRCT is given in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">b</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="F6" position="float">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(a and b) Comparative HRCT done 1.5 years apart showing no disease progression</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-61-193-g006"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-6">
      <title>Differential Diagnosis</title>
      <p>TSC is diagnosed on the basis of diagnostic criterion consisting of 11 major and 9 minor features [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>]. A definitive diagnosis of TCS either needs two major or one major plus 2 minor features.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Our patient had two major and one minor features as highlighted in bold text in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> confirming the diagnosis of TSC. The family history further supported the diagnosis.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Diagnostic criteria for tuberous sclerosis</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major features</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minor features</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facial angiofibromas (<italic>adenoma sebaceum</italic>) <italic>or forehead plaque</italic></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Hamartomatous rectal polyps</italic>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Non traumatic ungula or periungual fibroma</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple randomly distributed pits in dental enamel</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypomelanotic macules (&gt;3)</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bone cyst</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shagreen patch</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cerebral white matter migration line</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Multiple retinal nodular hamartomas</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Gingival fibroma</italic>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Cortical tuber</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Non renal hamartoma</italic>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Subependymal nodule</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retinal achromic patch</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Subependymal gaint cell astrocytoma</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confetti skin lesions</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Cardiac rhabdomyoma</italic>
              </td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple renal cyst</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <italic>Lymphangiomyomatosis</italic>
              </td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal angiomyolipoma</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn>
            <p>Bold texts are the lesions seen in our patient and italic texts are hamartomas seen in TCS</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>The reported lung manifestation of TCS are lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM), multifocal micronodular pneumocyte hyperplasia (MMPH), and clear cell tumour, of which LAM and MMPH are hamartomas.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Radiologically, MMPH presents as small, multiple randomly distributed nodules, LAM has cysts and clear cell tumour is a small solitary pulmonary nodule.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Our case on HRCT had multiple, randomly scattered nodules suggestive of MMPH. The nodules of MMPH are however less than 10 mm. These nodules do not have calcification and usually there is ground glass opacification.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] The nodules in our patient were &gt;10 mm. There was calcification and absence of ground glass opacity. The unusual features suggested either these lesions were precursor of LAM similar to histeocytosis X which is known to evolve from nodules, or variant of MMPH with calcification or a new manifestation of TSC. Transbronchial lung biopsy showed disorganised skeletal muscle suggesting the diagnosis of choristoma. The commonly seen lesions in TSC are hamartomas. Pathologically, pulmonary hamartoma is a benign neoplasm composed of cartilage, connective tissue, smooth muscle, fat, and bone.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] All these are native to lung. &#x2018;Choristoma&#x2019; is an entity similar to hamartoma but having non-native heterotopic tissue. Choristomahas not been reported in TSC. The other lesions seen in our patient on HRCT were cysts in lingular lobe. Characteristic features of pulmonary LAM are round, thin-walled cysts of variable size and contour distributed uniformly throughout the lungs with normal intervening parenchyma. They can involve the juxtaphrenic recesses and medial tips of the middle lobe and lingual but spare the extreme apices.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Thus, the cystic lesions involving lingular lobe suggested the diagnosis of localized LAM.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-7">
      <title>Clinicopathological correlation</title>
      <p>Tuberous Sclerosis Complex (TCS) is an autosomal dominant multisystem disorder characterised by the development of multiple hamartomas in numerous organs including central nervous system, skin, heart, kidney, eye and the lungs affecting 1 in 6000 people.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] The classical combination of seizures, mental retardation, and adenoma sebaceum also known as Vogt's triad is seen in only one-third of patients. Many of the TSC manifestations are hamartomasas shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> in italics. Of these, the skin, kidneys, brain, and heart hamartomas are very common. Hamartomas involving the retina, gingiva, bones, gastrointestinal tract, and lungs are rare.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p>
      <p>The pulmonary manifestations of TSC are primarily hamartomas. Hamartomas consists of tumorous native tissue whereas choristomas consists of of non-native abbarant rest. Hamartoma and choristoma, both are types of heteroplasias. Heteroplasia is defined as the development of cytological and histological elements that are not normal for the organ or part, in which they occur, or malposition of tissue/part that is otherwise normal. The former is choristoma, while the latter is hamartoma. Both are disorganized normal tissues of the body.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Choristoma (aberrant rest, heterotopic tissue) is histologically non-neoplastic tissue proliferationor nodule formation seldom reaching size greater than 1.5 cm.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] It may be single or multiple and may calcify.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Some of the choristomas had calcified in our case. The biopsy had picked up a non-calcified lesion hence calcification was not seen on biopsy but calcification was seen on HRCT. Skeletal muscle choristomas have been reported as an incidental finding associated with congenital anomalies of lung[<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] but not with TCS.</p>
      <p>Renal angiomyolipoma in our patient was diagnosed on the basis of macroscopic fat on CT scan, which is a characteristic feature of angiomyolipoma.[<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] Angiomyolipoma usually presents with Wunderlich syndrome, retroperitoneal hemorrhage, shock, or hyodronephrosis. Wunderlich syndrome is a rare condition, where spontaneous renal haemorrhage occurs into the subcapsular and perirenal spaces. Retroperitoneal hemorrhage is the commonest manifestation whereas hydronephrosis, the manifestation observed in our patient is seen rarely.[<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</p>
      <p>Follicular thyroid lesion seen in our patient could be incidental or a manifestation of TSC. It is difficult to prove or disprove one or the other. This is because small series and case reports have documented that tuberous sclerosis patients may have endocrine system alterations leading to dysfunction of the pituitary, parathyroid and other neuroendocrine tissue.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Pituitary adenomas, parathyroid adenomas and gastroenteropancreatic and adrenomedullary neuroendocrine tumours have been suggested as a feature of TSC.[<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] Benign thyroid nodules have not yet been reported in patients with TSC. Hence it is either a possible association or an incidental finding.</p>
      <p>There is no definite treatment for TSC. Surgical treatment is indicated for subependymal giant cell astrocytomas and symptomatic angiomyolipoma of more than 4 cm. Embolization of angiomyolipoma may also be performed if the size is more than 5cm.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Sirolimus is the only drug approved for the treatment of TSC. The indication for sirolimus in TSC is subependymal giant cell astrocytomas that cannot be removed surgically. Sirolimus has been also been studied in multiple randomized controlled trials for the management of kidney angiomyolipomas. Studies have shown that renal angiomyolipoma shrink during sirolimus therapy but tend to regrow after the therapy is stopped.[<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</p>
      <p>The most commonly reported sirolimus related adverse reactions are stomatitis, respiratory infection, skin lesions and hyperlipidemia. Our patient denied surgical management hence medical management was given, but it had to be stopped due to intolerable side effects.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-8">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In conclusion, Tuberous sclerosis complex is a multisystem disorder with formation of hamartoma in various organs. In addition to hamartoma of lung, choristoma, which is also a disorganized tissue, may be seen in TSC. Endocrine involvement may also be a feature of TSC. Medical treatment of TCS primarily consists of use of sirolimus.</p>
      <sec id="sec2-1">
        <title>Declaration of Patient Consent</title>
        <p>The authors certify that they have obtained all appropriate patient consent forms. In the form the patient(s) has/have given his/her/their consent for his/her/their images and other clinical information to be reported in the journal. The patients understand that their names and initials will not be published and due efforts will be made to conceal their identity, but anonymity cannot be guaranteed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2-2">
        <title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
        <p>Nil.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2-3">
        <title>Conflict of interest</title>
        <p>There are no conflicts of interest</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roach</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gomez</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Northrup</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tuberous sclerosis complex consensus conference: Revised clinical diagnostic criteria</article-title>
          <source>J Child Neurol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>624</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9881533</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Franz</surname>
              <given-names>DN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Non-Neurologic Manifestations of Tuberous Sclerosis Complex J Child Neurol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>690</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15563016</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moss</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Avila</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Litzenberger</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bechtle</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brooks</surname>
              <given-names>PG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence and clinical characteristics of lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM) in patients with tuberous sclerosis complex</article-title>
          <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>163</volume>
          <fpage>669</fpage>
          <lpage>1</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11520735</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kobashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sugiu</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mouri</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Irei</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakata</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multifocal micronodular pneumocyte hyperplasia associated with tuberous sclerosis: differentiation from multiple atypical adenomatous hyperplasia</article-title>
          <source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>451</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18535095</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>VK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abbas</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aster</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Robbins &amp; Cotran Pathologic Basis of Disease</article-title>
          <year>2014</year>
          <edition>7th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia (Pennsylvania)</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Elsevier Saunders</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baskin</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The pathogenesis and imaging of the tuberous sclerosis complex</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Radiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>936</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18414839</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Salant</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>George</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thorn</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polycystic kidney disease and other inherited Tubular Disorders</article-title>
          <source>Harrison's Text book Principles of Internal Medicine</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <edition>17th edition</edition>
          <publisher-loc>New yook</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Mc Graw Hill Medical</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1800</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tazelaar</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary angiomyolipomas nand multifocal micronodular pneumocyte hyperplasianassociated with tuberous sclerosis</article-title>
          <source>HumPathol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>1266</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <article-title>Osseous/Cartilaginous Choristoma</article-title>
          <date-in-citation>accessed on 15th February 2015. [Last accessed on 2015 Feb 15]</date-in-citation>
          <comment>
            <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.maxillofacialcenter.com/BondBook/softtissue/choristomabone.html">http://www.maxillofacialcenter.com/BondBook/softtissue/choristomabone.html</uri>
          </comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bansal</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Choristoma of the Oral Cavity</article-title>
          <source>Indian Journal of Pathology and Microbiology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>373</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551565</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fraggetta</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davenport</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magro</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cacciaguerra</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nash</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Striated muscle cells in non-neoplastic lung tissue: a clinicopathologic study</article-title>
          <source>Hum Pathol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>1477</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11150372</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Evans</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Curtis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The radiological appearance of tuberous sclerosis</article-title>
          <source>British Journal of Radiology</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10721329</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rapp</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lucioni</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sokoloff</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Angiomyolipoma Lesion Causing Unilateral Ureteral Obstruction</article-title>
          <source>The Internet Journal of Urology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <date-in-citation>accessed on 15th January 2015</date-in-citation>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <comment>Number 2, available at
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://ispub.com/IJU/2/2/12360">https://ispub.com/IJU/2/2/12360</uri></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DworakowskaDorota</surname>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grossman</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Are neuroendocrine tumours a feature of tuberous sclerosis?</article-title>
          <source>A systematic review Endocrine-Related Cancer</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18978035</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
              <given-names>ZF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>TT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>ZH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Efficacy and safety of sirolimus for renal angiomyolipoma in patients with tuberous sclerosis complex or sporadic lymphangioleiomyomatosis: a systematic review</article-title>
          <source>J Urol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>192</volume>
          <fpage>1424</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24813310</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
