<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJO</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25971183</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4448251</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJO-63-284</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0301-4738.156941</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Brief Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Isolated abscess in superior rectus muscle in a child</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bhalerao</surname>
            <given-names>Sushank Ashok</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Singh</surname>
            <given-names>Kamaljeet</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yadav</surname>
            <given-names>Birendra</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>Ravindra</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Ophthalmology, Regional Institute of Ophthalmology at Govt. M. D. Eye Hospital, Allahabad, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Dr. Sushank Ashok Bhalerao, Regional Institute of Ophthalmology at Govt. M. D. Eye Hospital, Dr. Katju Road, Allahabad - 211 003, Uttar Pradesh, India. E-mail: <email xlink:href="sushank55555@gmail.com">sushank55555@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>63</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>284</fpage>
      <lpage>286</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pyomyositis is a primary bacterial infection of striated muscles nearly always caused by <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. Development of the intramuscular abscess involving the extra-ocular muscles (EOMs) remains an extremely rare process. We herein present a case of isolated EOM pyomyositis involving superior rectus muscle in a 2-year male child who was referred with complaints of swelling in left eye (LE) and inability to open LE since last 1-month. Orbital computed tomography (CT) scan showed a well-defined, hypo-dense, peripheral rim-enhancing lesion in relation to left superior rectus muscle suggestive of left superior rectus abscess. The abscess was drained through skin approach. We concluded that pyomyositis of EOM should be considered in any patient presenting with acute onset of orbital inflammation and characteristic CT or magnetic resonance imaging features. Management consists of incision and drainage coupled with antibiotic therapy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Extra-ocular muscle</kwd>
        <kwd>pyomyositis</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>superior rectus abscess</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Pyomyositis is an acute bacterial infection occurring in the skeletal muscle. It was first described in 1885 by Scriba as an endemic disease in the tropics. Pyomyositis is a primary bacterial infection of striated muscles nearly always (over 90% of cases) caused by <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</p>
    <p>Any skeletal muscle can be involved, but the thigh and trunk muscles are commonly affected. Development of an intramuscular abscess involving the extra-ocular muscles (EOMs) remains an extremely rare process. It usually presents as pain, swelling, redness and movement restriction in the eye. Systemic symptoms may or may not be present. To our knowledge, only seven cases of pyomyositis in the eye have been reported in the literature.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</p>
    <p>An idiopathic muscle abscess is a rare condition that should be considered in the differential diagnosis of painful limitations of eye movements and double vision in children.</p>
    <p>We herein present a case of isolated EOM pyomyositis involving superior rectus muscle in a 2-year-old male child.</p>
    <sec id="sec1-1">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 2-year-old male child was referred to our hospital with complaints of swelling in left eye (LE) and inability to open LE since last 1-month [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>]. There was a history of fever since 1-month. On examination, there was a tender, palpable, ill-defined mass with a nodular surface was found in a superior portion of the orbit. Posterior segment was normal.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Patient photographs before (a), and 1-month after (b) treatment</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-63-284-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Ocular sonography (standardized echography, A- and B-scan) showed a thickening of the left superior rectus. Orbital computed tomography (CT) scan shows fullness in the superior portion of orbit due to a well-defined, hypo-dense, peripheral rim-enhancing lesion in relation to left superior rectus muscle closely abutting the globe without any intra-ocular extension. The sagittal reconstruction shows a ring-enhancing lesion in the superior rectus, suggestive of an abscess [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>]. Blood culture was negative.</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Computed tomography scan shows fullness in the superior portion of orbit due to a well-defined, hypo-dense, peripheral rim-enhancing lesion in relation to left superior rectus muscle closely abutting the globe without any intra-ocular extension. The sagittal reconstruction shows a ring-enhancing lesion in the superior rectus, suggestive of an abscess. Optic nerve was uninvolved. The, antero-posterior, cranio-caudal and transverse dimensions of the abscess were 2.0 cm, 1.2 cm and 1.8 cm respectively</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-63-284-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Provisional diagnosis of superior rectus muscle abscess was made, and the patient was started on cefotaxime 500 mg 12 hourly and gentamicin 40 mg 8 hourly intravenously. On the 2<sup>nd</sup> day, pus was drained through the skin approach. The swelling reduced on 2<sup>nd</sup> postoperative day and the child was able to open his LE. Gram stain showed Gram-positive cocci and the culture grew <italic>S. aureus</italic>. He was discharged with gatifloxacin twice daily orally. After 1-month, he had residual restriction in motility in superior gaze [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-2">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Of the seven reported cases, five were due to <italic>S. aureus</italic> and the two were idiopathic. <italic>S. aureus</italic> is responsible for 95% of the cases in tropical areas and 70% of the cases of pyomyositis in nontropical areas.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] The etiology of pyomyositis is uncertain.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Given the lack of adjacent orbital inflammation in our cases, we suspect that recti muscles were possibly seeded through hematogenous spread.</p>
      <p>Although the clinical features are frequently suggestive of myositis, they are nonspecific, and noninvasive investigations such as orbital ultrasonography and CT or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans are required for precise anatomical tissue localization and diagnosis. The role of ocular muscle biopsy is probably limited to atypical cases or those unresponsive to therapy, particularly to exclude neoplasia.</p>
      <p>Haufschild <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] reported an idiopathic isolated abscess of superior rectus muscle in an 11-year-old girl. MRI showed an abscess with central cavitation and a rim of enhancement. The patient was treated with intravenous antibiotics. Varma <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] reported two cases of young boys with EOM abscess on MRI. In both the patients, ultrasonography-guided aspiration was performed, and the patients were treated with antibiotics. The culture grew Staphylococcus in both of them. Acharya and Jethani[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] reported four cases of isolated EOM pyomyositis. CT scan of all patients showed a typical hypo-dense rim-enhancing lesion of the muscle involved. In all the above studies, patients were treated with intravenous antibiotics and drainage of pus.</p>
      <p>Main differential diagnoses in children are other inflammations and infections (e.g., diffuse orbital pseudotumor, orbital cellulitis), structural lesions (e.g., dermoid cyst), vascular neoplastic lesions (e.g., capillary hemangioma, lymphangioma), lymphoproliferative diseases (e.g., lymphocytic granuloma), neurogenic tumors (e.g., neuroblastoma, plexiform neurofibroma), mesenchymal tumors (e.g., rhabdomyosarcoma), and metastatic carcinoma. Differentiating features found in our patient suggestive of left superior rectus abscess were inability to open and swelling in LE, tender, palpable, ill-defined mass with a nodular surface in superior portion of orbit and orbital CT scan showing a well-defined, hypo-dense, peripheral rim-enhancing lesion in relation to left superior rectus muscle.</p>
      <p>It can be concluded that pyomyositis of EOM should be considered in any patient presenting with acute onset of orbital inflammation and characteristic CT or MRI features. After making the diagnosis, incision and drainage coupled with antibiotics eradicate the infection in most patients and the same happened in our patient.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scriba</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Beitrag zur aetiology of acute myositis</article-title>
          <source>Dtsch Z Chir</source>
          <year>1885</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>497</fpage>
          <lpage>507</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haufschild</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weber</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nuttli</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hecker</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flammer</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaiser</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Idiopathic isolated abscess in an extraocular muscle in a child</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>1233</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15302671</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Varma</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rathi</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malik</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolated abscess of extraocular muscle in two young boys: Clinical and imaging features</article-title>
          <source>Orbit</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12759870</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Acharya</surname>
              <given-names>IG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jethani</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pyomyositis of extraocular muscle: Case series and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>532</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20952842</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shepherd</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tropical myositis: Is it an entity and what is its cause?</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>1240</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6139580</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
