<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Orthop Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Orthop Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CIOS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2005-291X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2005-4408</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Orthopaedic Association</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25177464</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4143526</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4055/cios.2014.6.3.358</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Spontaneous Acetabular Periprosthetic Fracture in a Patient Continuously Having Zoledronic Acid</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tantavisut</surname>
            <given-names>Saran</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Tanavalee</surname>
            <given-names>Aree</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thanakit</surname>
            <given-names>Voranuch</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ngarmukos</surname>
            <given-names>Srihatach</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wilairatana</surname>
            <given-names>Vajara</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wangroongsub</surname>
            <given-names>Yongsak</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Department of Orthopaedics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>*</label>Department of Pathology, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Correspondence to: Aree Tanavalee, MD. Department of Orthopaedics, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, 1873 Rama IV Road, Bangkok 10330, Thailand. Tel: +66-2-256-4212, Fax: +66-2-256-4625, <email>areetana@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>05</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>358</fpage>
      <lpage>360</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 by The Korean Orthopaedic Association</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zoledronic acid has been used for prevention of osteolytic and osteoblastic bone metastasis. This case report illustrates an undesirable consequence from prolonged usage of zoledronic acid in bone metastasis prevention. Periprosthetic acetabular fracture in a patient treated with zoledronic acid for 7 years was reported. The clinical presentation, radiographic and pathological results were described. This is a rare complication after total hip arthroplasty which should not be ignored especially in patients who received long term bisphosphonate.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Hip arthroplasty</kwd>
        <kwd>Fracture</kwd>
        <kwd>Loosening</kwd>
        <kwd>Zoledronic acid</kwd>
        <kwd>Bisphosphonate</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Zoledronic acid has been used for prevention of osteolytic and osteoblastic bone metastases.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1)</xref> Additionally, Bobyn et al.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref> demonstrated that bisphosphonates improved cementless implant fixation by enhancing osteointegration. However, a long-term usage of bisphosphonates has been reported to relate with atypical fracture in subtrochanteric area.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4)</xref> To our knowledge, the periprosthetic acetabular fracture in association with the use of bisphosphonate has never been reported. We report a case of periprosthetic acetabular fracture in a patient having continuous zoledronic acid.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 75-year-old Asian woman was presented at our department in 2009, with a sudden right groin pain and a limp. She had the history of right breast cancer and was treated with simple mastectomy 15 years ago. She started her continuous course of 4-mg intravenous zoledronic acid therapy for every 6 weeks since 2002 when she was 68 years old. She developed progressive right hip pain due to primary osteoarthritis and underwent cementless total hip arthroplasty (THA) in late 2007. The preoperative radiograph showed reactive lateral cortex thickening at subtrochanteric area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Zoledronic acid course was cessated 3 months before the surgery and restarted again at 6 weeks after a THA. At the surgery, a specimen biopsy was taken around the right hip. The histological finding of the specimens and bones showed no evidence of malignant cells. The immediate postoperative radiograph is demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>. Following the THA, she had pain-free and improved clinical functions with well-aligned implant position shown on the radiograph. In 2009, following a long day of walking, she developed a sudden right groin pain and a limp. The radiograph and computerized tomography demonstrated a complete transverse acetabular fracture of the superomedial ilium with migration of acetabular component (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). A revision total hip surgery was performed. Intraoperatively, the acetabular component was easily removed with no evidence of bone ingrowth while the femoral component was well-fixed. The gross appearance of the acetabulum was yellowish without any abnormal space occupying soft tissue. The specimen from the periacetabular bone revealed necrosis of hematopoietic marrow, fat with various calcifications, and diffuse lack of osteocytes as osteonecrosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Periprosthetic fracture of acetabulum is an uncommon complication after a THA.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref> According to few of the previous studies, the causes of a postoperative fracture were related to unidentified intraoperative fracture,<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6)</xref> severe osteolysis,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref> trauma,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8)</xref> and stress fracture.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9)</xref> We considered that the periprosthetic acetabular fracture in this study was associated with zoledronic acid, due to 2 reasons. Firstly, the cortical thickening was observed in the lateral (tension) side of the subtrochanteric area, on a preoperative radiograph (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). This is a specific prefracture radiographic pattern resulting from a long-term use of bisphosphonate.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10)</xref> It can relatively indicates that the patient had sufficient dosage or length of time on bisphosphonate administration to cause systemic negative effects. Secondly, the specimen collected from the periprosthetic acetabular fracture site presented an unusual pathological result (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
      <p>We believe that following the cementless fixation of the acetabular component, the stability was dependent on mechanical fit and screw augmentation, while the biological fixation has not been developed. The acetabulum failed due to the chronic stress from repetitive workload with daily activities. A spontaneous fracture can indicate an extreme inhibition of bone turnover following a long-term therapy of zoledronic acid. However, atypical fracture in subtrochanteric area did not occur in this case, because the application of femoral prosthesis bypassed the subtrochanteric area.</p>
      <p>Zoledronic acid has been reported to have potential role of inducing osteointegration in cementless prosthesis.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref> However, the findings in this case were discordant with those reported studies. These findings may indicate that zoledronic acid did not enhance cementless fixation or the doses administered in this case was not proper to induce osteointegration.</p>
      <p>This case report informs the surgeons that a prolonged use of zoledronic for prevention of bone metastasis can cause periprosthetic acetabular fracture. The cessation of bisphosphonate, application of anabolic agent, and a period of delay before weight bearing may reduce the incidence of such complication. However, further study is needed to clarify these issues.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coleman</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seaman</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of zoledronic acid in cancer: clinical studies in the treatment and prevention of bone metastases</article-title>
          <source>Semin Oncol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>2 Suppl 6</issue>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>16</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11346860</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bobyn</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hacking</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krygier</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harvey</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Little</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanzer</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Zoledronic acid causes enhancement of bone growth into porous implants</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>416</fpage>
          <lpage>420</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15773657</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wernecke</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Namdari</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DiCarlo</surname>
              <given-names>EF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lane</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case report of spontaneous, nonspinal fractures in a multiple myeloma patient on long-term pamidronate and zoledronic acid</article-title>
          <source>HSS J</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>123</fpage>
          <lpage>127</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18815855</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lenart</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neviaser</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lyman</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Association of low-energy femoral fractures with prolonged bisphosphonate use: a case control study</article-title>
          <source>Osteoporos Int</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1353</fpage>
          <lpage>1362</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19066707</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McElfresh</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coventry</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Femoral and pelvic fractures after total hip arthroplasty</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>483</fpage>
          <lpage>492</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4822511</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharkey</surname>
              <given-names>PF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hozack</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Callaghan</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acetabular fracture associated with cementless acetabular component insertion: a report of 13 cases</article-title>
          <source>J Arthroplasty</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>426</fpage>
          <lpage>431</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10428222</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez-Sotelo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McGrory</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berry</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute periprosthetic fracture of the acetabulum associated with osteolytic pelvic lesions: a report of 3 cases</article-title>
          <source>J Arthroplasty</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>126</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10654474</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gelalis</surname>
              <given-names>ID</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Politis</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arnaoutoglou</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Georgakopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitsiou</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xenakis</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Traumatic periprosthetic acetabular fracture treated by acute one-stage revision arthroplasty: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Injury</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>421</fpage>
          <lpage>424</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19896125</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andrews</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barrack</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stress fracture of the medial wall of the acetabulum adjacent to a cementless acetabular component</article-title>
          <source>J Arthroplasty</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>117</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805938</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cermak</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shumelinsky</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alexiou</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gebhart</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case reports: subtrochanteric femoral stress fractures after prolonged alendronate therapy</article-title>
          <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>468</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>1991</fpage>
          <lpage>1996</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20020334</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Preoperative radiograph showing the lateral cortex thickening in the subtrochanteric area and osteoarthritic change of the hip.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-6-358-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Immediate postoperative radiograph.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-6-358-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Radiograph (A) and computer tomography scan (B) taken before the revision surgery showing transverse fracture of the acetabulum and loosened acetabular component.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-6-358-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Photomicrograph of the bone from the acetabular fragment at the time of the revision arthroplasty showing complete absence of osteoclastic and osteoblastic activity.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-6-358-g004"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
