<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cir Dig</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arq Bras Cir Dig</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cirurgia Digestiva : ABCD = Brazilian Archives of Digestive Surgery</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0102-6720</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2317-6326</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Col&#xE9;gio Brasileiro de Cirurgia Digestiva</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25626947</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4743230</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-67202014000400020</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letter to the Editor</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Local excision of papillary adenoma in patients with high surgical risk
for pancreaticoduodenectomy</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Excis&#xE3;o local de adenoma de papila em paciente com risco
cir&#xFA;rgico elevado para duodenopancreatectomia</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>ALMEIDA</surname>
            <given-names>Alexandra Mano</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>CO&#xCA;LHO</surname>
            <given-names>Gustavo R&#xEA;go</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SALES</surname>
            <given-names>Rodrigo Martins Paiva</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>GARCIA</surname>
            <given-names>Jos&#xE9; Huygens Parente</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff>From the Hospital Universit&#xE1;rio Walter Cant&#xED;dio, Faculdade de
Medicina, Universidade Federal do Cear&#xE1; (University Hospital Walter
Cant&#xED;dio, Faculty of Medicine, Federal University of Cear&#xE1;), Fortaleza,
Cear&#xE1;, Brazil</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Alexandra Mano Almeida. E-mail:
<email>alexandra_mano@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Oct-Dec</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Oct-Dec</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>27</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>306</fpage>
      <lpage>308</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License, which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Benign tumors of the hepatoduodenal ampulla are rare, with few cases reported in the
world literature. Among these tumors adenomas, lipomas, hemangiomas, carcinoid and
leiomyomas have been described. The villous adenoma remains the most frequent<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.
Necropsy studies have shown an incidence of around 0.04% to 0.12%, and for this rarely
remembered in the periampullary lesions differential diagnosis<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The adenoma of it affects more frequently women, an age group between 5<sup>th</sup> and
7<sup>th</sup> decades, and is often associated with colonic polyposis. Initially,
the patient may be asymptomatic and clinical findings begin to emerge with the growth of
the tumor<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The most common symptoms are biliary colic pain type and gastrointestinal bleeding; in
some cases there may be pancreatitis and obstructive jaundice<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. The diagnosis is given by histopathological lesion
obtained by upper endoscopy with duodenal papilla vision and always colonoscopy should
be performed to identify adenomatous colonic polyposis.</p>
      <p>Some authors<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> believe in the
existence of a pre-malignant lesions, where as malignant degeneration occurs in 30-40%
of cases. Because of this potential for considerable degeneration, treatment is still
controversial, with numerous discussions about the best approach, endoscopic, surgical
with it transduodenal local excision or pancreaticoduodenectomy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Woman of 77 years was admitted in General and Digestive Surgery Service, Walter
Cant&#xED;dio University Hospital,Fortaleza, CE, Brazil. Three months prior to
admission, the patient began exhibiting abdominal pain in the epigastrium without
irradiation and not associated with other symptoms. She denied weight loss, diarrhea,
appetite loss or icterus. On examination she was in good general condition, normal
colored and hydrated, focused and normal vital signs. Cardiac auscultation, pulmonary
and abdominal examination without changes. Suffered from systemic hypertension, diabetes
mellitus type 2 and dyslipidemia in regular medication use.</p>
      <p>Laboratory investigation showed normal serum levels of transaminases and bilirubin.
Endoscopy visualized polypoid lesion in the duodenal papilla, measuring about 5 cm,
which was biopsied at seven different sites. Histopathology was compatible with
tubulo-villous adenoma with low grade dysplasia. Abdominal ultrasonography showed normal
common bile duct and gallbladder and bile ducts without dilatation. Computed tomography
of the abdomen showed no changes. The colonoscopy was normal, not evidencing any other
polypoid lesion.</p>
      <p>The patient was taken to the operating room for the purpose of a transduodenal local
resection of the tumor (ampulectomy), but with all the pre-operative support for a
possible PD. During surgery, after duodenotomy, polypoid lesion of approximately 6 cm in
the duodenal papilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>) was observed.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Polypoid lesion o f the papilla: laparotomic transduodenal viewing</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abcd-27-04-0306-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The lesion was completely resected and the main pancreatic duct and common bile duct
were fixed with synthetic absorbable suture. The tumor was sent for frozen biopsy, which
resulted in tubulo-villous adenoma with high-grade dysplasia. Ampulectomy was done and
was also performed catheterization with good visualization of the common bile duct and
main pancreatic duct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Catheterization of the terminal common bile duct with output of bile and
catheterization of main pancreatic duct with output of pancreatic secretion</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abcd-27-04-0306-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <p>With the resected lesion was necessary to reconstruct the gap left. The top wall of the
pancreatic duct was sutured to the bottom wall of the bile duct with interrupted
stitches in synthetic absorbable sutures, thus forming a common channel. The duodenum
and the "new hepatopancreatic ampulla" were united with separated 4-0 absorbable
synthetic stiches to create an anastomosis of the mucosal lining of the ducts with the
duodenal wall. Afterwards, followed the duodenorrhaphy with separate 3-0 silk
sutures.</p>
      <p>Postoperatively, the patient stayed clinically stable, with physiological parameters and
good diet acceptance. He was discharged on the 6<sup>th</sup> postoperative day.</p>
      <p>Currently, the patient is asymptomatic and at six months follow-up. The final
histopathology of the surgical specimen was tubulo-villous adenoma with high-grade
dysplasia and free surgical margins. Postoperative endoscopy showed only papilla
surgical scar without tumor recurrence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Benign tumors of the duodenal papilla have a very low incidence around 0.04 to 0.12%.
And so, hardly enter the differential diagnosis of jaundice by periampullary diseases.
Most patients remained asymptomatic and develops symptoms of biliary colic,
gastrointestinal bleeding, or jaundice in accordance with tumor growth<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The patient in this case complained of pain in the upper abdomen, but at no time
presented jaundiced. The diagnosis was confirmed with histopathology obtained by
endoscopy.</p>
      <p>The treatment of benign tumors of the papilla is still controversial. There is no
consensus in the literature about the best approach to these tumors, endoscopic, if
surgical resection under local or pancreaticoduodenectomy<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. The proper approach to the patient should be thoroughly
discussed, it is known that there is a likelihood of malignancy of these tumors of
approximately 30-40%. In this case, patients undergoing endoscopic treatment or surgical
treatment with local resection should be rigorously followed in the clinic so that
recurrences are detected early<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The higher probability of malignant transformation of these tumors depends on a few
factors: the larger the tumor, the greater the chance of harboring "islands" of
adenocarcinoma; villous tumors are more associated with degeneration to carcinoma;
multicentric tumors have a higher risk of malignancy and lesions located in the ampulla
are more prone to malignancy than lesions located in the duodenum and small
intestine<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Some small adenomas
(&lt;1 cm) can be removed endoscopically with stenting of the biliar and pancreatic
ducts to allow the resolution without stenosis. Options for endoscopic resection of
these lesions include papillectomy or ampulectomy with snare and thermal ablation with
laser, argon plasma coagulation and electrosurgery. Four criteria for eligibility
endoscopic papillectomy are needed: the injury must have less than 4 cm and cannot be
endoscopic malignancy appearance (must have regular margin, absence of ulceration and
soft consistency); minimum of six biopsies confirmed the benign histology and absence
ductal invasion by endoscopic ultrasound<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. However, endoscopic
resection has a recurrence rate of 30% and often multiple attempts to be necessary
before complete tumor eradication. Morbidity about 20% have been reported, including
pancreatitis and duodenal perforation<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Surgical options for ampullary tumors include transduodenal local excision or
pancreaticoduodenectomy. In the case of villous adenomas, the risk of malignancy and the
loss of opportunity to cure must be weighed against the complications of
pancreaticoduodenectomy <sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Thinking of the considerable risk of malignancy, one can agree that the best approach
would be the pancreaticoduodenectomy, but one should be aware of the significant
morbidity and mortality of this procedure<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. The mortality rate of pancreaticoduodenectomy in centers
specializing in pancreatic surgery is in the range of 2-3%. Despite low mortality rates,
the incidence of postoperative complications remains high. Yeo et
al<italic>.</italic><sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> showed a
series of 650 consecutive pancreaticoduodenectomy in the John Hopkins Hospital. The
mortality rate was 1.4%. The three most common complications were delayed gastric
emptying in 19%, pancreatic fistula in 14% and surgical wound infection in 10%. These
conditions also significantly increase the duration of hospitalization for the patient
and hospital costs<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Even with so much discussion about the best surgical approach, it is known that most
surgeons agree that patients should be brought to the operating room with pre-operative
support for a wide resection for pancreaticoduodenectomy<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. This patient preparation is essential if freezing
demonstrate malignancy. If all these precautions are taken, it is known that local
excision transduodenal can be an excellent treatment for benign tumors of the bulb,
especially in patients with high surgical risk for PD<sup>12</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. After resection of the local
ampullary tumors should perform endoscopic control 6-12 months after surgery to assess
local recurrence. Patients who have pancreatitis or jaundice months or years after local
excision should undergo endoscopy with endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography
due to strong suspicion of relapse<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>In this patient, it was decided to hold the local surgical resection with ampulectomy,
because it showed the tumor&gt;4 cm, histopathological (obtained for seven biopsies) was
compatible with villous adenoma, freezing intraoperatively confirmed the nature benign
lesion and clinically the patient had comorbidities and high surgical risk.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflicts of interest: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>Financial source: none</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>COELHO</surname>
              <given-names>J&#xFA;lio Cezar Uili</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source xml:lang="pt">APARELHO DIGESTIVO - CL&#xCD;NICA E CIRURGIA</source>
          <edition>3rd edition</edition>
          <publisher-name>Atheneu</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>WIEDERKEHR</surname>
              <given-names>Julio Cesar</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>COELHO</surname>
              <given-names>Julio Cezar Uili</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>SIGWALT</surname>
              <given-names>Marcos Fabiano</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>NASSIF</surname>
              <given-names>Aissar Eduardo</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Adenoma viloso da ampola de Vater</article-title>
          <source>Revista do Col&#xE9;gio Brasileiro de Cirurgi&#xF5;es</source>
          <volume>Volume XXV</volume>
          <issue>N&#xFA;mero 6</issue>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>YEO</surname>
              <given-names>Charles</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DEMPSEY</surname>
              <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>KLEIN</surname>
              <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>PEMBERTON</surname>
              <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>PETERS</surname>
              <given-names>Jeffrey</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>SHACKELFORD'S SURGERY OF THE ALIMENTARY TRACT</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <edition>6th edition</edition>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>YEO</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>CAMERON</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Six hundred fifty consecutive pancreaticoduodenectomies in the 1990s:
pathology, complications, and outcomes</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>226</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>248</fpage>
          <lpage>257</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9339931</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>ZINNER</surname>
              <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>ASHLEY</surname>
              <given-names>Stanley</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>MAINGOT - Abdominal Surgery</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <edition>11th edition</edition>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
