<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Life</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Med Life</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMedLife</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Medicine and Life</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1844-122X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1844-3117</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Carol Davila University Press</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Romania</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25408729</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4197507</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JMedLife-07-220</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Presentation</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Primary omental torsion in a 9 year old girl: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Anyfantakis</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kastanakis</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Karona</surname>
            <given-names>V</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Symvoulakis</surname>
            <given-names>EK</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">***</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fragiadakis</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Katsougris</surname>
            <given-names>N</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bobolakis</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>*</label>Primary Health Care Centre of Kissamos, Chania, Crete, Greece</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>**</label>First Department of Surgery, Saint George General Hospital of Chania, Crete, Greece</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>***</label>Private Family Practice Unit in Heraklion, Crete, Greece</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp><bold>Correspondence to:</bold>Dimitrios Anyfantakis,
MD, Primary Health Care Centre of Kissamos, 13 Emmanouil Loulakaki, Chania, Crete, Greece
Phone: +30 2821044662, Mobile:+306937473215, E-mail: danyfantakis@med.uoc.gr 
</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>220</fpage>
      <lpage>222</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;Carol Davila University Press
</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>This is 
an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work 
is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abstract</p>
        <p>Primary torsion of the omentus is an extremely unusual cause of acute abdomen in the pediatric population. This condition occurs from twist of the pedicle of the omental apron around its longer axis, leading to edema, ischaemia and necrosis. Here we present a rare case of a 9 year old girl referred by her general practitioner due to severe right lower quadrant abdominal pain with a presumed diagnosis of acute appendiceal inflammation. Surgical operation disclosed primary omental torsion. The infarcted segment was resected and the girl&#x2019;s clinical recovery was uneventful without any complication. The condition may mimic a variety of other causes of acute abdominal symptoms. In this case report, a presumed diagnosis of acute appendicitis urgently induced the decision of a surgical approach. Physicians involved in the acute pediatric care have to include this rare condition in the differential diagnosis of acute onset right-sided abdominal pain. </p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>primary omental torsion</kwd>
        <kwd>acute abdomen</kwd>
        <kwd>diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>management</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="Introduction" id="sec1-1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Primary omental torsion represents an extremely rare etiology of acute abdomen [<bold><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></bold>], especially among children [<bold><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></bold>]. It is remarkable that Kimber et al, in a 20 years retrospective study among a paediatric population reported that the ratio of primary omental torsion to appendicitis was found less than 4/1000 respectively [<bold><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></bold>]. In a similar 10 year study in Greece this ratio was found 1/587 with overweight males to be mainly affected [<bold><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></bold>]. </p>
      <p> We report an unusual case of primary omental torsion in a 9 year old female. Information on clinical presentation, diagnosis and therapy is discussed.
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 9 year old girl was admitted to the Primary Health Care Centre of Kissamos complaining of acute onset abdominal pain for the last 6 hours located in the right lower quadrant. The girl was referred to the Emergency department of the Saint George General Hospital of Chania, Crete, Greece with the suspicion of acute appendiceal inflammation. Her vital signs on admission were within normal limits except of a slight elevation of her temperature (37.6 degrees Celsius). The girl&#x2019;s weight was normal for her age. Physical examination revealed a marked right lower abdominal tenderness with guarding while obturator and psoas signs were negative. Intestinal sounds were normal. Initial laboratory work up included complete blood count, renal and liver function tests, urine analysis and chest X ray which were found normal. White blood cell count was 9500 cells/&#x3BC;l with 78% polymorphonuclears, 14% lymphocytes and 7% monocytes. The only pathological finding was a moderate elevation of the C-reactive protein levels [2.1 mg/dl (normal range: 0-0.5 mg/dl)]. Ultrasound (US) examination showed a small amount of free fluid in the pouch of Douglas. Visualization of the appendix was not feasible, while ovaries were found normal. Due to the increasing character of the abdominal pain, the girl was transferred to the operation room. Intraoperatively, during exploration of the peritoneal cavity was detected in the sero-sanguineous fluid. Appendix was found normal. Further exploration for Meckel&#x2019;s diverticulum was negative. Torsion of the right omental part around its long axis (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref></bold> and <bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref></bold>) was discovered with evident signs of vascular congestion and necrosis (<bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref></bold>). Management consisted of resected of the twisted omentum. The girl recovered normally without any complications and she was discharged home 3 days later. </p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intraoperative image of the rezected part of the omentus torsioned around a pivotal point (arrow)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JMedLife-07-220-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intraoperative image of the omental part with evident signs of congestion and necrosis</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JMedLife-07-220-g002"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Discussion" id="sec1-3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Omental torsion was first described in 1899 by Eitel [<bold><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></bold>]. In regard to pathogenesis, torsion of the omentum around a pivotal point impairs its vascular perfusion resulting to severe congestion and oedema [1, 5]. Spontaneous derotation may occur at this stage [<bold><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></bold>]. However, if the torsion continues, edema progresses to acute hemorrhagic infarction and omental necrosis [<bold><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></bold>]. Extravasation of a sero-sanguineous liquid into the peritoneal cavity is often detected during surgery [<bold><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></bold>]. </p>
      <p> The condition according to its aetiology is further classified as primary or secondary to certain predisposing risk factors [<bold><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></bold>]. Secondary omental torsion occurs more frequently than the primary form and is associated with intra-abdominal inflammatory situations, tumours or cysts [<bold><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></bold>]. Morris et al reported that the majority of secondary omental torsion cases are presented in patients suffering from inguinal hernia [<bold><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></bold>]. Regarding the primary or idiopathic form, it occurs in the absence of any intra-abdominal disorder [<bold><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></bold>]. </p>
      <p>A certain causative mechanism for primary omental torsion has not yet been established [<bold><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></bold>]. Intraoperatively, twist of the greater omentum around the right epiploic artery is often observed [<bold><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></bold>]. Increased mobility and length of the right side of the omentum may explain the increased prevalence of right omental infarction [<bold><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></bold>]. Factors that predispose a patient to torsion include congenital pathological variations of the omentum. Among these are reported bifid omentum which is an accessory omentum derived from a narrow route, abnormal embryological position of the right omental part with secondary fragile blood vessels [<bold><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></bold>] and irregular accumulation of omental fat [<bold><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></bold>]. Precipitating factors are those causing sudden omental displacement and include trauma, coughing, violent exercise, hyperperistalsis and compression between abdominal wall and the liver [<bold><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></bold>]. </p>
      <p> Patients with omental torsion may present with a variety of non-specific symptoms and can mimic various aetiologies of acute abdomen [<bold><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></bold>]. Acute appendicitis, acute cholecystitis [<bold><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></bold>] and diverticulitis are conditions included in the differential diagnosis [<bold><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></bold>]. Right sided acute abdominal pain, fever, nausea and vomiting are the most frequently encountered symptoms at onset [<bold><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></bold>]. Physical examination reveals signs of peritoneal irritation with guarding and rebound abdominal tenderness [<bold><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></bold>]. A palpable abdominal mass has been also reported in rare cases [<bold><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></bold>]. Remarkably, patients with omental torsion share a more prolonged clinical course with less systematic manifestations compared to acute appendicitis [<bold><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></bold>].</p>
      <p> Although, US and Computed Tomography imaging are useful tools that assist the diagnosis by excluding acute appendicitis, cholecystitis and diverticulitis [<bold><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></bold>], the pathology is rarely diagnosed preoperatively, making exploratory laparotomy the most optimal diagnostic and therapeutic modality [<bold><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></bold>]. Surgical management of the primary omental torsion includes resection of the affected omental part with or without appendectomy [<bold><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></bold>]. Laparoscopic approach has been reported to be a safe and effective option [<bold><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></bold>]. Although conservative management has been described in some reports, surgery has been recommended as the treatment of choice in order to prevent severe complications related to conservative therapy such as sepsis and intra-abdominal abscess formation [<bold><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></bold>]. </p>
      <p> In this case report, a presumed diagnosis of acute appendicitis urgently induced the decision of a surgical management. The intraoperative diagnosis was this of omental torsion. Describing, in detail, this episode of care which occurred in a 9 year old child, it is crucial to properly rule out causes of abdominal symptoms.
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="Conclusions" id="sec1-4">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We presented an unusual case of primary omental torsion in a non-obese 9 years old girl. Although accurate preoperative diagnosis is seldom feasible, physicians involved in the pediatric care have to consider this condition in cases of acute onset right-sided abdominal pain.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Disclosures, Funding and Conflicts of Interest: None specified</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scabini </surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rimini </surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title> Primary omental torsion: A case report</article-title>
          <source>World J Gastrointest Surg</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>153</fpage>
          <lpage>155</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22110847</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mavridis </surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Livaditi </surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary omental torsion in children: ten-year experience</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Surg Int</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>879</fpage>
          <lpage>882</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17605020</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kimber </surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westmore </surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary omental torsion in children</article-title>
          <source>J Paediatr Child Health</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>34</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8652207</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eitel </surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rare omental torsion</article-title>
          <source>New York Med Rec </source>
          <year>1899</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>715</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andreuccetti </surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ceribelli </surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary omental torsion (POT): a review of literature and case report</article-title>
          <source>World J Emerg Surg</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21269497</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nihei </surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kojima </surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Omental bleeding with spontaneously derotated torsion--a case report.</article-title>
          <source>Jpn J Surg</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>700</fpage>
          <lpage>702</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1787620</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karayiannakis </surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Polychronidis </surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary torsion of the greater omentum: report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Surg Today</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>913</fpage>
          <lpage>915</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376793</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leitner </surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jordan </surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Torsion, infarction, and hemorrhage of the omentum as a cause of acute abdominal distress</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg </source>
          <year>1952</year>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>110</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14895152</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morris </surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Torsion of the omentum</article-title>
          <source>Arch Surg</source>
          <year>1932</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>40</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Theriot </surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sayat </surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Childhood obesity: a risk factor for omental torsion.</article-title>
          <source>Pediatrics</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>e460</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654645</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Puylaert </surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Right-sided segmental infarction of the omentum: clinical, US, and CT findings</article-title>
          <source>Radiology </source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>185</volume>
          <fpage>169</fpage>
          <lpage>172</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1523302</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Epstein </surname>
              <given-names>LI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lempke </surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary idiopathic segmental infarction of the greater omentum: case report and collective review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1968</year>
          <volume>167</volume>
          <fpage>437</fpage>
          <lpage>443</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5638529</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Efthimiou </surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kouritas </surname>
              <given-names>VK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary omental torsion: report of two cases</article-title>
          <source>Surg Today</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>64</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19132472</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsironis </surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zikos </surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute abdomen due to primary omental torsion: case report.</article-title>
          <source>J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>e45</fpage>
          <lpage>e48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22056551</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Jaberi </surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gharaibeh </surname>
              <given-names>KI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Torsion of abdominal appendages presenting with acute abdominal pain</article-title>
          <source>Ann Saudi Med</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>211</fpage>
          <lpage>213</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322659</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Young </surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee </surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary torsion of the greater omentum</article-title>
          <source>Int Surg</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>72</fpage>
          <lpage>75</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15285236</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
