<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27098182</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4839142</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">867</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12957-016-0867-8</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A carcinoid tumor arising from a mature cystic teratoma in a 25-year-old patient: a case study</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Joo-Yeon</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+82-51-797-3107</phone>
            <email>H00311@paik.ac.kr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Department of Pathology, Haeundae Paik Hospital, University of Inje College of Medicine, 1435 Jwa-dong, Haeundae-gu Busan, Republic of Korea </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <elocation-id>120</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Kim. 2016</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Mature cystic teratomas (MCTs) are common benign tumors occurring in the ovaries. Malignant transformation of teratomas (TMT) occurs in 1&#x2013;3&#xA0;% of all MCTs, usually in postmenopausal women. Squamous cell carcinoma is the most common tumor type. Primary carcinoid tumors of the ovary are uncommon, representing only 0.3&#xA0;% of all carcinoid tumors and less than 0.1&#xA0;% of all ovarian cancers.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A carcinoid tumor of the trabecular type arising from a MCT is presented in a 25-year-old woman. TMT was detected incidentally. Histologically, uniform, polygonal cells were arranged in a cord and trabecular pattern. Immunohistochemical staining showed positivity for neuro-specific enolase, synaptophysin, and CD56.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>This case represents a very rare example of carcinoid tumor occurring in a woman younger than 30&#xA0;years of age. Our findings suggest that sufficient tumor sampling is necessary to avoid overlooking small lesions, which, in our case, were not detected on either radiologic or gross examination.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Ovary</kwd>
        <kwd>Teratoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Carcinoid tumor</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Malignant transformation of teratoma (TMT) is uncommon condition occurring in 1&#x2013;3&#xA0;% of all mature cystic teratomas (MCTs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Moreover, TMT tends to occur in postmenopausal women, especially those who are 15&#xA0;years older than conventional MCT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The most common malignant tumor type in MCTs is squamous cell carcinoma, followed by adenocarcinoma and carcinoid tumors. Carcinoid tumors of the ovary are uncommon, particularly primary carcinoid tumors, representing only approximately 0.3&#xA0;% of all such tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Herein, we report a rare case of carcinoid tumor arising from a MCT in a 25-year-old nulliparous woman.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 25-year-old woman (gravida 0, para 0) presented with a 4-year history of an asymptomatic pelvic mass that had increased in size in the previous few months. The women had an unremarkable medical and gynecological history with a regular menstrual cycle.</p>
      <p>Ultrasonography confirmed the presence of a hypoechoic cystic mass of undetermined origin. Further evaluation was performed, including laboratory tests and computed tomography (CT). The serum level of CA 125 was found to be elevated (139.0&#xA0;U/mL), and a CT scan revealed tumors in both the ovaries. The right ovary showed a 7.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;4.5&#xA0;cm fat-containing cystic mass with internal calcification, and the left ovary showed 16.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;14.0&#xA0;cm fat-containing cystic mass with multiple septa and internal calcification (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). The radiologic findings suggested that both the ovarian tumors were mature teratomas, and the patient underwent bilateral ovarian cystectomy. Macroscopically, the left ovary revealed a multicystic mass containing viscous sebaceous material and hairs, measuring 20.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;12.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;7.5&#xA0;cm. The cystic wall also contained adipose and bony tissue. Similarly, the right ovary showed a cystic mass filled with sebum and hairs, measuring 6.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;5.0&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;4.0&#xA0;cm. Frozen sections of the left ovarian mass were made. On microscopic examination, mature squamous and respiratory epithelium, as well as mesenchymal tissue including the bone, cartilage, smooth muscle, and adipose tissue were observed. In addition, abundant brain tissue, such as glial tissue and choroid plexus, were observed. Through the frozen sections, the left ovarian mass was diagnosed as MCT, and therefore, no further intervention was performed at the time of the operation.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold> Gross appearance of the left ovary: A multicystic mass containing viscous sebaceous material and hair is visible. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Uniform cells are arranged in cords and trabeculae beneath the respiratory epithelium. <bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold> Tumor cells showing positivity for CD56 and synaptophysin. <bold>f</bold> The Ki-67 proliferative index in the carcinoid tumor is 1&#xA0;%</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2016_867_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>However, formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded multiple sections of the left ovary revealed an incidental microscopic focus that displayed a monomorphic population of polygonal cells beneath the respiratory epithelium. The focus measured 0.5&#xA0;cm in diameter and was not observed in the frozen sections. The tumor cells formed cords and trabeculae and had scant, eosinophilic cytoplasm, and round nuclei with mild atypia (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b, c</xref>). Immunohistochemical staining showed positivity for neuro-specific enolase (NSE), synaptophysin, and CD56 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d, e</xref>). One mitosis was seen per 10 high-power fields, and the Ki-67 proliferative index was 1&#xA0;% (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>). Therefore, the tumor was classified as low grade. Based on the morphological and immunohistochemical findings, the tumor was diagnosed as a carcinoid tumor (trabecular type) arising from a MCT. The right ovary, on the other hand, had no evidence of somatic type tumors.</p>
      <p>The patient received no further treatment. And she had no clinical symptoms associated with carcinoid syndrome including cardiac involvement that might be a major cause of death in this syndrome, so cardiac ultrasound had not performed. Also, no evidence of recurrence or metastasis was detected on abdomen and pelvic computer tomography (CT) after 8&#xA0;months of follow-up.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>MCTs account for approximately 20&#xA0;% of all ovarian neoplasms, and are often diagnosed in young women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Teratomas consist of diverse tissues derived from the three germ cell layers, the ectoderm, mesoderm, and endoderm. MCTs are usually benign; however, in 1&#x2013;3&#xA0;% of cases, they undergo TMT. Furthermore, patients with TMT are 15&#xA0;years older than those with MCT without malignant transformation. The most common tumor type is squamous cell carcinoma, comprising about 80&#xA0;% of cases of TMT. Other tumor types, including adenocarcinoma, thyroid carcinoma, and carcinoid tumor, have also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>Primary carcinoid tumors of the ovary are uncommon, accounting for only 0.3&#xA0;% of all carcinoid tumors and less than 0.1&#xA0;% of all ovarian cancers. Carcinoid tumors most commonly occur in the gastrointestinal tract. The second most common organ in which these tumors occur is the lungs. Ovarian carcinoid tumors may be primary or metastatic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Most primary ovarian carcinoid tumors are unilateral; however, in 16&#xA0;% of cases, the contralateral ovary displays a cystic teratoma or a mucinous neoplasm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>Primary ovarian carcinoid tumors are classified into four types, i.e., the insular, trabecular, mucinous, and mixed types. The most common type is the insular type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Primary ovarian carcinoid tumors, in particular one third of the insular type, have been associated with the carcinoid syndrome despite the absence of metastasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The other types of primary ovarian carcinoid tumors are not usually associated with carcinoid syndrome.</p>
      <p>In the present case, the patient had a trabecular type carcinoid tumor and did not have any symptoms of carcinoid syndrome for the previous 4&#xA0;years.</p>
      <p>Preoperative diagnosis of MCT of the ovary can be made through radiologic findings considering the presence of the fat tissue, hairs, bone, and cartilage within the tumor. However, TMT is not easily recognized. In most cases, a definitive diagnosis is possible only on postoperative examination of multiple tissue sections. Similarly, a small carcinoid tumor was identified incidentally in the present case. Tumor cells revealed immunoreactivity for the neuroendocrine markers following NSE, synaptophysin, and CD56, and these findings are typical of carcinoid tumors. This case suggests that, in teratomas, sufficient sampling from solid components is important not to miss the microscopic small areas showing TMT.</p>
      <p>The optimal treatment strategy for TMT remains the main challenge. Surgical excision is regarded as the first approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. A more aggressive surgical treatment may be considered according to the age of the patient. TMT usually occurs in postmenopausal women; therefore, radical surgery such as hysterectomy and bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy may be considered in such cases. However, in younger women, particularly those that are nulliparous, preservation of fertility is important. Despite the fact that there is no consensus regarding the optimal TMT treatment strategy for younger patients, local excision seems to be the most rational option [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. According to the literature, the prognosis of organ-confined tumors is excellent for primary ovarian carcinoid tumors and the 10-year survival rates are approximately 100&#xA0;%. However, in the advanced state, the 5-year survival rate decreases to 33&#xA0;% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p>
      <p>In conclusion, a primary carcinoid tumor arising from a MCT is very rare in young patients, particularly those less than 30&#xA0;years old, as demonstrated in the present case. Moreover, preoperative identification of TMT is not easy. Therefore, examination of multiple sections is necessary to detect even the smallest focus showing malignant transformation within solid tumor components.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patients for publication of these case reports and any accompanying images. Copies of the written consent are available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The author declares that he has no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>JYK provided the conception and design of the study and acquisition of data, drafted the article, revised and gave final approval of the version to be submitted.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>None. No funding to declare.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Byun</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mucinous adenocarcinoma and stromal carcinoid tumor arising in one mature cystic teratoma of the ovary with synchronous cervical cancer</article-title>
          <source>J Obstet Gynaecol Res</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1341-8076.2003.00073.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12696624</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bojana</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elizabeth</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anais</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Growing teratoma syndrome of the ovary: review of literature and first report of a carcinoid tumor arising in a growing teratoma of the ovary</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1913</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boyraz</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Selcuk</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guner</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Usubutun</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gunalp</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A primary insular type carcinoid tumor arising in a mature cystic teratoma of the ovary: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Case Rep</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>16</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Robert JK, Maria LC, Simon H, Robert HY. WHO Classification of tumors of female reproductive organs. 4th ed. Lyon: International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC); 2013; 60&#x2013;66.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stamp</surname>
              <given-names>GW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McConnell</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignancy arising in cystic ovarian teratomas. A report of 24 cases</article-title>
          <source>Br J Obestet Gynaecol</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>671</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-0528.1983.tb09289.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robby</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norris</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scully</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Insular carcinoid primary in the ovary. A clinicopathologic analysis of 48 cases</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>404</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0142(197508)36:2&lt;404::AID-CNCR2820360216&gt;3.0.CO;2-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1157010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taleraman</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurman</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Blaustein&#x2019;s pathology of the female genital tract</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <edition>5</edition>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mandal</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saroha</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary carcinoid tumor of the ovary: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Arch Gynecol Obstet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17611764</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stamatios</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ioannis</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chrysoula</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mature ovarian teratoma with carcinoid tumor in a 28-year-old patient</article-title>
          <source>Case Rep Obstet Gynecol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>2013</volume>
          <fpage>108582</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23984130</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kopf</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosti</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lanzanova</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marangolo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Locally advanced ovarian carcinoid</article-title>
          <source>J Exp Clin Res</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>313</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
