<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25830994</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4371673</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20153084</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Alopecia secondary to anti-tumor necrosis factor-alpha
therapy<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></sup></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
            <given-names>Lara Beatriz Prata</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rego</surname>
            <given-names>Juliana Carlos Gon&#xE7;alves</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Estrada</surname>
            <given-names>Bruna Duque</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bastos</surname>
            <given-names>Paula Raso</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pi&#xF1;eiro Maceira</surname>
            <given-names>Juan Manuel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sodr&#xE9;</surname>
            <given-names>Celso Tavares</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label>Faculdade de Medicina do ABC (FMABC) - S&#xE3;o Paulo (SP),
Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label>Instituto de Dermatologia Professor Rubem David Azulay -
Santa Casa de Miseric&#xF3;rdia do Rio de Janeiro (IDPRDA- SCMRJ) - Rio de Janeiro (RJ),
Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label>Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro (UERJ) - Rio de
Janeiro (RJ), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label>Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ) - Rio de
Janeiro (RJ), Brazil</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">MAILING ADDRESS: Lara Beatriz Prata Ribeiro, Rua Santa Luzia, 206
- Centro, 20.020-020 - Rio de Janeiro - RJ Brazil. E-mail:
<email>lara_prata@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Mar-Apr</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Mar-Apr</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>90</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>232</fpage>
      <lpage>235</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2015 by Anais Brasileiros de
Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any
medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Biologic drugs represent a substantial progress in the treatment of chronic
inflammatory immunologic diseases. However, its crescent use has revealed seldom
reported or unknown adverse reactions, mainly associated with anti-tumor
necrosis factor (anti-TNF). Psoriasiform cutaneous reactions and few cases of
alopecia can occur in some patients while taking these drugs. Two cases of
alopecia were reported after anti-TNF therapy. Both also developed psoriasiform
lesions on the body. This is the second report about a new entity described as
'anti-TNF therapy-related alopecia', which combines clinical and
histopathological features of both alopecia areata and psoriatic alopecia. The
recognition of these effects by specialists is essential for the proper
management and guidance of these patients.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Alopecia</kwd>
        <kwd>Alopecia areata</kwd>
        <kwd>Dermoscopy</kwd>
        <kwd>Psoriasis</kwd>
        <kwd>Tumor necrosis factor-alpha</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>The increased use of biologic drugs has been revealing new adverse effects. The
cutaneous reactions described include eczema, erythema, urticaria, lupus-like
syndrome and, paradoxically, psoriasis.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> The development of alopecia related to anti-TNF is a possible
although seldom reported collateral effect. In this context, alopecia areata (AA),
psoriatic alopecia and anti-TNF therapy-related alopecia are described, of which the
latter mixes clinical and histopathological characteristics of both psoriatic
alopecia and AA.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Two cases of alopecia associated with anti-TNF therapy were reported, which resulted
in cutaneous psoriasiform lesions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORTS</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 1</title>
        <p>Male patient, 28 years old, affected by Crohn's disease and treated with
infliximab for 3 years, presented alopecia plaques on the scalp and
erythematous-scaly lesions in the armpits, navel and perianal region for the
last 2 weeks. He denied personal or family history of psoriasis. During the
physical examination, 2 alopecia plaques were found in the left parietal region.
The oldest lesion, smooth and normochromic, showed clinical and dermoscopic
aspects of AA: black spots and exclamation-mark hairs, whereas the most recent
one presented erythema and desquamation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures
1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">3</xref>). Histopathology demonstrated extensive parakeratosis,
epidermal hyperplasia, dilated dermal papillae containing tortuous capillaries
and mononuclear inflammatory infiltrate, involving all levels of intra and
perifollicular structure and intense miniaturization of hair follicles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>). Direct mycological examination
was negative. Daily treatment was started with clobetasol gel, coal tar shampoo,
intralesional corticoid in monthly application on the scalp and tacrolimus 0.1%
on body lesions. Infliximab was maintained and after 3 months the desquamation
disappeared and there was complete hair regrowth and remission of cutaneous
lesions.</p>
        <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Dermoscopy of alopecic plaque. Exclamationmark hairs in the center,
vellus hairs and black spots on the edges of the plaque (10x
magnification)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0232-g01"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Alopecic plaques in different phases of evolution. Most recent plaque
with erythema and desquamation and the oldest one normochromic and
smooth</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0232-g02"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Dermoscopy of desquamative alopecic plaque. Detail of desquamation</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0232-g03"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Histopathology of alopecia plaque with desquamation (HE). Extensive
parakeratosis, epidermal hyperplasia, dilated dermal papillae containing
tortuous capillaries and mononuclear inflammatory infiltrate in the
interior and around miniaturized follicular structure (HE 100x)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0232-g04"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 2</title>
        <p>Female patient, 14 years old, had been treated with infliximab for 6 months due
to Crohn's disease. After 4 months of treatment, she presented
erythematous-desquamating lesions on the body and alopecia plaques with
desquamation of the scalp. She denied personal or family history of psoriasis.
At the physical examination, she presented erythematous-desquamating plaques on
the trunk, armpits, pubic region, breasts, plantar regions, elbows and knees. On
the scalp, alopecia desquamating plaques were detected in the bilateral frontal
and parietal region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Figure 5</xref>).
Trichoscopy revealed tortuous vessels compatible with psoriasis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Figure 6</xref>). Histopathology of the scalp
revealed hyperkeratosis which extended to the follicular ostia, small foci of
parakeratosis, pronounced miniaturization with only 50% of hair terminals in
anagen and mononuclear infiltrate, discrete perivascular and multifocal
intrafollicular. On the trunk a slight, irregular acanthosis was observed with
hyperkeratosis, non-confluent parakeratosis and neutrophilic aggregates in the
stratum corneum.</p>
        <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Detail of alopecia plaques. Presence of erythema and desquamation</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0232-g05"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>FIGURE 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Dermoscopy with polarized light and interface liquid of alopecia plaque
with desquamation. Areas of atrichia and thick, tortuous capillary loops
in the perifollicular region associated with balled capillary loops in
the periphery of the plaque (20x magnification)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0232-g06"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Coal tar shampoo was prescribed, along with betamethasone cream on the scalp, LCD
lotion 6% and mometasone on body lesions. After 5 months, there was hair
regrowth and remission of cutaneous lesions. Infliximab was maintained.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The estimated prevalence of psoriasiform eruptions during use of anti-TNF&#x3B1; is between
1.5 and 5%, mainly associated with infliximab.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> One of the proposed mechanisms was blocking TNF receptors,
which would increase the production of interferon-&#x3B1; by plasmacytoid dendritic cells
in genetically predisposed individuals. Interferon-&#x3B1; would become then the cytokine
responsible for activation and amplification of pathogenic T-cells.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> In a revision of psoriasis cases
induced by anti-TNF in patients with inflammatory intestinal disease, the flexural
area was affected in 31% of the cases and the scalp in 42%, although alopecia has
not been described.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Reports of
psoriasis on the scalp associated with alopecia induced by anti-TNF are
rare.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Recently, a new kind of psoriatic alopecia /
alopecia areata-like reaction secondary to anti-Tumor Necrosis Factor-&#x3B1; therapy has
been described based on the report of 3 alopecia cases that mixed clinical and
histopathological characteristics of AA and psoriasis.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> For this diagnosis, it would be necessary to meet
the following criteria: (1) development of psoriasiform lesions after treatment with
anti-TNF, (2) absence of previous psoriasis history, (3) alopecia plaque(s) on the
scalp, (4) erythematous - desquamative plaques on the scalp and/or pustular lesions
on the scalp and (5) development of psoriasiform rash on the body after
treatment.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> All patients
in this report presented all of these characteristics.</p>
      <p>In the histopathology of alopecia induced by anti-TNF, besides classic psoriasiform
epidermal changes, alterations similar to AA ones are observed on the dermis, such
as intense miniaturization, increase in catagen and telogen hairs and peribulbar
lymphocytic infiltrate in terminal hairs. Numerous plasmocytes and eosinophils were
also observed.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> We computed the
following discrepancies in the histological findings of Doyle et al.: 1) The
lymphocytic infiltrate was not restricted to the peribulbar region, occupying all
levels of the follicular structure. This does not invalidate AA dermal findings,
since the "swarm of bees" peribulbar lymphocytic infiltrate, typical of AA, is more
often associated with the acute phase.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Moreover, in psoriatic alopecia there is no lymphocytic
infiltrate in the peribulbar region; 2) Eosinophils and plasmocytes were not
identified in the inflammatory infiltrate.<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Eosinophils were found in 44% of the 109 cases of AA by
Peckhametal and plasmocytes are normal components of the occipital scalp
area.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> This way, we believe that the presence of
eosinophils and plasmocytes may not be fundamental to characterize this type of
alopecia.</p>
      <p>This combination of clinical, histopathological and dermoscopic characteristics of
psoriatic alopecia and AA reinforce the diagnosis of psoriatic alopecia / alopecia
areata-like reaction secondary to anti-Tumor Necrosis Factor-&#x3B1; therapy. The main
differential diagnoses are AA, psoriatic alopecia, pityriasis amiantacea and tinea
capitis.</p>
      <p>There is no consensus regarding maintenance or suspension of anti-TNF&#x3B1; in face of
cutaneous reaction triggered by these drugs. Upon revising 16 cases of AA induced by
anti-TNF&#x3B1;, treatment was suspended in 7 cases, and only 2 presented complete hair
regrowth.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> For psoriasis
induced by anti-TNF&#x3B1; they are usually maintained and topical treatment with
corticosteroids and vitamin D analog allow for total or partial remission of the
cutaneous lesions.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Iborra et al.
recommend the suspension of anti-TNF&#x3B1; when the lesions cover more than 5% of body
surface, are intolerable or if that is what the patient wishes.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> For these patients, infliximab was
maintained due to the small extension of psoriasiform lesions, achieving good
clinical evolution.</p>
      <p>The objective of this report was to demonstrate the first 2 cases described in
national literature of alopecia induced by anti-TNF&#x3B1; which fall within the category
described as psoriatic alopecia / alopecia areata-like reaction secondary to
anti-Tumor Necrosis Factor-&#x3B1; therapy, pointing out histopathological differences
regarding the only previous publication and emphasizing dermoscopic signs as an
auxiliary diagnostic tool.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of Interests: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial Support: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>How to cite this article: Ribeiro LBP, Rego JCG, Duque-Estrada B, Bastos RP,
Maceira JMP, Sodr&#xE9; CT. Alopecia secondary to Anti-Tumor Necrosis Factor-Alpha
therapy. An Bras Dermatol. 2015;90(2):232-5.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other" id="fn01">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Work performed at Instituto de Dermatologia Professor Rubem David Azulay - Santa
Casa de Miseric&#xF3;rdia do Rio de Janeiro (IDPRDA- SCMRJ) - Rio de Janeiro (RJ),
Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iborra</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beltran</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bastida</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aguas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nos</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Infliximab and adalimumab-induced psoriasis in Crohn's disease: A
paradoxical side effect</article-title>
          <source>J Crohns Colitis</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <lpage>161</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21453886</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Doyle</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sperling</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baksh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lackey</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vleugels</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psoriatic alopecia/alopecia areata-like reactions secondary to
anti-Tumor Necrosis Factor-a Therapy: A Novel Cause of Noncicatricial
Alopecia</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermatopathol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>161</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21317611</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Collamer</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Battafarano</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psoriatic skin lesions induced by tumor necrosis factor
antagonist therapy: clinical features and possible
immunopathogenesis</article-title>
          <source>Semin Arthritis Rheum</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>240</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20580412</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cullen</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kroshinsky</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheifetz</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Korzenik</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psoriasis associated with antitumor necrosis factor therapy in
inflammatory bowel disease: a new series and a review of 120 cases from the
literature</article-title>
          <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>1318</fpage>
          <lpage>1327</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21957906</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Medkour</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Babai</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chanteloup</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buffard</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delchier</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le-Louet</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of diffuse psoriasis with alopecia during treatment
of Crohn's disease with infliximab</article-title>
          <source>Gastroenterol Clin Biol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>140</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20138448</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Perman</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lovell</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Denson</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farrell</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lucky</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Five cases of anti-tumor necrosis factor alpha-induced psoriasis
presenting with severe scalp involvement in children</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dermatol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>454</fpage>
          <lpage>459</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21995665</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peckham</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sloan</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elston</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Histologic features of alopecia areata other than peribulbar
lymphocytic infiltrates</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>615</fpage>
          <lpage>620</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21684037</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bardazzi</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fanti</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orlandi</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chieregato</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Misciali</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psoriatic scarring alopecia: observations in four
patients</article-title>
          <source>Int J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>765</fpage>
          <lpage>768</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10561048</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>James</surname>
              <given-names>WD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berger</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elston</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Andrews diseases of the skin</source>
          <edition>10th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Saunders/Elsevier</publisher-name>
          <year>2006</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferran</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calvet</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almirall</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pujol</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maym&#xF3;</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alopecia areata as another immune-mediated disease developed in
patients treated with tumor necrosis factor-a blocker agents. Report of five
cases and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>479</fpage>
          <lpage>484</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20586836</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
