<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Ophthalmology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2415</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26496717</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4619091</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">131</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12886-015-0131-y</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A novel histopathologic finding in the Descemet's membrane of a patient with Peters Anomaly: a case-report and literature review</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ni</surname>
            <given-names>Wei</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>pkuniwei@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Wei</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+86-10-82268106</phone>
            <email>puh3_ww@bjmu.edu.cn</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hong</surname>
            <given-names>Jing</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>hongjing64@yahoo.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Pei</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>zhangpei_bj@163.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Cong</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>drcongliu@163.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Ophthalmology, Peking University Third Hospital, Beijing, 100191 China </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Key Laboratory of Vision Loss and Restoration, Ministry of Education, Beijing, China </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <elocation-id>139</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Ni et al. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Peters anomaly is a rare developmental abnormality of the anterior segment of the eye and is one of the main causes of congenital corneal opacities. Typically, histopathology of Peters anomaly shows immature or absent Descemet&#x2019;s membrane and attenuated endothelial cells in the area of the corneal opacity, in addition to thinning or absence of Bowman&#x2019;s membrane and defects in the posterior stroma. In this report, we present a novel histopathological finding, which has not been previously reported, in the Descemet's membrane of a patient who is clinically diagnosed with Peters anomaly.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 7-years old female child with developmentally delayed was born of a normal pregnancy, labor, and delivery. Apparent bilateral corneal opacifications were present at birth. On ophthalmologic examination, the child had a visual acuity of FC/20&#xA0;cm in the right eye and that of FC/10&#xA0;cm in the left one. Horizontal nystagmus and congenital cataract were found in both eyes. Slit-lamp examination revealed bilateral central corneal opacities which covered the iris and pupils. High-frequency UBM and AS-OCT both showed a shallow anterior chamber with multiple areas of iridocorneal adhesions and no corneal lenticular touch in each eye. A corneal specialist performed a penetrating keratoplasty with extra-capsular cataract extraction and intraocular lens implantation. Histopathologic procedures were conducted on the host corneal button, including Hematoxylin-Eosin stain and Periodic Acid-Schiff stain. All the sections were examined by light microscopy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The &#x201C;multiple-layer&#x201D; structure of the Descemet&#x2019;s membrane described in our case has not been reported before as in association with abnormalities of the cornea tissues in Peters anomaly. Such pathological finding need to be reported to enhance further understanding of the special structure of Descemet's membrane as an abnormality during embryogenesis and neural crest cell differentiations.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Peters anomaly</kwd>
        <kwd>Descemet's membrane</kwd>
        <kwd>Anterior segment dysgenesis</kwd>
        <kwd>Corneal opacity</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Peters anomaly is a rare developmental abnormality of the anterior segment of the eye, either sporadic or inherited. It is one of the main causes of congenital corneal opacities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Typically, histopathology in Peters anomaly shows immature or absent Descemet&#x2019;s membrane and attenuated endothelial cells in the area of the corneal opacity, in addition to thinning or absence of Bowman&#x2019;s membrane and defects in the posterior stroma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Corneal opacification is bilateral in approximately 80&#xA0;% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The opacity is caused by a defect in the underlying corneal endothelium and the Descemet membrane. In this case, we present a novel histopathological finding, which has not been previously reported, in the Descemet's membrane of a patient who is clinically diagnosed with Peters anomaly.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 7-years old female child with developmentally delayed was born of a normal pregnancy, labor, and delivery. There were no maternal infections and other illnesses detected during the pregnancy as well as the perinatal period, respectively. Ocular anomalies (apparent bilateral corneal opacifications) were present at birth. The infant did not show evidence of tearing, blepharospasm, photophobia, drainage, or ocular redness. On ophthalmologic examination, the child had a visual acuity of FC/20&#xA0;cm in the right eye and that of FC/10&#xA0;cm in the left one. The intraocular pressure was normal in both eyes. Slit-lamp examination revealed bilateral central corneal opacities which covered the iris and pupils (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>, <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">b</xref>). The anterior segments appeared abnormal with corectopia and iris cornea-peripheral anterior synechiae. Horizontal nystagmus and congenital cataract were found in both eyes. The central retina could not be examined clearly because of the severe corneal opacity. High-frequency UBM (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>) and AS-OCT (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>) both showed a shallow anterior chamber with multiple areas of iridocorneal adhesions and no corneal lenticular touch in each eye. The B-type ultrasound scan performed on the patient revealed no masses, vitreous debris, or retinal detachment in either eye.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Slit-lamp photographs of the anterior segment of the patient. <bold>a</bold> In the left eye, central corneal opacity, corectopia, anterior synechiae and whitish lens were observed. <bold>b</bold> In the right eye, central corneal opacity, corectopia, anterior synechiae and whitish lens were observed</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12886_2015_131_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Images by AS-OCT (<bold>a</bold>) and UBM (<bold>b</bold>) of the left eye. <italic>A1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, AS-OCT showed a shallow anterior chamber with anterior synechiae in the left eye. <italic>B1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, High-frequency UBM showed a shallow anterior chamber with anterior synechiae and there was no corneal lenticular touch in the left eye</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12886_2015_131_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      <p>Clinically, a pediatric ophthalmologist confirmed the Peters Anomaly diagnosis of the patient, who was then referred to a pediatrician for an examination of associated systemic anomalies. However, none was detected. Under this situation, a penetrating keratoplasty with extra-capsular cataract extraction and IOL implantation was performed by a corneal specialist. The cornea tissue underwent histopathological examination. The patient&#x2019;s visual acuity improved to 20/100 in the left eye and intraocular pressure was 8&#xA0;mmHg after the surgical procedures. In addition, the parents of this child were also examined and corneal opacity in the left eye was found in her father.</p>
      <p>Histopathologic Procedures were performed on the host corneal button, including Hematoxylin-Eosin stain and Periodic Acid-Schiff stain, to obtain the pathologic features of the cornea sections. All the sections were examined by light microscopy. On gross examination, the cornea (7&#xA0;mm&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;8&#xA0;mm) was densely opacified centrally. Histological section showed considerable cornea thinning centrally (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>), besides which the defects in the endothelium, Descemet's membrane, cornea stroma and Bowman&#x2019;s membrane were also observed at the corneal defect. Bowman&#x2019;s membrane was completely absent in the middle area of the corneal button and no vessels were found in the anterior stroma (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). The central internal stroma was hypoplastic and the fibers were extremely disarranged. (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). Most importantly, an abnormal thickness of Descemet&#x2019;s membrane was present with the &#x201C;multiple-layer&#x201D; structure in the peripheral part of the cornea (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">c</xref>). Pigmented tissues could be discovered inside these &#x201C;layers&#x201D; of Descemet&#x2019;s membrane (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). Furthermore, the pigmented cells situated within the cornea stroma and inserted anteriorly with adhesion to the posterior part of the cornea (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). Histopathologic examination also detected a large absence of the Descemet's membrane in the synechiae area (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>) and the endothelium membrane was completely absent from the cornea (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Histological photographs of the cornea. <bold>a</bold> Bowman&#x2019;s membrane was completely absent in the middle area of the cornea. The central internal stroma was hypoplastic and the fibers were extremely disarranged without vessels. The endothelium membrane was entirely absent from the cornea. (Periodic Acid-Schiff stain, original magnification&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;10). <bold>b</bold> An abnormal thickness of Descemet&#x2019;s membrane was present with the &#x201C;multiple-layer&#x201D; structures at the peripheral part of the defect. (Periodic Acid-Schiff stain, original magnification&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;40). <bold>c</bold> The &#x201C;multiple-layer&#x201D; structures were found in the Descemet&#x2019;s membrane and pigmented tissues could be found inside the &#x201C;layers&#x201D;. (Periodic Acid-Schiff stain, original magnification&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;100). <bold>d</bold> The pigmented cells situated within the cornea stroma and inserted anteriorly with adhesion to the posterior part of the cornea. Absence in Descemet's membrane in the peripheral synechiae area were shown. (Periodic Acid-Schiff stain, original magnification&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;100)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12886_2015_131_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>Taken together, the major histopathological findings in the patient include &#x201C;multiple-layer&#x201D; structure of the Descemet's membrane in the peripheral area, the absence of cornea endothelium, hypoplasia of the cornea stroma, absence of Bowman&#x2019;s membrane, and the attachment of iris to the cornea.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The incidence of ocular malformation in newborns ranges from 3.3 to 6.0 per 10,000 births [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] and Peters anomaly acounts for the largest proportion of the anterior segment dysgenesis. An estimate of 44-60 cases of Peters anomaly is reported in the United States annually [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. One of the essential features of Peters anomaly is congenital central corneal opacity with defects in the posterior stroma, Descemet&#x2019;s membrane, and endothelium. These conditions are characterised by both autosomal dominant and recessive patterns of inheritance with variable expressivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>Clinical features of Peters anomaly are diverse, from mild to severe. The most common ocular abnormalities associated with Peters anomaly were glaucoma (20&#xA0;%), microphthalmia (18&#xA0;%), and colobomas (6&#xA0;%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. A study by Traboulsi at al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] discovered that 25&#xA0;% of their patients had microphthalmia and/or chorioretinal colobomas and 48&#xA0;% had associated congenital systemic malformations. More recently, Peters anomaly was subdivided into 2 types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Type I is characterized by the central corneal opacity with iridocorneal adhesions, in which the lens may or may not be cataractous, whereas type II is characterized by the central corneal opacity with cataracts or corneorlenticular adhesions. Peters Plus Syndrome (PPS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] comprises anterior chamber defects along with other systemic anomalies. To prevent amblyopia, the earlier treatment is performed, the better the results are. There are a variety of surgical options available for treating Peters anomaly. Peripheral optical iridectomy may be carried out for patients with a clear peripheral cornea. As for patients with bilateral visually disabling corneal opacity, penetrating keratoplasty is recommended. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] It has been suggested that early keratoplasty for congenital corneal opacities might improve the visual outcome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. However, some studies showed a wide range of graft failure rates at 1&#xA0;year ranging from 22 to 67&#xA0;% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Due to the high prevalence of PKP graft failure, some doctors chose to use the Boston Type I Keratoprosthesis (KPro-1) in these patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>In Peters anomaly, the corneal opacity is either central or paracentral and it usually does not exhibit vascularization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Histopathology is often diagnostic. Previous histopathologic findings of Peters anomaly described the defects and absence in the endothelium, Descemet&#x2019;s membrane, posterior stroma and the Bowman&#x2019;s membrane of the cornea, which are consistent with our pathologic findings of this patient. However, the &#x201C;multiple-layer&#x201D; structure of the Descemet&#x2019;s membrane has not been reported as in association with abnormalities of the cornea tissues in Peters anomaly. The cause of this unusual structure, which may be due to genetic factors, environmental factors, or both, has not been clearly identified in pathologic studies so far.</p>
      <p>Peters anomaly is a genetic disease affecting multiple anterior segments, which is known to be sporadic, but sometimes inherited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Several genetic mutations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] act in concert to specify a population of mesenchymal progenitor cells, as they migrate anteriorly around the embryonic optic cup [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Waring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] demonstrated various developmental mechanisms for Peters anomaly, including faulty separation of the lens vesicle from the surface ectoderm, primary abnormal migration of neural crest cells into the cornea, and intrauterine corneal inflammation. Development of the ocular anterior segment depends largely on periocular mesenchyme cells, which are derived predominantly from neural crest cells (NCC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Specific and differential cell adhesion is expected to be instrumental in induction, migration, and differentiation of NCC. Tian et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] demonstrated that NCC-specific inactivation of p120 catenin mice perturbs the proper development of certain eye structures and causes anterior segment dysgenesis, including adhesion of the iris to the cornea, hypoplasia of iris and ciliary body, and dysgenesis of cornea, trabecular meshwork, and Schlemm&#x2019;s canal.</p>
      <p>Peters anomaly shows diverse clinical/pathologic features and visual outcomes. Consistent with previous findings, our case has discovered diverse histopathologic features of the cornea layers, especially in the Descemet's membrane. However, little is known of the development of the abnormal Descemet's membrane in patients with Peters anomaly. Although this observation does not imply causation and there still are many &#x201C;unknown areas&#x201D; in the pathological diagnosis of this special structure, such pathological findings need to be reported to enhance further characterization and it may be of interest to others who have observed similar associations. Further study of the disease may be required.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The &#x201C;multiple-layer&#x201D; structure of the Descemet&#x2019;s membrane described in our case has not been reported as associated with abnormalities of the cornea tissues in Peters anomaly. Such pathological findings need to be reported to enhance further understanding of the special structure of Descemet's membrane as an abnormality during embryogenesis and neural crest cell differentiations.</p>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Consent</title>
        <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient and her father for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the editor of this journal.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>WN drafted the manuscript, collected the data, and reviewed the literature. WW and WN were involved in the design of the study, interpretation of the data, drafting of the manuscript, and review of the literature. JH was the corneal specialist who performed the penetrating keratoplasty for this patient. CL and PZ participated in the histopathologic procedures, collection of the data, interpretation of the data and critically reviewed the manuscript. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>The authors thank the patient and her father who generously agreed to participate in this medical report. The authors also thank Dr. Wei Zhang for his excellent assistance in the histopathologic procedures.</p>
      <sec id="FPar1">
        <title>Funding</title>
        <p>National Natural Science Foundation of China (Number: 81170888)</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhandari</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferri</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whittaker</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazzaro</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Peters anomaly: review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Cornea.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>939</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ICO.0b013e31820156a9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21448066</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sowden</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular and developmental mechanisms of anterior segment dysgenesis</article-title>
          <source>Eye.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>1310</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.eye.6702852</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17914434</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kupfer</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuwabara</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stark</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The histopathology of Peters anomaly</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>653</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0002-9394(75)90397-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1180307</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kurilec</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zaidman</surname>
              <given-names>GW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Incidence of Peters anomaly and congenital corneal opacities interfering with vision in the United States</article-title>
          <source>Cornea.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>848</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ICO.0000000000000182</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24977984</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iseri</surname>
              <given-names>SU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osborne</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farrall</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wyatt</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirza</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>N&#xFC;rnberg</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Seeing clearly: the dominant and recessive nature of FOXE3 in eye developmental anomalies</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>1378</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.21079</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19708017</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Najjar</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christiansen</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bothun</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Summers</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Strabismus and amblyopia in bilateral peters anomaly</article-title>
          <source>JAAPOS.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Traboulsi</surname>
              <given-names>EI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maumenee</surname>
              <given-names>IH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Peters' anomaly and associated congenital malformations</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol.</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>1739</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archopht.1992.01080240079035</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1463415</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Buy</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wenniger-Prick</surname>
              <given-names>LJJM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hennekam</surname>
              <given-names>RCM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Peters' plus syndrome: a review</article-title>
          <source>Ann Genet.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>103</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-3995(02)01120-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119218</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dana</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schaumberg</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moyes</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gomes</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Corneal transplantation in children with peters anomaly and mesenchymal dysgenesis. multicenter pediatric keratoplasty study</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmology</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <fpage>1580</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0161-6420(97)30093-1</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9331194</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>YW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wee</surname>
              <given-names>WR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical outcome of penetrating keratoplasty in patients 5 years or younger: peters anomaly versus sclerocornea</article-title>
          <source>Cornea</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>1432</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ICO.0b013e31829dd836</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24104853</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Limaiem</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chebil</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baba</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Youssef</surname>
              <given-names>NB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mghaieth</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matri</surname>
              <given-names>LE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pediatric penetrating keratoplasty: indications and outcomes</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>649</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.transproceed.2011.01.055</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21440785</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aquavella</surname>
              <given-names>JV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gearinger</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akpek</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCormick</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pediatric keratoprosthesis</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>989</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2007.01.027</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17467531</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harissi-Dagher</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colby</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anterior segment dysgenesis: Peters&#x2019; anomaly and sclerocornea</article-title>
          <source>Int Ophthalmol Clin.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/IIO.0b013e318169526c</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18427259</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Waring</surname>
              <given-names>GO</given-names>
              <suffix>III</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laibson</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anterior chamber cleavage syndrome. A stepladder classification</article-title>
          <source>Survey of ophthalmology</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0039-6257(75)90034-X</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">808872</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tian</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reynolds</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ocular anterior segment dysgenesis upon ablation of p120 catenin in neural crest cells</article-title>
          <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>5139</fpage>
          <lpage>53</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.12-9472</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22736606</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
