<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25018811</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4085893</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-17-61</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2014.17.61.3368</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Images in Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Unusual actinomycosis of the chest wall</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bouaddi</surname>
            <given-names>Mouna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hassam</surname>
            <given-names>Badredine</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Department of Dermatology and Venereology, university of Medicine, University Mohammed V Souissi, Rabat, Morocco</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Mouna Bouaddi, Department of Dermatology and Venereology, university of Medicine, University Mohammed V Souissi, Rabat, Morocco</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <elocation-id>61</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Mouna Bouaddi et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Actinomycosis</kwd>
        <kwd>chest wall</kwd>
        <kwd>granulomatous infection</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="S0001">
      <title>Image in medicine</title>
      <p>Actinomycosis is a chronic infection due to anaerobic filamentous bacteria (Actinomyces), which occurs mostly in the cervicofacial region as a chronic granulomatous infection. We report the case of Mr KI, 17 years old, without past medical history, presented a painful ulceration on the right side of the chest wall which evolved since 2 months. The onset of symptoms was a nodule which ulcerated after 2 months with extruding yellowish pus. The examination objectified ulcerated and burgeoning lesion in right parasternal region from what came yellowish pus mixed with sulphur granule (A). A painful subcutaneous nodule was noted under the right breast. An examination of the oral mucosa was entirely normal as well as the rest of the physical examination. Histopathologic studies (hematoxylin-eosin staining) revealed the presence of inflammatory cells surrounding basophilic sulfur granules which were composed of a large number of filaments arranged in a radiating pattern (B). The chest x-ray was normal. The chest scan showed an infiltration of the anterior and right lateral wall without bone and lung injury. The results of aerobic and anaerobic culture showed mixed flora. The histopathologic findings led to the diagnosis of actinomycosis of the wall chest. Treatment was based on oral amoxicillin + clavulanic acid (1g + 125 mg 3 times daily). The size of the ulcerative lesion gradually decreased and completely healed by 4 weeks. Then antibiotherapy was continued for four months. No evidence of recurrence of this lesion was found after 24-month of follow-up.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A) ulcerated and burgeoning lesion in right parasternal region from what came yellowish pus mixed with sulphur granule; B)presence of inflammatory cells surrounding basophilic sulfur granules which were composed of a large number of filaments arranged in a radiating pattern</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-17-61-g001"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
  </body>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
