<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Intern Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Intern. Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1939-1676</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVIM</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0891-6640</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1939-1676</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26289121</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4858041</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.13599</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JVIM13599</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="overline">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>FOOD AND FIBER ANIMAL</subject>
          <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
            <subject>Case Report</subject>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
              <subject>Genetics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Genetic Abnormalities in a Calf with Congenital Increased Muscular Tonus</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Wiedemar et&#xA0;al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="jvim13599-cr-0001" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wiedemar</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim13599-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim13599-cr-0002" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Riedi</surname>
            <given-names>A.&#x2010;K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim13599-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim13599-cr-0003" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jagannathan</surname>
            <given-names>V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim13599-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim13599-cr-0004" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dr&#xF6;gem&#xFC;ller</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim13599-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim13599-cr-0005" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Meylan</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim13599-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="jvim13599-aff-0001">
        <label>
          <sup>1</sup>
        </label>
        <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Institute of Genetics</named-content>
        <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Vetsuisse Faculty</named-content>
        <institution>University of Berne</institution>
        <named-content content-type="city">Berne</named-content>
        <country country="CH">Switzerland</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="jvim13599-aff-0002">
        <label>
          <sup>2</sup>
        </label>
        <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Clinic for Ruminants</named-content>
        <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Vetsuisse Faculty</named-content>
        <institution>University of Berne</institution>
        <named-content content-type="city">Berne</named-content>
        <country country="CH">Switzerland</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: M. Meylan, Clinic for Ruminants, Vetsuisse Faculty of the University of Berne, Bremgartenstrasse 109a, 3012 Berne, Switzerland; e&#x2010;mail: <email>mireille.meylan@vetsuisse.unibe.ch</email>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>29</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.2015.29.issue-5</issue-id>
      <fpage>1418</fpage>
      <lpage>1421</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2015 American College of Veterinary Internal Medicine <copyright-statement>-->
        <copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">Copyright &#xA9; 2015 The Authors. Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of American College of Veterinary Internal Medicine.</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creativeCommonsBy-nc">
          <license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution&#x2010;NonCommercial</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:JVIM-29-1418.pdf"/>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated">
        <kwd id="jvim13599-kwd-0001">Arthrogryposis</kwd>
        <kwd id="jvim13599-kwd-0002">Cattle</kwd>
        <kwd id="jvim13599-kwd-0003">Mutation</kwd>
        <kwd id="jvim13599-kwd-0004">Myosin binding protein C slow type</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="4"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name>
          <meta-value>2.0</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>component-id</meta-name>
          <meta-value>jvim13599</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
          <meta-value>September/October 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:4.8.8 mode:remove_FC converted:25.04.2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <fn-group id="jvim13599-ntgp-0101">
        <fn id="jvim13599-note-0101">
          <p>This work was performed at the Vetsuisse Faculty of the University of Berne at the Clinic for Ruminants and the Institute of Genetics.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <def-list list-content="abbreviations" id="jvim13599-dl-0001">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-item>
        <term>bp</term>
        <def>
          <p>base pair</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MYBPC1</term>
        <def>
          <p>myosin binding protein C slow type</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>SNP</term>
        <def>
          <p>single nucleotide polymorphism</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
    <p>A 2&#x2010;week&#x2010;old female calf was referred to the Clinic for Ruminants at the Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Berne, Switzerland, with difficulty standing and muscle tremors since birth. Prior treatment by the private veterinarian with selenium, calcium, magnesium, and vitamins had not led to any improvement. The general status at arrival to the clinic was slightly reduced, though the calf was alert and attentive, and tachycardia (152/min) and tachypnea (80/min) were noticeable. Examination of the skin revealed an infected lesion on the fetlock of the left forelimb and several superficial lesions. Gastrointestinal, respiratory, and urinary tracts were without important abnormalities. The musculoskeletal system was normally developed, no atrophy was noticed, but the calf remained in a recumbent position unless lifted up and helped to stand. When standing, it showed tremor, ataxia, and could only move backward with hypermetria in the hind limbs and tip&#x2010;toe&#x2010;standing of the front limbs (Fig&#xA0;<xref rid="jvim13599-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Consciousness was normal but the calf was unable to orientate itself in its surroundings. Cranial nerve examination showed no deficits. Muscle tone was generally increased in the limbs. No painful reaction was noticed upon palpation of the limbs. The spinal reflexes were generally reduced. Sensibility was normal in the neck and shoulder area, but reduced in the limbs. The head and neck could be moved in all directions and the ears were symmetrical and loose. The clinical signs were localized in the peripheral nervous or musculoskeletal system.</p>
    <fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jvim13599-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Affected calf at 3&#xA0;weeks of age. Notice (<bold>A</bold>) the tip&#x2010;toe&#x2010;stance of the front legs with straight position of the carpus, and (<bold>B</bold>) the tendency to move backward and the instability on the hind legs.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="JVIM-29-1418-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Based on the clinical signs of weakness, stiffness, trembling, and inability to stand up on physical examination, white muscle disease was considered a possible differential diagnosis, as Switzerland is known for its selenium&#x2010;poor soils and high prevalence of selenium deficiency in calves.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1</xref>, <xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2</xref> A blood chemistry profile revealed no relevant abnormalities, muscle enzyme activities were within normal limits. Further differential diagnoses associated with increased muscle tone, such as spastic paresis<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref> and tetanus,<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref> or with abnormal footing, as deforming ankylosis of the coffin joint,<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref> were considered unlikely based on the clinical findings, and no further diagnostic steps were undertaken. To exclude a bone lesion in the left fetlock, a radiographic examination of the joint was conducted which revealed no abnormality. A complete blood count was within normal limits. A lumbar puncture was not conducted as the problem of the calf had been localized in the peripheral nervous or musculoskeletal system.</p>
    <p>The calf was treated with antibiotics (procaine&#x2010;penicillin 30,000&#xA0;IU/kg SID s.c.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0001">1</xref>) because of the deep lesion on the left fetlock. In addition, the calf was treated with vitamins of the B&#x2010;complex<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0002">2</xref> (5&#xA0;mg/kg thiamine, 2.5&#xA0;mg/kg pyridoxinhydrochloride SID i.m.) and selenium<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0003">3</xref> (sodium selenite 0.25&#xA0;mg/kg, alpha&#x2010;tocopherol 5&#xA0;mg/kg s.c. once).</p>
    <p>The calf was assisted to stand several times a day, and feed and water was always provided for the calf to consume in recumbent position. The movements of the calf did not improve with treatment, however, it always had a good appetite, and was bright and alert. The owner did not wish any further examinations such as electromyography, or nerve or muscle biopsies.</p>
    <p>Based on the calf's history of clinical signs since birth and lack of improvement despite treatment, on the clinical presentation and lack of specific findings matching the most common musculoskeletal diseases, congenital disease was suspected and veterinary geneticists were contacted during the calf's stay at the clinic in order to investigate possible genetic causes for the disorder observed in this calf.</p>
    <p>The calf was of especially high breeding value for the owner, who insisted to take the calf home for further care. The calf was released from the clinic under the agreement that it would be brought back for further examinations or necropsy if it did not improve. Information was gathered approximately weekly by telephone conversation. A month after returning home, the calf could stand up on its own and could even walk a few steps forward instead of only backward according to the owner. Unfortunately the owner suddenly decided to slaughter the calf without notice to the clinic 5&#xA0;weeks after discharge.</p>
    <p>During recent years, substantial progress has been made in the field of molecular genetics.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>, <xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref> Many domesticated animal genomes, including the cow genome, have been sequenced.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>, <xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> Recently the 1000 bull genomes project has been initiated and allows participants worldwide to access sequence data from a large number of cattle control genomes.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref> As there was no knowledge of a genetic disease with similar clinical signs in cattle, we assumed a spontaneous de novo mutation and therefore sequenced the entire genome of the affected animal. Because of the strong effect of the mutation, we hypothesized that most likely a mutation affecting the coding sequence of a gene would be responsible for the disease. Therefore, genomic DNA was isolated from blood using the Nucleon Bacc2 kit,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0004">4</xref> and a fragment library with a 300&#xA0;base pairs (bp) insert size was prepared. For whole genome resequencing, one lane of Illumina HiSeq2500 paired&#x2010;end reads (2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;100&#xA0;bp) was collected corresponding to roughly 15&#xD7; coverage of the genome.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0005">5</xref>
<sup>;</sup>
<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> The obtained sequence reads were mapped to the current version of the Bos taurus reference sequence (UMD3.1/bosTau6) as described before.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> The whole genome sequence of the affected calf has been deposited under accession number PRJEB7707 at the European Bioinformatics Institute short read archive. The data were checked for deviations (variants) like single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP), short insertions and deletions from the reference sequence as described before.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> A total of 67,310 sequence variants were detected across the whole exome, including untranslated regions and 10&#xA0;bp of flanking introns, of the affected animal. Subsequently, these variants were compared to 46 control cattle genomes that had been sequenced in our laboratory in the course of other ongoing studies to exclude sequence variants present in these controls as being causative. Thereby the number of candidate variants was reduced to a total of 360. In a second filtering step, the remaining list of candidate variants were further checked for presence in the recent sequence variant database containing 1,147 already sequenced cattle genomes of the ongoing 1,000 bull genome project.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref> Thereby, the number of private DNA variants present in the affected calf only was reduced to 18 (Table&#xA0;S1).</p>
    <p>Following the assumption that the calf was a carrier of a newly occurred mutation, we expected the causal mutation to be present in the calf and absent in its parents. Therefore, we screened the sire, dam, and the affected offspring for the 18 remaining candidate variants by Sanger sequencing. For this procedure, DNA of the parents was isolated from blood of the dam and semen of the sire, which was used for artificial insemination, using the Nucleon Bacc2 kit<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0004">4</xref>, and variant flanking primers were designed with Primer3 software<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0006">6</xref> after masking of repetitive sequences with RepeatMasker.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0007">7</xref> PCR products were amplified using AmpliTaq Gold360 Master Mix<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0008">8</xref> and directly sequenced on an ABI3730 capillary sequencer<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0009">9</xref> after treatment with exonuclease&#xA0;I<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0010">10</xref> and shrimp alkaline phosphatase.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0011">11</xref> The sequence data was analyzed with Sequencher&#xA0;5.1 software<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0012">12</xref> and sequence variants which were present in the parents were excluded. Other possible scenarios such as a dominant inheritance with incomplete penetrance or mosaicism in one of the parents would have permitted the mutation to be present in one of the parents also. For 14 of the 18 remaining variants, one parent was genotyped as heterozygous like the sequenced calf (Table&#xA0;S1), but no obvious functional candidate gene was affected. Therefore, these variants were considered as less likely to have been causative. In addition, 3 variants were shown to be called false positive as genotyping did not confirm their presence. Finally one single variant was left: a SNP replacing a thymine by a guanine on bovine chromosome&#xA0;5 at bp&#x2010;position 65,787,153. It was clearly identified as a de novo mutation as it was absent in both parents, but present in the calf (Fig&#xA0;<xref rid="jvim13599-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). Interestingly, this SNP situated in exon 13 of the myosin binding protein C slow type (<italic>MYBPC1</italic>) gene at position 885 of the open reading frame (c.885T&gt;G) is predicted to lead to an amino acid exchange from leucine to arginine of the encoded MYBPC1 protein sequence at position 295 (p.Leu295Arg). Leucine is an nonpolar (hydrophobic) amino acid with a molecular weight of 131, whereas arginine is positively charged (basic) with a molecular mass of 174. These physical differences are predicted to have an impact on the protein folding (increased length of a beta&#x2010;strand) using Phyre2 prediction software.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref> The affected residue is conserved among vertebrates (Fig&#xA0;<xref rid="jvim13599-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). The functional effects of the amino acid exchange were calculated by PolyPhen&#x2010;2<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0013">13</xref> and SWIFT,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim13599-note-0014">14</xref> they were predicted to be probably damaging and not tolerated, respectively.</p>
    <fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jvim13599-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A de novo missense mutation in <italic><styled-content style="fixed-case">MYBPC</styled-content>1</italic> is associated with the disease phenotype. (<bold>A</bold>) Electropherograms of the <italic><styled-content style="fixed-case">MYBPC</styled-content>1</italic> c.885T&gt;G mutation. (<bold>B</bold>) Multiple sequence alignment of the <styled-content style="fixed-case">MYBPC</styled-content>1 protein in the region of the p.Leu295Arg mutation. Note the perfect conservation of the leucine at position 295 in all known <styled-content style="fixed-case">MYBPC</styled-content>1 homologs. (<bold>C</bold>) Localization of known human and bovine mutations affecting the <styled-content style="fixed-case">MYBPC</styled-content>1 protein. The protein consists of seven immunoglobulin C2 repeats (displayed in green) and three fibronectin type&#x2010;<styled-content style="fixed-case">III</styled-content> repeats (blue). The positions of the published human mutations are marked with yellow triangles. The mutations, which cause dominant distal arthrogryposis type 1 are labeled with one star (*) and the mutation, that causes the recessive lethal congenital contractural syndrome type 4 is labeled with two stars (**). The mutation found in the presented calf is shown below with a red triangle.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="JVIM-29-1418-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Myosin binding protein C slow type consists of two repetitive domains: 3 fibronectin type&#x2010;III repeats and 7 immunoglobulin C2 repeats (Fig&#xA0;<xref rid="jvim13599-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C), and it is specifically expressed in skeletal muscle.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref> It has both structural and regulatory roles in muscle function, providing thick filament stability and modulating contractility through interactions with myosin and actin (OMIM 160794). In humans, two mutations in <italic>MYBPC1</italic> have been found to cause autosomal dominant distal arthrogryposis type&#xA0;1, a condition characterized by contractures in the hands and feet.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref> Both mutations are SNPs resulting in amino acid exchanges (p.Trp236Arg and p.Tyr856His respectively; Fig&#xA0;<xref rid="jvim13599-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). Another mutation, a SNP which introduces a premature stop codon (p.Arg318ter) has been associated with the recessive lethal congenital contractural syndrome type 4 in humans.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref> This syndrome is the most severe and neonatally lethal form of arthrogryposis. Interestingly, the mutation detected in the presented calf affected the same segment of the MYBPC1 protein as the human p.Trp236Arg mutation (Fig&#xA0;<xref rid="jvim13599-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). More remarkably, the calf's phenotype resembled the human distal arthrogryposis type 1 phenotype. Similar to the contractures in hands and feet in humans, the affected calf was not able to fully stretch its extremities. In addition, it was not able to stand; it walked backward only and showed reduced sensibility mainly in its hind limbs, although the interpretation of the neurological examination was difficult because of the contractures. In summary, the detected de novo missense variant in the <italic>MYBPC1</italic> gene, an apparent functional candidate gene which is associated with similar phenotypes in humans, strongly suggests this mutation as being causative for the observed phenotype.</p>
    <p>Currently, the responsible gene mutation of nearly every fifth rare disease in domestic animals has been determined.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref> This has been done during the past 25&#xA0;years either by targeted analysis of individual candidate genes or labor&#x2010; and resource&#x2010;intensive so&#x2010;called positional cloning approaches, like linkage mapping or genome wide association studies. To this purpose, a series of cases showing an identical phenotype is usually needed. The advent of next&#x2010;generation sequencing technology, in combination with the establishment of a reference genome sequence for domestic animal species, as for the bovine genome in 2009, has changed prospects enormously.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>, <xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, <xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref> Today, studying the molecular etiology of single cases is also feasible eg, in cattle<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, <xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref>, <xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref> as it is successfully performed in man since nearly 5&#xA0;years now.<xref rid="jvim13599-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>
</p>
    <p>In conclusion, we successfully identified the likely causative mutation for a rare disease with only 1 case by taking advantage of the most recent technologies. However, providing functional proof of causality for putative causative mutations remains a limiting factor. This study is an example of how current molecular genetic methods can provide a new tool to diagnose and explain previously unexplainable diseases in cattle. As progress in this field is rapid and techniques are becoming cheaper, these tools will become affordable for routinely diagnosing rare diseases in animals.</p>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supporting information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>Table&#xA0;S1</bold>. Private exonic sequence variants of the affected calf.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="JVIM-29-1418-s001.docx">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data">
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>Video S1.</bold> 2&#x2010;week old calf with increased muscular tonus, tremor and ataxia. Notice that the calf can only move backwards with hypermetria in the hind&#x2010;limbs and tip&#x2010;toe&#x2010;standing of the front limbs.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="JVIM-29-1418-s002.mp4">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack id="jvim13599-sec-0002">
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors are grateful to Ben Hayes, Amanda Chamberlain and Hans Daetwyler of the 1000 bull genomes project for providing variant data. We express our appreciation to the University of Berne for the use of the Next&#x2010;Generation Sequencing Platform in performing the whole genome resequencing experiment and the Vital&#x2010;IT high&#x2010;performance computing center of the Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics for performing computationally intensive tasks (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vital-it.ch/">http://www.vital-it.ch/</ext-link>). The authors thank the calf and dam's owner and the Swiss Holstein association for donating samples and sharing pedigree data. Sexygen AG, Wiler (Switzerland), is acknowledged for providing the sire's semen.</p>
      <p>
<italic>Grant support</italic>: No external funding was used for this project.</p>
      <p>
<italic>Conflict of Interest Declaration</italic>: Authors disclose no conflict of interest.</p>
      <p>
<italic>Off&#x2010;label Antimicrobial Declaration</italic>: Authors declare no off&#x2010;label use of antimicrobials.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group id="jvim13599-ntgp-0001">
      <title>Footnotes</title>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <p>Procacillin<sup>&#xAE;</sup> ad.us.vet, MSD Animal Health GmbH, Lucerne, Switzerland</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>Cor&#xE9;bral<sup>&#xAE;</sup> ad.us.vet, V&#xE9;toquinol AG, Ittigen, Switzerland</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <p>Selen&#x2010;E Vetag<sup>&#xAE;</sup> ad.us.vet., MSD Animal Health GmbH, Lucerne, Switzerland</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <p>Nucleon BACC2 Genomic DNA Extraction Kit, GE Healthcare, Uppsala, Sweden</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <p>Illumina HiSeq2500, Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <p>Homepage Primer3 (2014) Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.ut.ee/primer3-0.4.0">http://bioinfo.ut.ee/primer3-0.4.0</ext-link>. Accessed September 22, 2014.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <p>Homepage Repeat Masker Server (2014) Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.repeatmasker.org">http://www.repeatmasker.org</ext-link>
<underline underline-style="single">.</underline> Accessed September 22, 2014</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <p>AmpliTaq Gold360 Master Mix, LifeTechnologies, Zug, Switzerland</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <p>ABI3730 capillary sequencer, LifeTechnologies, Zug, Switzerland</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <p>Exonuclease&#xA0;I, Roche, Basel, Switzerland</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <p>Shrimp alkaline phosphatase, New England BioLabs, Ipswich, MA USA</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <p>Sequencher&#xA0;5.1 software, Gene Codes Corporation, Ann Harbor, MI, USA</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <p>Homepage PolyPhen2 (2014) Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph2">http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph2</ext-link>. Accessed September 17, 2014</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim13599-note-0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <p>Homepage SWIFT (2015) Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">http://sift.jcvi.org/</ext-link>. Accessed March 24, 2015</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="jvim13599-bibl-0001">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Zust</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hrovatin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Simundi&#x107;</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Assessment of selenium and vitamin E deficiencies in dairy herds and clinical disease in calves</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>394</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8913012</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Lejeune</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Schelling</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Meylan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Gammaglobulin and selenium status in healthy neonatal dairy calves in Switzerland</article-title>. <source>Schweiz Arch Tierheilkd</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>396</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22923323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Ledoux</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Bovine spastic paresis: Etiological hypotheses</article-title>. <source>Med Hypotheses</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>579</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11735313</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="jvim13599-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>MO</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>George</surname>
<given-names>LW</given-names>
</string-name>. <chapter-title>Diseases of the nervous system</chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>BP</surname><given-names>Smith</given-names></name></person-group>, ed. <source>Large Animal Internal Medicine</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>
<publisher-loc>St&#x2010;Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>:<fpage>1089</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1991</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Martig</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Riser</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Germann</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Deforming ankylosis of the coffin joint in calves</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec</source>
<year>1972</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>310</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5086410</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Mardis</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>The impact of next&#x2010;generation sequencing technology on genetics</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18262675</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Metzker</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Sequencing technologies &#x2013; The next generation</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Gen</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0008">
<collab collab-type="authors">Bovine Genome Sequencing and Analysis Consortium</collab>
, <string-name>
<surname>Elsik</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tellam</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#xA0;al. <article-title>The genome sequence of taurine cattle: A window to ruminant biology and evolution</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>324</volume>:<fpage>522</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19390049</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Zimin</surname>
<given-names>AV</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Delcher</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Florea</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#xA0;al. <article-title>A whole&#x2010;genome assembly of the domestic cow, <italic>Bos taurus</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>R42</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19393038</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Daetwyler</surname>
<given-names>HD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Capitan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pausch</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#xA0;al. <article-title>Whole&#x2010;genome sequencing of 234 bulls facilitates mapping of monogenic and complex traits in cattle</article-title>. <source>Nat Gen</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>858</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>865</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Murgiano</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jagannathan</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Benazzi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#xA0;al. <article-title>Deletion in the EVC2 gene causes chondrodysplastic dwarfism in Tyrolean Grey cattle</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e94861</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24733244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Kelley</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sternberg</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Protein structure prediction on the Web: A case study using the Phyre server</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>371</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19247286</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vaughan</surname>
<given-names>KT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Reinach</surname>
<given-names>FC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fischmann</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Complete sequence of human fast&#x2010;type and slow&#x2010;type muscle myosin&#x2010;binding&#x2010;protein C (MyBP&#x2010;C). Differential expression, conserved domain structure and chromosome assignment</article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>216</volume>:<fpage>661</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>669</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8375400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Gurnett</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Desruisseau</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>McCall</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#xA0;al. <article-title>Myosin binding protein C1: A novel gene for autosomal dominant distal arthrogryposis type 1</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Gen</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1165</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1173</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20045868</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Markus</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Narkis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Landau</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#xA0;al. <article-title>Autosomal recessive lethal congenital contractural syndrome type 4 (LCCS4) caused by a mutation in MYBPC1</article-title>. <source>Hum Mutat</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1435</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22610851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="jvim13599-cit-0016">
<article-title>Online Mendelian Inheritance in Animals, OMIA. Faculty of Veterinary Science, University of Sydney</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://omia.angis.org.au/">http://omia.angis.org.au/</ext-link>. Accessed August 03, 2015 (Last updated: 18 Jul 2015).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Murgiano</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jagannathan</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Calderoni</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>, et&#xA0;al. <article-title>Looking the cow in the eye: Deletion in the NID1 gene is associated with recessive inherited cataract in Romagnola cattle</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e110628</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25347398</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim13599-bib-0018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim13599-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Boycott</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vanstone</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bulman</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>MacKenzie</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Rare&#x2010;disease genetics in the era of next&#x2010;generation sequencing: Discovery to translation</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>681</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>691</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23999272</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
