<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Pharmacol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J Pharmacol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJPharm</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Indian Journal of Pharmacology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0253-7613</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-3751</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25878392</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4386141</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJPharm-47-232</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0253-7613.153440</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Drug Watch</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Oral contraceptive pills induced hemichorea in an adolescent female with polycystic ovarian disease</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharmila</surname>
            <given-names>Vijayan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Babu</surname>
            <given-names>Thirunavukkarasu Arun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Indira Gandhi Medical College and Research Institute, Puducherry, India</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, Indira Gandhi Medical College and Research Institute, Puducherry, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Dr. Thirunavukkarasu Arun Babu, E-mail: <email xlink:href="babuarun@yahoo.com">babuarun@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Mar-Apr</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>47</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>232</fpage>
      <lpage>233</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Indian Journal of Pharmacology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chorea is a neurological adverse effect of oral contraceptive pills (OCPs). The onset of chorea following OCPs usage varies widely from few weeks to several years. We report a rare case of chorea which developed within a week of starting OCPs in an adolescent girl with polycystic ovarian disease.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>KEY WORDS</title>
        <kwd>Chorea</kwd>
        <kwd>oral contraceptive pills</kwd>
        <kwd>polycystic ovarian disease</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Oral contraceptive pills (OCPs) are commonly used for contraception, polycystic ovarian syndrome, amenorrhea, menorrhagia, dysmenorrhea, endometriosis, etc., Common side effects of OCPs include nausea, vomiting, headache, bloating, breast tenderness, swelling of the feet, weight gain, breakthrough bleeding, and venous thromboembolism. Neurological adverse effects associated with OCPs are migraine, depression, psychosis, and cerebral infarction. Chorea caused by OCPs is extremely rare and only very few cases are reported in the literature.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] The onset of chorea usually varies from few weeks to several years after starting therapy. Here, we report a case of chorea developing within 1 week of initiating OCPs in an adolescent girl with polycystic ovarian disease.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 17-year-old non-obese, unmarried girl presented to our hospital with irregular cycles and hirsutism for 2 years duration. Ultrasound examination showed bilateral polycystic ovaries. Investigations revealed raised LH: FSH ratio (3:1) and a slightly raised serum testosterone level. She was diagnosed to have polycystic ovarian disease and was prescribed OCPs for treatment of irregular cycles. The OCPs contained a combination of ethinyl estradiol 0.035 mg and cyproterone acetate 2 mg, which was prescribed once daily for 21 days. The patient presented with complaints of abnormal movements of right extremities within 1 week of starting therapy. She had difficulty in writing as the abnormal movements involved her dominant hand. There was no personal or family history of abnormal movements. There was no previous history suggestive of Streptococcal infection, rheumatic fever or drug therapy. On examination, her vitals were stable. Neurological examination revealed choreiform movement of the right hand and right foot. Cognitive, sensory, and cerebellar examinations were normal with no focal neurological deficit. Other systems were within normal limits. Investigations revealed normal blood counts, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, serum electrolytes, renal, liver, and thyroid function tests. C-reactive protein and anti-streptolysin O titers were negative. Her electrocardiogram, chest X-ray, and echocardiogram were normal. She was diagnosed to have OCPs induced hemichorea after ruling out other common causes of chorea. OCPs were discontinued immediately. Her choreiform movements gradually improved and disappeared completely by 1 month of stopping OCPs. Patient was followed up for 6 months and was found to be neurological normal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Among neurological adverse effects of OCPs, chorea is extremely rare. Neurological side effects of OCPs have been linked to alterations in coagulation pathways and secondary vascular complications.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Chorea is an abnormal involuntary movement disorder characterized by brief, semi-directed, irregular movements that are not repetitive or rhythmic, but appear to flow from one muscle to the next. The first description of chorea associated with OCPs was reported by Fernando in 1966 and subsequently few similar published reports established OCPs as a cause of chorea.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] No particular oral contraceptive preparation was consistently associated with chorea, and both low and high-dose preparations can cause this movement disorder. It has been well-established that estrogens have a definite but complex modulatory action in dopaminergic systems.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Hence, the estrogenic component of OCPs is most likely the causative factor in the chorea induced by these agents. Some cases of OCPs induced chorea are caused by reactivation of Sydenham's chorea seen in rheumatic fever.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] However, OCPs induced chorea have no clear relationship with Sydenham's chorea, or Streptococcal infection have also been reported, similar to our case.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] The onset of chorea varies widely from few weeks to several years (Average duration: 9 weeks).[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] The shortest time interval between OCP intake and development of chorea reported in the literature is eight weeks in the patient with no significant medical history.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] In most cases, symptoms subside promptly after withdrawing the offending drug, usually within a period of 2&#x2013;3 months.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] In this index case, symptoms improved immediately after stopping the drug and completely disappeared within a month. Causality assessment by Naranjo Adverse Drug Reaction Probability scale got a score of 6, suggesting a &#x201C;probable&#x201D; relationship between the reaction and the drug.</p>
      <p>Prior knowledge of this rare adverse effect and high index of suspicion can help in early diagnosis and discontinuation of therapy.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> No.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miranda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cardoso</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giovannoni</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Church</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Oral contraceptive induced chorea: Another condition associated with anti-basal ganglia antibodies</article-title>
          <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>327</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14742621</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nausieda</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koller</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiner</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klawans</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chorea induced by oral contraceptives</article-title>
          <source>Neurology</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>1605</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">574224</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Butterworth</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giovannoni</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Church</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Logsdail</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chorea</article-title>
          <source>Clin Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>188</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19435132</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vela</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sfakianakis</surname>
              <given-names>GN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heros</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koller</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singer</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chorea and contraceptives: Case report with pet study and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Mov Disord</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15022195</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cardoso</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chorea gravidarum</article-title>
          <source>Arch Neurol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>868</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12020275</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Buge</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vincent</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rancurel</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ch&#xE9;ron</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hemichorea and oral contraceptives</article-title>
          <source>Rev Neurol (Paris)</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>141</volume>
          <fpage>663</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4089398</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
