<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26175813</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4491469</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-20-322</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2015.20.322.5998</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Large twisted ovarian fibroma in menopausal women: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Boujoual</surname>
            <given-names>Majdouline</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hakimi</surname>
            <given-names>Ihsan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kouach</surname>
            <given-names>Jaouad</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oukabli</surname>
            <given-names>Mohamed</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Moussaoui</surname>
            <given-names>Driss Rahali</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dehayni</surname>
            <given-names>Mohammed</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Department of Gynecology-Obstetric, University of Medicine Tangier, Military Training Hospital Med V, Rabat, Morocco</aff>
      <aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Department of Gynecology-Obstetric, Military Training Hospital Med V, Rabat, Morocco</aff>
      <aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>Department of Pathology, Military Training Hospital Med V, Rabat, Morocco</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Majdouline Boujoual, Department of Gynecology-Obstetric, University of Medicine Tangier, Military, Training Hospital Med V, Rabat, Morocco</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>06</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>20</volume>
      <elocation-id>322</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Majdouline Boujoual et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ovarian fibroma is the most common benign solid tumors of the ovary, commonly misdiagnosed as uterine fibromaor as malignant ovarian tumors. It occurs generally in older perimenopausal and postmenopausal women. Occasionally large fibromas may undergo torsion causing acute abdominal pain. Doppler Ultrasonographyimaging is the choice study. CT and MRI are often needed for further characterization and differentiation from other solid ovarian masses. The choice treatment is surgical removal with intraoperative frozensection. Immunohistochemicalanalysis is recommended to rule out the differential diagnosis. Here we present a case of a postmenopausal woman with a large twisted ovarian fibroma reflecting diagnostic and management difficulties including potential misdiagnosis of the tumor as a malignant ovarian neoplasm that may influence the surgical approach.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Ovarian fibroma</kwd>
        <kwd>torsion</kwd>
        <kwd>postmenopausal</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Ovarian fibromas are the most common benign solid tumors of the ovary (1-4%), typically detected in middle aged women [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], often difficult to diagnose preoperatively and commonly misdiagnosed as uterine fibromas, because of their same pathology, complications, clinical and ultrasonic features [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], or sometimes as malignant ovarian tumors because of accompanying ascites and increased serum CA-125 level [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Extra uterine fibromas present greater diagnostic challenge. Here we present a case of a 62 year-old postmenopausal with a large twisted ovarian fibroma presented as acute pelvic pain. This case highlights the diagnostic difficulties that may be encountered in the management of twisted ovarian fibroma including potential misdiagnosis of the tumor as a malignant ovarian neoplasm that may influence the surgical approach.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Patient and observation</title>
      <p>A 62-year-old post-menopausal, multiparous woman waspresented in emergency with nausea; vomiting and a 6-day history of worsening abdominal pain started in the right lower quadrant and subsequently spread to the whole abdomen. In her past medical history wereintermittent episodes of abdominal discomfort and a sensation of abdominal heaviness during the preceding months. Her vital signs were all within normal limits. Physical examination revealed a palpable abdominal mass in the lower abdomen with sensibility and involuntary guarding. Vaginal examination revealed a normal sized uterus and a large painful irregular mass of 10 cm size, firm in consistency. Pelvic ultrasonography showed a non-homogeneous mass (120 &#xD7; 10 mm) in the upper and right latero uterinewithout any flow on color Doppler. Pelvic computed tomography revealed a right enlarged ovary with heterogeneous iso-dense mass in the midline, rotated toward the contralateral side of the pelvis measuring 122&#xD7; 86cm with deviation of the uterus without lymphadenopathy or pelvic effusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>). Anexploratory laparotomy had showed a black bluish encapsulated mass arising from the twisted right adnexa, measuring 140x100x60 mm with irregular surface and hemorrhagicreshuffle, attached to the right ovary with a thrice twisted pedicle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005">Figure 5</xref>). Both the uterus and left adnexa appeared normal. A total hysterectomy and bilateral salpingo-ooferectomy were performed. According to pathological and immunohistochimical findings, the diagnosis of ovarian fibroma with extensive ischemic necrosis was confirmed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0006">Figure 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0007">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Pelvic computed tomography revealing an enlarged ovary with iso-dense mass in the midline, measuring 122&#xD7; 86cm with deviation of the uterus</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-20-322-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Pelvic computed tomography showing rotated mass toward the contralateral side of the pelviswithout lymphadenopathy or pelvic effusion</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-20-322-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intraoperative picture showing a black bluish encapsulated mass arising from the twisted right adnexa, measuring 140x 100x 60 mm</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-20-322-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Intraoperative picture showing an ovarian mass with irregular surface, hemorrhagicreshuffle and thrice twisted pedicle</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-20-322-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Macroscopic appearance of the resected ovarian fibroma.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-20-322-g005"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histopathology of ovarian fibroma showing benignspindle cellproliferation (X4)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-20-322-g006"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 7</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histopathology of ovarian fibroma showing ischemic necrosis (X4)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-20-322-g007"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0003">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Mesenchymal neoplasms of the ovary are uncommon, not specific and determine difficult problems in diagnosis, histogenesis, behavior, and therapy [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Ovarian fibroma is seen between 20 and 65 years oldwith mean ages in the fifth and sixth decades [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Ovarian fibroma can be bilateral in 4-8% of patients and multiple in 10% of cases [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], especially in Gorlin syndrome [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], or associated with pleural effusion and ascites in Meigs&#x2019; syndrome [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. It is often seen concomitantly with uterine leiomyoma suggesting an identical hormonal stimulation [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and rarely associated with hirsutism or infertility [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>These tumors are often asymptomatic despite their large size and are mostly discovered on routine examination [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Sometimes, they manifest with abdominal enlargement, urinary symptoms, abdominal pain [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and occasionally withtorsion [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] which is rare in the postmenopausal patient such us our case [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Also, ovarian fibromacan mimic ovarian cancer because of his solid nature, his association with ascites, pleural effusions [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and elevated CA-125 levels [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] which is more pronounced in torsion due to necrosis and inflammation [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Ultrasound features are usually nonspecific [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Doppler imaging is the study ofchoice when ovarian torsion is suspected. Classically, the ovary appears enlarged, amorphous, and hypoechoic with heterogeneous stroma because of hemorrhage and edema [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and coexistent mass, free pelvic fluid, lack of arterial or venous flow, and a twisted vascular pedicle [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p>
      <p>On CT, ovarian fibroma usually appears as homogeneous solid tumors with delayed enhancement [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. While, diagnostic criteria for torsion include an adnexal mass in the midline, rotated toward the contralateral side of the pelvis; deviation of the uterus to the side of the affected ovary and ascites [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p>
      <p>MRI is often needed for further characterization and differentiation of ovarian fibromas from other solid ovarian masses [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The tumor appeared as well-circumscribed low signal intensity mass on T1, with mixed signal intensity on T2 due to degeneration of the leiomyoma [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]: hemorrhage, necrosis, cyst formation, calcareous and sarcomatous degeneration [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In fact, suggestive signs of malignancy include: solid mass, size greater than 10 cm, internal hypervascularity, advanced age, extension of the tumor into the pelvis or surrounding viscera and metastases [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. While, suggestive signs of torsion include: tube thickening, ascites, deviation to the twisted side, hemorrhage in the thickened tube, and torsion knot [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p>
      <p>Because of its rarity, the immunohistochemical analysis with desmin, inhibin &#x3B1;-smooth muscle actin or histochemical staining with Masson&#x2032;s trichrome is recommended to rule out the differential diagnosis especially leiomyosarcoma and sex-cord stromal tumors (thecoma and sclerosing stromal tumor) [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>Early recognition of ovarian torsion and restoration of blood flow are important to avoid irreversible ovarian damage. Adnexectomy has been the standard treatment, rather than untwisting the affected ovary due to fear of thromboembolism into the systemic circulation after untwisting the ovarian vasculature [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In fact, treatment for ovarian fibroma need surgical removal with intraoperative frozen whether laparoscopic or open. However, surgeons are reluctant to use laparoscopic approach because of extraction difficulty. Moreover, the benign nature cannot be definitely diagnosed preoperatively and safe removal must be achieved without peritoneal contamination [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Cystectomy only can be performed in young women [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. While, a total hysterectomy and bilateral salpingooophorectomy is be the treatment of choice in the elderly patient [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S0004">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Ovarian fibromas are uncommon but are the most common benign solid tumor of the ovary. Despite its rarity, it should be preoperatively considered in the differential diagnosis. Its treatment requires surgical removal with intraoperative frozen section and immunohistochemical analysis for definitive diagnosis.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="S0005">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare no competing interest.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0006">
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>All authors had participated in the management of this case and the realization of this work. All authors read and agreed to the final version of this manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nigam</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lal</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Twisted Ovarian Fibroma Mimicking as an Ectopic Pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Journal of case reports.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>64</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gogineni</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sunitha</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chelamkuri</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extrauterine Postmenopausal fibroid with torsion</article-title>
          <source>IOSR Journal of Dental and Medical Sciences.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Najmi</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehdizadehkashi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kadivar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamannaie</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaichian</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Laparoscopic Approach to a Large Ovarian Fibroma: A Case Report</article-title>
          <source>J Reprod Infertil.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24696796</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Macci&#xF2;</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madeddu</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kotsonis</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pietrangeli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paoletti</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large twisted ovarian fibroma associated with Meigs&#x2019; syndrome, abdominal pain and severe anemia treated by laparoscopic surgery</article-title>
          <source>BMC Surgery.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24962423</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cambruzzi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pegas</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Milani</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cruz</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guerra</surname>
              <given-names>EH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrari</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Angiosarcoma arising in an ovarian fibroma: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Patholog Res Int.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <month>10</month>
          <day>31</day>
          <volume>2010</volume>
          <fpage>842592</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21151524</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taskin</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozturk</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yildirim</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozdemir</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inceboz</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary ovarian leiomyoma:a case report</article-title>
          <source>Int J Surg Case Rep.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>665</fpage>
          <lpage>668</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25194600</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Son</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeon</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bae</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Laparoscopic Surgical Management and Clinical Characteristics of Ovarian Fibromas</article-title>
          <source>JSLS.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>16</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21902936</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yen</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khong</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lamba</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corwin</surname>
              <given-names>M.T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gerscovich</surname>
              <given-names>E.O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ovarian Fibromas and FibrothecomasSonographic Correlation With Computed Tomography and Magnetic Resonance Imaging:a 5-Year Single-Institution Experience</article-title>
          <source>J Ultrasound Med.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <month>1</month>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>13</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23269706</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aram</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moghaddam</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bilateral ovarian fibroma associated with Gorlin syndrome</article-title>
          <source>JRMS.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21772861</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seracchioli</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagnoli</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colombo</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Missiroli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Venturoli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Conservative treatment of recurrent ovarian fibromas in a young patient affected by Gorlin syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Hum Reprod.</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <month>6</month>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1261</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11387302</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yazdani</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alijanpoor</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharbatdaran</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bouzari</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abedisamakoosh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lakaieandi</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohammadpour</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Meigs&#x2019; syndrome with elevated serum CA125 in a case of ovarian fibroma /thecoma</article-title>
          <source>Caspian Journal of Internal Medicine.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24490014</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rajabi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hani</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagheri</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirzadeh</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large ovarian leiomyoma in young woman</article-title>
          <source>Adv Biomed Res.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>88</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24761396</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>T&#xE2;rcoveanu</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dimofte</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niculescu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasilescu</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moldovanu</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferariu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marcovici</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ovarian Fibroma in the Era of Laparoscopic Surgery: a General Surgeon's Experience</article-title>
          <source>Actachirbelg.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>664</fpage>
          <lpage>669</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhatt</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dogra</surname>
              <given-names>VS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pearls and Pitfalls in Diagnosis of Ovarian Torsion</article-title>
          <source>Radio Graphics.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <season>Sep-Oct</season>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>1355</fpage>
          <lpage>68</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vandermeer</surname>
              <given-names>FQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong-You-Cheong</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imaging of Acute Pelvic Pain</article-title>
          <source>Clin Obstet Gynecol.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <month>3</month>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19179858</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shinagare</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meylaerts</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laury</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mortele</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MRI Features of Ovarian Fibroma and FibrothecomaWithHistopathologic Correlation</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <month>3</month>
          <volume>198</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>W296</fpage>
          <lpage>303</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22358029</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0017">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rha</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Byun</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hahn</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CT and MRI Findings of Sex Cord&#x2013;Stromal Tumor of the Ovary</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <month>7</month>
          <volume>185</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>207</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15972425</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
