<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Card Anaesth</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Card Anaesth</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ACA</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Annals of Cardiac Anaesthesia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0971-9784</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0974-5181</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26440257</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4881660</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ACA-18-609</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0971-9784.166487</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Lipomatous hypertrophy of the interatrial septum and fibrosing mediastinal lymphadenopathy causing superior vena cava obstruction</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baikoussis</surname>
            <given-names>Nikolaos G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Argiriou</surname>
            <given-names>Orestis</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kratimenos</surname>
            <given-names>Theodoros</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dedeilias</surname>
            <given-names>Panagiotis</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Argiriou</surname>
            <given-names>Michalis</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Cardiovascular and Thoracic Surgery, Evangelismos General Hospital of Athens, Athens, Greece</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Interventional Radiology, Evangelismos General Hospital of Athens, Athens, Greece</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Nikolaos G. Baikoussis, 45-47 Ipsilantou Street, Kolonaki, Athens, Greece. E-mail: <email xlink:href="nikolaos.baikoussis@gmail.com">nikolaos.baikoussis@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Oct-Dec</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>18</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>609</fpage>
      <lpage>611</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; 2015 Annals of Cardiac Anaesthesia</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lipomatous hypertrophy of the interatrial septum (LHIS) is an uncommon cause of superior vena cava syndrome (SVCS). Fibrosing mediastinal lymphadenopathy is another cause of SVCS. We present a 65-year-old female patient with a history of tuberculosis (TB) and the coexistence of LHIS and fibrosing mediastinitis due to TB of the lung. Fibrosing or sclerosing mediastinitis is a rare entity with few cases published in the western literature. She presented with mild symptomatology of SVCS and she underwent on transthoracic and transesophageal echocardiography, computed tomography scan, magnetic resonance imaging, and venography. Due to the development of an abundant collateral venous system seen on venography and her negation for any treatment, she did not undergo yet on any intervention. To our knowledge, this is the first case reported in the international bibliography in which LHIS and sclerosing lymphadenopathy are simultaneously diagnosed in the same patient.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Fibrosing mediastinal lymphadenopathy</kwd>
        <kwd>Lipomatous hypertrophy of the interatrial septum</kwd>
        <kwd>Superior vena cava syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Tuberculosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Lipomatous hypertrophy of the interatrial septum (LHIS) is defined as a noncapsulated, circumscribed fatty mass, 2 cm thick of the atrial septum.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] LHIS is uncommon, but due to technology is more frequently recognized. In several clinical studies no typical symptoms of LHIS are described. This cardiac lesion can cause right atrial obstruction, superior vena cava syndrome (SVCS), intractable supraventricular arrhythmias, or sudden cardiac death.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] It was first described by Prior in 1964 in five patients at postmortem examination.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Although many theories have been suggested, etiology of LHIS is still unknown.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Fibrosing mediastinal lymphadenopathy due to tuberculosis (TB) is a rare cause of SVCS.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>We present a 65-year-old female with a history of a treated TB and mild symptomatology of SVCS. She underwent on transthoracic and transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) and then in computed tomography (CT) scan and venography. In transthoracic and TEE as well as in CT scan was seen an LHIS [Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">b</xref>]. This lesions, as above mentioned, are usually clinically silent and discovered incidentally at echocardiography or intraoperatively. It may cause SVCS or supraventricular arrhythmias. Our patient had an obstructed SVC but the reason of this, was the fibrosing mediastinal lymphadenopathy due to TB. This woman developed a chronic obstruction of the SVC as a complication of mediastinal and lung TB. However, she developed, as a complication, an obstruction of the SVC that became chronic due to a late diagnosis. The fibrosing mediastinitis is well shown in CT scan [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>] and then the cavography [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>] showed a severe and extensive obstruction of the SVC at the level of junction of the left and right innominate vein, before the composition of the SVC. There is not any reason to treat the LHIS because our patient had normal sinus rhythm, and she has never experienced any palpitation or syncoptic episode. The second finding, the scherosing mediastinitis which obstructs the SVC could be treated. We had the dilemma between affront or not affront this lesion. Due to patient negation for any treatment and the mild symptomatology as well as the existence of an abundant collateral venous system seen on venography, it has been decided to not perform any intervention. According the international bibliography the endovascular therapy is of primary selected way of treatment with the implantation <italic>in situ</italic> a stent.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Thoracic computed tomography scan. (a) A heavily calcified mass with almost 4 cm diameter, at the level of the conjunction of the anonymous veins, compressing the superior vena cava (arrow). Multiple small vessels in the anterior mediastinum. No ascending aorta involvement is noticed. (b) Upper pulmonary field level; fibrosis of the right upper pulmonary lobe (arrow)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ACA-18-609-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(a) Transesophageal echocardiography, interatrial septal fatty infiltration was demonstrated (arrow). Interatrial septum of 1.6 cm thick (b) beside subtraction venography shows: On the right, progressive stenosis of the right anonymous vein and finally stop before the superior vena cava origin (white arrow) with multiple venous collateral vessels formation. On the left, there is a stop at the distal part of left anonymous vein (black arrow) and presence of enlarged varicose veins at the level of the left heart margin area (yellow arrow)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ACA-18-609-g002"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Although LHIS has often been identified incidentally, atrial arrhythmias, including atrial fibrillation, atrial premature complexes, supraventricular tachycardia, ectopic atrial rhythm, and junctional rhythm, have been associated with lipomatous hypertrophy.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Intervention is not usually required. Surgical resection has been performed in symptomatic patients with SVC obstruction or with intractable arrhythmias.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] It differs from a pure lipoma in that lipomas are true neoplasms and usually occur in a much younger patients. However, surgical treatment is similar for both.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] CT scan and magnetic resonance imaging can be useful in selected patients with large fatty infiltration or marked hypertrophy of the septum. Lipomatous hypertrophy of the IAS can be surgically excised. The large IAS defect that results after excision of the mass requires closure using a pericardial or a synthetic patch. Recurrence after excision has not been reported, and the long-term prognosis is excellent. Malignant degeneration is a rare occurrence.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Surgical therapy appears to be reserved to patients with SVC obstruction or any rhythm disturbances.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] The main problem is differentiating LHIS from a cardiac neoplasm when the lesion is discovered with echocardiography. With improvements in imaging, LHIS should possibly be recognized more frequently. However, surgical resection should only be performed in symptomatic patients.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</p>
      <p>The second finding was the fibrosing mediastinal lymphadenopathy. The most common etiologies for sclerosing mediastinitis are TB and histoplasmosis.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] In TB sclerosing mediastinitis, hilar adenopathy or active pulmonary disease are not a common found. Interestingly, of the following vascular structures, such as a pulmonary artery, pulmonary veins, and SVC, the latter is the least frequently compromised.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-4">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>We will suggest considering LHIS as a part of the differential diagnosis for any atrial cardiac tumor. It may be the cause of SVCS, but other causes as mediastinal lymphadenopathy may be responsible. The rich diagnostic armamentarium helps us to take the right decision and to perform the correct intervention.</p>
      <sec id="sec2-1">
        <title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
        <p>Nil.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2-2">
        <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
        <p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Connor</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Recavarren</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nichols</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parwani</surname>
              <given-names>AV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lipomatous hypertrophy of the interatrial septum: An overview</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>397</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16519573</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Christiansen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stypmann</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baba</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hammel</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scheld</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical management of extensive lipomatous hypertrophy of the right atrium</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Surg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>88</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10661712</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moinuddeen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marica</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clausi</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zama</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lipomatous interatrial septal hypertrophy: An unusual cause of intracardiac mass</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>468</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12204749</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verberkmoes</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kats</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tan-Go</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sch&#xF6;nberger</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Resection of a lipomatous hypertrophic interatrial septum involving the right ventricle</article-title>
          <source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>654</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17670727</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Esquivel</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Diaz-Picado</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fibrosing TB mediastinitis presenting as a superior vena cava syndrome: A case presentation and echocardiogram correlate</article-title>
          <source>Echocardiography</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>588</fpage>
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911334</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
