<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26166118</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4504606</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000001135</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">01135</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>5700</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>C3 Vertebral Metastases From Tongue Adenoid Cystic Carcinoma</article-title>
        <subtitle>A Rare Case Report</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>Helin</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MM</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
            <given-names>Peng</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MM</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
            <given-names>Jianfa</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MM</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Feng</surname>
            <given-names>Jiangang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Wei.</surname>
            <given-names>Leizhen</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>From the Department of Orthopedics, The Fourth Affiliated Hospital of Hebei Medical University, Shijiazhuang, Hebei, P.R. China (HF, JW, PG, JX, JF).</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Correspondence: Jiangang Feng, The Fourth Affiliated Hospital of Hebei Medical University, Shijiazhuang, Hebei, P.R. China (e-mail: <email>fengjiangang0311@126.com</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>94</volume>
      <issue>27</issue>
      <elocation-id>e1135</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0, where it is permissible to download, share and reproduce the work in any medium, provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-94-e1135.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>We report a rare case involving a patient with C3 vertebral body metastasis secondary to adenoid cystic carcinoma of the tongue.</p>
        <p>Five years after local resection of the primary tumor, magnetic resonance imaging showed a metastasis located in the left posterior border of the C3 vertebral body. Additionally, multiple pulmonary metastases were identified by computed tomography. Based on these findings, the patient underwent C2&#x2013;3, C3&#x2013;4 discectomy; C3 corpectomy; and titanium mesh fusion with a Zephir plate. The diagnosis was confirmed by the pathology findings. During 6 months of follow-up, the patient showed improvement and return of function of the cervical vertebrae, with no serious complications.</p>
        <p>Because of the scarcity of cases of vertebral metastases from tumors of the tongue in the literature, we have reported this case to add to the available evidence regarding this rarely encountered condition.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Authors&#x2019; contributions: H.F. conceived of the case report and drafted the manuscript; J.W. helped to draft the manuscript; P.G. and J.X. obtained the images; and J.F. edited the manuscript.</p>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Tongue cancer is the most common type of oral cancer<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>; however, most malignant tongue tumors are squamous cell carcinoma (SCC).<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Other common locations of oral SCCs include the salivary glands,<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> followed by the hard palate and the base of the tongue.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> On the other hand, tongue adenoid cystic carcinoma (ACC) is rarely seen in the clinic.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Further, while this rare malignancy has been reported to frequently metastasize to the lung and bones,<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> we here describe a very rare case involving a patient who presented with a left posterior tongue lesion with metastatic spread to the C3 vertebrae. The patient was successfully treated with surgery and radiotherapy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>In 2009, a 52-year-old woman was referred to our hospital with an asymptomatic volume growth on her left posterior tongue. Examination of a biopsy specimen showed cancer cells. Accordingly, she was diagnosed with tongue cancer and underwent local resection. The tumor was diagnosed as tongue ACC based on the pathology findings (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The patient received interstitial iodine-125 implantation postoperatively. Five years later, in June 2014, she started to experience paralysis in both hands and reported pain in her neck. X-ray imaging showed that the C3 posterior edge density was slightly decreased (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A and B). Further, T1-weighted magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) demonstrated a subtle decrease in signal in the C3 vertebral body (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C and D). The findings of each imaging modality showed that the left posterior border of the C3 vertebral body was invaded, and that multiple pulmonary metastases were present (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, we performed anterior C2&#x2013;3, C3&#x2013;4 discectomy; C3 vertebral resection; and titanium mesh fusion with a Zephir plate. The operation was successful, and the intraoperative blood loss was approximately 200&#x200A;mL. Histopathological analysis demonstrated a neoplasm that was formed of microcystic spaces surrounded by atypical hyperchromatic epithelial cells invading the adjacent muscular tissue. The pathology findings of the C3 vertebral body lesion revealed ACC (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). After 2 weeks of adjuvant chemoradiation therapy, the patient remained in good health. Two months later, magnetic resonance images and computed tomography showed no recurrence (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). At the 6-month follow-up, the patient was alive and the function of the cervical vertebrae was improved. The patient provided written informed consent for the publication of these case details and the consent procedure was approved by the Human Ethics and Research Ethics committees of the Fourth Hospital of Hebei Medical University.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Pathology findings resulted in a diagnosis of the tumor as tongue adenoid cystic carcinoma.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e1135-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>X-ray imaging (A and B) showed that the C3 posterior edge density was slightly decreased (arrow). T1-weighted magnetic resonance images without contrast enhancement (C, sagittal; D, axial) demonstrated a subtle decrease in signal in the C3 vertebral body (arrow).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e1135-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Chest radiographs revealed multiple pulmonary metastases (arrow).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e1135-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Microphotograph, showing the formation of microcystic spaces surrounded by hyperchromatic cells (hematoxylin and eosin stain).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e1135-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F5" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The patient was followed-up with magnetic resonance imaging and computed tomography scans, which did not show any detectable recurrence at 2 months.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e1135-g005"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>In 1859, Billroth first coined the term &#x201C;cylindroma&#x201D; to describe the histological standard of 4 salivary gland tumors. This term was widely used until 1953, when Foote and Frazell redesignated these lesions as &#x201C;adenoid cystic carcinomas.&#x201D;<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> ACC can originate from both the minor and major salivary glands,<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> and a recent study suggested that 4.4% of minor salivary gland tumors are located on the tongue.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> These tumors generally progress slowly and tend to show wide perineural invasion into the adjacent nerves and distant metastasis. The primary tumor generally metastasizes via the lymphatics<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and rarely metastasizes via the blood. Carlson and Ord<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> reported the cases of 4 patients with 13 involved vertebrae, all of whom presented with symptoms such as severe pain, hypercalcemic somnolence, and flaccid paralysis of the lower extremities as part of cauda equina syndrome. Accordingly, the authors advocated that such patients, especially those with bone pain, should undergo radiographic examinations to identify distant metastases. Mendes et al<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> described 3 patients who presented with symptoms and signs of nerve root compression affecting the upper limbs secondary to tongue cancer metastasis. Further, in 2007, Lee et al<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> reported 2 cases in which signs of spinal cord compression developed due to tongue tumor metastasis to the lumbar vertebrae, and the authors suggested that oral cancer may cause vertebral metastasis. In a more recent report, Tornwall et al<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> described a case of spinal cord metastases from oral SCC that started with pain in the lower limbs and spine. However, the present case differed from previously reported cases in several respects aspects: including the facts that it was involved tongue ACC rather than SCC, showed metastasis to the C3 vertebrae, and that the patient achieved significant improvements in quality of life using the management strategies that have been described above. In resemblance with the previously reported cases, our case indicated that tongue cancer has a tendency toward distant metastasis, and clinicians should hence be aware of the possibility of spine metastasis in any patient presenting with tongue cancer.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: ACC = adenoid cystic carcinoma, MRI = magnetic resonance imaging, SCC = squamous cell carcinoma.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Carcinoma of the tongue: a case series analysis of clinical presentation, risk factors, staging, and outcome</article-title>. <source><italic>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</italic></source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>552</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15529126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyree</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Increasing incidence of oral tongue squamous cell carcinoma in young white women, age 18 to 44 years</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Oncol</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1488</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1494</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21383286</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carreiro</surname><given-names>FFP</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Adenoid cystic carcinoma of the tongue: case report and literature review</article-title>. <source><italic>Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>E475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>E478</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18667978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khafif</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anavi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Haviv</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Adenoid cystic carcinoma of the salivary glands: a 20-year review with long-term follow-up</article-title>. <source><italic>Ear Nose Throat J</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <volume>662</volume>:<fpage>664</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>667</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Laskin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Evolution of an adenocarcinoma in response to selection by targeted kinase inhibitors</article-title>. <source><italic>Genome Biol</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>R82: 1-12</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20696054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsubara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimatsu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Establishment and characterization of a human adenoid cystic carcinoma line of the salivary gland which is serially transplantable and spontaneously metastasises to the lung in nude mice</article-title>. <source><italic>Oral Oncol</italic></source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11755818</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leafstedt</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaeta</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sako</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Adenoid cystic carcinoma of major and minor salivary glands</article-title>. <source><italic>Am J Surg</italic></source>
<year>1971</year>; <volume>122</volume>:<fpage>756</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>762</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4331409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foote</surname><given-names>FW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Frazell</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Tumors of the major salivary glands</article-title>. <source><italic>Cancer</italic></source>
<year>1953</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1065</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13106826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Sukhun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindqvist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hietanen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Central adenoid cystic carcinoma of the mandible: case report and literature review of 16 cases</article-title>. <source><italic>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>308</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16504862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baskaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mithra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sathyakumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Adenoid cystic carcinoma of the mobile tongue: a rare case</article-title>. <source><italic>Dent Res J (Isfahan)</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>9</volume>
<issue>(Suppl. 1)</issue>:<fpage>S115</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>S118</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23814551</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mesolella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luce</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Treatment of c-kit positive adenoid cystic carcinoma of the tongue: a case report</article-title>. <source><italic>Oncol Lett</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>312</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24959267</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Ord</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Vertebral metastases from oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</italic></source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>858</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>862</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12149726</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nutting</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Residual or recurrent head and neck cancer presenting with nerve root compression affecting the upper limbs</article-title>. <source><italic>Br J Radiol</italic></source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>688</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>690</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15326051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Halfpenny</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiruchelvam</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Spinal cord compression in patients with oral squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>e16</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>e18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17275365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tornwall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Snall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesimaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A rare case of spinal cord metastases from oral SCC</article-title>. <source><italic>Br J Oral Maxillofac Surg</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>594</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>595</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18359540</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
