<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Med Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Medical Case Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1752-1947</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24934580</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4077239</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1752-1947-8-195</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-1947-8-195</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Postsurgical <italic>Pantoea calida</italic> meningitis: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1">
          <name>
            <surname>Fritz</surname>
            <given-names>Shirley</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>shirley.fritz@ymail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2">
          <name>
            <surname>Cassir</surname>
            <given-names>Nadim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>nadimcassir@hotmail.it</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3">
          <name>
            <surname>Noudel</surname>
            <given-names>Remy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>remynoudel@yahoo.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4">
          <name>
            <surname>De La Rosa</surname>
            <given-names>Silvestre</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>doctor_delarosa@hotmail.com</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5">
          <name>
            <surname>Roche</surname>
            <given-names>Pierre-Hugues</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>pierre-hugues.roche@ap-hm.fr</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A6">
          <name>
            <surname>Drancourt</surname>
            <given-names>Michel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref>
          <email>michel.drancourt@univ-amu.fr</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>URMITE, UMR63 CNRS 7278, IRD 198, Inserm 1095, Aix Marseille Universit&#xE9;, 13005 Marseille, France</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Service des Maladies Infectieuses et Tropicales, H&#xF4;pital Nord, Assistance Publique &#x2013; H&#xF4;pitaux de Marseille, Chemin des Bourrely, 13915 Marseille Cedex 20, France</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Service de Neurochirurgie, H&#xF4;pital Nord, Assistance Publique &#x2013; H&#xF4;pitaux de Marseille, Chemin des Bourrely, 13915 Marseille Cedex 20, France</aff>
      <aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Facult&#xE9; de M&#xE9;decine, Unit&#xE9; de recherche sur les maladies infectieuses et tropicales &#xE9;mergentes, 27, Boulevard Jean Moulin, Marseille Cedex 5, France</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <fpage>195</fpage>
      <lpage>195</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 Fritz et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Fritz et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jmedicalcasereports.com/content/8/1/195"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p><italic>Pantoea calida,</italic> a recently described environmental Enterobacteriaceae organism, has not yet been associated with human infection.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>We report a case of postoperative meningitis caused by <italic>P. calida.</italic> After pituitary adenoma resection, a 52-year-old Caucasian woman developed febrile meningitis confirmed by cerebrospinal fluid analysis. <italic>P. calida</italic> was grown in pure culture from this fluid and was firmly identified with partial <italic>rpoB</italic> gene sequencing. She was cured by a 14-day course of meropenem.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p><italic>P. calida</italic> must be added to the list of opportunistic Enterobacteriaceae pathogens responsible for postsurgical meningitis. It is easily identified by matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Health-care associated infection</kwd>
        <kwd>Meningitis</kwd>
        <kwd>Neurosurgery</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Pantoea calida</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><italic>Pantoea calida</italic> has been recently described as a species of Enterobacteriaceae after its seminal isolation and culture from powdered infant formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. It has not yet been associated with any infections and no clinical isolate has been reported. Here, we isolated one strain of <italic>P. calida</italic> from a cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) specimen and identified it as the cause of postsurgical meningitis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 52-year-old Caucasian woman had a medical history of hypertension, smoking and alcoholism. She presented with binocular diplopia. A computed tomography scan showed an intrasellar lesion with invasion of her right cavernous sinus that was further confirmed by brain magnetic resonance imaging. An endoscopic endonasal biopsy was performed and histopathology showed a nonspecific inflammation and subacute hemorrhagic alteration of her nasal mucosa. An antibiotic prophylaxis with cefazolin 2gr was given. A transnasal surgical excision was performed, and no leak of CSF was observed after the surgery. Histopathology confirmed a single prolactin pituitary adenoma. Five days after the surgery, she presented a fever (38.6&#xB0;C) and a meningeal syndrome with consciousness disorder, neck stiffness and a Glasgow Coma Scale evaluated at 13 (E4V4M5) but without focal neurological deficits. The CSF collected by lumbar puncture showed hypoglycorrhachia (1.33mmol/L; CSF/serum glucose ratio=0.20), an elevated protein level (5.88g/L) and 4500 leukocytes/mL including 98% polymorphonuclear leukocytes. There was no detectable organism on direct microscopic examination after Gram staining. Treatment combining intravenous vancomycin 1gr twice a day and intravenous meropenem 2gr three times a day was started for presumptive postsurgical meningitis. Her clinical condition rapidly improved, with apyrexia and a net regression of the meningeal syndrome within 2 days. Five days after the onset of symptoms, vancomycin was stopped and meropenem 6gr per day was continued for a total of 14 days. At 90-day follow-up she was afebrile, healthy and without any sign of meningitis.</p>
      <p>The CSF was inoculated on Polyvitex (bioM&#xE9;rieux, La Balme-les-Grottes, France) and Columbia agar with 5% sheep blood and incubated at 37&#xB0;C under a 5% carbon dioxide atmosphere. After 48-hour incubation, small whitish round shiny domed colonies were observed on both culture media. Matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF-MS) performed as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] yielded <italic>P. calida</italic> with identification score of 2.26, 2.17 and 2.17 for the three spots deposited on the MALDI-TOF-MS plate. Furthermore partial <italic>rpoB</italic> gene sequencing performed as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] confirmed the identification of <italic>P. calida</italic> with 99.88% sequence similarity with the reference sequence (GenBank GQ892191). Antimicrobial susceptibility was performed by diffusion method in agar and incubated aerobically for 24 hours at 37&#xB0;C. The isolate was resistant to ampicillin (minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC)&#x2009;&gt;8mg/L), amoxicillin-clavulanate (MIC, 1mg/L), and cephalothin (MIC, 1mg/L). It was susceptible to ceftriaxone (MIC, 0.5mg/L), imipenem (MIC, 0.5mg/L), ciprofloxacin (MIC, 0.25mg/L), gentamicin (MIC&lt;1mg/L) and co-trimoxazole (MIC&lt;1mg/L).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Here, <italic>P. calida</italic> was isolated from the CSF of a patient with postoperative meningitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The isolate was firmly identified by using two different complementary approaches: MALDI-TOF-MS which is an advanced proteomics method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] relying on the analysis of unique peptidic signatures; and partial <italic>rpoB</italic> gene sequencing which relies on the analysis of unique nucleotidic signatures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. These two technical approaches yielded unambiguous, concordant identification. In particular, MALDI-TOF-MS proved to be efficient to identify this species, despite the fact that no clinical isolate was previously included in the database.</p>
      <p>The absence of any bacteria other than <italic>P. calida</italic> on the culture of CSF, as well as the fact that it was the first identification of this microorganism in our laboratory, secure the conclusion that <italic>P. calida</italic> was responsible for this postoperative meningitis. Accordingly, the patient was rapidly cured after an effective antibiotic treatment was administrated. In this case, the source of infection remained unknown. Indeed, <italic>P. calida</italic> has been documented only in powdered infant formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] and our patient had no contact with such formula. Of interest, the <italic>Cronobacter</italic> species (formerly <italic>Enterobacter sakazakii</italic>) causing health-care-associated meningitis in neonates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] is also contaminating powdered infant formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Indeed, <italic>P. calida</italic> is closely related to members of the Enterobacteriaceae genus <italic>Erwinia</italic>, <italic>Tatumella</italic>, <italic>Kluyvera</italic>, <italic>Citrobacter</italic> and <italic>Cronobacter</italic>, which also comprise opportunistic pathogens causing meningitis, mainly in newborns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Whereas <italic>Erwinia</italic> and <italic>Tatumella</italic> organisms have not been associated with central nervous system infection, <italic>Kluyvera</italic> meningitis has been reported in a newborn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Also <italic>Citrobacter</italic> bacteria are opportunistic pathogens seldom reported as causing meningitis in neonates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] and adults with cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Recently, one case of <italic>Citrobacter koseri</italic> meningitis has been reported after free-diving [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Lastly, <italic>Cronobacter</italic> species along with <italic>Enterobacter</italic> species have been reported as causes of health-care-associated meningitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p><italic>P. calida</italic> should be added to the list of Enterobacteriaceae pathogens responsible for infectious postoperative meningitis. Sources different from powdered infant formula should be investigated. <italic>P. calida</italic> meningitis can be cured by appropriate antibiotic treatment. This new pathogen can easily be identified by using MALDI-TOF-MS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <p>CSF: Cerebrospinal fluid; MALDI-TOF-MS: Matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry; MIC: Minimal inhibitory concentration.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>NC, RN, SDLR, and PHR took care of the patient. SF and MD took care of the microbiology of the specimens. SF, NC, RN, and SDLR wrote the case. PHR and MD evaluated the draft and suggested revisions. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This work was supported by URMITE, Marseille, France.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Popp</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cleenwerck</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Iversen</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>De Vos</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Stephan</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>Pantoea gaviniae</italic> sp. nov. and <italic>Pantoea calida</italic> sp. nov., isolated from infant formula and an infant formula production environment</article-title>
          <source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>2786</fpage>
          <lpage>2792</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.019430-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20061487</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Seng</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Drancourt</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gouriet</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>La Scola</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fournier</surname>
            <given-names>PE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rolain</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raoult</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Ongoing revolution in bacteriology: routine identification of bacteria by matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>543</fpage>
          <lpage>551</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/600885</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19583519</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Seng</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Abat</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rolain</surname>
            <given-names>JM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Colson</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lagier</surname>
            <given-names>JC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Gouriet</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fournier</surname>
            <given-names>PE</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Drancourt</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>La Scola</surname>
            <given-names>B</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raoult</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Identification of rare pathogenic bacteria in a clinical microbiology laboratory: impact of matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization-time of flight mass spectrometry</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>2182</fpage>
          <lpage>2194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00492-13</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23637301</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Mollet</surname>
            <given-names>C</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Drancourt</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raoult</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>rpoB</italic> sequence analysis as a novel basis for bacterial identification</article-title>
          <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1005</fpage>
          <lpage>1011</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1997.6382009.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9426137</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tavares</surname>
            <given-names>WM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Machado</surname>
            <given-names>AG</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Matushita</surname>
            <given-names>H</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Plese</surname>
            <given-names>JP</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>CSF markers for diagnosis of bacterial meningitis in postoperative neurosurgical patients</article-title>
          <source>Arq Neuropsiquiatr</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>592</fpage>
          <lpage>595</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0004-282X2006000400012</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17119799</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Ad&#xE9;kambi</surname>
            <given-names>T</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Drancourt</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Raoult</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>The <italic>rpoB</italic> gene as a tool for clinical microbiologists</article-title>
          <source>Trends Microbiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>45</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2008.09.008</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19081723</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Hunter</surname>
            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bean</surname>
            <given-names>JF</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>Cronobacter</italic>: an emerging opportunistic pathogen associated with neonatal meningitis, sepsis and necrotizing enterocolitis</article-title>
          <source>J Perinatol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>581</fpage>
          <lpage>585</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jp.2013.26</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23538645</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Cai</surname>
            <given-names>XQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>HQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruan</surname>
            <given-names>ZX</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>LL</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Bai</surname>
            <given-names>JS</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Qiu</surname>
            <given-names>DY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Jian</surname>
            <given-names>ZH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Xiao</surname>
            <given-names>YQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>JY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Le</surname>
            <given-names>TH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Zhu</surname>
            <given-names>XQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Rapid detection and simultaneous genotyping of <italic>Cronobacter</italic> spp. (formerly <italic>Enterobacter sakazakii</italic>) in powdered infant formula using real-time PCR and high resolution melting (HRM) analysis</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>e67082</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067082</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23825624</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Yan</surname>
            <given-names>QQ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Condell</surname>
            <given-names>O</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Power</surname>
            <given-names>K</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
            <given-names>F</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tall</surname>
            <given-names>BD</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Fanning</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>Cronobacter</italic> species (formerly known as <italic>Enterobacter sakazakii</italic>) in powdered infant formula: a review of our current understanding of the biology of this bacterium</article-title>
          <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2012.05281.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22420458</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Rosso</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Rojas</surname>
            <given-names>P</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Garcia</surname>
            <given-names>E</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Marquez</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Losada</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Munoz</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>Kluyvera</italic> meningitis in a newborn</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1070</fpage>
          <lpage>1071</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/INF.0b013e31812e4b96</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17984822</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Cuadros</surname>
            <given-names>EN</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Castilla</surname>
            <given-names>CY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Algarra</surname>
            <given-names>CM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>P&#xE9;rez</surname>
            <given-names>DM</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lopez</surname>
            <given-names>BR</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Martin</surname>
            <given-names>FJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cardona</surname>
            <given-names>AU</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Medical and neurosurgical management of <italic>Citrobacter koseri,</italic> a rare cause of neonatal meningitis</article-title>
          <source>J Med Microbiol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>144</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.063586-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24243285</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Prais</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Nussinovitch</surname>
            <given-names>M</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Harel</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Amir</surname>
            <given-names>J</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>Citrobacter koseri</italic> (<italic>diversus</italic>) meningitis in an otherwise healthy adolescent</article-title>
          <source>Scand J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>202</fpage>
          <lpage>204</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0036554021000027020</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12751719</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Tan</surname>
            <given-names>CK</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lai</surname>
            <given-names>CC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>SH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Liao</surname>
            <given-names>CH</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>YT</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hsueh</surname>
            <given-names>PR</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Fatal <italic>Citrobacter farmeri</italic> meningitis in a patient with nasopharyngeal cancer</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>1499</fpage>
          <lpage>1500</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00282-10</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20181904</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Pollara</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Savy</surname>
            <given-names>L</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Cropley</surname>
            <given-names>I</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hopkins</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title><italic>Citrobacter koseri</italic> meningitis: another freediving risk?</article-title>
          <source>J Infect</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>103</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2010.09.036</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20933000</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <name>
            <surname>Kuo</surname>
            <given-names>CC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>JY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chien</surname>
            <given-names>JY</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>YF</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>VC</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Tsai</surname>
            <given-names>CW</given-names>
          </name>
          <name>
            <surname>Hwang</surname>
            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
          </name>
          <article-title>Nontraumatic pneumocephalus due to nosocomial <italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic> infection</article-title>
          <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>108</fpage>
          <lpage>110</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2009.03.024</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19442474</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
