<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Korean J Parasitol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Korean J. Parasitol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KJP</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Korean Journal of Parasitology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0023-4001</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1738-0006</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Society for Parasitology and Tropical Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24850963</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4028457</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3347/kjp.2014.52.2.189</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Visceral Leishmaniasis without Fever in an 11-Month-Old Infant: a Rare Clinical Feature of Kala-azar</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Sayyahfar</surname>
            <given-names>Shirin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ansari</surname>
            <given-names>Shahla</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mohebali</surname>
            <given-names>Mehdi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Behnam</surname>
            <given-names>Babak</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, Ali Asghar Children Hospital, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Parasitology and Mycology, School of Public Health, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Genetics and Molecular Biology, Ali Asghar Children Hospital, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Corresponding author (<email>sayyahfar.sh@iums.ac.ir</email>)
</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>52</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>189</fpage>
      <lpage>191</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2014, Korean Society for Parasitology and Tropical Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Visceral leishmaniasis or kala-azar is an endemic parasitic disease in some parts of the world which is characterized by fever, splenomegaly, and pancytopenia in most of the cases. Herein we report an 11 month-old male infant with diagnosis of kala-azar who presented with pallor, hepatosplenomegaly, failure to gain weight, and no history of fever. Surprisingly, fever started after beginning of meglumine antimoniate treatment in this patient. As far as we are aware of, this is a rare presentation of visceral leishmaniasis. Therefore, clinicians especially in endemic areas are highly recommended to include kala-azar among differential diagnosis of unexplained anemia without fever to prevent misdiagnosis of this potentially fatal, but treatable condition.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>afebrile</kwd>
        <kwd>anemia</kwd>
        <kwd>kala-azar</kwd>
        <kwd>splenomegaly</kwd>
        <kwd>visceral leishmaniasis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Visceral leishmaniasis (VL) or kala-azar is an endemic parasitic disease in some parts of Iran which is caused predominantly by <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic> [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Fever and splenomegaly are detected in more than 80% of patients as the most common clinical manifestations. Neutropenia, anemia, thrombocytopenia, elevated ESR, and hypergammaglobulinemia are the most common laboratory abnormalities of this disease [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Herein we report a rare case of kala-azar in a pediatric age group without fever.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE RECORD</title>
      <p>An 11-month-old male was referred to Ali Asghar Children Hospital following pallor and illness for 5 months. Prior to admission in our hospital, he had received packed cell 4 times and underwent bone marrow aspiration 2 times in 2 previous admissions with no definite diagnosis. He had no history of fever, icterus, bleeding tendency, and gastrointestinal or respiratory symptoms; however, irritability, anorexia, and failure to gain weight were reported by his care givers during this time.</p>
      <p>On physical examination his vital signs were within normal range. He had hepatosplenomegaly without lymphadenopathy and rash. The span of spleen and liver measured by ultrasound examination were 122 mm&#xD7;38 mm and 78 mm, respectively. His primary laboratory data was as follows: WBC 10.6&#xD7;10<sup>3</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup> (normal range:6.0-13.5&#xD7;10<sup>3</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup>), neutrophils 21%, lymphocytes 78%, eosinophils 1%, hemoglobin (Hb) 6.4 g/dl (normal range: 11-13 g/dl), platelet 138,000/mm<sup>3</sup> (normal range: 140,000-440,000), ESR 82 mm/hr (normal:&lt;15 mm/hr), qualitative CRP 2+, reticulocyte count 2%, LDH 7,03I U/L (normal: up to 480). Serum albumin, total protein, and routine liver and kidney function test results were within normal limits. HIV test and direct coombs were also negative.</p>
      <p>Examination of bone marrow aspirate revealed a large number (grade 5+) [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] of <italic>Leishmania</italic> sp. under a light microscope with high magnification (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The parasite load in the bone marrow smears before, in the middle, end of the treatment, and relapse time was graded based on World Health Organization guidance [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. DNA from the slides was extracted and subjected to PCR-reverse fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) assay. The ribosomal internal transcribed spacer 1 (ITS1) was amplified with specific primers, and the PCR products were digested with a restriction enzyme (<italic>Hae</italic>III).</p>
      <p>The species of parasite documented by PCR-RFLP assay was <italic>L. infantum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Rapid kala-azar K39 immunochromatographic dipstick serological test for <italic>L. infantum</italic> infection was also positive. Specific anti-leishmanial antibodies detected by indirect fluorescent antibody test (IFAT) and direct agglutination test (DAT) were at titers of 1:320 and 1:3,200, respectively. Work-up for immunodeficiency disorders performed by flow cytometry showed no abnormal findings. Two days after starting treatment with meglumine antimoniate (Glucantime&#xAE;), at a dose of 20 mg/kg, the patient became febrile and fever persisted despite continuing Glucantime&#xAE; for 9 days.</p>
      <p>We switched our treatment to amphotericin B deoxycolate (1 mg/kg/day), and fever was stopped 48 hr after starting this drug. He received amphotericin B for a period of 28 days. The results of bone marrow aspiration in the middle of this time showed decreasing load of Leishman bodies (grade 2+) [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and was negative at the end of the treatment.</p>
      <p>Three months after discharge, he became pale and febrile again, and his liver and spleen were found to become enlarged on monthly examinations. He underwent bone marrow aspiration and was admitted with positive bone marrow aspirate for leishman bodies (grade 4+) [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. He was leukopenic (WBC 2,500/mm<sup>3</sup>, neutrophils 37%, lymphocytes 61%, monocytes 1%, eosionophils 1%), anemic (Hb 7.6 mg/dl) and thrombocytopenic (platelet 79,000/mm<sup>3</sup>). ESR was 108 mm/hr.</p>
      <p>His treatment was started with liposomal amphotericin B (Ambisome&#xAE;) 4 mg/kg on days 1-5 and at the 14th and 21th day in combination with daily subcutaneous human recombinant interferon-&#x3B3; at the dose of 100 &#xB5;g/m<sup>2</sup> plus oral allopurinol at the dose of 20 mg/kg/day in 3 divided doses. He was discharged 24 hr after becoming afebrile on the 5th day of receiving Ambisome&#xAE;. He received the rest of the treatment in outpatient manner. Six months follow-up showed no relapse or complications.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Visceral leishmaniasis is known as an endemic disease in some parts of the world including Iran [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The most common clinical findings are fever, splenomegaly, and anemia. Hepatomegaly is less frequent than splenomegaly, and features such as jaundice, edema, and ascites are less frequently reported [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Signs and symptoms of VL in Iran are compatible with the Mediterranean type except for the absence of significant lymphadenopathy [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Fever with maximum rate of 100% is the most common symptom but may be absent in immunocompromised patients, subclinical forms especially in endemic areas, and rarely immunocompetent ones [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Our patient was afebrile at presentation despite no documented immunodeficiency, and his bone marrow aspirate showed a large number of leishman bodies. It seems that high parasite load might suppress the inflammatory response in body and prevent fever, the phenomenon which could be noted in other diseases such as tuberculosis and lepromatous leprosy [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. It might also address the normal leukocyte count and serum albumin/total protein ratio in our case. The patient became febrile 2 days after starting treatment, and this might be due to massive release of antigens after starting therapy with a subsequent triggering of an immune response. Subsiding fever in kala-azar is usually considered as a clinical response to the treatment. Our patient did not have fever at the beginning of the treatment but fever was started after Glucantime&#xAE; treatment. We had no rapid clinical marker for response to the treatment and were compelled to discontinue Glucantime&#xAE; after 9th day of fever. It was according to some documented evidence of resistance to Glucantime&#xAE; against <italic>L. infantum</italic> and <italic>L. tropica</italic> in our area [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>We switched our treatment to amphotericin B deoxycolate and continued it for 30 days. Amphotericin B deoxycolate is usually used at a dose of 0.75-1.0 mg/kg/IV/daily for 15-20 doses for VL caused by <italic>L. donovani</italic> and up to 30 days for VL caused by <italic>L. infantum</italic> [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Three months after the end of treatment, the patient experienced an episode of relapse. Relapse could occur in kala-azar despite proper treatment and efficient immune state [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In general, diseases caused by intracellular microorganisms might recur secondary to residual organisms escaped pharmacologically and/or immunologically [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Heavy leishman body load at that first bone marrow aspiration might be a risk factor in our patient for relapse.</p>
      <p>According to its high concentration in reticuloendothelial system, we decided to use Ambisome&#xAE; and added human recombinant interferon-&#x3B3; and allopurinol as adjuvant therapies to increase the eradication rate. The indication of using interferon-&#x3B3; and allopurinol in combination with liposomal amphotericin B in patients with relapse but no documented immunosuppressant state or resistance to antimonials is poorly defined. Different regimens of Ambisome&#xAE; have been recommended for treatment of kala-azar [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The regimen which is usually administered in immunocompetent pediatric patients was scheduled for our patient [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p>
      <p>In conclusion, medical practitioners especially in endemic areas should be aware of and consider VL among differential diagnosis of afebrile unexplained anemia.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>We declare that we have no conflict of interest related to this study.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mohebali</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Visceral leishmaniasis in Iran: review of the epidemiological and clinical features</article-title>
          <source>Iran J Parasitol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>348</fpage>
          <lpage>358</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24454426</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mohebali</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edrissian</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shirzadi</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosseingholizadeh</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pashaei</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ganji</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zarei</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kousha</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akhoundi</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajjaran</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malekafzalli</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Integrated visceral leishmaniasis surveillance system in primary care for children in Meshkin-Shahr district, north-western Islamic Republic of Iran</article-title>
          <source>East Mediterr Health J</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1050</fpage>
          <lpage>1054</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21222421</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alborzi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pouladfar</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aelami</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Visceral leishmaniasis; literature review and iranian experience</article-title>
          <source>Iran J Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>99</fpage>
          <lpage>108</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mohan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reddy</surname>
              <given-names>EV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samantaray</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A rare presentation of visceral leishmaniasis without fever or splenomegaly in an elderly person</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Intern Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>158</fpage>
          <lpage>160</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17338973</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <collab>World Health Organization</collab>
          <source>Basic Laboratory Methods in Medical Parasitology</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited 2013, Nov 18</date-in-citation>
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/malaria/publications/atoz/9241544104_part1/en/index.htm">http://www.who.int/malaria/publications/atoz/9241544104_part1/en/index.htm</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hadighi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohebali</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boucher</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajjaran</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khamesipour</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ouellette</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unresponsiveness to glucantime treatment in Iranian cutaneous leishmaniasis due to drug-resistant <italic>Leishmania tropica</italic> parasites</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Medicine</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>e162</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16605301</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kazemi-Rad</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohebali</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khadem-Erfan</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saffari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raoofian</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajjaran</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hadighi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khamesipour</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rezaie</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abedkhojasteh</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heidari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of antimony resistance markers in <italic>Leishmania tropica</italic> field isolates through a cDNA-AFLP approach</article-title>
          <source>Exp Parasitol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <fpage>344</fpage>
          <lpage>349</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23928349</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kazemi-Rad</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohebali</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khadem-Erfan</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajjaran</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hadighi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khamesipour</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rezaie</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saffari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raoofian</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heidari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Over expression of ubiquitin and amino acid permease genes in association with antimony resistance in <italic>Leishmania tropica</italic> field isolates</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Parasitol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>419</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24039283</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bagher Khadem Erfan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohebali</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kazemi-Rad</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajjaran</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edrissian</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mamishi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saffari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raoofian</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heidari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Down regulation of calcineurin gene is associated with Glucantime&#xAE; resistance in Leishmania infantum</article-title>
          <source>Iran J Parasitol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>359</fpage>
          <lpage>366</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24454427</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McGwire</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Satoskar</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Leishmaniasis: clinical syndromes and treatment</article-title>
          <source>QJM</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/qjmed/hct116">10.1093/qjmed/hct116</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23744570</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment of visceral leishmaniasis (kala-azar): a decade of progress and future approaches</article-title>
          <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>158</fpage>
          <lpage>177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11179920</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thakur</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A single high dose treatment of kala-azar with ambisome (amphotericin B lipid complex): a pilot study</article-title>
          <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>67</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11137652</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Griensven</surname>
              <given-names>JV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balasegaram</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meheus</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alvar</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lynen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boelaert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Combination therapy for visceral leishmaniasis</article-title>
          <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>184</fpage>
          <lpage>194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20185097</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tunccan</surname>
              <given-names>OG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tufan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Telli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aky&#xFC;rek</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pamuk&#xE7;uo&#x11F;lu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Y&#x131;lmaz</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>H&#x131;zel</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Visceral leishmaniasis mimicking autoimmune hepatitis, primary biliary cirrhosis, and systemic lupus erythematosus overlap</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Parasitol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>133</fpage>
          <lpage>136</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22711924</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nielsen-Saines</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Leishmaniasis</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Feigin</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cherry</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demmler-Harrison</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaplan</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Feigin and Cherry's Textbook of Pediatric Infectious Diseases</source>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, USA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>2920</fpage>
          <lpage>2930</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Bone marrow aspiration slide (Giemsa stain) showing <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic> bodies (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjp-52-189-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) patterns obtained from <italic>Leishmania</italic> stocks and patient's sample. Lane 1, negative control; Lane 2, <italic>L. tropica</italic>; Lanes 3, 4, <italic>L. major</italic>; Lane 5, <italic>L. infantum</italic>; Lane 6, PCR product from patient's sample, <italic>L. infantum</italic>. M, 100-bp size marker (Fermentas).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="kjp-52-189-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
