<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Otolaryngology - Head &amp; Neck Surgery</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1916-0208</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1916-0216</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26138824</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4495949</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">77</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40463-015-0077-3</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Nasal Chondromesenchymal Hamartoma (NCMH): a systematic review of the literature with a new case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4515-1780</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Mason</surname>
            <given-names>Katrina Anna</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>katrina.a.mason@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Navaratnam</surname>
            <given-names>Annakan</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>annakan.navaratnam@nhs.net</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Theodorakopoulou</surname>
            <given-names>Evgenia</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>e.theodorakopoulou@nhs.net</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chokkalingam</surname>
            <given-names>Perumal Gounder</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>chokks@btopenworld.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Barts and The London School of Medicine and Dentistry, The Blizard Institute of Cell and Molecular Science, 4 Newark Street, Whitechapel, E1 2AT London, UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Colchester Hospital University NHS Foundation Trust, Colchester, UK </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>44</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>28</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Mason et al. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma (NCMH) is a very rare, benign tumour of the sinonasal tract usually presenting in infants. We present a systematic review of NCMH cases alongside a case report of an adult with asymptomatic NCMH.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>A systematic review was conducted in accordance with PRISMA guidelines. A PubMed, EMBASE and manual search through references of relevant publications was used to identify all published case-reports of NCMH. Data was collected from each case-report on: patient demographics, laterality, size and location of NCMH, presentation, co-morbidities, investigations, treatment and follow-up.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The systematic review identified 48 patients (including ours): 33 male, 15 female. Mean age was 9.6&#xA0;years (range: 1&#xA0;day&#x2013;69&#xA0;years) with the majority aged 1&#xA0;year or younger at presentation (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;18). Presentations included: nasal congestion (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;17), nasal mass (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;15) and eye signs (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;12). NCMH also involved the paranasal sinuses (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;26), orbit (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;16) and skull-base (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;14). All patients underwent operative resection of NCMH. A small 2014 case-series found DICER1 mutations in 6 NCMH patients, establishing a link to the DICER1 tumour spectrum.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>NCMH is a rare cause of nasal masses in young children and adults. In light of the newly established link between NCMH and DICER1 mutations surgeons should be vigilant for associated DICER1 tumours, as NCMH may be the &#x2018;herald tumour&#x2019; of this disease spectrum.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Nasal neoplasms</kwd>
        <kwd>Hamartoma</kwd>
        <kwd>DICER1 protein human</kwd>
        <kwd>Review</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p><sc>N</sc>asal chondromesenchymal hamartoma (NCMH) is a very rare, benign tumour of the sinonasal tract. Forty-seven cases have been reported in the English literature and the vast majority of these presentations are in infants and young children often below the age of one. NCMHs have a mixed morphological structure comprised of predominantly mesenchymal and cartilaginous components. NCMH patients present with symptoms that are dependent on the location of the tumour in the nasal cavity or paranasal sinuses and their compression of local structures. These symptoms range from nasal obstruction to visual impairment and facial and dental pain. To date there have only been 6 cases of adult presentation of NCMH. Here we present the first systematic review of NCMH cases published in the literature to assess the patient demographics, presentation, management and prognosis of NCMH alongside a new and unusual case in an adult.</p>
      <sec id="Sec2">
        <title>Case report</title>
        <p>A 49-year-old man was referred to our outpatient clinic presenting with a small mass in his right nasal cavity. The lump, which the patient first noticed 5&#xA0;years ago, had been growing insidiously over time and by the time of presentation had become visible at the right anterior naris. The patient did not complain of any symptoms but sought consultation as his wife was concerned by the cosmetic appearance of the mass.</p>
        <p>Examination revealed a large firm mass arising from the right side of the anterior nasal septum with approximately 0.5&#xA0;cm attachment to the anterior cartilage of the septum. The left and right nasal cavities were otherwise unremarkable. Clinically, the mass had the appearance of a papilloma confined to the nasal cavity with an attachment to the septum only and therefore further imaging was not undertaken. The differential diagnoses considered at the time of presentation were: nasal polyp, squamous papilloma or inverted papilloma.</p>
        <p>The patient subsequently underwent excisional biopsy of the right nostril mass under general anaesthetic using a circumferential subperichondrial incision with a small margin. Intraoperatively, the mass had the macroscopic appearance of a 0.5&#xA0;cm&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2&#xA0;cm&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2&#xA0;cm calcified nodule. Due to a small 0.5&#xA0;cm base, subsequent healing was achieved by secondary intention aided by the routine application of topical antibacterial cream. Histopathological analysis showed the nodule to contain cartilage and aneurysmal bone covered in stratified squamous epithelium with keratinisation (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Histopathological diagnosis was made using a haematoxylin &amp; eosin stain. These findings were consistent with a diagnosis of a nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Nodule containing cartilage and aneurysmal bone and covered by stratified squamous epithelium with keratinisation (magnification &#xD7;25, haematoxylin &amp; eosin stain)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40463_2015_77_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Areas of osteoid formation (magnification &#xD7;200, haematoxylin &amp; eosin stain)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40463_2015_77_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
        <p>The patient was followed up in clinic and was discharged after 2&#xA0;years having shown no signs of recurrence. Furthermore, a telephone interview was conducted 4&#xA0;years post operation and the patient reported no recurrence of the nasal mass. He confirmed that he had no post-operative complications and was happy with the outcome of the operation.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p>A systematic review was undertaken in accordance with PRISMA guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. No systematic review protocol was used, however our systematic review methodology is described below and a four-phase flow diagram is represented in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. All published case-reports of NCMH were included in the review. A PubMed search (MEDLINE) (1975 to May Week 2, 2015) was carried out using the following terms [(chondromesenchymal hamartoma) AND (nasal OR sinus OR maxillary OR ethmoid OR sphenoid OR frontal OR orbit OR cranial)]. An EMBASE search (1975 to May Week 2, 2015) was carried out using a best sensitivity-combination strategy. The PubMed search resulted in 32 citations of which 24 were relevant, 6 were not NCMH case-reports, one was a Chinese language case-report, and one case was a duplicate case-report publication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. An EMBASE search and a manual search through references of relevant publications yielded 11 further relevant citations. Of these only 6 were included in the analysis; one case was found to have been a duplicate case report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] and four other possible cases of NCMH were found through publication citation search, but were labelled as &#x201C;Mesenchymal chondrosarcoma&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] &#x201C;nasal hamartoma&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], &#x201C;nasopharyngeal hamartoma&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], and &#x201C;congenital mesenchymoma&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and were therefore not included. Thirty-one publications that report 47 cases of NCMH were included in this systematic review. Data was collected on patient demographics (age, gender), laterality, size and site of NCMH, presentation, co-morbidities, investigations, treatment and follow-up. These were also the principle summary measures. Two authors performed the database search, the manual search through references of relevant publications, and extracted the relevant data from the case-reports. Data was entered into an Excel 2013&#xA0;Microsoft Office&#x2122; database which was used to carry out basic statistical analysis.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Four-phase flow diagram of systematic review in accordance with PRISMA guidelines * Two individual publications of single case-reports were excluded from analysis as these had previously been published, Schultz et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and Kang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].** See Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40463_2015_77_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Results of systematic review</title>
        <p>Forty-Eight NCMH patients (including our case) have been reported in the English literature (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Most cases presented in males; 33 male and 15 female, with a male to female ratio of 2.2:1 ratio. The mean age was 9.6&#xA0;years (range: 1&#xA0;day&#x2013;69&#xA0;years). A large proportion of these patients were aged 1&#xA0;year or younger at presentation (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;18) and only 8 adult patients (including our case) have been described. Site of pathology was limited to the nasal cavity only in 10 patients, and involved the paranasal sinuses (maxillary, ethmoid, sphenoid) in 26 patients, the orbit in 16 patients, extending to the skull base in 14 patients, had intracranial extension in 8 cases, involved the nasopharynx in 3 patients and the oropharynx in 2 patients (see Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary table of systematic review of NCMH cases reported in the literature</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Author, Publication date</th><th>Case No</th><th>Age D/M/Y</th><th>Sex</th><th>Side &amp; Size</th><th>Site</th><th>Symptoms</th><th>Co-morbidity</th><th>Investigations</th><th>Treatment</th><th>Follow Up/</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="16">(1) McDermot, 1998 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] USA</td><td rowspan="2">1</td><td rowspan="2">5 D</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Mass</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">CT</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at2 years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Respiratory Difficulties</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">2</td><td rowspan="3">3&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Mass</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence at 2&#xA0;years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid Sinus</td><td rowspan="2">2. Otitis Media</td></tr><tr><td>3. Intracranial extension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">3</td><td rowspan="2">3&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Choanal Mass</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">Biopsy then surgical excision Subsequent chemotherapy</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at 4&#xA0;years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Respiratory distress</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">4</td><td rowspan="2">2&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="2">1. Nasal Mass</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at 18&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Intracranial extension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">5</td><td rowspan="2">12 D</td><td rowspan="2">F</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="2">1. Nasal Mass</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">CT</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical excision &amp; further re-excision after 16&#xA0;months</td><td rowspan="2">Unchanged persistent tumour in superior nasal cavity at 12&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Intracranial extension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">6</td><td rowspan="3">14 D</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Mass</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">CT</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical excision VP shunt for hydrocephalus</td><td rowspan="3">Residual tumour in anterior cranial fossa at 9&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td><td rowspan="2">2. Hydrocephalus &amp; agenesis of corpus callosum</td></tr><tr><td>3. Intracranial extension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">7</td><td rowspan="2">7 Y</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Mass</td><td rowspan="2">PPB</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at 2&#xA0;months NB later reported by Priest et al. 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]- showed with multiple recurrences in first 3&#xA0;years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Sphenoid sinus</td><td>2. Nasal Congestion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(2) Chae 1999 Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] *abstract only, Korean paper</td><td rowspan="3">8</td><td rowspan="3">3&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">Right Size: 3.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;7.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.5&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Epistaxis</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">CT</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td><td rowspan="2">2. Obstruction</td></tr><tr><td>3. Cribriform plate</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(3) Kim D 1999 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] USA</td><td rowspan="3">9</td><td rowspan="3">3&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">Right Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal mass</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical excision with mid-facial de-gloving and bi-frontal craniotomy</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence at 18&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Intracranial extension</td><td rowspan="2">2. Otitis media</td></tr><tr><td>3. Ethmoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(4) Kato, 1999 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] Japan</td><td rowspan="3">10</td><td rowspan="3">4&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">Left Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Mass</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">CT</td><td rowspan="2">Two stage surgical excision 1st intracranial/sinus lesion, 2nd intranasal lesion</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence at 13&#xA0;years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Intracranial extension</td><td>2. Respiratory distress with cyanosis when feeding</td></tr><tr><td>3. Extension to left orbit</td><td>3. Opthalmoplegia left eye</td><td>Radiotherapy post op</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">(5) Hsueh 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] Taiwan (2 cases)</td><td rowspan="5">11</td><td rowspan="5">0 D</td><td rowspan="5">M</td><td rowspan="5">Left Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Left facial swelling</td><td rowspan="5">None stated</td><td rowspan="5">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="5">Excision biopsy then subsequent surgical excision with lateral rhinotomy and craniofacial approach</td><td rowspan="5">Recurrence after excision biopsy No recurrence at 5&#xA0;years after second surgery</td></tr><tr><td>1. Sphenoid sinus</td><td>2. Left nasal mass</td></tr><tr><td>3. Ethmoid sinus</td><td rowspan="2">3. Respiratory distress &amp; cyanosis when feeding</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">4. Compression of left orbit</td></tr><tr><td>4. Proptosis on recurrence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">12</td><td rowspan="2">9&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">Right ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Asymmetric face</td><td rowspan="2">None stated</td><td rowspan="2">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at 9&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Maxillary sinus</td><td>2. Right opthalmoplegia, enopthalmos and hypotropia</td></tr><tr><td>(6) Alrawi 2003 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] Ireland</td><td>13</td><td>16 Y</td><td>M</td><td>Left 1.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;1.5&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal swelling</td><td>None stated</td><td>CT MRI</td><td>Surgical resection with delayed reconstruction with forehead flap</td><td>No recurrence at 8&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">(7) Shet, 2004 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] India</td><td rowspan="4">14</td><td rowspan="4">1 Y</td><td rowspan="4">M</td><td rowspan="4">Left Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Proptosis of left eye</td><td rowspan="4">Non stated</td><td rowspan="4">CT</td><td rowspan="4">Chemotherapy (VID) as biopsy suggested spindle cell sarcoma- 30&#xA0;% reduction in tumour size Then Left maxillectomy and surgical excision</td><td rowspan="4">Residual tumour at 1.5&#xA0;years near eye but no further re-growth &amp; stable</td></tr><tr><td>2. Extension into left orbit</td><td rowspan="3">2. Left facial swelling</td></tr><tr><td>3. Ethmoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td>4. Sphenoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">(8) Kim B, 2004 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] Korea</td><td rowspan="4">15</td><td rowspan="4">5&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="4">M</td><td rowspan="4">Left Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="4">1. Left eye ptosis</td><td rowspan="4">None stated</td><td rowspan="4">CT</td><td rowspan="4">Frontal craniotomy &amp; trans-nasal surgical resection</td><td rowspan="4">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Compression of left orbit</td></tr><tr><td>3. Defect left ethmoidal bone</td></tr><tr><td>4. Defects anterior cranial fossa</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">(9) Norman, 2004 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] USA</td><td rowspan="2">16</td><td rowspan="2">11 Y</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">Left Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="2">1. Headaches left sided</td><td rowspan="2">None stated</td><td rowspan="2">CT</td><td rowspan="2">Endoscopic biopsy and anterior craniofacial resection</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Displacement left orbital wall</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(10) Ozolek, 2005 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] USA (4 cases)</td><td rowspan="3">17</td><td rowspan="3">11 Y</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">Left Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="3">1. Nasal mass</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">Surgery and care undertaken in another hospital</td><td rowspan="3">ND Surgery and care undertaken in another hospital</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td>3. Extension into left orbit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8"/><td rowspan="2">18</td><td rowspan="2">17 Y</td><td rowspan="2">F</td><td rowspan="2">ND Size: ND</td><td rowspan="2">1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal obstruction</td><td rowspan="2">None stated</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Facial pain</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">19</td><td rowspan="4">25 Y</td><td rowspan="4">M</td><td rowspan="4">Bilateral 8&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;3.5&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="3">1. Respiratory distress from obstructing oropharyngeal tumour requiring emergency tracheostomy</td><td rowspan="4">1. Multiple Intracranial vascular aneurysms 2. Longstanding nasopharyngeal tumour- biopsy aged 13 &#x2018;chronic inflamed polyp&#x2019;</td><td rowspan="4">CT</td><td rowspan="4">Multiple surgical resections within one year including, tracheostomy and initial surgical resection, further surgical resection of bulbar mass and nasal tumour, then Le-Fort osteotomy and further surgical resection</td><td rowspan="4">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Maxillary sinus</td></tr><tr><td>3. Nasopharynx</td></tr><tr><td>2. Oropharynx</td><td>2. Chronic sinusitis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">20</td><td rowspan="2">69 Y</td><td rowspan="2">F</td><td rowspan="2">Right Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">None stated</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">(11) Low 2006 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] UK</td><td rowspan="2">21</td><td rowspan="2">11 Y</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">Right Size: ND</td><td rowspan="2">1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Obstruction</td><td rowspan="2">None stated</td><td rowspan="2">CT</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at 2&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Epistaxis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(12) Johnson, 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] USA</td><td rowspan="3">22</td><td rowspan="3">15 Y</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">Bilateral Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal obstruction</td><td>1. PPB</td><td rowspan="3">CT</td><td rowspan="3">Endoscopic surgical excision</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence at 6&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">2. Nasopharynx</td><td rowspan="2">2. Chronic sinusitis</td><td>2. Sertoli-Leydig cell Ovarian Tumour</td></tr><tr><td>3. Congenital phthisi bulbi</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(13) Silkiss, 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] USA</td><td rowspan="3">23</td><td rowspan="3">7&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">Right 3.2&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;1.4&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Ptosis</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical resection- right lateral rhinotomy</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence at 18&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Erosion of cribriform plate</td><td>2. Extropia</td></tr><tr><td>3. Compression of right orbit</td><td>3. Strabismus 4. Stertor</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">(14) Nakagawa 2008 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] Japan</td><td rowspan="4">24</td><td rowspan="4">12 Y</td><td rowspan="4">M</td><td rowspan="4">Left 1.5&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="4">1. Nasal obstruction</td><td rowspan="4">None stated</td><td rowspan="4">CT</td><td rowspan="4">Endoscopic surgical resection and further endoscopic surgical resection after recurrence</td><td rowspan="4">Recurrence at 2&#xA0;months No recurrence at 5&#xA0;months post second surgery</td></tr><tr><td>2. Sphenoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td>3. Ethmoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td>4. Maxillary sinus</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">(15) Finitsis, 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] Greece</td><td rowspan="4">25</td><td rowspan="4">12&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="4">M</td><td rowspan="4">Left 4&#xA0;cm&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;4.2&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="4">1. Respiratory distress</td><td rowspan="4">None stated</td><td rowspan="4">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="4">Pre-operative embolization Then Surgical resection with midface de-gloving</td><td rowspan="4">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Compression of left orbit</td></tr><tr><td>3. Maxillary sinus compression</td></tr><tr><td>4. Nasopharynx</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(16) Kim J, 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] Korea</td><td rowspan="3">26</td><td rowspan="3">19&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">Left 2.7&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;3.5&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Watery rhinorrhoea</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Endoscopic surgical resection &#xD7;2</td><td rowspan="3">Recurrence at one year; 2nd surgery. No recurrence 10&#xA0;months after second surgery</td></tr><tr><td>2. Orbital extension</td><td rowspan="2">2. Nasal Obstruction</td></tr><tr><td>3. Intracranial extension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9">(17) Priest, 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] USA *case previously reported by McDermot et al. 1998 **case previously reported by Johnson et al. 2007 (2 new cases)</td><td rowspan="2">-</td><td rowspan="2">7 Y *</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">Initially unilateral, then bilateral</td><td>1. Sphenoid sinus</td><td>1. Nasal Congestion</td><td>1. PPB type II&#x2013;III</td><td rowspan="2"/><td rowspan="2">Four resections over 3&#xA0;years</td><td rowspan="2">Followed up for 13&#xA0;years with multiple recurrences in first 3&#xA0;years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Left Nasal cavity</td><td>2. Nasal mass</td><td>2. Lung cysts</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">-</td><td rowspan="4">15 Y **</td><td rowspan="4">F</td><td rowspan="4">Bilateral</td><td>1. Bilateral nasal cavities</td><td>1. Chronic Sinusitis</td><td>1. PPB Type II</td><td rowspan="4"/><td rowspan="4">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="4">No recurrence at 51&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Bony erosion of posterior septum</td><td>2. Facial Pain</td><td>2. Sertoli-Leydig Cell Ovarian Tumour</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">2. Extending into nasopharynx</td><td>3. Nasal Congestion</td><td rowspan="2">3. Congenital phthisi bulbi Stickler syndrome</td></tr><tr><td>4. Nasal obstruction</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>10 Y</td><td>F</td><td>Bilateral Size: ND</td><td>1. Bilateral nasal cavities</td><td>1. Nasal obstruction</td><td>1. PPB Type III</td><td>CT</td><td>Surgical resection</td><td>No recurrence at 21&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">28</td><td rowspan="2">11 Y</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">Right Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="2">1. Nasal obstruction</td><td rowspan="2">1. PPB Type III</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at 4&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Extension to anterior skull base</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(18) Sarin, 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] India</td><td rowspan="3">29</td><td rowspan="3">2.5 Y</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">Right Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="3">1. Right eye oculomotor impairment</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Biopsy and then lateral rhinotomy for excision</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Maxillary, ethmoid and sphenoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td>3. Erosion of middle wall of orbit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">(19) Eloy 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] Belgium</td><td rowspan="4">30</td><td rowspan="4">18&#xA0;M*</td><td rowspan="4">M</td><td rowspan="4">Right 0.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;0.4&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal obstruction</td><td rowspan="4">None stated</td><td rowspan="4">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="4">Endoscopic surgical resection</td><td rowspan="4">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td><td>2. Nasal mass</td></tr><tr><td>3. Extension into right orbit</td><td>3. Hypertelorism, proptosis, diplopia</td></tr><tr><td>4. Intracranial extension</td><td>4. Nasal swelling *symptoms 1st noticed at 2&#xA0;months- delayed referral from Algeria to Brussels</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(20) Jeyakumar 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] USA</td><td rowspan="3">31</td><td rowspan="3">7 D</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">Right Size: ND</td><td rowspan="3">1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Mass</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Endoscopic surgical excision</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Stertor</td></tr><tr><td>3. Proptosis right eye</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">(21) Mattos 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] USA</td><td rowspan="5">32</td><td rowspan="5">3 Y</td><td rowspan="5">M</td><td rowspan="5">Left Size : ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Eye infections</td><td rowspan="5">None stated</td><td rowspan="5">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="5">Endoscopic excision the further surgical excision</td><td rowspan="5">Recurrence at 21&#xA0;months required further resection</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td><td>2. Eye congestion</td></tr><tr><td>3. Extension into right orbit</td><td>3. Nasal obstruction</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">4. Left maxilla</td><td>4. Cheek fullness</td></tr><tr><td>5. Intermitted left eye/face pain</td></tr><tr><td>(22) Behery, 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] USA</td><td>33</td><td>11 Y</td><td>M</td><td>ND</td><td>ND</td><td>Nasal Obstruction</td><td>1. PPB</td><td/><td>Surgical resection</td><td>ND</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">(23) Uzomefuna, 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] Ireland</td><td rowspan="2">34</td><td rowspan="2">8 Y</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td>1. Sphenoid sinus</td><td rowspan="2">1. Frontal Headache</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="2">Endoscopic surgical resection</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at 6&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">(24) Cho, 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] Korea</td><td rowspan="4">35</td><td rowspan="4">14 Y</td><td rowspan="4">M</td><td rowspan="4">Left 5&#xA0;cm&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;5.3&#xA0;cm&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;4&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Swelling and pain to left face</td><td rowspan="4">None stated</td><td rowspan="4">CT</td><td rowspan="4">Subtotal maxillectomy, removal or orbital floor, removal of medial nasal mucous membrane. Reconstruction with iliac crest bone block</td><td rowspan="4">No recurrence at 4&#xA0;years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Maxillary sinus</td><td rowspan="3">2. Tooth mobility</td></tr><tr><td>3. Intraoral</td></tr><tr><td>4. Orbital floor destruction</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(25) Li Y, 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] China</td><td rowspan="3">36</td><td rowspan="3">40 Y</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">Bilateral Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal Cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Obstruction</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Complete radical resection</td><td rowspan="3">Recurrence at 3&#xA0;months *Malignant transformation seen on histology</td></tr><tr><td>2. Maxillary sinus</td><td rowspan="2">2. Bloody rhinorrhoea</td></tr><tr><td>3. Ethmoid sinus</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(26) Li GY 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] China</td><td rowspan="3">37</td><td rowspan="3">23 Y</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">Left 3.2&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2.5&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Naval cavity</td><td>1. Left Lacrimal Sac</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">Endoscopic surgical excision</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence at 3&#xA0;months follow up</td></tr><tr><td>2. Extension to lacrimal sac &amp; left orbit</td><td>2. Proptosis</td></tr><tr><td>3. Ethmoid sinus</td><td>3. Lateral displacement of globe</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">(27) Moon, 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] Korea</td><td rowspan="4">38</td><td rowspan="4">9&#xA0;M</td><td rowspan="4">F</td><td rowspan="4">Right Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td rowspan="4">1. Incomitant esotropia of right eye (inability to abduct right eye) No nasal symptoms</td><td rowspan="4">None stated</td><td rowspan="4">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="4">Surgery and care undertaken in another hospital</td><td rowspan="4">ND Surgery and care undertaken in another hospital</td></tr><tr><td>2. Maxillary sinus</td></tr><tr><td>3. Erosion of orbital wall</td></tr><tr><td>4. Erosion of cribriform plate</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">(28) Wang T, 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] China (2 cases)</td><td rowspan="3">39</td><td rowspan="3">5 Y</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">Right 2.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;3.6&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;4.3&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Recurrent sinusitis</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence at 3&#xA0;years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td><td rowspan="2">2. Nasal Obstruction</td></tr><tr><td>3. Intracranial extension</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">40</td><td rowspan="2">6&#xA0;W</td><td rowspan="2">F</td><td rowspan="2">Left 2.6&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;3.4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;3.9&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal obstruction</td><td rowspan="2">None stated</td><td rowspan="2">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="2">No recurrence at 10&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Pressure remodelling of adjacent bones</td><td>2. Watery rhinorrhoea</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">(29) Obidan, 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] Saudi Arabia</td><td rowspan="2">41</td><td rowspan="2">14 Y Size: ND</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">Bilateral</td><td rowspan="2">1. Bilateral nasal cavities</td><td>1. Nasal Obstruction</td><td rowspan="2">1. PPB</td><td rowspan="2">CT</td><td rowspan="2">Surgical endoscopic resection</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td></tr><tr><td>2. Decreased sense of smell</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="20">(30) Stewart, 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] USA **4 patients previously reported by Priest et al. 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] (4 new cases)</td><td rowspan="2">-</td><td rowspan="2">7 Y**</td><td rowspan="2">M</td><td rowspan="2">Initially unilateral, then bilateral</td><td rowspan="2">ND</td><td rowspan="2">1. Nasal Congestion</td><td>1. PPB</td><td rowspan="2"/><td rowspan="2">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="2">Multiple recurrences</td></tr><tr><td>2. Lung cysts</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">-</td><td rowspan="3">15 Y**</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">Bilateral</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td>1. Chronic Sinusitis</td><td>1. PPB</td><td rowspan="3"/><td rowspan="3">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence</td></tr><tr><td>2. Facial Pain</td><td rowspan="2">2. Sertoli-Leydig Cell Ovarian Tumour</td></tr><tr><td>3. Nasal Congestion</td></tr><tr><td>-</td><td>10 Y**</td><td>F</td><td>Bilateral</td><td>ND</td><td>1. Nasal congestion</td><td>1. PPB</td><td/><td>Surgical resection</td><td>No recurrence</td></tr><tr><td>-</td><td>11 Y**</td><td>M</td><td>Right</td><td>ND</td><td>1. Nasal Congestion</td><td>1. PPB</td><td/><td>Surgical resection</td><td>No recurrence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">42</td><td rowspan="3">8 Y</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">ND Size: ND</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">1. ND</td><td>1. PPB</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence</td></tr><tr><td>2. Pulmonary cysts in utero</td></tr><tr><td>3. Jejunal Polyps</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">43</td><td rowspan="3">13 Y</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">Bilateral Size: ND</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">1. ND</td><td>1. PPB</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence</td></tr><tr><td>2. Thyroid Papillary carcinoma</td></tr><tr><td>3. Sertoli-Leydig tumour</td></tr><tr><td>44</td><td>8 Y</td><td>M</td><td>Bilateral Size: ND</td><td>ND</td><td>1. Chronic Sinusitis</td><td>1. PPB</td><td>ND</td><td>Surgical resection</td><td>No recurrence</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">45</td><td rowspan="3">6 Y</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">ND Size: ND</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td>1. PPB</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence</td></tr><tr><td>2. Left cystic nephroma</td></tr><tr><td>3. Small bowel loop</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">46</td><td rowspan="3">21 Y</td><td rowspan="3">F</td><td rowspan="3">Right Size: ND</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td>1. Nasal Congestion</td><td>1. PPB</td><td rowspan="3">ND</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical resection</td><td rowspan="3">Recurrence at 4&#xA0;years</td></tr><tr><td>2. Septal deviation</td><td>2. Sertoli-Leydig Tumour</td></tr><tr><td>3. Nasal Obstruction (at recurrence)</td><td>3. Multi-nodular goitre</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">(31) Chandra 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] India</td><td rowspan="3">47</td><td rowspan="3">12 Y</td><td rowspan="3">M</td><td rowspan="3">Right Size: ND</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal Obstruction</td><td rowspan="3">None stated</td><td rowspan="3">CT MRI</td><td rowspan="3">Surgical excision</td><td rowspan="3">No recurrence at 5&#xA0;months</td></tr><tr><td>2. Ethmoid sinus</td><td>2. Proptosis</td></tr><tr><td>3. Extension into right orbit</td><td>3. Right facial pain</td></tr><tr><td>(32) Mason 2015 UK</td><td>48</td><td>49 Y</td><td>M</td><td>Right 0.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;2&#xA0;cm</td><td>1. Nasal cavity</td><td>1. Nasal mass</td><td>None stated</td><td>None</td><td>Surgical excision</td><td>No recurrence at 4&#xA0;years</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>Y</italic> Years, <italic>M</italic> Months, <italic>D</italic> Days, <italic>M</italic> Male, <italic>F</italic> Female, <italic>ND</italic> not documented, <italic>PPB</italic> Pleuropulmonary blastoma, <italic>CT</italic> Computed Tomography, <italic>MRI</italic> Magnetic Resonance Imaging</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Clinical presentations of NCMH patients included: nasal congestion or obstruction (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;17), nasal mass (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;15), eye signs (proptosis, hypotropia, enopthalmos, strabismus, exotropia etc.) (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;12), facial swelling (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;8), headaches or facial pain (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;6), stertor or respiratory distress (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;8), ophthalmoplegia (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4), recurrent sinusitis (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4), rhinorrhoea (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;3), otitis media (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;2), epistaxis (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;2), toothache (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1), hyposmia (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1), hydrocephalus (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1) and 4 patients were asymptomatic or had no signs and symptoms documented (see Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
        <p>All patients underwent operative resection of NCMH and the surgical approach was dependent on disease location. One patient had pre-operative chemotherapy due to initial misdiagnosis on biopsy as spindle cell sarcoma. One patient had pre-operative embolization to reduce operative blood loss. Follow up times were included for 24 patients, mean time for follow-up was 24&#xA0;months, (range 2&#x2013;156&#xA0;months). Eleven patients were found to have persistent disease or disease recurrence on follow up, seven required further surgery, three patients were described as stable, and no further information was given on the other patient. Li et al. described the first and only reported case of malignant transformation of NCMH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
        <p>Thirty-six patients had no documented past medical problems. One adult patient had a history of multiple vascular aneurysms. Eleven of the patients had been diagnosed with pleuropulmonary blastoma (PPB) prior to NCMH detection. Of these 11 patients, 5 had other co-morbidities including three with Sertoli-Lleydig cell ovarian tumours, two with pulmonary cysts, one jejunal polyps, one papillary thyroid carcinoma, one cystic nephroma and one multinodular goitre.</p>
        <p>A potential weakness of this systematic review is the possibility of reporting bias through publication bias both within individual case reports and across the review. This reporting bias is three-fold: firstly in the incomplete publication of all the clinical aspects of the case-reports by the original authors, for example not reporting follow-up times or co-morbidities etc. Secondly it is possible that there have been cases of NCMH that have not been reported in the literature and can therefore not be included in the systematic review. Thirdly the exclusion of case-reports of &#x201C;Mesenchymal chondrosarcoma&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] &#x201C;nasal hamartoma&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], &#x201C;nasopharyngeal hamartoma&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], and &#x201C;congenital mesenchymoma&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] alongside others, which are published prior to the first description of NCMH by McDermot et al. in 1998, may have resulted in an underreporting of true NCMH cases. However without being able to retrospectively assess and re-classify the histology of these cases we feel it is appropriate to have excluded them from our analysis and conclusions. These sources of reporting biases could potentially reduce the validity of conclusions drawn in terms of not fully representing or capturing all possible cases of NCMH.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>NCMHs are predominantly benign lesions that are locally destructive and because of their aggressive appearance can be mistaken for a malignant tumour. However NCMHs can be slow growing and therefore have a delayed presentation. Histopathologically these lesions are analogous to other mesenchymal hamartomas, and consist of islands of chondroid tissue such as hyaline cartilage, areas of calcification, and mesenchymal cellular elements such as spindle cells and myxoid stroma.</p>
      <p>McDermott et al. were the first to recognise NCMH as a distinct clinic-pathological entity in 1998 when they described a case series of seven patients with a tumefactive process of the nasal passages and contiguous paranasal sinuses with a detectable mass in the nose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In this case series, six of the seven patients were infants under the age of 3&#xA0;months. As our systematic review demonstrates NCMH predominantly presents in young children and infants under the age of one, but there have now been seven case reports, including ours, of adults with NCMH up to the age of 69 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In 2013 the first and only reported case of malignant transformation of an NCMH was described in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>In our case, the NCMH was initially thought to be a papilloma confined to the nasal septal wall and therefore further imaging was not undertaken prior to resection. However pre-operative imaging of these lesions provides valuable information regarding involvement of adjacent structures such as the paranasal sinuses, orbit and intracranial cavity. On computed tomography (CT) imaging, NCMH are typically seen as non-encapsulated, poorly defined masses often with cystic components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of NCMH demonstrates a heterogeneous mass on T1 weighted images and T2 weighted images show the presence of cystic components. MRI also has the advantage of superior tissue characterisation and delineation of invasion of adjacent structures in comparison to CT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Due to rarity of NCMH, even after thorough clinical and radiographic examination NCMH can be misdiagnosed, and differential diagnoses include: inverted papilloma, aneurysmal bone cysts or ossifying fibromas, nasoethmoidal encephalocoele, chondrosarcoma, nasal lymphoma, nasal glioma and rhabdomyosarcoma. Histopathological analysis following surgical resection is therefore needed for accurate diagnosis.</p>
      <p>Patients with NCMH most commonly present with symptoms of nasal obstruction, nasal mass, or eye signs, which reflects the involvement of NCMH in the nasal passages and orbit. Ophthalmic signs include signs of globe displacement such as strabismus, extropia, hypertelorism, proptosis, enophthalmus and ophthlmoplegia, direct results of the intra-ocular extension of NCMH or ocular compression by NCMH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. There has also been a report of a patient presenting with intra-oral symptoms due to involvement of the oral cavity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Patients can therefore present to otolaryngology, ophthalmology or maxillo-facial departments and doctors in these specialties should be aware of this rare pathology. In our case, the patient did not complain of any cranial, ophthalmic or nasal symptoms but was aware of a slowly enlarging nasal mass. This is most likely due to the relatively small size of the tumour at the anterior nasal septum which did not obstruct the nasal passage.</p>
      <p>The aetiology of NCMH is thought to be due to an underlying genetic predisposition therefore accounting for the early presentation in the majority of cases. Priest et al. and Stewart et al. investigated patients with both NCMH and the rare paediatric dysembryonic sarcoma of the lung and pleura: pleuropulmonary blastoma (PPB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In patients with NCMH and PPB Stewart et al. found germline <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations in 6 out of 8 evaluated patients, and somatic <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations in 2 out of those 6 patients with germline mutations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This recent finding has established genetic proof of NCMH tumour association with <italic>DICER1</italic> mutations and Stewart et al. therefore feel that NCMH should be considered part of the <italic>DICER1</italic> tumour spectrum. The <italic>DICER1</italic> familial tumour susceptibility syndrome confers an increased risk most commonly for pleuropulmonary blastoma (PPB) but also ovarian sex cord-stromal tumours; Sertoli-Leydig cell tumor [SLCT], juvenile granulosa cell tumour [JGCT] and gynandroblastomas. Less commonly the <italic>DICER1</italic> tumour spectrum includes: cystic nephroma (CN), and thyroid gland neoplasia, multinodular goitres [MNG], adenomas, or differentiated thyroid cancers. The rarest observed tumours in this spectrum, alongside NCMHs, are ciliary body medulloepithelioma (CBME), botryoid-type embryonal rhabdomyosarcoma (ERMS) of the cervix or other sites, renal sarcomas, pituitary blastomas, and pineoblastomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Eleven patients in our systematic review had previous PPB and five of these also had other <italic>DIECR1</italic> tumours. Surgeons and physicians should therefore be aware of these disease associations and should be vigilant of a diagnosis of NCMH in patients presenting with sino-nasal or orbital symptoms who have a history of any of these tumours. Johnson et al. importantly also point out that due to its location, NCMH is more likely to present early in life than the other <italic>DICER1</italic> tumours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Surgeons and physicians should therefore either offer <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation analysis if available, or ensure long-term follow up of these patients and be vigilant for associated tumours, as NCMH may be the &#x2018;herald tumour&#x2019; of this disease spectrum.</p>
      <p>There are also cases in the literature of children, adolescents and adults with NCMH who have had an asymptomatic infancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. This may imply that there are non-genetic components to NCMH pathogenesis. Alternatively it may simply reflect the insidious growth of the tumour or that some NCMH patients may only exhibit the phenotype later in life. However as this is an extremely rare pathology with only very recent formal association with the <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation, the majority of the 42 reported cases have not had formal <italic>DICER1</italic> mutation analysis. Therefore an association or lack thereof in the non-tested cases cannot be inferred.</p>
      <p>Successful management of NCMH entails complete resection in order to prevent recurrence. A complete excision however is not always technically feasible, especially in cases of intracranial extension of NCMH. An incomplete resection poses the risk of recurrence as well as the possibility of continued tumour growth and progressive symptoms. Nine patients in this systematic review were found to have disease recurrence, most likely from incomplete surgical excision.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6" sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We present an unusual case of NCMH in an adult without nasal obstructive symptoms due to the anatomical location of the NCMH attached to the nasal septum. A systematic review of the literature has highlighted that presentation is mostly related to tumour location, with nasal mass, nasal obstruction and ophthalmic signs being the most common forms of presentation. The majority of patients presenting with NCMH are children and infants below the age of one, but there have now been a few adult cases of presentation. Surgical resection is the treatment of choice with low recurrence rates in the majority of cases. There has only been one reported case of malignant transformation and NCMH is still considered a benign tumour. NCMH&#x2019;s association with the <italic>DIECR1</italic> mutation has very recently been established and therefore in light of this any patient with a <italic>DICER1</italic>-related tumour spectrum and new nasal or orbital symptoms should raise the suspicion of NCMH. Furthermore surgeons should subsequently be vigilant for associated <italic>DICER1</italic> related tumours, as due to their location NCMHs may be the &#x2018;herald tumour&#x2019; for this disease spectrum. This case and systematic review highlights the fact that NCMH can mimic other benign and malignant lesions and that surgeons and physicians should be aware of rare pathologies accounting for nasal masses.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the editor-in-chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>NCMH</term>
          <def>
            <p>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>EMBASE</term>
          <def>
            <p>Excerpta medica database</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CT</term>
          <def>
            <p>Computed tomography</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MRI</term>
          <def>
            <p>Magnetic resonance imaging</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PPB</term>
          <def>
            <p>Pleuropulmonary blastoma</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SLCT</term>
          <def>
            <p>Sertoli-leydig cell tumour</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>JGCT</term>
          <def>
            <p>Juvenile granulosa cell tumour</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CN</term>
          <def>
            <p>Cystic nephroma</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MNG</term>
          <def>
            <p>Multinodular goitres</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CBME</term>
          <def>
            <p>Ciliary body medulloepithelioma</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ERMS</term>
          <def>
            <p>Embryonal rhabdomyosarcoma</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>DICER1</term>
          <def>
            <p>is not an abbreviation, but the name of gene located on chromosome 14 at position q32.13</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>Contribution to conception and design: KM, AN, PC. Contribution to acquisition of data, analysis and interpretation: KM, AN, ET. Involved in drafting the manuscript &amp; revising it critically: KM, AN, ET, PC. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; information</bold>
        </p>
        <p>KM is a clinical teaching fellow with Barts and The London School of Medicine and Dentistry. ET is a clinical teaching fellow with Barts and The London School of Medicine and Dentistry AN is a junior registrar in ENT surgery in the London Deanery. PC is a locum consultant at a regional teaching hospital where the case was encountered.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>Thanks to Dr Ian Seddon (Consultant Histopathologist, Colchester Hospital University NHS Foundation Trust) for providing the histopathology images.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moher</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liberati</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tetzlaff</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Altman</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Group</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1006</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2009.06.005</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19631508</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schultz</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doros</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stewart</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>pleuropulmonary blastoma familial tumor predisposition syndrome: a unique constellation of neoplastic conditions</article-title>
          <source>Pathology Case Rev</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>90</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PCR.0000000000000027</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kang Jun</surname>
              <given-names>HYO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahn Gueng</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim Young</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cha Hee</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>H-J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal Chondromesenchymal Hamartoma a case report</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Pathol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>258</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sung</surname>
              <given-names>IY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Son</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ord</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma: report of a case presenting with intraoral signs</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>72</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joms.2012.03.020</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22695010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roland</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khine</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Velzen</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A rare congenital intranasal polyp: mesenchymal chondrosarcoma of the nasal region</article-title>
          <source>J Laryngol Otol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1081</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022215100121814</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1487666</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Terris</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Billman</surname>
              <given-names>GF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pransky</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal hamartoma: case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0165-5876(93)90150-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8300318</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zarbo</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McClatchey</surname>
              <given-names>KD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasopharyngeal hamartoma: report of a case and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Laryngoscope</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>494</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6834978</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ludemann</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tewfik</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meagher-Villemure</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bernard</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Congenital mesenchymoma transgressing the cribriform plate</article-title>
          <source>J Otolaryngol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>270</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9263898</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>QX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tian</surname>
              <given-names>XT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant transformation of nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in adult: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Histol Histopathol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>337</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23348387</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McDermott</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ponder</surname>
              <given-names>TB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dehner</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma: an upper respiratory tract analogue of the chest wall mesenchymal hamartoma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>425</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000478-199804000-00006</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9537469</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ozolek</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carrau</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunt</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in older children and adults: series and immunohistochemical analysis</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>129</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>1444</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16253025</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>GY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiao</surname>
              <given-names>YY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endonasal endoscopy for removing nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma extending from the lacrimal sac region</article-title>
          <source>Can J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>e22</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcjo.2012.10.007</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23561613</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stewart</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Messinger</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Field</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schultz</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartomas arise secondary to germline and somatic mutations of DICER1 in the pleuropulmonary blastoma tumor predisposition disorder</article-title>
          <source>Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>1443</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00439-014-1474-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25118636</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alrawi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McDermott</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orr</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russell</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesynchymal hamartoma presenting in an adolescent</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>669</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-5876(03)00067-3</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12745162</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Norman</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bergman</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trupiano</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma: report of a case and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dev Pathol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>517</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10024-004-1003-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15547776</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yao-Lee</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajaram</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma: correlation of typical MR, CT and pathological findings</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Radiol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>675</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00247-011-2034-2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21400084</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kato</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ijiri</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hara</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sekido</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma of infancy: the first Japanese case report</article-title>
          <source>Pathol Int</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>731</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1827.1999.00933.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10504541</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silkiss</surname>
              <given-names>RZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mudvari</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shetlar</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ophthalmologic presentation of nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in an infant</article-title>
          <source>Ophthal Plast Reconstr Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>243</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/IOP.0b013e31803eaa0d</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17519672</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moon</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma with incomitant esotropia in an infant: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Can J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>e30</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcjo.2013.11.011</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24513379</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mattos</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Early</surname>
              <given-names>SV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma: a case report and literature review</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatric Otorhinolaryngology Extra</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>215</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedex.2010.09.005</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shet</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borges</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nair</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desai</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mistry</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Two unusual lesions in the nasal cavity of infants&#x2013;a nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma and an aneurysmal bone cyst like lesion. More closely related than we think?</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>359</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2003.10.014</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15129948</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Min</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rhee</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma of infancy clinically mimicking meningoencephalocele</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>136</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000079857</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367805</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ko</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma: CT and MR imaging findings</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Radiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>416</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3348/kjr.2009.10.4.416</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19568473</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sarin</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prasher</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A silent nasal mass with ophthalmic presentation</article-title>
          <source>Orbit</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/01676830.2010.522296</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21158582</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eloy</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trigaux</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nassogne</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weynand</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rombaux</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma: case report</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatric Otorhinolaryngology Extra</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>300</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedex.2011.02.002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jeyakumar</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McEvoy</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fettman</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neonatal nasal mass: Chondromesenchymal hamartoma</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatric Otorhinolaryngology Extra</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>223</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedex.2010.10.001</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Priest</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mize</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dehner</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McDermott</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in children with pleuropulmonary blastoma&#x2013;A report from the International Pleuropulmonary Blastoma Registry registry</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>1240</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2010.07.022</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20822816</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Doros L, Schultz KA, Stewart DR, Bauer AJ, Williams G, Rossi CT, et al. DICER1-Related Disorders. In: Pagon RA, Adam MP, Ardinger HH, Bird TD, Dolan CR, Fong CT, et al., editors. GeneReviews(R) Seattle (WA). 1993.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagaraj</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Esguerra</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wasdahl</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wurzbach</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma: radiographic and histopathologic analysis of a rare pediatric tumor</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Radiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00247-006-0352-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17091268</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chae HJ</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal Chondromesenchymal Hamartoma</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Pathol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>225</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Low</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Billman</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wickersham</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kearns</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chondroid hamartoma presenting as a neonatal nasal mass</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>253</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-5876(98)00121-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10321780</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hsueh</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsueh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez-Crussi</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in children: report of 2 cases with review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>400</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11231491</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Low</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sethi</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davies</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stafford</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in an adolescent</article-title>
          <source>Histopathology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>321</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2559.2006.02431.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16918986</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakagawa</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakamoto</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in an adolescent</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatric Otorhinolaryngology Extra</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedex.2008.09.002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Finitsis</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giavroglou</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Potsi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Constantinidis</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mpaltatzidis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rachovitsas</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in a child</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>593</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00270-008-9458-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18972159</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Behery</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bedrnicek</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazenby</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grove</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Translocation t(12;17) (q24.1;q21) as the sole anomaly in a nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma arising in a patient with pleuropulmonary blastoma</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dev Pathol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>249</fpage>
          <lpage>53</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2350/11-11-1121-CR.1</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22356457</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Uzomefuna V, Glynn F, Russell J, McDermott M. Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma with no nasal symptoms. BMJ Case Rep. 2012;2012.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cui</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chu</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in young children: CT and MRI findings and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>World J Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7819-12-257</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25117604</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Obidan</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashoor</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal chondromesenchymal hamartoma in an adolescent with pleuropulmonary blastoma</article-title>
          <source>Saudi Med J</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>876</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25129191</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chandra Manis</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Venkatahalam</surname>
              <given-names>VP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nasal Chondormesenchymal Hamartoma: a case report and review of literature</article-title>
          <source>JK-Practitioner</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
