<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transplantation</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transplantation</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TP</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Transplantation</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0041-1337</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1534-6080</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25929605</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4539195</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">TP141647</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/TP.0000000000000759</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00042</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letters</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Successful Catheter Ablation of Right Atrial Tachycardia After Bilateral Lung Transplantation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sz&#xE9;plaki</surname>
            <given-names>G&#xE1;bor</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Szegedi</surname>
            <given-names>N&#xE1;ndor</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tahin</surname>
            <given-names>Tam&#xE1;s</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Merkely</surname>
            <given-names>B&#xE9;la</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD, DSc</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gell&#xE9;r</surname>
            <given-names>L&#xE1;szl&#xF3;</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup> Heart and Vascular Center, Semmelweis University, Budapest, Hungary.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">G&#xE1;bor Sz&#xE9;plaki, MD, PhD, Heart and Vascular Center, Semmelweis University, 1122 Varosmajor St 68, Budapest, Hungary. (<email>szeplaki.gabor@gmail.com</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>05</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>99</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <fpage>e115</fpage>
      <lpage>e116</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-request">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 3.0 License, where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="tp-99-e115.pdf"/>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>STATUS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>ONLINE-ONLY</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A 47-year-old woman underwent bilateral lung transplantation for pulmonary fibrosis in June of 2013. The early postoperative period was complicated by continuous atrial arrhythmias that proved unresponsive to antiarrhythmic agents (propafenon and bisoprolol). Therefore, in February 2014, we performed an electrophysiological study after adequate antibiotic and antimycotic prophylaxis. During the procedure, the clinical tachycardia was easily inducible with burst atrial pacing and programmed atrial extrastimuli. Tachycardia cycle length varied between 380 ms and 420 ms, and A-A-V response after ventricular burst pacing suggested atrial tachycardia. Entrainment mapping from the area of early activation failed to demonstrate reentry as the underlying mechanism of the tachycardia, thus ectopic atrial tachycardia was diagnosed. Electroanatomical mapping was performed with ENSITE NavX system (Endocardial Solutions Inc.) during ongoing arrhythmia (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Activation map showed that earliest activation was in the right atrium, corresponding to a scar of the extracorporeal membrane oxigenator (ECMO) cannula during lung transplantation. To avoid paralysis of the diaphragm, we paced the high right atrial region with high energy to demonstrate and mark the location of right phrenic nerve. Subsequently, we performed RF ablation with 3.5 mm irrigated tip catheter (AlCath Flux Blue G eXtra) using 40 W energy and 43&#xB0;C temperature limit. After the application of one RF ablation at the site of earliest activation (ablation time 46 seconds), the arrhythmia stopped immediately and was no longer inducible even after administration of isoproterenol. The total procedure time was 75 minutes with a fluoroscopy time of 2.3 minutes. No procedural complications occurred. Outpatient visits and 24-hour Holter electrocardiogram monitoring were scheduled every 3 months. The patient was free of symptoms and arrhythmia episodes without any antiarrhythmic medication during the 9-month follow-up period.</p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>FIGURE 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Left side: 12 lead surface electrocardiogram (paper speed 100 mm/sec) and intracardiac electrocardiogram (ablation catheter and coronary sinus catheter) during ongoing arrhythmia. Cycle length is changing from beat to beat. The local activation recorded from the ablation catheter precedes the beginning of surface P wave with 51 ms indicating that this is the site of earliest activation (see red dot on the right side). Right side: activation map of the right atrium during ongoing atrial tachycardia (left lateral view). Small blue dots show the points where phrenic nerve stimulation was observed, big red dot shows the site of successful ablation. IVC indicates inferior vena cava; RAA, right atrial appendage; SVC, superior vena cava.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="tp-99-e115-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Atrial tachyarrhythmias are frequent after lung transplantation but the incidence of right atrial tachycardia is very low. Most commonly atrial fibrillation is observed in the early postoperative period and left atrial tachycardia occurs later in time.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Right atrial tachycardia might also be associated to the operation, during which an ECMO is implanted with cannulation of the right atrium and aorta. Damaging the anterior part of the high right atrium during this step might be the ground of arrhythmia substrate formation.</p>
    <p>To the best of our knowledge, our case represents the first successful ablation of right atrial tachycardia after lung transplantation due to scarring of a passagere cannula of ECMO. Ablation of typical right atrial flutter and left atrial tachycardias originating from the donor pulmonary veins has been reported previously.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Atrial ablation in lung transplant recipients is rarely performed, in contrast to heart transplant recipients, where ablation of atrial arrhythmias has repeatedly been reported and arrhythmias are dominantly originating from the right atrium.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>This work was supported by Hungarian Foundation Programs: Bolyai J&#xE1;nos Research Scholarships of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences (to GS and LG) and the Hungarian Scientific Research Fund (OTKA K 105555).</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>See</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts-Thomson</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Atrial arrhythmias after lung transplantation: epidemiology, mechanisms at electrophysiology study, and outcomes</article-title>.
<source><italic>Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol</italic></source>. 
<year>2009</year>;
<volume>5</volume>:
<fpage>504</fpage>&#x2013;
<lpage>510</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19843918</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Roten</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Noninvasive electrocardiographic mapping for prediction of tachycardia mechanism and origin of atrial tachycardia following bilateral pulmonary transplantation</article-title>.
<source><italic>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</italic></source>. 
<year>2012</year>;
<volume>5</volume>:
<fpage>553</fpage>&#x2013;
<lpage>555</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22487050</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Nazmul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Munger</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Atrial tachycardia originating from a donor pulmonary vein in a lung transplant recipient</article-title>.
<source><italic>Circulation</italic></source>. 
<year>2011</year>;
<volume>11</volume>:
<fpage>1288</fpage>&#x2013;
<lpage>1289</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21911797</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Sacher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vest</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Incessant donor-to-recipient atrial tachycardia after bilateral lung transplantation</article-title>.
<source><italic>Heart Rhythm</italic></source>. 
<year>2008</year>;
<volume>1</volume>:
<fpage>149</fpage>&#x2013;
<lpage>151</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18060844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group><name><surname>Nof</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Catheter ablation of atrial arrhythmias after cardiac transplantation: findings at EP study utility of 3-D mapping and outcomes</article-title>.
<source><italic>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</italic></source>. 
<year>2013</year>;
<volume>24</volume>:
<fpage>498</fpage>&#x2013;
<lpage>502</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23387552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
