<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SaudiMedJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Saudi Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0379-5284</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1658-3175</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Saudi Medical Journal</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Saudi Arabia</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25987120</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4454912</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SaudiMedJ-36-747</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15537/smj.2015.6.11305</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Saddle pulmonary embolus and bronchiolitis obliterans with organizing pneumonia develop simultaneously after first cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, 5FU chemotherapy for breast cancer</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Al-Hameed</surname>
            <given-names>Fahad M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, FRCPC</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <italic>From the Department of Intensive Care, College of Medicine, King Saud bin Abdulaziz University for Health Sciences, King Abdulaziz Medical City, National Guard Health Affairs, Jeddah, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia</italic>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">
          <italic>Address correspondence and reprint request to: Dr. Fahad M. Al-Hameed, Department of Intensive Care, College of Medicine, King Saud bin Abdulaziz University for Health Sciences, King Abdulaziz Medical City, National Guard Health Affairs, Jeddah, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. E-mail: <email xlink:href="fahadalhameed@hotmail.com">fahadalhameed@hotmail.com</email></italic>
        </corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>36</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>747</fpage>
      <lpage>750</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Saudi Medical Journal</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 62-year-old woman underwent a right mastectomy with axillary node dissection for a poorly differentiated ductal carcinoma. One month later, she underwent a left nephrectomy for a renal cell carcinoma. Two weeks after, she received her first cycle of cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, and 5FU (CMF) as a part of her breast cancer treatment. We describe an unusual case of non-occlusive saddle pulmonary embolus with extensive bilateral deep vein thrombosis and severe bronchiolitis obliterans with organizing pneumonia developing simultaneously after the first CMF chemotherapy for breast cancer.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Pulmonary embolism (PE) is a serious condition that commonly develops in hypercoagulable states such as malignancy and post chemotherapy treatment.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> When associated with hemodynamic instability, immediate recognition, and treatment are essential for a favorable outcome.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Elevated pulmonary artery pressures (PAP) and pulmonary vascular resistance (PVR) may be the clue to diagnosis and subsequently the treatment of PE.<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Bronchiolitis obliterans with organizing pneumonia (BOOP) is another serious disease that is frequently misdiagnosed and is associated with significant morbidity and mortality. Early recognition and treatment usually leads to better outcomes.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The objective in presenting this particular case is to describe a rare case of significant pulmonary embolism and severe BOOP developing simultaneously after the first cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, 5FU (CMF) chemotherapy for breast cancer.</p>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 62-year-old woman underwent a right mastectomy with axillary node dissection for a poorly differentiated ductal carcinoma. One month later she underwent left nephrectomy for renal cell carcinoma. After 14 days, she received her first cycle of CMF as a part of her breast cancer treatment. Two weeks later, she developed progressive shortness-of-breath, dry cough, and mild fever, for which she was started on antibiotics for possible pneumonia. Two days later, her respiratory status deteriorated and she required intubation and mechanical ventilation. Because of hemodynamic instability and hypotension, she was started on inotropes and transferred to the intensive care unit. On examination, her blood pressure was 110/70 mm Hg, pulse of 104 beats per minute, normal temperature, and her jugular venous pressure was 8 cm above the sternal angle. Chest examinations revealed bilateral bronchial breathing and diffuse crackles. Cardiovascular and abdominal examinations were unremarkable. Her initial chest x-ray showed bilateral mixed alveolar and interstitial infiltrates with volume loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>). Her arterial blood gases on room air prior to intubation, were partial pressure of oxygen 47torr, partial pressure of carbon dioxide 32torr, pH 7.49, bicarbonate 21, O<sub>2</sub> saturation was 85%. The PAP was 36/21 mm Hg, pulmonary capillary wedge pressure 12 mm Hg, central venous pressure 20 cm H<sub>2</sub>O, cardiac index of 2.0 L/min/m<sup>2</sup>, and calculated PVR was 560 dynes sec/cm-5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>). A spiral CT of the chest showed a non-occlusive saddle pulmonary embolism with multiple bilateral pulmonary emboli (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref></bold>). She was treated with thrombolytics (100 mg rt-PA) followed by heparin without complications. She improved hemodynamically, and the inotropes were discontinued. Doppler ultrasound of the legs confirmed bilateral deep vein thrombosis. Because of persistent pulmonary infiltrates (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref></bold>), she underwent a fiberoptic bronchoscopy with bronchoalveolar lavage, which was negative. This was followed by open lung biopsy that showed loose organizing granulation tissue in the small airways consistent with BOOP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5"><bold>Figure 5</bold></xref>). She was treated with a pulse of steroids (1 g of methylprednisolone intravenously daily for 3 days followed by 1 mg/kg of prednisone daily). She was extubated 8 days later. She was transferred to the medical ward and was discharged home on long-term anticoagulation and steroids 2 weeks later. She had a chest x-ray before discharge, which showed near resolution of the infiltrate and restoration of lung volumes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6"><bold>Figure 6</bold></xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Initial chest x-ray showed bilateral mixed alveolar and interstitial infiltrates.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="SaudiMedJ-36-747-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Chest x-ray after intubation and pulmonary artery catheter insertion, showed endotracheal tube and pulmonary artery catheter in good place with bilateral air space.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="SaudiMedJ-36-747-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Spiral CT scan of the chest showed a non occlusive saddle pulmonary embolism.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="SaudiMedJ-36-747-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Spiral CT scan of the chest showed multiple bilateral pulmonary emboli and bilateral air space.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="SaudiMedJ-36-747-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Arrows show loose organizing granulation tissue in small airways consistent with an organizing pneumonia pattern of cryptogenic organizing pneumonia or bronchiolitis obliterans with organizing pneumonia.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="SaudiMedJ-36-747-g005"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F6" position="float">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Chest x-ray before discharge, which showed near resolution of the infiltrate and restoration of lung volumes.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="SaudiMedJ-36-747-g006"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Massive PE is a catastrophic entity that often results in acute right ventricular failure, hemodynamic instability, and death.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The diagnosis of massive PE relies mainly upon clinical suspicion followed by the appropriate investigation.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Spiral CT of the chest is the diagnostic modality that is most often used in ventilated patients, although pulmonary angiogram remains the gold standard.<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Clinical instability may interfere with the institution of an effective diagnostic strategy, and could therefore delay early therapy. In our case, pulmonary artery catheter data led to the suspicion of PE and subsequent appropriate investigation and early therapeutic intervention. Thrombolysis is currently the standard treatment of massive PE with hemodynamic instability.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></p>
      <p>Bronchiolitis obliterans with organizing pneumonia is another distinct clinical entity of unknown etiology. It is also called cryptogenic organizing pneumonia, and is defined pathologically by the presence in the distal air spaces of buds of granulation tissue progressing from fibrin exudates to loose collagen containing fibroblasts.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> It is commonly presented with pneumonia-like symptoms that do not respond to antibiotics. Organizing pneumonia (BOOP) may be classified into 3 categories according to its cause: organizing pneumonia of determined cause, organizing pneumonia of undetermined cause but occurring in a specific and relevant context, and cryptogenic (idiopathic) organizing pneumonia. Several possible causes and/or associated disorders may co-exist in the same patient. There are no clear distinguishing clinical and radiological features between cryptogenic and secondary organizing pneumonia.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p>
      <p>With drug-induced organizing pneumonia, it is sometimes difficult to determine causality since organizing pneumonia may also be associated with the underlying disease. In many cases however, it is not possible to determine whether the drug is responsible or not, for example, in patients with cancer or hematological malignancies who may be treated with several drugs that are able to induce organizing pneumonia.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Bleomycin and busulphan are the most common chemotherapy drugs associated with BOOP. However, on MEDLINE review, we were unable to source CMF described in the literature as a cause of BOOP after the first cycle of chemotherapy. Chemotherapy, particularly cyclophosphamide, has been used as a second line treatment after steroids for BOOP. Though cyclophosphamide and methotrexate treatment have been rarely reported in the literature to cause BOOP, 5-FU has not been reported to cause BOOP.<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Systemic corticosteroid therapy is the mainstay of treatment with initial doses of 0.75 to 1 mg/kg per day, and gradual weaning over 6 to 12 months.<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Because of her respiratory failure requiring mechanical ventilation, our patient received a pulse of steroids over 3 days followed by 1 mg/kg of prednisone daily.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p>
      <p>This case highlights the importance of using the new chemotherapy regimen for breast cancer with fewer side effects including lung toxicities. In our case, BOOP was suspected after ruling out active infection and following an adequate course of antibiotic coverage. Open lung biopsy provided the definite diagnosis. Corticosteroids remain the mainstay of therapy.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, multiple primary causes for respiratory failure in a single patient are not uncommon. In a patient at risk for PE, the diagnosis should be pursued further in the presence of unexplained high PAP and PVR. Bronchiolitis obliterans with organizing pneumonia is being increasingly diagnosed as a cause of respiratory failure and should, in the classical setting be commonly included in the differential diagnosis. The presence of an evident cause for respiratory failure should not deter further investigation.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>
<boxed-text position="float"><p><bold>Disclosure.</bold> The author has no conflict of interests, and the work was not supported or funded by any drug company.</p></boxed-text>
</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <sec id="sec1-4">
      <title/>
      <boxed-text position="float">
        <caption>
          <title>Related Articles</title>
        </caption>
        <p>Thabet FC, Alhejaili AS, Alodayani AN, Chehab MS. Septic pulmonary embolism secondary to <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> septic thrombophlebitis in a pediatric patient. <bold><italic>Saudi Med J</italic></bold> 2013; 34: 1080-1082.</p>
        <p>Darwish HS, Qamar SR. Paddlewheel multi-slice helical computed tomography reformation in the detection of pulmonary embolism. <italic>An initial experience</italic>. <bold><italic>Saudi Med J</italic></bold> 2013; 34: 896-900.</p>
        <p>El-Essawy MT, Al-Harbi SR. Multiple pulmonary and systemic ectopic emboli following endoscopic injection sclerotherapy for gastric fundal varices. <bold><italic>Saudi Med J</italic></bold> 2012; 33: 321-323.</p>
      </boxed-text>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Konstantinides</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldhaber</surname>
              <given-names>SZ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary embolism: risk assessment and management</article-title>
          <source>Eur Heart J</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>3014</fpage>
          <lpage>3022</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22961946</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dobromirski</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gurwith</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Managing pulmonary embolism from presentation to extended treatment</article-title>
          <source>Thromb Res</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>148</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24182642</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stein</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kayali</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hull</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spiral computed tomography for the diagnosis of acute pulmonary embolism</article-title>
          <source>Thromb Haemost</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>713</fpage>
          <lpage>720</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17938792</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rog</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bronchiolitis obliterans organizing pneumonia mimicking community-acquired pneumonia</article-title>
          <source>J Am Board Fam Pract</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>45</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9456446</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lohr</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boland</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Douglas</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dockrell</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colby</surname>
              <given-names>TV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Swensen</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>et</surname>
              <given-names>al</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Organizing pneumonia. Features and prognosis of cryptogenic, secondary, and focal variants</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>157</volume>
          <fpage>1323</fpage>
          <lpage>1329</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9201006</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schlesinger</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koss</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The organizing pneumonias: an update and review</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Pulm Med</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>422</fpage>
          <lpage>430</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16093817</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garrido</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Brien</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clavero</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orellana</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cryptogenic organizing pneumonitis during oxaliplatin chemotherapy for colorectal cancer: case report</article-title>
          <source>Chest</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>1997</fpage>
          <lpage>1999</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079234</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>In</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Organizing pneumonia associated with oxaliplatin-combined chemotherapy: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Med Princ Pract</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>89</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bradley</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Branley</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Egan</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greaves</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hansell</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harrison</surname>
              <given-names>NK</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interstitial lung disease guideline: the British Thoracic Society in collaboration with the Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand and the Irish Thoracic Society</article-title>
          <source>Thorax</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <issue>Suppl 5</issue>
          <fpage>v1</fpage>
          <lpage>v58</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18757459</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schlesinger</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koss</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The organizing pneumonias : a critical review of current concepts and treatment</article-title>
          <source>Treat Respir Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          <lpage>206</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16696589</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
