<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arq. Bras. Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Arq. Bras. Cardiol.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cardiologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0066-782X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-4170</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24217436</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4062379</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/abc.20130195</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Exuberant Pattern of Late Gadolinium Enhancement in Hypertrophic
Cardiomyopathy</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fernandes</surname>
            <given-names>Elsa</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Camargo</surname>
            <given-names>Gabriel C.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Derenne</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Eduarda</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rothstein</surname>
            <given-names>Tamara</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gottlieb</surname>
            <given-names>Ilan</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff>CDPI - Cl&#xED;nica de Diagn&#xF3;stico por Imagem, Rio de Janeiro, RJ - Brazil</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing Address: Tamara Rothstein,</bold> Rua Ataulfo de Paiva, 669,
Leblon. Postal Code 22430-210, Rio de Janeiro, RJ - Brazil. E-mail:
<email>tamaragott@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>101</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>e80</fpage>
      <lpage>e82</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Cardiomyopathy, Hypertrophic</kwd>
        <kwd>Endomyocardial Fibrosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Ventricular Dysfunction</kwd>
        <kwd>Tachycardia Ventricular</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) is the most common form of genetic heart disease,
with an incidence of 1: 500 individuals in the general population, being the most
frequent cause of sudden death in athletes and young adults in the United
States<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMRI) is a noninvasive imaging method that allows
the accurate identification of various forms of hypertrophy, quantification of
ventricular volume and mass and characterization of myocardial fibrosis through the
late enhancement technique<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The presence of myocardial fibrosis in CMRI is associated with the risk of sudden
death, ventricular tachycardia and systolic dysfunction<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. The presence of late enhancement is the strongest
predictor of worse prognosis, even after adjustment for other factors such as
maximum thickness and myocardial mass, obstruction of the LV outflow tract and
clinical variable<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The purpose of this study is to report the case of a patient with HCM, asymptomatic,
with extensive/exuberant myocardial fibrosis detected by CMRI and to discuss a
potential therapeutic implication.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>Patient aged 42, Caucasian, asymptomatic, with family history of HCM and diagnosis of
the same cardiomyopathy 22 years ago. The 24-h Holter heart rhythm monitoring (April
5, 2012) showed sinus rhythm, rare atrial ectopic beats, presence of 2,970 isolated
ventricular extrasystoles and five outbreaks of non-sustained ventricular
tachycardia (NSVT), the longest one presenting 13 QRS complexes. Given the Holter
results, the patient was referred by the assistant physician to cardiac magnetic
resonance imaging for a better phenotypic characterization of the myocardium.</p>
      <p>CMRI was performed on a 3T-Verio scanner (Siemens, Germany) on May 9, 2012 and Cine
SSFP (steady-state free precession) sequences and were used for functional
assessment and Inversion Recovery-GRE (gradient echo) for the late enhancement. The
following observations were made: severe asymmetric hypertrophy, where the point of
greatest thickness was measured at 2.4 cm on the mid inferoseptal wall; normal left
ventricular mass; outbreaks of hypointense signal on all sequences in the septal and
anterior mid-apical LV walls, which may represent calcifications; LV of normal
cavity volumes with mild global systolic dysfunction at the expense of segmental
hypokinesis of the anterior and septal walls; severe muscular thickening of the RV
apical region; late enhancement on contrast media in hypertrophied LV and RV
segments of predominantly mesocardial distribution (nonischemic pattern). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref> illustrate some of these findings.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>4-chamber long axis image. Septal hypertrophy and hypertrophy of the apical
portion of the RV and a potential calcification in the apical septum
(hypointense signal area &#x2014; arrow).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-101-04-0e80-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Images of late enhancement in 4-chamber (A), 3-chamber (B) and 2-chamber (C)
long-axis and short-axis (D). Presence of diffuse enhancement, including in
the RV middle-apical region (A and D).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-101-04-0e80-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient underwent implantation of cardioverter on June 2, 2012 and remains
asymptomatic to date.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The patient under discussion has had longtime hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (for 22
years) with biventricular involvement, severe myocardial fibrosis and mild systolic
dysfunction. There were no classical markers of high risk for sudden death, such as
myocardial thickness &#x2265; 30 mm, family history of sudden death, syncope, ventricular
tachycardia (VT) or obstruction of the LV outflow tract or abnormal behavior of
blood pressure during exercise testing. The markers that suggested that this patient
was at higher risk for sudden death were non-sustained ventricular tachycardia and
the presence of severe late enhancement on MRI.</p>
      <p>Although sustained VT is clearly associated with sudden death, the association with
non-sustained VT is less robust. However, a recent study showed no association of
non-sustained VT with death in multivariate analysis<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The detection of myocardial fibrosis in HCM by CMRI using the late enhancement
technique has an incidence of 50-80% of cases of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy and is
believed to be the anatomical substrate for the occurrence of malign ventricular
tachyarrhythmias<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The late enhancement pattern most often described is the heterogeneous and
mesocardial pattern, preferably located in hypertrophied segments and at the points
of insertion of the right ventricle with the interventricular septum<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. In the clinical case reported, only the anterolateral and
inferolateral segments (both basal and mid) and lower basal were free of late
enhancement, which characterizes a pattern of an unusual presentation.</p>
      <p>In the patient reported, the late enhancement area measured using five standard
deviations of the remote area is 46.9% of the left ventricular mass. There is no
consensus on what percentage value should be considered higher risk for adverse
events, but 46.9% is certainly considered a high percentage. Some studies show that
the presence of late enhancement above 5% of the LV mass is associated with
increased risk of sudden death, appropriate therapy by implantable defibrillator and
ventricular tachyarrhythmia<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The right ventricular involvement has been reported in approximately 18% of patients
with HCM, affecting the middle and apical region also found in the clinical case
reported<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. These patients
may have maximum wall thickness greater than 8 mm, as well as increased right
ventricular mass<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. The presence of
severe late enhancement in the right ventricle in this patient is another atypical
characteristic.</p>
      <p>The apparent discrepancy between the maximum myocardial thickness and the severe late
enhancement may result from burnt out hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, i.e., fibrosis
and ventricular thinning due to disease duration. Myocardial calcifications may
corroborate this long aggression on the cardiac muscle<sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The importance of late enhancement in patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy was
investigated in two recent studies, and both demonstrated that the enhancement is
not only an independent predictor of cardiovascular events in multivariate analysis,
but also the best predictor compared to the usual predictors, such as maximum
myocardial thickness, obstruction of the LV outflow tract, clinical factors and
family history of sudden death<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. However, we recognize that the
presence of late enhancement has a low positive predictive value for sudden death as
mentioned in the guidelines of the ACC/AHA of 2011<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, and confirmed in a meta-analysis in which the
presence of enhancement was significantly associated with cardiovascular outcomes,
but not with mortality from arrhythmia<sup><xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The patient has no classical markers of high risk for sudden death, and the decision
to implant ICD was made based on the presence of NSVT on 24-h Holter, severe
myocardial fibrosis on MRI after discussion of risks and benefits with the patient
and the family. The presence of late enhancement by CMRI is an emerging marker of
prognosis, but its role in directing the therapy is still controversial.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="con">
        <p>
          <bold>Author contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>Conception and design of the research and Analysis and interpretation of the
data: Gottlieb I ; Acquisition of data: Fernandes E, Camargo GC, Rothstein T,
Gottlieb I; Writing of the manuscript: Fernandes E, Gottlieb I; Critical
revision of the manuscript for intellectual content: Camargo GC, Derenne ME,
Rothstein T, Gottlieb I.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>
          <bold>Potential Conflict of Interest</bold>
        </p>
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>
          <bold>Sources of Funding</bold>
        </p>
        <p>There were no external funding sources for this study.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>
          <bold>Study Association</bold>
        </p>
        <p>This study is not associated with any post-graduation program.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maron</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hypertrophic cardiomyophaty: a systematic review</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>287</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1308</fpage>
          <lpage>1320</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11886323</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gersh</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maron</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonow</surname>
              <given-names>RO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dearani</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fifer</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Link</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
            <collab>American College of Cardiology Foundation</collab>
            <collab>American Heart Association Task Force on Practice
Guidelines</collab>
            <collab>American Association for Thoracic Surgery</collab>
            <collab>American Society of Echocardiography</collab>
            <collab>American Society of Nuclear Cardiology</collab>
            <collab>Heart Failure Society of America</collab>
            <collab>Heart Rhythm Society</collab>
            <collab>Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions</collab>
            <collab>Society of Thoracic Surgeons</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>2011 ACCF/AHA Guideline for the Diagnosis and Treatment of
Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy: A Report of the American College of Cardiology
Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice
Guidelines</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>124</volume>
          <issue>24</issue>
          <fpage>e783</fpage>
          <lpage>e831</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22068434</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shiozaki</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raymond</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parga</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tassi</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arteaga</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rochitte</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Resson&#xE2;ncia magn&#xE9;tica cardiovascular na
cardiomiopatia hipertr&#xF3;fica</article-title>
          <source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>243</fpage>
          <lpage>248</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17384845</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Noureldin</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nacif</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Judge</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halushka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abraham</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The diagnosis of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy by cardiovascular
magnetic resonance</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          <lpage>17</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22348519</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#xB4;Hanlon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grasso</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roughton</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moon</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wage</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prognostic significance of myocardial fibrosis in hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>867</fpage>
          <lpage>874</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20688032</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bruder</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ong</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kispert</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myocardial scar visualized by cardiovascular magnetic resonance
imaging predicts major adverse in patients with hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>875</fpage>
          <lpage>887</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20667520</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elliott</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gimeno</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tom&#xE9;</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thaman</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Left ventricular outflow tract obstruction and sudden death risk
in patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>Eur Heart J</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>16</issue>
          <fpage>1933</fpage>
          <lpage>1941</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16754630</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maron</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical utility of cardiovascular magnetic resonance in
hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Magn Reson</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>13</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22296938</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adabag</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maron</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Appelbaum</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harrigan</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buros</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibson</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occurrence and frequency of arrhythmias in hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy in rElation to delayed enhancement on cardiovascular
resonance</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>1369</fpage>
          <lpage>1374</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18387438</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fluechter</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>extent of late gadolinium enhancement detected by cardiovascular
magnetic resonance correlates with the inducibility of ventricular
tachyarrhythmia in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>journal of cardivascular magnetic resonance</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hughes</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mckenna</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>New insights into the pathology of inherited
cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>Heart</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>264</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15657260</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berger</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kramer</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salermo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prognostic value of late gadolinium enhancement in clinical
outcomes for hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol Imaging</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>370</fpage>
          <lpage>377</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
