<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arq. Bras. Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abc</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cardiologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0066-782X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-4170</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia - SBC</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26761371</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4693668</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/abc.20150145</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Anatomopathological Session</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Case 6/2015 - 40-Year-Old Female with Acute Chest Pain, Dyspnea and
Shock</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Daiana Zupirolli</surname>
            <given-names>Gon&#xE7;alves</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Paulo Sampaio</surname>
            <given-names>Gutierrez</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff01">Instituto do Cora&#xE7;&#xE3;o - (InCor) - HC-FMUSP, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP - Brazil</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing Address: Vera Demarchi Aiello,</bold> Avenida Dr. En&#xE9;as
de Carvalho Aguiar, 44, subsolo, bloco I, Cerqueira C&#xE9;sar. Postal Code 05403-000, S&#xE3;o
Paulo, SP - Brazil. E-mail: <email>demarchi@cardiol.br</email>,
<email>vera.aiello@incor.usp.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>105</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>637</fpage>
      <lpage>641</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Aortic Dissection / surgery</kwd>
        <kwd>Aortic Diseases / surgery</kwd>
        <kwd>Hypertension</kwd>
        <kwd>Marfan Syndrome</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>The patient is a 40-year-old female referred to the emergency unit due to thoracic pain,
dyspnea and shock.</p>
    <p>She reported a history of arterial hypertension, IgA nephropathy and HELLP syndrome in
pregnancy (hypertension, hemolysis, increased liver enzymes and low platelet count).</p>
    <p>The patient sought the Osasco Regional Hospital complaining of chest and low back pain and
lower limb paresthesia (Nov 10, 2013), being then assessed and discharged. As her symptoms
persisted, she returned to that hospital on the following day. On admission, the patient
showed hypotension (80/50 mmHg), hyperthermia (temperatures ranging from 37.8&#xB0;C to 38&#xB0;C),
hypoxemia, crepitant rales in both lungs, and heart murmur on auscultation.</p>
    <p>She received empirical antibiotic therapy for pneumonia (ceftriaxone, clarithromycin and
oseltamivir) and was heparinized due to suspicion of pulmonary thromboembolism.</p>
    <p>Chest angiotomography for the diagnosis of pulmonary thromboembolism revealed type A aortic
dissection, enlarged cardiac area, and areas of consolidation in the pulmonary bases.</p>
    <p>She progressed with arterial hypotension and respiratory insufficiency due to acute
pulmonary edema, requiring endotracheal intubation.</p>
    <p>On admission at the Instituto do Cora&#xE7;&#xE3;o (InCor) of the HCFMUSP, the physical examination
(Nov 15, 2013) showed a sedated patient, with orotracheal intubation, FIO<sub>2</sub> of
100%, O<sub>2</sub> saturation of 98%, blood pressure of 90/40 mmHg, heart rate of 120 bpm,
with no jugular vein stasis and asymmetrical pulses in the lower limbs. Lung auscultation
revealed a decrease in respiratory sounds at the bases. Cardiac auscultation showed low
heart sounds, systolic murmur +++/6+ and blowing diastolic murmur +++/6+ in the aortic
region. The abdomen was flaccid, with normal gut sounds, and the liver was palpable 3 cm
from the right costal margin.</p>
    <p>Intravenous noradrenalin was introduced, and echocardiography and angiotomography of the
aorta were indicated, in addition to cardiovascular surgery assessment.</p>
    <p>The laboratory tests (Nov 15, 2013; 2h5) revealed: hemoglobin, 10.3 g/dL; red blood count,
32%; mean corpuscular volume, 97 fl; mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration, 32 g/dL;
leukocytes, 15,010/mm<sup>3</sup> (neutrophils 77%, eosinophils 3%, lymphocytes 15%,
monocytes 5%); platelets, 186,000/mm<sup>3</sup>; CK-MB, 5.49 ng/mL; troponin I, 2.43
ng/mL; urea, 51 mg/dL; creatinine, 0.97 mg/dL; magnesium, 1.6 mEq/L; C-reactive protein,
105.23 mg/L; sodium, 137 mEq/L; potassium, 4.8 mEq/L; ionized calcium, 1.17 mmol/L;
arterial lactate, 12 mg/dL. Arterial blood gas analysis revealed: pH, 7.46;
pCO<sub>2</sub>, 32.5 mm Hg; pO<sub>2</sub>, 129 mmHg; O<sub>2</sub> saturation, 98.7%;
bicarbonate, 22.9 mmol/L; base excess, (-) 0.1 mmol/L.</p>
    <p>Echocardiography (Nov 15, 2013) showed chambers of normal measures, left ventricular
ejection fraction of 65%, tricuspid aortic valve, and the following aortic diameters: root,
33 mm; and ascending aorta, 54 mm. The abdominal aorta showed intimal tear of dissection.
Assessment with Doppler echocardiography and flow mapping revealed severe aortic
regurgitation.</p>
    <p>Angiotomography revealed extensive acute aortic dissection, Stanford A, initiating at the
aortic root, involving the entire thoracic and abdominal aorta, and extending into the
common iliac arteries, the brachiocephalic trunk and initial segment of the right common
carotid artery. In addition, collapse of the true aortic lumen was observed at the end of
diastole, with a suggestive image of dynamic obstruction of the left main coronary
artery.</p>
    <p>The patient was referred to emergency surgery, with orotracheal intubation and mechanical
ventilation, on intravenous noradrenaline (0.5 &#xB5;g/kg/min), but hypotensive. On
anesthesia induction, she had cardiac arrest with pulseless electrical activity, did not
respond to resuscitation maneuvers, and died (Nov 15, 2013; 15h45).</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Clinical aspects</title>
      <p>The patient is a 40-year-old female with aortic dissection, hypovolemic shock and death.
She had arterial hypertension and HELLP syndrome in pregnancy, which is characterized by
hemolysis, increased liver enzymes and low platelet count.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The following are considered risk factors for aortic dissection:<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> a) arterial hypertension; b) Marfan's
syndrome; c) bicuspid aortic valve; d) Turner's syndrome; e) pregnancy. In a study on
the postmortem examinations performed at InCor between 1998 and 2007, 82 cases of aortic
dissection were diagnosed.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Most
dissections were associated with other diseases, mainly arterial hypertension present in
73/82 cases (90%). Other diseases related were Marfan's syndrome, other connective
tissue diseases, bicuspid aortic valve and trauma related to thoracic surgeries. Another
study assessing the postmortem examination of 161 patients with aortic
dissection<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> has reported
arterial hypertension in 93/161 (57.7%) cases. Other causes found were Marfan's syndrome
(16 cases), atherosclerosis of the aorta (38) and degeneration of the aorta (30). Other
less prevalent risk factors were bicuspid aortic valve, Turner's syndrome, aortic
coarctation and pregnancy. However, the likelihood of aortic dissection due to aortic
coarctation is related to the coexistence of arterial hypertension or congenital
bicuspid aortic valve. Although pregnancy is considered a spontaneous risk factor for
aortic dissection, that mechanism is uncommon, being 25% to 50% of the cases
concomitantly associated with hypertension.</p>
      <p>A study conducted in the state of S&#xE3;o Paulo<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> has reported 42,615 deaths due to aortic aneurysm and dissection over
25 years, 36,088 of which (84.7%) had the following underlying causes of death
identified: aortic dissection (37%), ruptured abdominal aortic aneurysm (17.3%) and
ruptured aortic aneurysm of unspecified location (17.5%). Among women, aortic dissection
(38.6%) and aneurysms of unspecified location (25.4%) were reported. That study showed
that among women aortic dissection was more prevalent, while among men aortic aneurysm
was more frequent.</p>
      <p>Another relevant factor in that study was the association of arterial hypertension as
the cause of aortic dissection observed in 49% of the patients.</p>
      <p>The diagnosis of aortic dissection can be difficult, because the initial signs and
symptoms can be unspecific. The patient here reported sought medical care complaining of
thoracic and low back pain with paresthesia of the lower limbs, and on the first
clinical examination, the data obtained did not allow a diagnosis to be made. As the
symptoms worsened, she returned to the hospital on the following day in a very severe
condition, with hypotension, hypoxemia, fever and heart murmur.</p>
      <p>The major classic clinical findings of a patient with aortic dissection are severe
thoracic pain and syncope. A study with 464 patients<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> has shown that severe pain of sudden onset was the most common
complaint, and the clinical presentation, diverse. Syncope occurred in 12% of those
patients, 10 of whom (2.2%) had no pain. Although the physical examination can provide
important data for the diagnosis of aortic dissection, pulse deficit, a classical sign,
was identified in less than 20% of those patients, and aortic regurgitation murmur was
documented in 44% of them.</p>
      <p>Because of its high morbidity and mortality, the diagnosis and treatment of aortic
dissection should not be delayed.</p>
      <p>The surgical treatment aims at preventing fatal complications, such as: 1) cardiac
tamponade secondary to aortic rupture; 2) acute myocardial infarction; 3) symptomatic
aortic insufficiency (present in the patient here reported); 4) neurological
complications.<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
<bold>(Daiana Zupirolli Gon&#xE7;alves, MD)</bold>
</p>
      <list list-type="order">
        <title>Diagnostic hypotheses:</title>
        <list-item>
          <p>acute aortic dissection</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>aortic valve insufficiency</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p>acute myocardial infarction</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Postmortem examination</title>
      <p>The postmortem examination evidenced characteristic changes of systemic arterial
hypertension, such as renal arteriolosclerosis and left ventricular concentric
hypertrophy. Hypertension was the underlying disease. The major disease was acute aortic
dissection, with delamination extending from 1 cm above the valvar plane, site of the
dissection orifice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>), to the end of the
abdominal aorta. Consequent to the dissection, there were aortic insufficiency, shock
leading to acute tubular necrosis and myocardial infarction with few hours of evolution
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>). As a consequence of the infarction,
whose size could not be precisely outlined due to the short course of disease, and of
aortic insufficiency, acute pulmonary edema was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>), the final factor accounting for the patient's death. There was
neither dissection, nor severe atherosclerosis nor thrombosis of the coronary arteries
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>). <bold>(Paulo Sampaio Gutierrez,
MD)</bold></p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Ascending aorta showing cleavage that characterizes aortic dissection.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-105-06-0637-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histological section showing recent myocardial necrosis area (arrows).
Hematoxylin-Eosin, 20x.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-105-06-0637-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Histological section showing alveolar spaces filled with amorphous, slightly
eosinophilic material, corresponding to acute pulmonary edema. Hematoxylin-Eosin,
10x.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-105-06-0637-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Photomicrography: cross section of the coronary artery showing only mild
atherosclerosis (atherosclerotic plaque indicated by the asterisk). Movat
pentachrome stain, 1x.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-105-06-0637-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <p><bold>Anatomopathological diagnoses:</bold> acute aortic dissection (DeBakey type I,
Stanford type A) with underlying systemic arterial hypertension</p>
      <p><bold>Cause of death:</bold> acute pulmonary edema<bold> (Paulo Sampaio Gutierrez,
MD)</bold></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Comments</title>
      <p>The anatomopathological method could not precisely outline the area affected by the
acute myocardial infarction, because of the short course of disease in this case.
Whether the injury was large and the major cause of the pulmonary edema, or only a
factor associated with aortic insufficiency, which seems less likely, could not be
determined. A patient with aortic dissection can have myocardial infarction due to
several mechanisms, such as hypovolemic shock, aortic dissection extending to the
coronary artery, extrinsic compression of the coronary artery caused by a hematoma in
the false lumen, or, as shown on this patient's angiotomography, direct reduction in the
coronary flow resulting from delamination of the aorta. Despite the occurrence of
myocardial infarction, acute pulmonary edema is an uncommon cause of death in patients
with acute aortic dissection, which usually progresses with hypovolemia due to rupture
and bleeding. Acute renal tubular necrosis can have contributed due to the increase in
blood volume.</p>
      <p>In addition, this case illustrates limits and advantages of some methods. Only
<italic>in vivo</italic> imaging could show coronary flow obstruction, because it is
a dynamic test. The postmorten examination lacks that component, and, thus, could not
have confirmed that. <bold>(Paulo Sampaio Gutierrez, MD)</bold></p>
      <p><bold>Section Editor:</bold> Alfredo Jos&#xE9; Mansur
(<email>ajmansur@incor.usp.br</email>)</p>
      <p><bold>Associated Editors:</bold> Desid&#xE9;rio
Favarato(<email>dclfavarato@incor.usp.br</email>)</p>
      <p>Vera Demarchi Aiello (<email>anpvera@incor.usp.br</email>)</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref-list>
        <ref id="r01">
          <label>1</label>
          <element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Amaral</surname>
                <given-names>LM</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cunningham</surname>
                <given-names>MW</given-names>
                <suffix>Jr</suffix>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Cornelius</surname>
                <given-names>DC</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>LaMarca</surname>
                <given-names>B</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Preeclampsia: long-term consequences for vascular
health</article-title>
            <source>Vasc Health Risk Manag</source>
            <year>2015</year>
            <volume>11</volume>
            <fpage>403</fpage>
            <lpage>415</lpage>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26203257</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="r02">
          <label>2</label>
          <element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Hagan</surname>
                <given-names>PG</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Nienaber</surname>
                <given-names>CA</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Isselbacher</surname>
                <given-names>EM</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Bruckman</surname>
                <given-names>D</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Karavite</surname>
                <given-names>DJ</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Russman</surname>
                <given-names>PL</given-names>
              </name>
              <etal/>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>The International Registry of Acute Aortic Dissection (IRAD): new
insights into an old disease</article-title>
            <source>JAMA</source>
            <year>2000</year>
            <volume>283</volume>
            <issue>7</issue>
            <fpage>897</fpage>
            <lpage>903</lpage>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10685714</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="r03">
          <label>3</label>
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Gutierrez</surname>
                <given-names>PS</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>A matriz extracelular nas doen&#xE7;as da aorta</source>
            <publisher-loc>S&#xE3;o Paulo</publisher-loc>
            <publisher-name>Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de S&#xE3;o Paulo</publisher-name>
            <year>2008</year>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="r04">
          <label>4</label>
          <element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Larson</surname>
                <given-names>EW</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Edwards</surname>
                <given-names>WD</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Risk factors for aortic dissection: a necropsy study of 161
cases</article-title>
            <source>Am J Cardiol</source>
            <year>1984</year>
            <volume>53</volume>
            <issue>6</issue>
            <fpage>849</fpage>
            <lpage>855</lpage>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6702637</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="r05">
          <label>5</label>
          <element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Santo</surname>
                <given-names>AH</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Puech-Le&#xE3;o</surname>
                <given-names>P</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Krutman</surname>
                <given-names>M</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Trends in aortic aneurysm- and dissection-related mortality in the
state of S&#xE3;o Paulo, Brazil, 1985-2009: multiple-cause-of-death
analysis</article-title>
            <source>BMC Public Health</source>
            <year>2012</year>
            <volume>12</volume>
            <fpage>859</fpage>
            <lpage>859</lpage>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23046791</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="r06">
          <label>6</label>
          <element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Daily</surname>
                <given-names>PO</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Trueblood</surname>
                <given-names>HW</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Stinson</surname>
                <given-names>EB</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Wuerflein</surname>
                <given-names>RD</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Schumway</surname>
                <given-names>NE</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Management of acute aortic dissections</article-title>
            <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
            <year>1970</year>
            <volume>10</volume>
            <issue>3</issue>
            <fpage>237</fpage>
            <lpage>247</lpage>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5458238</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="r07">
          <label>7</label>
          <element-citation publication-type="journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Miller</surname>
                <given-names>DC</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Surgical management of acute aortic dissection: new
data</article-title>
            <source>Semin Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>
            <year>1991</year>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <issue>3</issue>
            <fpage>225</fpage>
            <lpage>237</lpage>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1958743</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
