<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nagoya J Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nagoya J Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nagoya Journal of Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0027-7622</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2186-3326</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Nagoya University</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22515124</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4831263</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>SIMULTANEOUS SURGICAL RESECTIONS OF TWO DISTANT METASTATIC MALIGNANT MELANOMA LESIONS &#x2014; CASE REPORT &#x2014;</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>TANEI</surname>
            <given-names>TAKAFUMI</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>NAKAHARA</surname>
            <given-names>NORIMOTO</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>TAKEBAYASHI</surname>
            <given-names>SHIGENORI</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>HIRANO</surname>
            <given-names>MASAKI</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>WAKABAYASHI</surname>
            <given-names>TOSHIHIKO</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Nagoya Central Hospital, Nagoya, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Nagoya University Graduate School of Medicine, Nagoya, Japan</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="fn1">
          <p>Corresponding Author: Takafumi Tanei, MD, PhD</p>
          <p>Department of Neurosurgery, Nagoya Central Hospital, 3-7-7 Taiko, Nakamura-ku, Nagoya 453-0801, Japan</p>
          <p>Phone: +81-452-3165; Fax: +81-452-3190, E-mail: nsgtakasyun@msn.com</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>74</volume>
      <issue>1-2</issue>
      <fpage>173</fpage>
      <lpage>179</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License. To view the details of this license, please visit (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>ABSTRACT</title>
        <p>A 41-year-old woman presented with disturbance of consciousness, right hemiparesis, and symptoms of Gerstmann syndrome. She had a history of malignant melanoma resections of an ear mole and her right neck lymph nodes and parotid gland, with subsequent chemotherapy and radiotherapy. Computed tomography showed two large lesions in the right frontal and left parietal lobes surrounded by severe brain edema. Magnetic resonance images revealed that the two lesions were strongly enhanced with cystic change, and a small round lesion was located in the left head of the caudate nucleus. (18F) fluoro-2-deoxyglucose positron emission tomography showed high accumulation in both lesions, and no sign of metastatic lesions except within the brain. The two lesions were large, causing increased intracranial pressure. Simultaneous surgical resections were performed using two approaches. The patient&#x2019;s neurological symptoms were greatly improved after surgery, and her Karnofsky Performance Status improved from 20% to 90%. She was discharged to her home almost completely free of neurological deficits. Although, simultaneous one-stage tumor resections for multiple metastatic brain tumors do not extend the survival period, they improve the quality of the patient&#x2019;s limited remaining life, and may be a treatment choice for young patients with well-controlled systemic disease.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Key Words</title>
        <kwd>Malignant melanoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Multiple</kwd>
        <kwd>Simultaneous</kwd>
        <kwd>Surgical resection</kwd>
        <kwd>Metastatic</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Malignant melanoma is the third most common cause of central nervous system metastasis.<sup><xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)</sup> The prognosis of patients with malignant melanoma brain metastases is very poor. The median survival rate reported for surgically treated patients with brain metastases from melanoma ranges from 5 to 22 months.<sup><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>)</sup> The most significant factor influencing the survival of patients with brain metastases is the number of their cerebral metastases.<sup><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>-<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup> Surgical treatment of multiple brain metastases is only considered a palliative solution for improving the quality of life. However, recently the performance of multiple resections of brain metastases from melanoma has led to a reconsideration of the surgery&#x2019;s benefits.<sup><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup></p>
      <p>We report one case of multiple brain metastases from malignant melanoma with two large lesions located in the right frontal and left parietal lobes. This is a case report of simultaneous one-stage resections of distant lesions with two approaches for multiple metastatic malignant melanoma lesions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 41-year-old woman had a mole in her right ear that grew noticeably, and swelling was detected in her right neck lymph nodes. Aspiration biopsy cytology of the neck lymph node was performed, and malignant melanoma was diagnosed. She underwent an operative resection of the ear lesion, right neck lymph nodes and parotid gland with subsequent chemotherapy and radiotherapy. She later presented with headache and multiple brain metastases were detected. Her level of consciousness had deteriorated, and she was transferred to our hospital 6 months after being diagnosed with malignant melanoma. On admission, her Glasgow Coma Scale score was 11 (E2V3M6), and she had a right hemiparesis. Additionally, symptoms of Gerstmann syndrome such as finger agnosias, right-left disorientation, acalculia and agraphia were noted.</p>
      <p>Computed tomography showed two large lesions in the right frontal lobe and left parietal lobe surrounded with severe brain edema (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A, E</xref>). Magnetic resonance (MR) images revealed that the two lesions were strongly enhanced with cystic change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B, C, F, G</xref>), and a small round lesion was present in the left head of the caudate nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1I</xref>). The subarachnoid space surrounding the left parietal lesion was also enhanced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1J</xref>). (18F) fluoro-2-deoxyglucose positron emission tomography ((18F) FDG PET) exhibited high levels of accumulation in the two large lesions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1D, H</xref>), but revealed no signs of metastatic lesions except in the brain. Cerebral angiography showed mild tumor staining in the two lesions.</p>
      <fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A, E: Computed tomography images reveal right frontal and left parietal mass lesions.</p>
          <p>B, C, F, G: Magnetic resonance (MR) images show right frontal and left parietal mass lesions as strongly enhanced on T1-weighted image with gadolinium (B, F), and peripheral edema on the T2-weighted image (C, G).</p>
          <p>D, H: (18F) fluoro-2-deoxyglucose positron emission tomography images show high accumulations in right frontal and left parietal lesions.</p>
          <p>I, J: Axial (I) and sagittal (J) of T1-weighted images with gadolinium revealed an enhanced, small mass lesion in the left head of the caudate nucleus (I), and enhanced subarachnoid space surrounding the left parietal lesion (J).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="2186-3326-74-0173-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Surgical resections of the two lesions were performed to relieve high intracranial pressure. First, the patient was placed in a prone position. A left parietal craniotomy and a parietal lesion resection were performed. The patient was then turned to a supine position under general anesthesia, after which a right frontal craniotomy and a frontal lesion resection were performed. Both frontal and parietal lesions consisted of soft and fragile black tissues. The black malignant melanoma tissues had invaded the subarachnoid space (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). The border between the tissues and normal brain could not be distinguished (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Both lesions were resected, but the malignant melanoma tissues in the subarachnoid space were residual (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2C</xref>). Histological examinations showed typical numerous pleomorphic and hyperchromatic cells, which confirmed the diagnosis of metastatic malignant melanoma.</p>
      <fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A, B, C: Intraoperative microscopic views show the black malignant melanoma tissues spread in subarachnoid space (A), the border with normal brain was not clear (B), and tumor tissues of subarachnoid space were residual (C).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="2186-3326-74-0173-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient&#x2019;s neurological symptoms improved dramatically following the surgery. Her consciousness disturbance, right hemiparesis and symptoms of Gerstmann syndrome could no longer be seen. Her Karnofsky Performance Status improved from 20% to 90%. She was discharged to her home 10 days after the operation, almost completely free of neurological deficits. Following surgery, the patient received a course of whole brain radiation therapy consisting of 30 Gy in 10 fractions, and chemotherapy at another hospital. Then she presented with pain in her extremities, but there were no signs of bone metastases detected by FDG-PET and bone scintigraphy. MR images showed a mild enlargement of the left head of the caudate nucleus lesion, but no signs of problems around previous surgical resections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3A, B, C</xref>). Spinal MR images revealed a small mass lesion attached to the spinal dura mater at the atlas level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3D, E, F</xref>). The patient presented with a generalized seizure and was again admitted to a nearby hospital. Eventually, she was able to spend time with her family for 3 months at home. Her clinical symptoms gradually deteriorated, and she died 4 months after the operation. No autopsy was performed.</p>
      <fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A-C: MR T1-weighted images with gadolinium show mild enlargement of the left head of the caudate nucleus lesion 3 months after the operation (A), but not presenting recurrence as mass lesions at left frontal and right parietal lesions (B, C).</p>
          <p>D-F: Spinal MR T1-weighted images with gadolinium revealed a small mass lesion attached to spinal dura mater at the atlas level with no signs of spinal cord compression 3 months after operation.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="2186-3326-74-0173-g003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Melanomas are the third most common source of intracranial metastases after breast and lung carcinomas.<sup><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>)</sup> The incidence of central nervous system (CNS) metastases in patients with melanomas ranges from 10% to 40% in clinical studies.<sup><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>)</sup> CNS metastasis is the most worrisome feature of malignant melanoma, leading directly to death in the majority of patients.<sup><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>)</sup> A standard treatment for patients with metastatic malignant melanoma has not been established. The prognosis for patients with malignant melanoma brain metastasis is poor, with a median survival time ranging between 2 to 10 months.<sup><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>-<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</sup> It is noteworthy that only 10% of patients survive more than 1 year after diagnosis.<sup><xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</sup></p>
      <p>An important factor strongly influencing the therapeutic response of patients is the number of metastases.<sup><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>-<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup> Age, sex, and the time interval from the primary malignant melanoma manifestation to the cerebral metastasis seem not to affect the clinical outcome.<sup><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>)</sup> The intracranial secondary spread of malignant melanoma is frequently multiple.<sup><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup> Prospective randomized trials have demonstrated the benefit of surgery for the treatment of a single metastasis in the brain.<sup><xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)</sup> Surgical therapy is ordinarily used for the majority of patients with a single metastatic lesion,<sup><xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</sup> but only a few selected patients with multiple metastases in the brain are treated surgically.<sup><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup> Recently, Konstadoulakis <italic>et al</italic>. reported that the median survival time of surgical resection for multiple brain metastases was 8 months.<sup><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup> They concluded that performing multiple resections of brain metastases from melanoma is considered a radical approach, especially in young patients with well-controlled systemic disease. The main aim of a simultaneous one-stage resection for multiple metastatic lesions is limited improvement in the quality of the patient&#x2019;s limited remaining life, so the indications are extremely limited. The two preconditions are that the patients are young and have well-controlled systemic disease, and that dramatic improvements of neurological symptoms may be expected following the resections.</p>
      <p>The surgical options for managing two intracranial lesions are influenced by the presence of another intracranial tumor. When two lesions are contiguous, they may usually be removed using a single approach, but when they are distant from each other, the surgical approach depends upon the type of lesions.<sup><xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</sup> When one tumor is malignant and the other is benign, the malignant tumor must be removed first. A second craniotomy may be performed at least 10 to 12 months later, when the benign tumor is large enough and/or symptomatic, or shows a tendency to grow. When the two lesions are malignant, large, or symptomatic tumors, both lesions may require early resection. In such cases, there is no consensus as to the best surgical management.</p>
      <p>In the present case, the patient presented with two large distant symptomatic metastatic lesions. Therefore, we selected simultaneous one-stage tumor resection with a left parietal craniotomy and a right frontal craniotomy, and found no adverse events associated with the simultaneous one-stage operation. The one-stage operation using two approaches has several risks. The patient&#x2019;s surgical position must be changed under general anesthesia, and the operation time is longer, and more invasive. Nevertheless, the significant reduction of intracranial pressure obtained by surgery may produce immediate and dramatic improvements of the patient&#x2019;s neurological symptoms. The conventional treatment for multiple metastatic brain tumors is radiotherapy.<sup><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</sup> The superiority surgical treatment has over radiotherapy for managing multiple metastatic brain tumors is an immediate reduction in intracranial pressure. While our patient&#x2019;s survival period was not extended, her symptomatic improvements enabled her to return home and spend time with her family. Because it improves the quality of the patient&#x2019;s limited remaining life, simultaneous one-stage tumor resection using two approaches is a viable option for the surgical management of multiple metastatic brain tumors, especially in young patients with well-controlled systemic disease.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Amer MH, Al-Sarraf M, Baker LH, Vaitkevicius VK. Malignant melanoma and central nervous system metastases: incidence, diagnosis, treatment and survival. <italic>Cancer</italic>, 1978; 42: 660<italic>&#x2212;</italic>668.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Konstadoulakis MM, Messaris E, Zografos G, Androulakis G, Karakousis C. Prognostic factors in malignant melanoma patients with solitary or multiple brain metastases. Is there a role for surgery? <italic>J Neurosurg Sci</italic>, 2000; 44: 211<italic>&#x2212;</italic>218.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oredsson S, Ingvar C, Stromblad LG, Jonsson PE. Palliative surgery for brain metastases of malignant melanoma. <italic>Eur J Surg Oncol</italic>, 1990; 16: 451<italic>&#x2212;</italic>456.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wronski M, Arbit E. Surgical treatment of brain metastases from melanoma: a retrospective study of 91 patients. <italic>J Neurosurg</italic>, 2000; 93: 9<italic>&#x2212;</italic>18.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zacest AC, Besser M, Stevens G, Thompson JF, McCarthy WH, Culjak G. Surgical management of cerebral metastases from melanoma: outcome in 147 patients treated at a single institution over two decades. <italic>J Neurosurg</italic>, 2002; 96: 552<italic>&#x2212;</italic>558.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sampson JH, Carter JH Jr, Friedman AH, Seigler HF. Demographics, prognosis, and therapy in 702 patients with brain metastases from malignant melanoma. <italic>J Neurosurg</italic>, 1998; 88: 11<italic>&#x2212;</italic>20.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Somaza S, Kondziolka D, Lunsford LD, Kirkwood JM, Flickinger JC. Stereotactic radiosurgery for cerebral metastatic melanoma. <italic>J Neurosurg</italic>, 1993; 79: 661<italic>&#x2212;</italic>666.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stevens G, Firth I, Coates A. Cerebral metastases from malignant melanoma. <italic>Radiother Oncol</italic>, 1992; 23: 185<italic>&#x2212;</italic>191.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kingdom TT, Lalwani AK, Pitts LH. Isolated metastatic melanoma of the cerebellopontine angle: case report. <italic>Neurosurgery</italic>, 1993; 33: 142<italic>&#x2212;</italic>144.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Morita A, Meyer FB, Laws ER Jr. Symptomatic pituitary metastases. <italic>J Neurosurg</italic>, 1998; 89: 69<italic>&#x2212;</italic>73.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Amer MH, Al-Sarraf M, Vaitkevicius VK. Clinical presentation, natural history and prognostic factors in advanced malignant melanoma. <italic>Surg Gynecol Obstet</italic>, 1979; 149: 687<italic>&#x2212;</italic>692.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Budman DR, Camacho E, Wittes RE. The current causes of death in patients with malignant melanoma. <italic>Eur J Cancer</italic>, 1978; 14: 327<italic>&#x2212;</italic>330.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <label>13)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ferraresi V, Ciccarese M, Zeuli M, Cognetti F. Central nervous system as exclusive site of disease in patients with melanoma: treatment and clinical outcome of two cases. <italic>Melanoma Res</italic>, 2005; 15: 467<italic>&#x2212;</italic>469.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <label>14)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fife KM, Colman MH, Stevens GN, Firth IC, Moon D, Shannon KF, Harman R, Petersen-Schaefer K, Zacest AC, Besser M, Milton GW, McCarthy WH, Thompson JF. Determinants of outcome in melanoma patients with cerebral metastases. <italic>J Clin Oncol</italic>, 2004; 22: 1293<italic>&#x2212;</italic>1300.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <label>15)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hofmann M, Kiecker F, Wurm R, Schlenger L, Budach V, Sterry W, Trefzer U. Temozolomide with or without radiotherapy in melanoma with unresectable brain metastases. <italic>J Neurooncol</italic>, 2006; 76: 59<italic>&#x2212;</italic>64.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <label>16)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Meier S, Baumert BG, Maier T, Wellis G, Burg G, Seifert B, Dummer R. Survival and prognostic factors in patients with brain metastases from malignant melanoma. <italic>Onkologie</italic>, 2004; 27: 145<italic>&#x2212;</italic>149.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <label>17)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Petrovich Z, Yu C, Giannotta SL, O&#x2019;Day S, Apuzzo ML. Survival and pattern of failure in brain metastasis treated with stereotactic gamma knife radiosurgery. <italic>J Neurosurg</italic>, 2002; 97: 499<italic>&#x2212;</italic>506.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <label>18)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Retsas S, Gershuny AR. Central nervous system involvement in malignant melanoma. <italic>Cancer</italic>, 1988; 61: 1926<italic>&#x2212;</italic>1934.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <label>19)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fernandez E, Maira G, Puca A, Vignati A. Multiple intracranial metastases of malignant melanoma with long-term survival. Case report. <italic>J Neurosurg</italic>, 1984; 60: 621<italic>&#x2212;</italic>624.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <label>20)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Noordijk EM, Vecht CJ, Haaxma-Reiche H, Padberg GW, Voormolen JH, Hoekstra FH, Tans JT, Lambooij N, Metsaars JA, Wattendorff AR, Brand R, Hermans J. The choice of treatment of single brain metastasis should be based on extracranial tumor activity and age. <italic>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</italic>, 1994; 29: 711<italic>&#x2212;</italic>717.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <label>21)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Salvati M, Frati A, D&#x2019;Elia A, Pescatori L, Piccirilli M, Pietrantonio A, Fazi M, Santoro A. Single brain metastases from melanoma: remarks on a series of 84 patients. <italic>Neurosurg Rev</italic>, 2011; 14: [Epub ahead of print].</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <label>22)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maiuri F, Cappabianca P, Iaconetta G, Esposito F, Messina A. Simultaneous presentation of meningiomas with other intracranial tumours. <italic>Br J Neurosurg</italic>, 2005; 19: 368<italic>&#x2212;</italic>375.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <label>23)</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Assouline A, Levy A, Chargari C, Lamproglou I, Mazeron JJ, Krzisch C. Whole brain radiotherapy: prognostic factors and results of a radiation boost delivered through a conventional linear accelerator. <italic>Radiother Oncol.</italic> 2011; 99: 214<italic>&#x2212;</italic>217.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
