<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Med Res</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J. Med. Res</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJMR</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Indian Journal of Medical Research</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0971-5916</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0975-9174</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25488455</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4277147</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJMR-140-565</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Correspondence</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A report on the presence of GES-5 extended spectrum beta-lactamase producing <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> associated with urinary tract infection from north-east India</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Maurya</surname>
            <given-names>Anand Prakash</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Choudhury</surname>
            <given-names>Debarati</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Talukdar</surname>
            <given-names>Anupam Das</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dhar (Chanda)</surname>
            <given-names>Anupam</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chakravarty</surname>
            <given-names>Atanu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bhattacharjee</surname>
            <given-names>Amitabha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Microbiology, Assam University, Silchar 788 011, India</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Life Science &amp; Bioinformatics, Assam University, Silchar 788 011, India</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Microbiology, Silchar Medical College &amp; Hospital, Silchar 788 014, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><italic>For correspondence</italic>: <email xlink:href="ab0404@gmail.com">ab0404@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>140</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>565</fpage>
      <lpage>567</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Indian Journal of Medical Research</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Sir,</p>
    <p>Guiana extended spectrum (GES) beta lactamase belongs to molecular class A<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> frequently found in Gram-negative rods by and large in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> in addition to other members of <italic>Enterobacteriacae</italic><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>. Till date, only a few studies on epidemiology and environmental burden of GES-type ESBLs have been published<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>.</p>
    <p>We present the occurrence of <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> harbouring <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> isolated from human urine specimen from north-east India.</p>
    <p>The study was conducted in the department of Microbiology, Assam University, Silchar, Assam, India, from January to December 2012. The first isolate (AM 328) was obtained from the urine sample of a 4 month old female in May 2012 and the second isolate (AM 438) was recovered from the urine of a 39-year-old male in July 2012 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table</xref>). These patients attended the Out Patient Department of Silchar Medical College and Hospital, Silchar, Assam and diagnosed with urinary tract infection. The selection of the samples was based on the initial screening of isolates for the presence of ESBL<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. Antimicrobial susceptibility was determined by Kirby Bauer disc diffusion method on Muller-Hinton agar plates<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. The following antibiotics were used for antimicrobial susceptibility: cefopodoxime (10 &#x3BC;g), amikacin (30 &#x3BC;g), gentamicin (10 &#x3BC;g), ciprofloxacin (30 &#x3BC;g), trimithoprim/dulphamethoxazole (1.25/23.75 &#x3BC;g), tigecycline (15 &#x3BC;g), cefepime (30 &#x3BC;g), imipenem (10 &#x3BC;g), meropenem (10 &#x3BC;g), ceftriaxone (30 &#x3BC;g), aztreonam (30 &#x3BC;g) and cefoxitin (30 &#x3BC;g). Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) of various antibiotics [cefotaxime, ceftazidime, Ceftriazone, cefepime, imipenem, meropenem, ertapenem and aztreonam (Hi-Media, Mumbai, India] were determined on Muller Hinton agar plates containing 2,4, 8, 16, 32, 64, 128, 256 mg/l of antibiotics, by agar dilution method according to Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidelines<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>.</p>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Clinical information and molecular details of <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> carrying <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> urinary isolates</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="IJMR-140-565-g001"/>
    </table-wrap>
    <p>For amplification and characterization of <italic>bla</italic><sub>ESBL</sub> genes, a set of six primers were used: <italic>bla</italic><sub>TEM</sub>, <italic>bla</italic><sub>CTX-M</sub>, <italic>bla</italic><sub>SHV</sub>, <italic>bla</italic><sub>OXA-2</sub>, <italic>bla</italic><sub>OXA-10</sub> and <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES</sub> as described previously<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>. Reactions were run under the following conditions: initial denaturation 94&#xB0;C for 5 min, 33 cycles at 94&#xB0;C for 35 sec, 51&#xB0;C for one min, 72&#xB0;C for one min and final extension at 72&#xB0;C for seven min. PCR product was purified by Gene Jet PCR purification Kit (Thermo Scientific, Lithuania); 30 &#x3BC;l of purified products were used for sequencing along with <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES</sub>. Efflux pump activity of the isolates was phenotypically detected by double disc synergy test<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> using imipenem (10 &#x3BC;g), ertapenem (10 &#x3BC;g) and CCCP (100mM) (carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone) (Hi-Media, Mumbai, India) as described earlier<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>. MIC reduction assay was performed using imipenem and ertapenem alone and in combination with CCCP at a concentration 20 &#x3BC;g/ml<sup>5</sup>. For detection of class 1 and class 2 integron, integrase gene PCR were performed as described previously<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. For detection of association of gene cassette with <italic>bla</italic><sub>ESBL</sub> gene, two PCR reactions were carried out, one with HS287 and <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-1-B</sub>, another with HS286 and <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-1-B</sub><xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>. The amplified products were further sequenced. Transformation was carried out using <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> JM107 as recipient. Transformants were selected on Luria-Bertani (L-B) agar (Hi-Media, Mumbai, India) plates containing 0.5 mg/l cefotaxime. L-B agar with and without cefotaxime 0.5 mg/l control plate was used. Conjugation experiments were performed between clinical isolates as donors and a streptomycin resistant <italic>E. coli</italic> recipient strain B (Genei, Banglore). Overnight culture of the bacteria was diluted in L-B broth and was grown at 37 &#xB0;C till the optical density (O.D.) of the reciepient and donor culture reached 0.8-0.9 at A<sub>600</sub> absorbance. Donor and recipient cells were mixed at 1:5 donor-to-recipient ratios and transconjugants were selected on cefotaxime (0.5 mg/l) and streptomycin (800 mg/l) agar plates; 1.0 &#x3BC;l of each sample was used for plasmid profiling and analysed by agarose gel electrophoresis (1% agarose, Hi-Media, Mumbai, India). For the detection of incompatibility group type of plasmid in all <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> producing strains, PCR based replicon typing was carried out targeting 18 different replicon types, to perform five multiplex and three simplex PCRs to amplify the FIA, FIB, FIC, HI1, HI2, I1/I&#x3B3;, L/M, N, P, W, T, A/C, K, B/O, X, Y, F and FIIA replicons as described previously<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>. Typing of <italic>bla</italic><sub>OXA-2</sub> harbouring isolates was done by Enterobacterial repetitive intergenic consensus sequences PCR<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>.</p>
    <p>When characterized genotypically, the first isolate AM 328 possessed multiple beta lactamase genes, harboured <italic>CTX-M</italic>, <italic>SHV</italic> and <italic>GES</italic> while the second isolate AM 438 harboured only single <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES</sub> gene. Sequencing of the PCR product with the GES primers revealed that both the isolates harboured a <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> variant gene. Efflux pump mediated carbapenem resistance was also noticed in both isolates. A sharp reduction in MIC was observed against ertapenem when CCCP was added at a fixed concentration of 20 &#x3BC;g/ml. Class 1 integron was found in both isolates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table</xref>). Sequencing results confirmed that <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> was class 1 integron borne. Both isolates were carrying multiple plasmids. A plasmid of ~ 40 Kb was common in both. Incompatibility typing of the first isolate showed that there was diverse Incompatibility groups Inc groups: I1/I&#x3B3;, FIA, FIB, W, FIC, FrepB and K while in the second isolate group I1/I&#x3B3;, FIA, FIB, W, FIC and FrepB were found (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table</xref>). Transformation was successful with AM-438 where it was found that <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> was located within W Inc type plasmid. However, these were not conjugatively transferable to <italic>E. coli</italic>. The first isolate was found to be susceptible to imipenem and cefoxitin and the second isolate showed suceptibility against imipenem, meropenem and gentamicin. While the first isolate showed MIC for all tested antibiotics as &gt;256 mg/l, the second isolate showed 64 mg/l to carbapenems and monobactam and 32 mg/l to cephalosporins. ERIC PCR result showed that both isolates belonged to diverse clonal types.</p>
    <p>The presence of GES-5 gene has been frequently detected in <italic>E. coli</italic><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <italic>Klesbsiella pneumoniae</italic><xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic><xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>.</p>
    <p>In agreement with the current study, integron mediated GES-5 has been earlier reported from other parts of the Asia<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>. However, in our study, presence of <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> was traced from the community isolate which emphasized the need for epidemiological investigation, origin and evolution of this resistant determinant from this geographical location. Unlike the previous concept<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, the studied isolates were phenotypically susceptible to carbapenem, whereas presence of efflux pump activity was noticed with ertapenem.</p>
    <p>In conclusion, the presence of <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> is perhaps the first report from this part of India. Presence of this rare type ESBL in community and their presence within plasmid require further investigation for potential transmission dynamics and proper therapeutic alternatives.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence of Ambler class A and D &#x3B2;- lactamases among clinical isolates of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> in Korea</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>122</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15890715</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nordmann</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guibert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extended-spectrum beta-lactamases in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>128</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9738828</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <article-title>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI). Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing; 21st Informational Supplement S21</article-title>
          <year>2011</year>
          <publisher-loc>M100, Wayne, PA, USA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>CLSI</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quale</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bratu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Landman</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heddurshetti</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular epidemiology and mechanisms of carbapenem resistance in <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> endemic in New York City</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>214</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12856214</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kriengkauykiat</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Porter</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lomovskaya</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong-Beringer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Use of an efflux pump inhibitor to determine the prevalence of efflux pump-mediated fluoroquinolone resistance and multidrug resistance in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title>
          <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>565</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15673734</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koeleman</surname>
              <given-names>JGM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stoof</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Der bijl</surname>
              <given-names>MWV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vandenbroucke-grauls</surname>
              <given-names>CMJE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Savelkoul</surname>
              <given-names>PHM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of epidemic strains of <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> by integrase gene PCR</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11136740</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stokes</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holmes</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nield</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holley</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nevalainen</surname>
              <given-names>KMH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mabbutt</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gene cassette PCR: Sequence-independent recovery of entire genes from environmental DNA</article-title>
          <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>5240</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11679351</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carattoli</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bertini</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villa</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falbo</surname>
              <given-names>VV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hopkins</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Threlfall</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of plasmids by PCR-based replicon typing</article-title>
          <source>J Microbiol Methods</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>219</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15935499</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Versalovic</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koeuth</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lupski</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Distribution of repetitive DNA sequences in eubacteria and application to fingerprinting of bacterial genomes</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acid Res</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>6823</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1762913</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vourli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giakkoupi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miriagou</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tzelepi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vatopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tzouvelekis</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel GES/IBC extended spectrum beta-lactamase variants with carbapenemase activity in clinical enterobacteria</article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>234</volume>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15135524</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bae</surname>
              <given-names>IK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeong</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Emergence of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> sequence type ST131 carrying both the <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub> and <italic>bla</italic><sub>CTX-M-15</sub> Genes</article-title>
          <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>2974</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21444709</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jeong</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bae</surname>
              <given-names>IK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>First outbreak of <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> clinical isolates producing GES-5 and SHV-12 extended spectrum beta-lactamases in Korea</article-title>
          <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>4809</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16251340</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cai</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mi</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> isolate producing the GES-5 extended-spectrum beta-lactamase</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>1261</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16617065</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Polotto</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casella</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>MGDL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xFA;bio</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nogueira</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> harboring <italic>bla</italic><sub>CTX-M-2</sub>, <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-1</sub> and <italic>bla</italic><sub>GES-5</sub>, <italic>bla</italic><sub>IMP-1</sub> and <italic>bla</italic><sub>SPM-1</sub> causing infections in Brazilian tertiary-care hospital</article-title>
          <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>176</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22863113</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Queenan</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bush</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carbapenemases: the versatile &#x3B2;-Lactamases</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>440</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630334</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
