<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arq. Bras. Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cardiologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0066-782X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-4170</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25993598</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4415871</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/abc.20140215</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinicoradiological Session</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Case 4/2015 A 48-year-old Male Patient with Coarctation of the Aorta,
Bicuspid Aortic Valve and Normal Ascending Aorta</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Atik</surname>
            <given-names>Edmar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Arrieta</surname>
            <given-names>Raul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Coelho</surname>
            <given-names>Ot&#xE1;vio Rizzi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff01"> Instituto do Cora&#xE7;&#xE3;o, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade
de S&#xE3;o Paulo &#x2013; USP, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP - Brazil</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing Address: Edmar Atik,</bold> Rua Dona Adma Jafet, 74,
conj. 73, Bela Vista. Postal Code 01308-050. S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP &#x2013; Brazil. E-mail:
<email>eatik@cardiol.br</email>; <email>conatik@incor.usp.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>104</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>e27</fpage>
      <lpage>e29</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution NonCommercial License which permits unrestricted noncommercial
use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium provided the original work is
properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Coarctation of Aorta, Bicuspid Aortic Stenosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Percutaneous</kwd>
        <kwd>Aortic Treatment</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><bold>Clinical data</bold>: The patient reported that, at the age of 23 years, he had been
diagnosed with hypertension, which was controlled with five antihypertensive medications.
An ultrasound study performed one month ago detected low blood flow through the abdominal
aorta. Coarctation of the aorta was suspected, and further confirmed by angiographic CT
scan. He had no cardiovascular complaints, but had a sedentary lifestyle.</p>
    <p><bold>Physical examination</bold>: normal breathing; acyanotic; brisk pulses in upper
limbs, absent in lower limbs. Weight:&#xA0;77 kg; height: 168 cm; Blood pressure - BP&#xA0;=&#xA0;right
arm = left arm = 125/75 mmHg; BP legs = 75 mmHg; heart rate - HR:&#xA0;86&#xA0;bpm. Aorta clearly
palpable on the suprasternal notch. Mild grade 1/4 systolic murmur on the suprasternal
notch.</p>
    <p>Apical impulse not palpable in the precordium; absence of systolic impulses on the left
sternal border. Normal heart sounds; grade 1/4 coarse systolic murmur in the aortic area,
with no irradiation. No murmurs in the back. Liver not palpable.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Laboratory tests</title>
      <p><bold>Electrocardiogram:</bold> Normal sinus rhythm, no chamber overload. Sokoloff index
= 20 mm; mild ventricular repolarization abnormality. Left anterior hemiblock and septal
fibrosis. PA: +60&#xBA;; QRSA: -45&#xBA;; TA: +100&#xBA; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Chest radiography showing normal cardiac silhouette. 40 x 18-mm stent positioned
in the beginning of the descending aorta, corresponding to the arch of the
pulmonary artery. Hyperdensity can be observed in the lower border of some ribs.
On electrocardiogram, left anterior hemiblock, septal fibrosis and upper lateral
ischemia.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-104-04-0e27-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p><bold>Chest radiograph:</bold> Normal cardiac silhouette (cardiothoracic ratio: 0.48).
Normal pulmonary vascular network and concave arch of pulmonary artery. The posterior
aortic arch was not bulged; hyperdensity in some rib borders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
      <p><bold>Echocardiogram: </bold>Bicuspid aortic valve with maximum and mean pressure
gradient of 14 and 7 mmHg, respectively. The ascending aorta (AscAo) was not dilated (35
mm); aortic arch = 37 mm; narrowing in the isthmic region (3 mm), with pressure gradient
of 51 mmHg. Cardiac chambers of normal size. No myocardial hypertrophy; septum and
posterior wall with 9-mm thickness. Normal left ventricular function (69%).</p>
      <p><bold>CT angiography of the aorta:</bold> AscAo = 40 mm; aortic crossing and descending
aorta (DescAo) = 32 mm; narrowing at isthmus = 3 mm and at diaphragm = 25 mm. Marked
collateral circulation, corresponding to the intercostal, bronchial and mammary
arteries.</p>
      <p><bold>Cardiac catheterization:</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>).
Pressure levels were as follows: left ventricle - LV = 160/12, AscAo = 130/80 and DescAo
= 90/80 mmHg. Angiography showed clear narrowing at the aortic isthmus of approximately
2.5 cm past the left subclavian artery, with no AscAo or DescAo dilatation distal to the
obstruction.</p>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Upper angiographic images (A and B) show marked isthmic coarctation of the aorta
with normal ascending aorta, and exuberant collateral circulation; C and D show
images of the descending aorta after placement of a 40 x 18-mm stent, with uniform
diameters and no post-stenotic dilatation.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-104-04-0e27-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <p><bold>Clinical diagnosis:</bold> Severe coarctation of the aorta at the isthmic region
and mild aortic valve stenosis in bicuspid valve with no AscAo dilatation or
hypertrophy, in natural course.</p>
      <p><bold>Clinical reasoning:</bold> The clinical elements of coarctation of the aorta are
clear and easy to identify, and are mainly represented by contrasting pulses and BP
between the upper and lower limbs, as occurred in this case, although detected late by
indirect means of abdominal ultrasound. Noteworthy, despite the long-standing heart
disease with pressure overload, no myocardial hypertrophy, signs of electric overload or
symptoms are observed. This results from the fact that, in this obstructive anomaly,
there is formation of collateral vessels that deviate blood in order to nourish the
general circulation. Chest radiograph with normal cardiac silhouette expresses preserved
ventricular function, and surprisingly there is no AscAo dilatation despite the presence
of bicuspid aortic valve and coarctation of the aorta.</p>
      <p><bold>Differential diagnosis:</bold> Aortic obstructions in adulthood usually result
from previous aortitis, as occurs in Takayasu and Kawasaki disease, as well as in
connective tissue and infectious diseases.</p>
      <p><bold>Management:</bold> In view of the long-standing systolic impact, even without
myocardial hypertrophy and with increased pressures in the proximal aorta circuit,
operation is mandatory aiming at relieving the arterial obstruction, which would imply a
greater possibility of development of myocardial fibrosis, heart failure, arrhythmias
and earlier death. Dilatation of the isthmic region was chosen using therapeutic cardiac
catheterization from the right femoral artery with placement of a 40 x 18-mm stent just
past the origin of the left subclavian artery. Systolic BP immediately decreased to 100
mmHg even without the use of antihypertensive drugs. Adequate enlargement of the region
was achieved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>) with equalization of
pressures between limbs. The mild systolic murmur of aortic valve stenosis remained
unchanged.</p>
      <p><bold>Commentaries:</bold> Cardiac compensation with maintained antegrade flow, in
coarctation of the aorta, is achieved by the myocardial hypertrophy and/or development
of collateral circulation, which alleviates the aortic obstruction and satisfactorily
nourishes the circulation. In this case, the marked aortic obstruction detected in
adulthood and manifested by hypertension, was compensated by exuberant collateral
circulation. Hence the favorable outcome until the fifth decade of life. Left anterior
hemiblock and septal fibrosis on the electrocardiogram are difficult to explain in the
absence of myocardial hypertrophy. Even when hemodynamically compensated, this
obstructive anomaly should be treated early so as to prevent an unfavorable outcome in
relation to the development of myocardial fibrosis, arrhythmias and heart failure. In
the course of bicuspid aortic valve, unfavorable elements such as AscAo dilatation
arise, and these invariably should be treated surgically in a timely manner. However, in
this patient, the expected aortic dilatation was not observed, and this makes a good
outcome possible even for a longer term. Aortic dilatation seems to be more related to
inherent factors of the arterial wall (adequate morphology of the parietal muscle) than
to hemodynamic aspects<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>Reference</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrini</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caidahl</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eriksson</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liska</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eriksson</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bicuspid aortic valve leaflet morphology in relation to aortic root
morphology: a study of 300 patients undergoing open-heart surgery</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>e118</fpage>
          <lpage>e124</lpage>
          <comment>Erratum in: Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2012;41(2):471</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21620721</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
