<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24646603</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4143646</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13-0471</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.13-0471</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Surgery</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Note</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Vaginal Cyst Causing Dysuria and Dyschezia in a Bitch</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>WATANABE</surname>
            <given-names>Toshifumi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>MISHINA</surname>
            <given-names>Mika</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SAKURAI</surname>
            <given-names>Yohei</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Department of Nephrology-Urology, Azabu University
Veterinary Teaching Hospital, 1&#x2013;17&#x2013;71 Fuchinobe, Chuo-ku, Sagamihara-shi, Kanagawa
252&#x2013;5201, Japan</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Watanabe, T., Azabu University
Veterinary Teaching Hospital, 1&#x2013;17&#x2013;71 Fuchinobe, Chuo-ku, Sagamihara-shi, Kanagawa
252&#x2013;5201, Japan. e-mail: <email xlink:href="watanabe@azabu-u.ac.jp">watanabe@azabu-u.ac.jp</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>76</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>1039</fpage>
      <lpage>1043</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2014 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>ABSTRACT</title>
        <p>A 9-year-old female dog was
referred to Azabu University Veterinary Teaching Hospital for dysuria and dyschezia after
ovariohysterectomy. After a series of diagnostic imaging, vaginal obstruction was
suspected by vaginal fluid retention. Surgical repair was attempted three times to
establish patency through the vagina and the vestibule by episiotomy and laparotomy.
Another laparotomy was performed to remove the entire vaginal mucosal layer to prevent
recurrence, which resulted in favorable outcome. Histopathological examination revealed
that the resected tissue was a cyst originated from mesonephric duct remnant. In the
present case, the cyst was curable by the entire resection of the cyst lining membrane,
which could eradicate all the secretory cells with least damage to the urethral
vasculature and innervation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>canine</kwd>
        <kwd>dysuria</kwd>
        <kwd>vaginal cyst</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A vaginal cyst is a formation of cystic structure within the vaginal wall. It may arise from
a remnant of the embryonic urogenital duct or an entrapment of the mucosal epithelium under
the mucosal layer by trauma or surgery [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Vaginal cysts
are classified based on the type of epithelial cells that are lining the cyst, such as
M&#xFC;llerian cysts, Gartner&#x2019;s ducts cysts and epithelial inclusion cysts [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In humans, the majority of
vaginal cysts are asymptomatic, however, which may cause pain, dysuria and/or dystocia due to
their enlargement. Therefore, surgical intervention, such as cystectomy and marsupialization,
is required [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In veterinary medicine, vaginal cysts are known to be one of common reproductive
failure in cattle [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], which are rarely seen in dogs
[<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. As in
humans, canine vaginal cysts are either asymptomatic or symptomatic depending on the size
[<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], and surgical repair is required for symptomatic
cysts [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Laparotomic cystectomy can be applied to
remove the cysts [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], however, one study reports that
marsupialization is preferred to keep the urinal vasculature and innervation intact [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In the present study, we report a case of a vaginal cyst
observed in a dog experiencing dysuria and dyschezia, which was successfully controlled by
entire resection of the cyst lining membrane.</p>
    <p>A 9-year-old, female Shih Tzu dog, weighing 3.74 kg (body condition score of 2/5), was
presented to a referral veterinary clinic for neutering. Ovariohysterectomy was performed, and
then, the uterine cervix was found enlarged in a ball-like shape, 5 cm in diameter. The
enlarged uterine cervix was removed at its most caudal end with the ovaries and uterine horns.
It was filled with brown-colored and viscous sterile fluid, and the cervical lining membrane
was smooth without any evidence of mass. The ovaries and uterus horns were not submitted for
histopathological examination. The dog developed dysuria on the following day of the
ovariohysterectomy and was followed by dyschezia two weeks later. A 6 cm &#xD7; 3 cm non-echogenic mass was detected caudal to the bladder by
abdominal ultrasonography, and then, the dog was referred to Azabu University Veterinary
Teaching Hospital for detailed evaluation and treatment (Day 0).</p>
    <p>During physical examination, a 5-cm mass was palpated caudal to the bladder. Results of CBC
and serum chemistry were within reference range. By survey radiography, the soft tissue
density mass was detected caudal to the bladder, and the colon was displaced dorsally due to
its presence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig.
1A</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>(A) A lateral radiograph of the abdomen. The soft tissue density mass (arrowhead) was
observed caudal to bladder (B), and the colon was displaced dorsally due to the presence
of the mass. (B) A lateral vaginourethrogram showing a contrast filling defect in the
vagina. The contrast medium stopped at the cranial end of the vestibule (arrow),
indicating blind ending of the vestibule. The urethra was displaced ventrally due to the
presence of the mass.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1039-g001"/></fig>). Abdominal ultrasonography revealed a non-echogenic fluid-filled structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Caudal abdominal ultrasonography. There was a non-echogenic fluid-filled mass (M)
caudal to the bladder (B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1039-g002"/></fig>). The aspirated fluid was brown-colored and viscous, and neutrophils and nucleated
cornified epithelial cells were also detected by cytology. The fluid was negative for
bacterial culture. Vaginourethrography was then performed, contrast medium did not fill the
vagina, and ventral displacement of the urethra was also evident (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1B</xref>). Based on these findings, we suspected that
dysuria and dyschezia were caused by vaginal obstruction, which led to the vaginal fluid
retention and mechanical compression of the urethra and the colon.</p>
    <p>On Day 2, an episiotomy was performed to examine the cause of the vaginal obstruction and to
drain the cyst under anesthesia. After pretreatment with 0.025 mg/kg atropine sulfate
(ATROPINE SULFATE Injection 0.5 mg, Mitsubishi Tanabe Pharma, Osaka, Japan), SC, and
anesthetic induction with 6 mg/kg propofol (1% Propofol Injection, Mylan Seiyaku, Tokyo,
Japan), IV, the patient was intubated and maintained on isoflurane (ISOFLU<sup>&#xAE;</sup>, DS
Pharma Animal Health, Osaka, Japan). Antibiotic, cefovecin sodium 8 mg/kg (CONVENIA<sup>&#xAE;</sup>, Pfizer, Tokyo, Japan), was administered
subcutaneously before the surgical examination. The patient was positioned in ventral
recumbency with the pelvic limbs hanged over the edge of the table. After an incision in the
perineum, it was visually confirmed that the vestibule was blind ending cranially to the
external urethral orifice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3A</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Images at the first surgery. (A) The vaginal vestibule was blind ending cranially to
the external urethral orifice. (B) Marsupialization was performed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1039-g003"/></fig>). The smooth and blind end was cut open and removed with forceps, the
cranial part was incised with a scalpel, and the fluid ran out of the vagina. The fluid was
withdrawn, and the incision was extended to visualize the vaginal mucosa. Marsupialization was
then performed by suturing the vaginal mucosa and the incised vestibular mucosa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p>
    <p>Postoperatively, there was an improvement in urination and defication. However, on Day 7,
dysuria and dyschezia developed again, and recurrence of vaginal fluid retention was detected
by the abdominal ultrasonography. Therefore, an exploratory laparotomy was performed on Day 9
to further investigate the cause of fluid retention, pretreatment and anesthesia as previously
explained. The patient was positioned in dorsal recumbency, and the abdominal cavity was
exposed by a median incision in the lower abdomen. It was found that a distended vagina was
severely adhered to the bladder neck and the urethra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_004">Fig. 4</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_004" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>An image at the second surgery. The distended vagina was severely adhered to the
bladder neck and urethra (arrowhead).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1039-g004"/></fig>). The bladder was inverted to examine the cranial part of the vagina, but there was no
evident sign of stump pyometra, cysts or any other abnormalities that could cause the vaginal
fluid retention. The bladder was returned to its original position, and a further 2-cm
incision was made in the ventral wall of the vagina to place drainage. Forceps were inserted
through the incision and advanced caudally to re-establish the patency through the vagina and
the vestibule. An 8-French balloon catheter (All Silicone Foley Balloon Catheter, Create
Medic, Yokohama, Japan) was inserted from the vulva by guiding its tip with forceps and placed
in the vagina. The vaginal incision was sutured with 3-0 polyglyconate, and the laparotomy was
closed in a standard manner.</p>
    <p>Urination and defecation improved postoperatively. <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> was
detected by bacterial culture, using the vaginal fluid and urine samples which were obtained
during the operation. Based on drug susceptibility test, 5 mg/kg imipenem hydrate and cilastatin sodium (TIENAM<sup>&#xAE;</sup> for
Intravenous Drip Infusion 0.25 g, MSD, Tokyo, Japan) was administered intravenously after the
surgery. During hospitalization, the vagina was washed with saline using a balloon catheter
twice a day. The amount of vaginal fluid gradually decreased. On Day 16, only a minimal amount
of vaginal fluid was detected by abdominal ultrasonography, so the patient was discharged
after removing the catheter on the same day. However, on Day 28, dysuria and dyschezia
recurred. Abdominal ultrasonography revealed an enlarged vagina to the size of 6 cm &#xD7; 3 cm. An
attempt to insert a catheter through the vulva into the vagina was unsuccessful, indicating
that due to failure of the re-establishment of patency, another vaginotomy was performed on
Day 37.</p>
    <p>After performing the anesthetic procedure as previously explained, the patient was positioned
in ventral recumbency. When the vestibule was exposed by episiotomy, it was evident that the
marsupialized opening had been fully closed. The closure was incised, and forceps were
advanced cranially to separate the tissue. A membranous structure was visually confirmed
deeper in the vagina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_005">Fig.
5A</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_005" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Images at the third surgery. (A) A membrane-like structure was present in the cranial
vagina. (B) The cyst lining (arrow) was separated from the serous membrane
(arrowhead).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1039-g005"/></fig>). The patient was repositioned in dorsal recumbency for a lower median laparotomy to
re-establish the patency, since the incision was unable to perform due to its thickness.
Similar to the second surgery, a 2-cm incision was made in the ventral wall of the vagina, and
forceps were advanced caudally, however, the vestibule was not reachable at this time. The
incision was extended cranially and caudally to expose the vaginal mucosa, and the entire
mucosal layer was separated from the serosa and fully removed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_005">Fig. 5B</xref>). The serous membrane was not sutured, and the
abdomen was closed in the standard manner.</p>
    <p>Histopathological examination of the resected tissue with H&amp;E staining revealed a lack of
the stratified squamous epithelial lining, which is normally seen in the vaginal mucosa.
Instead, the tissue was lined with simple cuboidal and columnar epithelia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_006">Fig. 6A</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_006" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Histopathological images of the cyst. H&amp;E staining, &#xD7; 400. (A) The cyst was lined
with simple cuboidal and columnar epithelial cells. (B) A glandular structure was
present under the mucosal layer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1039-g006"/></fig>). Moreover, under the mucosal layer, some plasma cells, lymphocytes and macrophages as
well as glandular structures were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_006">Fig.
6B</xref>). From these findings, chronic active inflammation was diagnosed in the cystic
structure, and the site of cyst formation suggested that the resected tissue may be a remnant
of a duplicated bladder, Gartner&#x2019;s duct or some other remnant structure originated from the
mesonephric duct.</p>
    <p>After the third surgery, no recurrence of the cyst was detected. Although the patient
experienced incontinence while sleeping, the symptom gradually subsided and resolved after six
months by administration of clenbuterol hydrochloride 10 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>g/head
(SPIROPENT<sup>&#xAE;</sup> Tablet 10 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>g, Teijin Pharma, Tokyo, Japan), PO, bid.
After the surgery, this patient remained stable with no further problems regarding to
urination and defication.</p>
    <p>In the present case, a Gartner&#x2019;s duct cyst was indicated as the main cause of dysuria and
dyschezia. During the embryonic development, the mesonephric duct differentiates into the
deferent duct in males. It normally regresses in female mammals, however, the caudal part may
persist as a Gartner&#x2019;s duct in the vaginal wall [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. A Gartner&#x2019;s duct cyst is formed as a result of
secretion from the glandular cells present in the Gartner&#x2019;s duct [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. As the secretions accumulated
by the inflammation of the cyst caused by surgical invasion, such as ovariohysterectomy, the
cyst may enlarge and cause mechanical interference with other organs, such as the urethra and
the colon, and this may result in dysuria and dyschezia as seen in the present case.</p>
    <p>In the present case, since vaginal obstruction was strongly suspected by the first
vaginourethrography and intraoperative findings at the first surgery, the presence of a
Gartner&#x2019;s duct cyst was not diagnosed. Clinical symptoms and findings, such as pain, dysuria
and dyschezia, may develop in both vaginal obstruction and Gartner&#x2019;s duct cysts due to
physical urethral and/or intestinal compression [<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Imaging findings are also similar, both
typically being detected as a mass-like opacity caudal to the bladder by radiographs, and a
non-echogenic fluid-filled structure is detected by ultrasonography. On the other hand,
vaginography may play a key role to differentiate vaginal obstruction from Gartner&#x2019;s duct
cyst. A contrast-filled defect in the vagina is typical for vaginal obstruction, while with a
Gartner&#x2019;s duct cyst, the vaginal part caudal to the cyst should be easily seen. In the present
case, the vagina was not filled with the contrast medium, which leads to difficulty in making
a diagnosis of vaginal cyst (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_007">Fig. 7</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_007" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>A schematic image of the Gartner&#x2019;s duct cyst observed in the present case.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-1039-g007"/></fig>).</p>
    <p>Marsupialization has been recommended for surgical repair of vaginal cysts by Holt [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Although it is known to be the least invasive technique,
it is not suitable for small-breed dogs and cysts which are located to the cranial part of the
vagina. This can be explained that suturing the cyst wall and vaginal mucosa would be
technically difficult due to the limited operative field. The glandular cells in the cysts may
continue to secrete mucosal fluid even after the surgery. Thus, if the marsupialized opening
is fully closed, there exists a risk of recurrence. Cystectomy would be curative surgical
method, but if there is a severe adhesion with the urethra, colon and/or other surrounding
structures, urethral blood vessels and nerves may be damaged during intraoperative
manipulation of a cyst that is located caudal to the urethra [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p>
    <p>In the present case, since marsupialization and cystectomy were difficult, only the cyst
lining membrane was removed leaving the serous membrane. However, recurrence of cyst
distention has not been observed. Although transient incontinence was experienced
postoperatively due to surgical invasion, the patient was able to urinate and defecate without
any problems at Day 650. We attribute this successful outcome to the complete eradication of
glandular cells in the cyst lining membrane, as well as the minimally invasive approach to
preserve the surrounding tissues without damaging the urethral vasculature and innervation.
Thus, removal of the cyst lining membrane may be a noble and effective option for symptomatic
vaginal cysts with adhesions to the surrounding structures.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cauvin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year>
<article-title>Vaginal cysts causing tenesmus in a
bitch</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Small Anim.
Pract.</italic></source><volume>36</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>324</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.1995.tb02938.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7474963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Crum</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicci</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>: pp. 215&#x2013;216. Diagnostic Gynecologic and Obstetric
Pathology, 2nd ed., Saunders, Philadelphia.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ginther</surname><given-names>O. J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1965</year>
<article-title>Segmental aplasia of the Mullerian ducts
(white heifer disease) in a White Shorthorn heifer</article-title>. <source><italic>J.
Am. Vet. Med. Assoc.</italic></source><volume>146</volume>:
<fpage>133</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>137</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14231096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year>
<article-title>Urinary retention in a
bitch</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet. Rec.</italic></source><volume>132</volume>:
<fpage>592</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.132.23.592-a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8337806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year>
<article-title>A Gartner duct cyst of the vagina causing
dysuria and dyschezia in a Yorkshire Terrier</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet.
Sci.</italic></source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>429</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4142/jvs.2007.8.4.427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17993759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Mcgeady</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>FitzPatrick</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year> Genital ducts. pp. 249&#x2013;251. <italic>In</italic>:
Veterinary Embryology. Wiley-Blackwell, Hoboken.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Persaud</surname><given-names>T. V. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torchia</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year> Development of Genital Ducts. pp. 269&#x2013;273.
<italic>In</italic>: The Developing Human, 9th ed., Saunders,
Philadelphia.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Ostrzenski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year>: pp. 220&#x2013;221. Gynecology: Integrating Conventional,
Complementary, and Natural Alternative Therapy. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins,
Philadelphia.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Tsumagari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeishi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Memon</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>
<article-title>A case of a bitch with imperforate hymen
and hydrocolpos</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet. Med.
Sci.</italic></source><volume>63</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>477</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.63.475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11346188</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Viehoff</surname><given-names>F. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sjollema</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>
<article-title>Hydrocolpos in dog: surgical treatment in
two cases</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Small Anim.
Pract.</italic></source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>404</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>407</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2003.tb00176.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14510330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
