<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Orthop Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Orthop Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CIOS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinics in Orthopedic Surgery</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2005-291X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2005-4408</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Orthopaedic Association</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26640638</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4667123</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4055/cios.2015.7.4.519</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>High Grade Infective Spondylolisthesis of Cervical Spine Secondary to Tuberculosis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hadgaonkar</surname>
            <given-names>Shailesh</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Shah</surname>
            <given-names>Kunal</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shyam</surname>
            <given-names>Ashok</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sancheti</surname>
            <given-names>Parag</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">Sancheti Institute for Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, Pune, India.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Correspondence to: Kunal Shah, MS. Sancheti Institute for Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, 16 Shivajinagar, Pune, India. Tel: +91-96-3736-2911, Fax: +91-20-2553-0333, <email>orthokunal@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>519</fpage>
      <lpage>522</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015 by The Korean Orthopaedic Association</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Spondylolisthesis coexisting with tuberculosis is rarely reported. There is a controversy whether spondylolisthesis coexists or precedes tuberculosis. Few cases of pathological spondylolisthesis secondary to tuberculous spondylodiscitis have been reported in the lumbar and lumbosacral spine. All cases in the literature presented as anterolisthesis, except one which presented as posterolisthesis of lumbar spine. Spondylolisthesis in the cervical spine is mainly degenerative and traumatic. Spondylolisthesis due to tuberculosis is not reported in the lower cervical spine. The exact mechanism of such an occurrence of spondylolisthesis with tuberculosis is sparsely reported in the literature and inadequately understood. We report a rare case of high grade pathological posterolisthesis of the lower cervical spine due to tubercular spondylodiscitis in a 67-year-old woman managed surgically with a three-year follow-up period. This case highlights the varied and complex presentation of tuberculosis of the lower cervical spine and gives insight into its pathogenesis, diagnosis, and management.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Spondylolisthesis</kwd>
        <kwd>Tuberculosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Subaxial spine</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Tuberculosis rarely involves the lower cervical spine, which has a high association with neurological complications.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1)</xref> Its presentation varies in children and adults. The adult type is a localized disease with the involvement of a vertebral body and less pus formation as compared to the pediatric version.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1)</xref> Spondylolisthesis is rarely seen in the cervical spine as compared to the lumbar spine and is most commonly degenerative.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref> Although pathological spondylolisthesis due to various causes has been described in the cervical spine, tuberculous spondylolisthesis has not been described.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref> Spondylolisthesis in case of tuberculosis has been described in lumbar or lumbosacral spine.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref> Anterolisthesis the common presentation.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref> There is only one report of posterolisthesis in a tuberculous lumbar spine.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref> There is controversy as to whether spondylolisthesis coexists or precedes the tuberculosis of spine and the exact mechanism of this has been inadequately described in the literature.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3)</xref></p>
    <p>We report a rare adult type of paradiscal lower cervical tuberculous infection with posterolisthesis in a 67-year-old female which was managed surgically with a three-year follow-up period. This case highlights the varied and complex presentation of cervical tuberculosis and gives insight into its pathogenesis, diagnosis, and management.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 67-year-old female patient presented with neck pain and stiffness for the past 4 months. The neck pain radiated to both upper limbs and was associated with tingling and numbness. The symptoms had increased in intensity over the past month.</p>
      <p>The patient had constitutional symptoms, including loss of appetite, loss of weight (5 kg over a month), evening rise of temperature, and night cries. She was disabled and bedridden due to her severe imbalance while walking. She did not have any history of trauma or coexisting medical illnesses.</p>
      <p>On physical examination, there was severe tenderness over the lower cervical spine. Neck movements were painful and grossly restricted. There was no sensory or motor weakness. Reflexes were brisk. Bladder and bowel function was normal. There were no other respiratory or systemic complaints. X-rays of cervical spine showed a kyphotic deformity, destruction of C6 vertebral body with only a thin part of inferior end plate of C6 remaining, and the associated posterolisthesis of C5 over C6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      <p>Blood reports showed lymphocytosis with raised erythrocyte sedimentation rate and C-reactive protein values. A magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) showed infective spondylitis of C5/C6 with a pre/paraspinal abscess from C2 to T2 which indented the pharyngeal wall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). A computed tomography scan showed posterolisthesis of C5 over C6 with bony spinal canal stenosis, anterior wedging of C6, erosion of the superior end plate of C5, and prevertebral soft tissue from C3 to C6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p>
      <p>A diagnosis of infective spondylodiscitis of C5 and C6 secondary to tuberculosis was made. Although the patient was intact neurologically, there was extensive bone destruction and high grade spondylolisthesis; thus, an operative line of management was preferred.</p>
      <p>Since operative management was likely and the MRI was highly suggestive of tuberculous spondylodiscitis, a preoperative biopsy was not considered. The patient was scheduled for anterior decompression and stabilization. The surgery was performed under general anesthesia in the supine position through the right anterior approach. C5 and C6 corpectomy using an anterior cage and cervical plating from C4 to C7 was performed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Tissues were taken for biopsy and sent for histopathology examination. Postoperative antitubercular treatment was started. The histopathological examination confirmed tuberculosis.</p>
      <p>Postoperatively, there was no neurological deficit and patient was given a cervical collar. The anti-tuberculous treatment was continued for 18 months. After 2 years, an MRI was performed, which showed that the disease had been healed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). A radiograph showed solid fusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). After 3 years, the patient was symptomatically better and did not have any recurrence of the disease.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The spine is the most common site of skeletal tuberculosis. The thoracolumbar spine is the most commonly affected.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3)</xref> The cervical spine is a rare site for tuberculous infections. Clinically, pain is the most common symptom in cervical spine tuberculosis, with varying degrees of kyphosis and instability.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1)</xref> Constitutional symptoms are non-specific and do not lead to the diagnosis.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8)</xref></p>
      <p>Tuberculosis of the lower cervical spine presents differently in children and adults. In children, it is of an aggressive nature with diffuse involvement and abscess formation. Healing results in significant kyphosis.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9)</xref> In adults, it is more localized and involves a single vertebral body with less pus formation. The resulting kyphosis in adults is not as severe because the articular surfaces are spared.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9)</xref></p>
      <p>Spondylolisthesis is a rare presentation in of any cervical spine pathology. It is most commonly due to trauma and degeneration.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref> Although pathological spondylolisthesis in the cervical spine have been reported in cases of aneurysmal bone cyst, neurofibromatosis, and skeletal fluorosis, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2)</xref> spondylolisthesis as a presentation of tuberculous has not been reported.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref> In our case, there was a pathological posterolisthesis subsequent to the tuberculosis. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> shows the reports of concomitant tuberculosis with spondylolisthesis described in the literature. In the case described by Ratliff,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref> anterolisthesis was present before the vertebral tuberculous affection. Nissen-Lie (as described by Ratliff<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref>) in his report, postulated that, since the disease involved posterior elements of vertebra, it lead to the development of a stress lesion, causing anterolisthesis. The details of cases by Newman and Stone<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4)</xref> and Tuli<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6)</xref> are obscure. Chadha et al.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3)</xref> described three cases, in which one case had preexistent anterolisthesis and other two had tuberculosis of the posterior elements causing the anterolisthesis. Kirkman and Sridhar<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref> described a case of grade 4 posterolisthesis due to a vertebral tuberculous affection in a 12-year-old girl. Our case did not have any prior complaints of neck pain or radiculitis, so we feel that the destruction of the vertebral body due to the tuberculous process may have led to the instability and subsequent posterolisthesis.</p>
      <p>Treatment of cervical spine tuberculosis should be undertaken early to prevent neurological deficits and deformities.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10)</xref> Anterior surgery remains the mainstay treatment of cervical tuberculosis with instability, allowing for the debridement and evacuation of an abscess with stabilization of the anterior collapsed segment.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10)</xref> Posterior surgery is rarely used in lower cervical tuberculosis unless there is a posterior abscess.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9)</xref> Our case showed destruction of the vertebral body with posterolisthesis and a prevertebral abscess, so we performed an anterior decompression and stabilization. The fixation was adequate and additional posterior fixation was not required.</p>
      <p>Thus, we conclude that tuberculosis of the cervical spine can present as spondylolisthesis. This is rarely reported in literature and should be borne in mind. The exact mechanism of this infection is inadequately understood and reported. Early and prompt diagnosis is necessary to initiate the appropriate treatment and obtain a satisfactory outcome.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>CONFLICT OF INTEREST:</bold> No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hsu</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leong</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tuberculosis of the lower cervical spine (C2 to C7): a report on 40 cases</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6693464</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Woiciechowsky</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomale</surname>
              <given-names>UW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kroppenstedt</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Degenerative spondylolisthesis of the cervical spine: symptoms and surgical strategies depending on disease progress</article-title>
          <source>Eur Spine J</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>680</fpage>
          <lpage>684</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15221569</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chadha</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agarwal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spinal tuberculosis with concomitant spondylolisthesis: coexisting entities or 'cause andeffect'?</article-title>
          <source>Spinal Cord</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>399</fpage>
          <lpage>404</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16304566</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Newman</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stone</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The etiology of spondylolisthesis</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>
          <year>1963</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>39</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ratliff</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tuberculosis at the site of spondylolisthesis</article-title>
          <source>Br J Surg</source>
          <year>1956</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>181</issue>
          <fpage>502</fpage>
          <lpage>504</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13316038</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tuli</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Tuberculosis of the skeletal system</source>
          <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Jaypee Brothers Medical Publishers</publisher-name>
          <year>1997</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kirkman</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sridhar</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Posterior listhesis of a lumbar vertebra in spinal tuberculosis</article-title>
          <source>Eur Spine J</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20689971</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramani</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jituri</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muzumdar</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anterior instrumentation for cervical spine tuberculosis: an analysis of surgical experience with 61 cases</article-title>
          <source>Neurol India</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>89</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805662</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ram</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Swapnil</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Tuberculosis of the lower cervical spine</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Shetty</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanna</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajasekaran</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Spinal infections and trauma</source>
          <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Jaypee Brothers Medical Publishers</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
          <fpage>151</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yilmaz</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Selek</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gurkan</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erdemli</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Korkusuz</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anterior instrumentation for the treatment of spinal tuberculosis</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>1261</fpage>
          <lpage>1267</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10505522</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>(A) Preoperative plain radiographs of the cervical spine. (B) Dynamic views of the cervical spine.</title>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-7-519-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>(A) Preoperative magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) showing the tuberculous affection of C5/C6 with pre/paravertebral abscess. (B) Preoperative computed tomography scan showing the posterolisthesis of C5 over C6. (C) Postoperative MRI at two years showing the healed spine.</title>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-7-519-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>(A) Immediate postoperative radiographs. (B) Radiographs at two years postoperatively.</title>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="cios-7-519-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Reports of Tuberculosis Coexisting with Spondylolisthesis</title>
      </caption>
      <alternatives>
        <graphic xlink:href="cios-7-519-i001"/>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="rows">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th>
              <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of cases</th>
              <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</th>
              <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterolisthesis/posterolisthesis</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratliff et al.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref> (1956)</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lumbar</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterolisthesis</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nissen-Lie<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5)</xref> (1956)<sup>*</sup></td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lumbar</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterolisthesis</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Newman and Stone<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4)</xref> (1963)</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterolisthesis</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tuli<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6)</xref> (1997)</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterolisthesis</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chadha et al.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3)</xref> (2006)</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lumbar/lumbosacral</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterolisthesis</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kirkman and Sridhar<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7)</xref> (2011)</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lumbar</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterolisthesis</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present case</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cervical</td>
              <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterolisthesis</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </alternatives>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>NA: not available.</p>
          <p><sup>*</sup>Study was described by Ratliff.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
