<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Otorhinolaryngologica Italica</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0392-100X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1827-675X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pacini Editore SpA</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25709153</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4299155</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinical Techniques and technology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title xml:lang="en">Arterial microanastomoses on the reverse flow of the internal carotid artery reverse flow: an extreme solution in free-flap revascularisation. How we do it</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="it">
          <trans-title>Microanastomosi arteriosa su flusso retrogrado dell'arteria carotide interna: una soluzione estrema nella rivascolarizzazione dei lembi liberi</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baj</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Bolzoni</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Torretta</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pignataro</surname>
            <given-names>L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Department of Maxillofacial Surgery, Department of Specialistic Surgical Sciences, "Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico", Universit&#xE0; di Milano;</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label> Department of ENT, Department of Specialistic Surgical Sciences "Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico", Universit&#xE0; di Milano</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">Address for correspondence: Alessandro Remigio Bolzoni, Department of Clinical Sciences and Community Health, Universit&#xE0; di Milano, Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico, via F. Sforza 35, 20122 Milano, Italy. Tel. +39 02 50320245. Fax +39 02 50320248. E-mail: <email xlink:href="alessandro.bolzoni1@unimi.it">alessandro.bolzoni1@unimi.it</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>34</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>368</fpage>
      <lpage>371</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Copyright by Societ&#xE0; Italiana di Otorinolaringologia e Chirurgia Cervico-Facciale</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way. For details, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>SUMMARY</title>
        <p>Microvascular free tissue transfer in head and neck reconstruction requires suitable recipient vessels, which are frequently compromised by prior surgery, radiotherapy, or size of the tumour. A surgical description of an arterial free flap pedicle anastomosis on the reverse internal carotid arterial flow in a vessel-depleted neck is presented. A 66-year-old male with a relapse of hypopharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma previously treated with both surgical and radiation therapy for carcinoma of the tongue and the larynx was successfully reconstructed using a free forearm flap with reverse internal carotid arterial flow. The involvement of the carotid glomus and prior surgery excluded the other vessels as recipients. The forearm free flap survived without any complications. This procedure can be considered an alternative rescue technique for salvage reconstruction in a vessel-depleted neck.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="it">
        <title>RIASSUNTO</title>
        <p>La ricostruzione con lembi liberi richiede la presenza di vasi riceventi che spesso possono essere compromessi da precedenti interventi chirurgici, radioterapia o dalle dimensioni del tumore. In questo articolo abbiamo riportato la tecnica chirurgica da noi utilizzata per la realizzazione di una microanastomosi effettuata sul segmento distale dell'arteria carotide interna sfruttando il suo flusso retrogrado effettuata in un collo privo di altri vasi utilizzabili. Un paziente di 66 anni con recidiva di carcinoma squamocellulare dell'ipofaringe, precedentemente trattato con chirurgia e radioterapia per un carcinoma squamocellulare della lingua e della laringe, &#xE8; stato ricostruito con successo con un lembo libero di avambraccio rivascolarizzato con il flusso retrogrado dell'a. carotide interna. Il coinvolgimento del glomo carotideo ed il precedente trattamento chirurgico avevano impedito l'utilizzo di altri vasi del collo. Il lembo di avambraccio non ha riportato complicanze nel post-operatorio. Questa procedura pu&#xF2; essere considerata un'alternativa estrema per consentire la ricostruzione nei casi in cui i vasi del collo risultino inadeguati e/o assenti.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>KEY WORDS</title>
        <kwd>Head and neck cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>Free-flap</kwd>
        <kwd>Microanastomoses</kwd>
        <kwd>Carotid artery</kwd>
        <kwd>Reverse flow</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="introduction" id="S1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>To date, microvascular free-tissue transfer represents a reliable technique for reconstruction of defects following surgical treatment of head and neck cancer. Free tissue transfers have a high overall success rate, ranging between 91% and 99% of cases <xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>, and are generally performed with good functional and aesthetic outcomes, even considering donor-site morbidity <xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. However, the procedure requires specific surgical skills, especially for management of the vascular pedicle. In particular, identification and preparation of recipient vessels and microsurgical vascular anastomoses are crucial steps in the field of reconstructive surgery <xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Meticulous attention to these points should be paid to avoid dangerous and life-threatening complications, and improve the overall success rate.</p>
      <p>In fact, the management of vascular pedicles can be a troublesome aspect, especially in pre-irradiated graft beds, on the basis of vascular fibrosis and endothelial thickening. In addition to this, surgeons faced with free-flap reconstruction have to be trained, to modify <italic>in itiner</italic> during a radial forearm flap set up for reconstruction following resection of a relapsing hypopharyngeal tumor in an irradiated patient.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S2">
      <title>Clinical techniques and technology</title>
      <p>A microvascular transfer of the radial forearm was planned to reconstruct the digestive tract in a 66-yearold man with a relapsing hypopharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (SCC). The patient's relevant history began 14 years before when he underwent a partial glossectomy with bilateral functional neck dissection for an undifferentiated SCC, followed by post-operative radiotherapy. In July 2010, a total laryngectomy was performed for the development of an undifferentiated SCC in the left pyriform sinus, extending to the homolateral larynx.</p>
      <p>The patient was also affected by arterial hypertension and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.</p>
      <p>For the tumour recurrence in the residual hypopharyngeal lateral left wall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), also considering his previous irradiation history, surgery was therefore planned. An en bloc tumour resection englobing the proximal portion of the involved common carotid artery at the level of the carotid artery bifurcation (previously undetected to the pre-operatory radiologic assessment) was performed, and a right fascio-cutaneous radial forearm flap was set up and tubulised for reconstructive purposes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Ablation.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-34-368-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Reconstruction. T: tongue; IJV: internal jugular vein, C: carotid artery.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="0392-100X-34-368-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Due to the lack of appropriate arterial flow on the arteries tributary to both the ipsilateral and contralateral external carotid artery, the reversed flow in the distal portion of the left internal carotid artery was used for arterial microanastomoses. Venous microanastomosis was performed between the right tyreo-linguo-facial venous trunk and the cephalic donor vein.</p>
      <p>A left pectoral muscle flap was then transposed to protect the residual carotid artery, and a cutaneous Tiersch graft taken from the anterolateral left thigh was used to cover the residual donor site defect.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>To date, microsurgical reconstruction of the head and neck after oncological surgery based on free flaps is, in experienced hands, an effective and successful technique <xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>. The most common used recipient vessels for arterial microanastomoses are the branches of the external carotid artery, such as the facial, superior thyroid, and lingual arteries. However, it is generally accepted that each artery having, once resected, any pulsatile and adequate flow at its distal end can be used as a recipient vessel <xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>.</p>
      <p>However, in managing head and neck reconstruction, surgeons must be ready to modify <italic>in itinere</italic> their reconstructive strategy on the basis of unexpected anatomic extension of the disease (e.g. vascular involvement) or impairment of vascular structures suitable for microanastomoses due to unsuspected flow obstruction or reduced vascular flow (e.g. related to atheromatous disease, postattinic atherosclerosis, or, less frequently, to intimal injury after the positioning of intra-arterial infusion catheter). In addition to these, some technical difficulties may arise, including troublesome pedicle management due to limited pedicle length, reduced vessel caliber or kinking of the pedicle <xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>. In order to overcome these pitfalls, some authors <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> have suggested that interposition of venous grafts can be used to reach an adequate pedicle length. However, it must be pointed out that surgical strategies using fragile and thin-walled vessels such as graft veins may predispose to intravascular thrombosis.</p>
      <p>Therefore, under unexpected and unfavourable conditions, aside from other less effective reconstructive techniques such as delayed locoregional flaps <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>, the use of reverse arterial flow can be considered as an extreme surgical choice. In fact, Neligan and co-workers described 28 cases of superior thyroid and facial artery reverse flow used for free flap revascularisation with good clinical outcomes <xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. These positive results may be related to adequate arterial flow, corresponding to 57-76% of systemic arterial pressure as documented by clinical and physiopathologic studies <xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>. In addition to this, Batchelor <xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> stated that the distal flow of an extracranial reverse flow vessel would be enhanced by recruitment of its peripheral capillary branches resulting in overflow leading to an adequate flap blood supply. At any rate, it may be speculated that the above mentioned conditions related to extracranial reverse flow recipients would be valid in case of intracranial vessels, thus leading to a successful outcome such in this case. However, to our knowledge, no previous descriptions of arterial microanastomoses performed on the reverse flow of the internal carotid artery have been reported.</p>
      <p>With regards to the donor site, forearm free flaps should be considered as the preferred choice compared to perforator flaps in such difficult situations, on the basis of their long and well-caliber pedicles <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>. Indeed, in our patient, the forearm flap allowed us to reach the distal portion of the inner carotid artery and use its reverse flow for revascularisation. Moreover, the large size of the radial artery used achieved a good matching with the most of the secondary arterial neck branches and even with the internal carotid artery. In addition to this, a long pedicle is useful when contralateral arterial supply management is required, as in our report, due to impaired patency of the ipsilateral arterial.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, microvascular surgery in vessel-depleted necks is a challenge and somewhat troublesome aspect. The case presented herein suggests the feasibility of internal carotid artery reflow for free flap revascularisation when no other safer or easier technical options are possible.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tarsitano</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pizzigallo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sgarzani</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Head and neck
cancer in elderly patients: is microsurgical free-tissuetransfer
a safe procedure?</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>371</fpage>
          <lpage>375</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23349555</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deganello</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gitti</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parrinello</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cost analysis in
oral cavity and oropharyngeal reconstructions with microvascular
and pedicled flaps</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>380</fpage>
          <lpage>387</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376293</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Giordano</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bondi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrario</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Radial forearm free
flap surgery: a modified skin-closure technique improving
donor-site aesthetic appearance</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>158</fpage>
          <lpage>163</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22767980</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baj</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beltramini</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demarchi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extended-pedicle
peroneal artery perforator flap in intraoral reconstruction</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>282</fpage>
          <lpage>285</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24043917</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tarsitano</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sgarzani</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Betti</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vascular pedicle ossification
of free fibular flap: is it a rare phenomenon? Is
it possible to avoid this risk?</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>307</fpage>
          <lpage>310</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227895</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pellini</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mercante</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spriano</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Step-by-step mandibular
reconstruction with free fibula flap modelling</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol
Ital</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>405</fpage>
          <lpage>409</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23349561</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Batchelor</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Discussion: Reverse flow as an option in microvascular
recipient anastomoses</article-title>
          <source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>1786</fpage>
          <lpage>1787</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Neligan</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>She-Yue</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gullane</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reverse flow as an option
in microvascular recipient anastomoses</article-title>
          <source>Plast Reconstr
Surg</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>1780</fpage>
          <lpage>1785</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9393476</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>H&#xF6;lzle</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hohlweg-Majert</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kesting</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reverse
flow facial artery as recipient vessel for perforator flaps</article-title>
          <source>Microsurgery</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>437</fpage>
          <lpage>442</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19308955</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Biemer</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Vein grafts in microvascular surgery</article-title>
          <source>Br J Plast
Surg</source>
          <year>1977</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>197</fpage>
          <lpage>199</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">890197</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Colletti</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Autelitano</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tewfik</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Autonomized flaps
in secondary head and neck reconstructions</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol
Ital</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>335</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23326014</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tarsitano</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vietti</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cipriani</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional results
of microvascular reconstruction after hemiglossectomy:
free anterolateral thigh flap versus free forearm flap</article-title>
          <source>Acta
Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>374</fpage>
          <lpage>379</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376292</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Putten</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
              <prefix>Van der</prefix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spasiano</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bree</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
              <prefix>de</prefix>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Flap reconstruction
of the hypopharynx: a defect orientated approach</article-title>
          <source>Acta Otorhinolaryngol Ital</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>288</fpage>
          <lpage>296</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23326007</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
