<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Res Notes</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Res Notes</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Research Notes</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1756-0500</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26892467</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4759855</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1932</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-016-1932-7</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Thyroid gland rupture caused by blunt trauma to the neck</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Hara</surname>
            <given-names>Hirotaka</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+81-836-22-2280</phone>
            <email>harahiro@yamaguchi-u.ac.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hirose</surname>
            <given-names>Yoshinobu</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>hirose-y@yamaguchi-u.ac.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamashita</surname>
            <given-names>Hiroshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>hiro-shi@yamaguchi-u.ac.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Department of Otolaryngology, Yamaguchi University Graduate School of Medicine, Ube, Yamaguchi 755-8505 Japan </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <elocation-id>114</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Hara et al. 2016</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Thyroid rupture following blunt trauma is extremely rare, and neck pain without swelling may be the only presenting symptom. However, hemorrhage and hematoma subsequently causes severe tracheal compression and respiratory distress.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 71-year-old Japanese woman visited our emergency room with a complaint of increasing right-sided neck pain at the thyroid cartilage level after she tripped and accidentally hit her neck against a pole 3&#xA0;h back. On admission, her vital signs were stable. There was no swelling or subcutaneous emphysema. Laryngeal endoscopy revealed mild laryngeal edema, although there was no impairment in vocal fold mobility on either side. Contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) revealed rupture of the right lobe of the thyroid gland accompanied by a large hematoma extending from the neck to the mediastinum. Under general anesthesia, the right lobe was resected and the hematoma was evacuated.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Only a few isolated cases of thyroid rupture caused by blunt neck trauma have been reported in patients with normal thyroid glands and neck pain without swelling may be the only presenting symptom. When suspected, CT should be performed to confirm the diagnosis determine the optimal treatment.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Thyroid rupture</kwd>
        <kwd>Blunt trauma</kwd>
        <kwd>Neck pain</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution>The study was funded by the authors.</institution>
          </funding-source>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Thyroid rupture following blunt trauma to the neck is extremely rare. Because the thyroid gland is located in the anterior cervix, neck pain without swelling may be the only presenting symptom immediately after neck trauma. However, hemorrhage and hematoma subsequently causes severe tracheal compression and respiratory distress. Here we report the case of a 71-year-old woman whose thyroid ruptured after blunt neck trauma, leading to the formation of a large hematoma extending from the paratracheal region to the upper mediastinum. Successful treatment was achieved with hemithyroidectomy and hematoma removal.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 71-year-old woman presented to our emergency room with a complaint of increasing right-sided neck pain at the thyroid cartilage level after she accidentally tripped and hit her neck against a pole 3&#xA0;h back. At the time of admission, her vital signs were stable without evidence of respiratory distress, and there was no swelling or subcutaneous emphysema (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Laryngeal endoscopy revealed normal vocal fold mobility and mild edema of the arytenoids.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Preoperative image of the patients neck. Erythema can be noted at the trauma site at the level of the thyroid cartilage</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2016_1932_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>Contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) revealed rupture of the right lobe of the thyroid gland accompanied by a large hematoma extending from the thyroid to the mediastinum (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, b). There were no cysts or goiter in either thyroid lobe and no fracture of the laryngeal framework, cartilages, and trachea. In view of the patient&#x2019;s condition and the presence of the large hematoma, neck exploration under general anesthesia was undertaken. During surgery, the dorsal side of the right lobe of the thyroid gland was found to be ruptured with lacerations (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The ruptured right lobe was resected and the hematoma, which extended to the upper mediastinum, was evacuated. Pathological examination of the resected lobe revealed otherwise normal anatomy, with no evidence of goiter or cyst.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Computed tomography of the neck and chest. Computed tomography showing thyroid rupture, with a large hematoma (<italic>arrow</italic>) extending from the neck (<bold>a</bold>) to the mediastinum (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2016_1932_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Intraoperative views. The dorsal side of the right lobe of the thyroid gland is lacerated and ruptured. The hematoma (<italic>arrowhead</italic>) is extending along the paratracheal region to the upper mediastinum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2016_1932_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Gross findings of the resected right lobe of the thyroid. Lacerations (<italic>arrowhead</italic>) are evident on the dorsal side of the right lobe of the thyroid gland</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2016_1932_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      <p>The patient required postoperative intubation for 24&#xA0;h because of laryngeal edema, but she subsequently made a full and uneventful recovery.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Thyroid injury secondary to blunt neck trauma is uncommon and mostly occurs in patients with preexisting goiters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Only a few isolated cases of thyroid rupture caused by blunt neck trauma have been reported in patients with normal thyroid glands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Common causes of thyroid injury include traffic accidents, particularly with motorcycles or bicycles, and falls or slips. Although extremely rare, spontaneous thyroid hemorrhage following the muscular effort of heavy lifting has also been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Although rare, thyroid injury secondary to blunt neck trauma is clinically significant because hematomas can present inconspicuously and cause respiratory distress and serious complications, particularly if they are large and extending to the mediastinum.</p>
      <p>To confirm the diagnosis of thyroid rupture, ultrasound (US) and computed tomography are essential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. CT reportedly exhibits high sensitivity in diagnosing tracheal ruptures in patients with blunt neck trauma and is the initial diagnostic modality of choice in stable patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] because it also permits the evaluation of other structures in the anterior cervix. Doppler-mode US can be useful for assessing thyroid lacerations and hematomas and is particularly useful in the emergency room prior to emergency CT. In our patient, we used both US and CT because the nature of the injury necessitated a detailed assessment of other vital structures, including the laryngeal framework cartilages, trachea, and large vessels.</p>
      <p>To minimize the risk of breathing distress, laryngeal or bronchial fibroscopy should be performed to assess laryngeal edema and evaluate vocal fold mobility. Although our patient did not complain of dyspnea on admission, laryngeal fibroscopy revealed arytenoid edema.</p>
      <p>According to the literature, the management of this type of injury varies. The majority of patients require close observation because of the potential seriousness of any complications, and several patients have reportedly undergone hemi or total thyroidectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Conservative or surgical treatment should be determined on the basis of CT findings and vital signs. Securing the airway when necessary should be the priority [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The thyroid gland has a rich blood supply that can easily result in an expanding hematoma capable of causing airway compromise. If a hematoma is present, surgical intervention may be necessary, and if not, close monitoring and conservative treatment may be appropriate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Given the rarity of the condition, it is difficult to recommend duration of monitoring. However, Chartier and Turner reported a 75&#xA0;year-old lady who developed respiratory distress from a hematoma as late as 33&#xA0;h after initial trauma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p>
      <p>The primary reason for surgical intervention in our patient was evacuation of the rapidly extending hematoma. The retropharyngeal prevertebral space is an important pathway from the neck to the mediastinum, and deep neck infections usually follow this route. Airway distress can occur in patients with massive hemorrhage from the thyroid or a branch of the internal jugular vein. Because there was a massive hematoma extending to the upper mediastinum, with the risk of severe complications, we opted for open surgery and evacuation of the hematoma.</p>
      <p>Isolated thyroid rupture is very rare. Sow et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] reported a case of with fracture of the thyroid cartilage, mandible, and both first ribs. There are few case reports of blunt neck trauma causing thyroid rupture in elderly patients. In Japan, many elderly patients with locomotive disorders are at risk of falls and neck trauma. Furthermore, many elderly patients may be on anticoagulant therapy for the prevention of infarction or atherosclerosis, thus increasing their risk of hemorrhage. Fortunately, our patient was not on any anticoagulant therapy; nevertheless, physicians should bear this in mind when managing an elderly patient after a fall.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We described a rare case of thyroid rupture following blunt neck trauma. When suspected, CT should be performed to confirm the diagnosis, and if there is evidence of a hematoma, surgical intervention may be necessary. For uncomplicated cases, conservative treatment and monitoring is recommended.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Ethics</title>
      <p>Permission for publication of this case was obtained by Yamaguchi University Hospital Institutional Review Board.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images.
</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>CT</term>
          <def>
            <p>computed tomography</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>US</term>
          <def>
            <p>ultrasound</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ack>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>HH was the main consultant surgeons involved in the management of the patient. HH reviewed the literature and wrote the manuscript. YH and HY were involved in caring for the patient in hospital and contributed the case history notes used in this report. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      <sec id="FPar1">
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <p>The study was funded by the authors. There are no additional acknowledgements.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar2">
        <title>Competing interests</title>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Behrends</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Low</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute goiter hematoma following blunt neck trauma</article-title>
          <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1300</fpage>
          <lpage>1301</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0196-0644(87)80247-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3662196</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oka</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishijima</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azuma</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inada</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyazaki</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakano</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishida</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakata</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hashimoto</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Izukura</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Blunt thyroid trauma with acute hemorrhage and respiratory distress</article-title>
          <source>J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>381</fpage>
          <lpage>385</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jemermed.2006.08.019</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17499691</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>KK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeong</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Son</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid gland rupture after blunt cervical trauma</article-title>
          <source>J Ultrasound Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>943</fpage>
          <lpage>946</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16798911</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stunell</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Brien</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benfayed</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torreggiani</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid gland rupture after blunt cervical trauma</article-title>
          <source>J Ultrasound Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>992</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17592066</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>Perez Fontan FJ</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Santos Hernandez M, Pombo Vazquez S, Lago Novoa M. Thyroid gland rupture after blunt neck trauma: sonographic and computed tomographic findings</article-title>
          <source>J Ultrasound Med</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1249</fpage>
          <lpage>1251</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11758032</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Watson</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Traumatic rupture of the thyroid gland</article-title>
          <source>Australas Radiol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>363</fpage>
          <lpage>364</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1673.1999.433675.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10901938</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahrens</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juttner</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heidt</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scheinichen</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Przemeck</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid gland rupture: a rare case of respiratory distress</article-title>
          <source>J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jemermed.2009.05.010</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19545965</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chartier</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Delayed intrathyroidal hematoma causing respiratory distress after a seemingly benign fall: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Int J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>431</fpage>
          <lpage>433</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12245-010-0196-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21373316</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saylam</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Comcali</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozer</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coskun</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid gland hematoma after blunt neck trauma</article-title>
          <source>West J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>247</fpage>
          <lpage>249</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20046242</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heizmann</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmid</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oertli</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Blunt injury to the thyroid gland: proposed classi&#x2423;cation and treatment algorithm</article-title>
          <source>J Trauma</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>1012</fpage>
          <lpage>1015</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.ta.0000238621.83780.e0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17033582</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weeks</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>FD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferzoco</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gates</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Blunt trauma to the thyroid: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Am Surg</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>518</fpage>
          <lpage>521</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16044935</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hsieh</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chou</surname>
              <given-names>FF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nonsurgical treatment of thyroid injury after blunt cervical trauma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>739</fpage>
          <lpage>741</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0735-6757(00)90313-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11043637</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blaivas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hom</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Younger</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid gland hematoma after blunt cervical trauma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>348</fpage>
          <lpage>350</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0735-6757(99)90083-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10452430</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ryan</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hemorrhage into the thyroid gland resulting from muscular effort: report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1942</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>469</fpage>
          <lpage>471</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-194203000-00016</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Donatini</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Persistent dyspnea following thyroid hematoma after neck blunt trauma</article-title>
          <source>Updates Surg</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13304-011-0076-5</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21598075</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zawawi</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varshney</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Payne</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manoukian</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid gland rupture: a rare finding after a blunt neck trauma</article-title>
          <source>Int J Pediatr Otorhinolaryngol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>863</fpage>
          <lpage>865</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijporl.2013.02.019</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23522054</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chartier</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Delayed intrathyroidal hematoma causing respiratory distress after a seemingly benign fall: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Int J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>431</fpage>
          <lpage>433</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12245-010-0196-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21373316</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sow</surname>
              <given-names>YL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aziz</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ng</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid rupture secondary to blunt neck trauma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>760.e3</fpage>
          <lpage>760.e5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2012.12.005</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23399341</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
