<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Med Imaging</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Med Imaging</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Medical Imaging</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2342</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26271929</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4535668</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">70</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12880-015-0070-3</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Hemodynamic monitoring using a single-use indwelling transesophageal echocardiography probe in an unstable patient after open-heart surgery</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Begot</surname>
            <given-names>Emmanuelle</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>emmanuellebegot@yahoo.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Clavel</surname>
            <given-names>Marc</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>marc.clavel@chu-limoges.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Piccardo</surname>
            <given-names>Alessandro</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>alessandro.piccardo@chu-limoges.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bellier</surname>
            <given-names>R&#xE9;mi</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>remybellier@yahoo.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fran&#xE7;ois</surname>
            <given-names>Bruno</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>b.francois@unilim.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pichon</surname>
            <given-names>Nicolas</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>nicolas.pichon@chu-limoges.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Vignon</surname>
            <given-names>Philippe</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+(33) 5 55 05 62 40</phone>
            <email>philippe.vignon@unilim.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Medical-surgical intensive care unit, Dupuytren University Hospital, 2 Ave. Martin Luther King, 87042 Limoges, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Inserm, CIC-1435, F-87000 Limoges, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label/>Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, Dupuytren University Hospital, Limoges, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label/>Universit&#xE9; de Limoges, F-87000 Limoges, France </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <elocation-id>31</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Begot et al. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Hemodynamic monitoring is frequently needed in ventilated patients with unstable hemodynamics after open-heart surgery. Novel miniaturized single-use transesophageal echocardiographic probe has been scarcely used in this clinical setting.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A patient who underwent a scheduled open-heart surgery developed a ventilator-associated pneumonia and was referred to the intensive care unit for post-operative acute respiratory distress syndrome. Hemodynamic monitoring was performed with a single-use indwelling transesophageal echocardiography probe during 50&#xA0;h. Initially, a contrast study depicted a patent foramen ovale with a right-to-left shunt. Nitric oxide was administered and positive end-expiration pressure was reduced. Subsequently, the patient became hemodynamically unstable and the identification of a localized tamponade due to compressive left atrial hematoma prompted reoperation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>The novel hemodynamic monitoring device described here appears valuable to help identifying severe post-operative complications and guide acute care.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Monitoring</kwd>
        <kwd>Transesophageal echocardiography</kwd>
        <kwd>Patent foramen ovale</kwd>
        <kwd>Tamponade</kwd>
        <kwd>Mediastinal hematoma</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Although multiplane transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) is increasingly used in intensive care unit (ICU) settings, it is not ideally suited for serial hemodynamic assessment of unstable ventilated patients. A commercially available miniaturized single-use 72-h indwelling TEE probe appears promising for the hemodynamic monitoring of ventilated ICU patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], as illustrated in the present case report.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 57-year-old patient with multiple cardiovascular risk factors was hospitalized for an uncomplicated anterolateral non-ST elevation acute coronary syndrome. He was treated with Aspirin, unfractionned Heparin and Prasugrel. The coronary angiography showed a three-vessel disease of the left anterior descending, lateral and right coronary arteries. Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) was 56&#xA0;% with a mild anterolateral hypokinesis. Triple coronary artery bypass grafting was scheduled. The procedure was prolonged by intraoperative bleeding which was difficult to control (extracorporeal circulation: 4&#xA0;h16; aortic clamping: 3&#xA0;h13). Postoperative TEE disclosed a moderately decreased LVEF of 45&#xA0;% with an anterolateral hypokinesis, normal left ventricular (LV) filling pressures and right ventricular (RV) function. A vasopressor support (1.6&#xA0;mg/h) was required due to unstable hemodynamics (lactate: 4.28&#xA0;mmol/L). On Day 4, a ventilator-associated pneumonia was diagnosed (<italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>Hemophilus influenzae</italic>). Despite adapted antibiotic therapy, the patient developed a severe acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) on Day 7, with a PaO<sub>2</sub>/FiO<sub>2</sub> ratio of 74 (FiO<sub>2</sub>: 1).</p>
      <p>Hemodynamic monitoring was initiated on Day 6 due to persistent need of vasopressor support and worsening of gas exchange. It was performed using a single-use, monoplane TEE miniaturized probe (diameter 5.5&#xA0;mm) connected to a dedicated echographic system which allows two-dimensional imaging and color Doppler mapping, but has no spectral Doppler capability (Imacor&#xAE;, New-York, NY, USA). This device is approved by the Food and Drug Administration and has a European Community mark for 72&#xA0;h of continuous use (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The patient was hemodynamically assessed every 6 to 8&#xA0;h and whenever a clinically relevant event occurred. The transverse view of great vessels, long axis view and transgastric short-axis view of the heart were analyzed to determine the main mechanism that caused circulatory failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The first hemodynamic evaluations ruled out a preload-dependence, a relevant ventricular dysfunction and valvulopathy, and a pericardial effusion (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Specifically, there was no evidence for an early surgery-related complication such as mediastinal hematoma. Accordingly, the vasopressor support was maintained since patient&#x2019;s hemodynamic status was stabilized with steady infusion rates. Despite a protective ventilation and a PEEP trial (FiO<sub>2</sub>: 1; respiratory rate: 22/min; tidal volume: 6&#xA0;ml/kg ideal body weight; PEEP: 14 cmH<sub>2</sub>O), the PaO<sub>2</sub>/FiO<sub>2</sub> ratio remained as low as 63. Accordingly, a contrast study was performed at H37 to screen for a potential patent foramen ovale (PFO). A PFO shunting was depicted with an atrial septum aneurysm (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). PEEP was decreased to 8&#xA0;cm H<sub>2</sub>O and inhaled nitric oxide was administered while the patient remained hemodynamically stable under vasopressor support (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This resulted in an increase of the PaO<sub>2</sub>/FiO<sub>2</sub> ratio up to 130. At H46, the clinical course was complicated by an abrupt hemodynamic deterioration with hypotension, skin mottling and oliguria associated with a rapid supraventricular tachycardia (170&#xA0;bpm), which was efficiently treated by anti-arrhythmic drugs. A new hemodynamic assessment using the miniaturized TEE probe disclosed a large mediastinal hematoma compressing the entire left atrium (LA) and a moderate, non compressive pericardial effusion. To ascertain the diagnosis of localized tamponade prior to surgical decompression, a regular multiplane TEE study was immediately performed and was confirmatory (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Single-use miniaturized transesophageal echocardiographic probe. The single-use indwelling monoplane transesophageal echocardiography probe can be left in place for up to 72&#xA0;h and is easily connected to a dedicated system for serial hemodynamic assessments (<italic>left panel</italic>). Its small size compared to regular multiplane transesophageal echocardiographic probes facilitates hemodynamic monitoring (<italic>right panel</italic>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12880_2015_70_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Hemodynamic monitoring using the single-use 72-h indwelling transesophageal echocardiography probe<sup>a</sup>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>H0</th><th>H5</th><th>H14</th><th>H22</th><th>H28</th><th>H37</th><th>H46</th><th>H50</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Variations of SVC size</td><td>Moderate</td><td>Moderate</td><td>Moderate</td><td>None</td><td>None</td><td>None</td><td>None</td><td>None</td></tr><tr><td>LV fractional area change</td><td>Normal</td><td>Normal</td><td>Normal</td><td>Normal</td><td>Normal</td><td>Normal</td><td>Decreased</td><td>Normal</td></tr><tr><td>RV dilatation</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td></tr><tr><td>Paradoxical septal motion</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td></tr><tr><td>Severe left-sided valvular regurgitation</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td><td>Absence</td></tr><tr><td>Other relevant abnormality</td><td>No</td><td>No</td><td>No</td><td>No</td><td>No</td><td>PFO shunting</td><td>Posterior mediastinal hematoma compressing the left atrium</td><td>No</td></tr><tr><td>Therapeutic impact</td><td>Vaso-pressor</td><td>Vaso-pressor</td><td>Vaso-pressor</td><td>Vaso-pressor</td><td>Vaso-pressor</td><td>Reduce PEEP Nitric oxide</td><td>Emergency surgical evacuation of left atrial hematoma</td><td>Vaso-pressor</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>SVC</italic> superior vena cava, <italic>LV</italic> left ventricle, <italic>RV</italic> right ventricle, <italic>PEEP</italic> positive end-expiratory pressure</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>In the presence of a circulatory failure, the following therapeutic algorithm based on the analysis of three transverse views (great vessels, transesophageal long-axis four-chamber view of the heart, transgastric short-axis view of the heart) was used: large respiratory variations of superior vena cava size (inspiratory collapse) in the transverse view of the great vessel were indicative of preload-dependence (fluid loading); a right ventricular end-diastolic area exceeding the left ventricular end-diastolic area in the transesophageal long-axis four-chamber view of the heart was indicative of a marked dilatation of a failing right ventricle, potentially associated with an acute cor pulmonale; left ventricular fractional area change&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;45&#xA0;% in the transgastric short-axis view of the heart was indicative of systolic dysfunction in the absence of preload-dependence (administration of inotropes), while a paradoxical septal motion with a restrained left ventricle in this view was indicative of acute cor pulmonale (protective ventilation, reduced PEEP level, prone ventilation, nitric oxide administration, vasopressor support)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Patent foramen ovale revealed by a contrast study. The injection of agitated saline fully opacified the moderately dilated right atrium and underlined a septal aneurysm bulking towards the left atrium at end-expiration (<italic>thick arrow</italic>). A large shunting through a patent foramen ovale with full opacification of the left atrium was evidenced in this patient with severe acute respiratory distress syndrome (<italic>thin arrows</italic>). Abbreviations: LA, left atrium; RA, right atrium; RV, right ventricle</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12880_2015_70_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Extrapericardial tamponade. The miniaturized transesophageal echocardiographic probe disclosed a large mediastinal hematoma compressing the left atrium in this patient with severe shock (<italic>left panel, asterisks</italic>). The presence of a localized tamponade was confirmed during conventional transesophageal echocardiography which depicted a rounded heterogeneous mass consistent with a recent hematoma which compressed the left atrium and impaired atrial filling (<italic>mid panel, asterisks</italic>), as reflected by a narrow and turbulent inflow on color Doppler mapping (<italic>right panel, arrow</italic>). Abbreviations: LA, left atrium; RA, right atrium; RV, right ventricle</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12880_2015_70_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>The patient was immediately reoperated. The surgeon confirmed the presence of a non compressive hemopericardium of ~300&#xA0;mL and of a tamponade secondary to a large LA hematoma of ~500&#xA0;mL of fresh blood. The patient sustained shock with multiple organ failure. Further TEE assessment confirmed the full evacuation of LA hematoma and ruled out a preload-dependence or a ventricular dysfunction. Despite the increase of vasopressor therapy, the patient died on Day 3 secondary to refractory shock.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Discussion and conclusions</title>
      <p>In our unstable ventilated patient with cardiorespiratory compromise, the novel single-use TEE probe was left in place for 50&#xA0;h and allowed 8 hemodynamic assessments, two of which had a direct therapeutic impact, including urgent reoperation. In a recent pilot study, image quality was deemed adequate or optimal in more than 90&#xA0;% of ventilated ICU patients and directly influenced therapy in 52 out of 94 patients (68&#xA0;%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Long-term esophageal intubation by the single-use 72-h indwelling TEE probe was complicated by minor self-limited gastric bleeding (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;2) and lip mechanical ulceration (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;2), but none of these events had clinical consequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>In our patient, TEE hemodynamic monitoring confirmed that initial therapy based on vasopressor support was adequate since no preload-dependence or ventricular dysfunction was observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. It also ruled out an acute cor pulmonale which occurs in approximately 22&#xA0;% of patients with moderate-to-severe ARDS despite protective ventilation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Since ARDS patients with PFO shunting are poor responders to PEEP trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], we performed a contrast study which has been reported to be positive in 15.5 to 19.2&#xA0;% of ventilated ARDS patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Decreased PEEP level and nitric oxide administration improved hypoxemia, presumably in reducing RV afterload. Our patient was not ventilated in prone position because of unstable hemodynamics and recent sternotomy.</p>
      <p>As the hemodynamic status was deteriorating, TEE monitoring disclosed a LA hematoma which developed within a few hours and would presumably have been missed otherwise, since typical tamponade physiology is uncommon after open-heart surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The miniaturized TEE probe depicted an echodense, rounded mass which compressed the LA, with an inverted free wall curvature and turbulent intracavitary blood flow on Doppler color flow mapping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. We confirmed the diagnosis using conventional TEE because it remains the gold standard due to the poor diagnostic accuracy of transthoracic echocardiography [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Despite emergency reoperation, the patient developed lethal refractory shock. This complication results in a mortality rate of 22&#xA0;% for this type of localized tamponade despite prompt surgical evacuation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>In closing, hemodynamic monitoring using a single-use miniaturized TEE monoplane probe allows the identification of postoperative complications in patients with cardiopulmonary compromise after open-heart surgery. The diagnostic capability of this new device remains to be confirmed by further studies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the next of kin of the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>ARDS</term>
          <def>
            <p>Acute respiratory distress syndrome</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ICU</term>
          <def>
            <p>Intensive care unit</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>LA</term>
          <def>
            <p>Left atrium</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>LV</term>
          <def>
            <p>Left ventricle</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>LVEF</term>
          <def>
            <p>Left ventricular ejection fraction</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PEEP</term>
          <def>
            <p>Positive end-expiratory pressure</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PFO</term>
          <def>
            <p>Patent foramen ovale</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>RV</term>
          <def>
            <p>Right ventricle</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>TEE</term>
          <def>
            <p>Transesophageal echocardiography</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>EB, MC, AP and RB were involved in patient&#x2019;s management, EB, BF, NP, and PV contributed to the draft of the manuscript. All authors read and approve the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vieillard-Baron A, Slama M, Mayo P, Charron C, Amiel JB, Esterez C, et al. A pilot study on safety and clinical utility of a single-use 72-hour indwelling transesophageal echocardiography probe. Intensive Care Med. 2013;39:629&#x2013;35.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bouferrache K, Amiel JB, Chimot L, Caille V, Charron C, Vignon P,&#xA0;et al. Initial resuscitation guided by the surviving sepsis campaign recommendations and early echocardiographic assessment of hemodynamics in intensive care unit septic patients: a pilot study. Crit Care Med. 2012;40:2821&#x2013;7.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lheritier G, Legras A, Caille A, Lherm T, Mathonnet A, Frat JP,&#xA0;et al. Prevalence and prognostic value of acute cor pulmonale and patent foramen ovale in ventilated patients with early acute respiratory distress syndrome: a multicenter study. Intens Care Med. 2013;39(10):1734&#x2013;42. Epub.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mekontso Dessap A, Boissier F, Leon R, Carreira S, Roche Campo F, Lemaire F,&#xA0;et al. Prevalence and prognosis of shunting across patent foramen ovale during acute respiratory distress syndrome. Crit Care Med. 2010;38:1786&#x2013;92.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vieillard-Baron A, Schmitt JM, Augarde R, Fellahi JL, Prin S, Page B,&#xA0;et al. Acute cor pulmonale in acute respiratory distress syndrome submitted to protective ventilation: incidence, clinical implication, and prognosis. Crit Care Med. 2001;29:1551&#x2013;5.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Grumann A, Baretto L, Dugard A, Morera P, Cornu E, Amiel JB,&#xA0;et al. Localized cardiac tamponade after open-heart surgery. Ann Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2012;18:524&#x2013;9.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kochar</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobs</surname>
              <given-names>LE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kotler</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Right atrial compression in postoperative cardiac patients: detection by transoesophageal echocardiography</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>511</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0735-1097(90)90613-T</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2373832</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
