<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Postgrad Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Postgrad Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPGM</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Postgraduate Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-3859</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0972-2823</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26515990</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4944328</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JPGM-62-40</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0022-3859.168739</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Persistent &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T large granular lymphocytosis in a patient with refractory pure red cell aplasia, celiac disease, and chronic hepatitis B infection</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sreedharanunni</surname>
            <given-names>S</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sachdeva</surname>
            <given-names>MUS</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Prakash</surname>
            <given-names>G</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Das</surname>
            <given-names>R</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Hematology, Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh, Punjab and Haryana, India</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh, Punjab and Haryana, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Prof. Reena Das, E-mail: <email xlink:href="das.reena@pgimer.edu.in">das.reena@pgimer.edu.in</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jan-Mar</season>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>62</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>40</fpage>
      <lpage>43</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; 2016 Journal of Postgraduate Medicine</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The disorders of large granular lymphocytes include reactive proliferation as well as indolent or aggressive neoplasms of cytotoxic T cells, &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T cells, and natural killer (NK) cells. They are associated with autoimmune and infectious disorders and have varied immunophenotypic features. We report a case, which highlights this complex association of autoimmune and infectious diseases with large granular lymphocytosis, the overlapping spectrum of large granular lymphocyte leukemias, and &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T cell lymphomas as well as the difficulties in the diagnosis and management of these indolent T cell lymphomas in the usual clinical settings.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>KEY WORDS</title>
        <kwd>Celiac disease (CD)</kwd>
        <kwd>large granular lymphocyte (LGL)</kwd>
        <kwd>pure red cell aplasia (PRCA)</kwd>
        <kwd>&#x3B3;&#x3B4; T cell</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Large granular lymphocytes (LGLs) are a distinct subpopulation of lymphocytes, which constitute 10-15% of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (0.1-0.3 &#xD7; 10<sup>9</sup> /l) and are derived from cytotoxic T cells, &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T cells, or natural killer (NK) cells. The disorders of LGLs include reactive proliferation, indolent neoplasms such as T-cell LGL (T-LGL) leukemia, and a chronic lymphoproliferative disorder of NK cells as well as their aggressive variants. They are associated with various autoimmune and infectious disorders.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] These disorders, especially the indolent ones being uncommon and having overlapping features with reactive proliferations, lead to diagnostic dilemmas in routine clinical practice. Here, we report such a case of complex association of large granular lymphocytosis with pure red cell aplasia (PRCA), celiac disease (CD), and chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 46-year-old male presented with severe transfusion dependent anemia. He was diagnosed with CD and was asymptomatic on a gluten-free diet. One year back, he had an episode of fever and anemia during which he was found to have chronic HBV infection for which he was treated with entecavir 0.5 mg daily. During the present admission, he had no significant physical examination findings except for severe pallor and mild hepatomegaly. He was managed with blood transfusions and hematinics and evaluated for the cause of anemia. The investigation results are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. There was anemia with reticulocytopenia. Peripheral blood (PB) smear showed absolute lymphocytosis (6993/&#x3BC;l) with &gt;90% of them being LGLs [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>]. Bone marrow examination (BME) revealed normocellular bone marrow (BM) with erythroid hypoplasia, the myeloid to erythroid ratio being 40:1 and without any dyserythropoiesis or any viral cytopathic change. BM trephine biopsy showed multiple reactive lymphoid nodules composed of both B cells and T cells, as revealed by immunohistochemistry [Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1b</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">f</xref>]. A multiparameter flow cytometric immunophenotyping (MFCI) performed from the PB using a limited panel of antibodies showed an excess of CD8+CD16+ T cells. Serological tests for immunoglobulin M (IgM) Parvovirus antibodies were negative. Considering the possibility of PRCA, the patient was treated with prednisolone 1 mg/kg/day, along with entecavir. The subsequent clinical course is summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. A repeat BME, 16 months after the initial BME showed PRCA, increased stainable iron (Perls stain), and multiple reactive lymphoid nodules. MFCI of PB lymphocytes [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>] showed that 92% of them were T cells. There was an increase in &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T cells (CD2<sup>+</sup> CD5<sup>-</sup> CD7<sup>+</sup> CD4<sup>-</sup> CD8<sup>variable</sup> CD16<sup>+</sup> CD56<sup>-</sup> CD57<sup>variable</sup>), which constituted approximately 48% of T cells. The last follow-up (20 months after initial BME) revealed the persistence of large granular lymphocytosis and refractory anemia being supported with blood transfusions and iron chelation. The patient was asymptomatic of CD and HBV infection.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Summary of investigations during initial workup of anemia</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin (after transfusion)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 g/L</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum iron</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 &#xB5;g/dL</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total leukocyte count</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1&#xD7;10<sup>9</sup>/L</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum ferritin</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1123 ng/mL</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet count</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65&#xD7;10<sup>9</sup>/L</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total iron binding capacity</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322 &#xB5;g/dL</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reticulocyte count (corrected)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99%</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transferrin saturation</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma hemoglobin</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not raised</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum vitamin B12</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1346 pg/mL</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine hemoglobin</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stool for occult blood</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBV DNA</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;20 IU/L</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver function tests</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal function tests</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thyroid function tests</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgA tissue transglutaminase</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;5 U/ml</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antinuclear antibodies (ANAs)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiliver kidney microsome (LKM) antibodies</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimitochondrial antibodies (AMAs)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiparietal cell antibodies (PCAs)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antismooth muscle actin (SMA) antibodies</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Peripheral blood smear shows large granular lymphocyte (a) [100x, May-Gr&#xFC;nwald-Giemsa (MGG) stain]; Bone marrow aspirate shows erythroblastopenia and large granular lymphocytes (b) (100x, MGG stain); trephine biopsy shows reactive lymphoid nodules (c) (20x, H&amp;E stain) composed of CD20<sup>+</sup> cells (d) (20x) and CD3<sup>+</sup> cells (e) (20x); CD8<sup>+</sup> cells in the interstitium (f) (20x)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-62-40-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Clinical course of the patient. (MMF - mycophenolate mofetil; CsA - cyclosporine)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-62-40-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Flow cytometry performed on peripheral blood. CD3<sup>+</sup> cells (92% of lymphocytes) were gated. 48% of T cells were &#x3B3;&#x3B4; TCR<sup>+</sup> (3a), which were CD2+CD7<sup>+</sup> (not shown), CD8+ (variable) (3a), CD5<sup>&#x2212;</sup> (3b), CD4<sup>&#x2212;</sup> (3c), CD57<sup>+</sup>(variable), CD56<sup>&#x2212;</sup> (3d), and CD16<sup>+</sup> (not shown)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JPGM-62-40-g003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The association of PRCA with large granular lymphocytosis is reported in the literature, which could be either nonclonal as in idiopathic PRCA or clonal as in LGL leukemias. There are isolated cases of PRCA associated with CD[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and HBV infection.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] Expansion of LGLs can be transient or chronic reactive proliferation, neoplastic, or borderline between reactive and leukemic disorders. Reactive causes include various autoimmune disorders, splenectomy, post allogenic stem cell or solid organ transplantation, HIV and other viral infections.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] LGL leukemias are indolent disorders with a survival of more than 10 years in usual settings and characterized by persistent (&gt;6 months), large granular lymphocytosis in PB, usually of 2-20 &#xD7; 10<sup>9</sup> /L without a clearly identifiable cause. They are often associated with infections, various hematologic manifestations such as PRCA, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia as well as various autoimmune disorders and autoantibodies.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] BM shows subtle interstitial infiltrate with intravascular or linear pattern highlighted by immunohistochemistry and often associated with reactive nodular aggregates of B and T cells.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Normal LGLs are either CD3<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> cytotoxic T cells (T LGL) or CD3<sup>-</sup> NK cells. Normal T LGLs are CD3<sup>+</sup> CD2<sup>+</sup> CD4<sup>-</sup> CD5<sup>+</sup> CD7<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup>&#x3B1;&#x3B2;TCR<sup>+</sup>&#x3B3;&#x3B4;TCR<sup>-</sup> while LGL leukemias show abnormal immunophenotype such as abnormal expression of CD2, CD5, and CD7 and coexpression of CD16, CD56, and CD57.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Most of the LGL leukemias show CD3<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> CD4<sup>-</sup>&#x3B1;&#x3B2;TCR<sup>+</sup> phenotype. Other phenotypes include CD3<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>-</sup> CD4<sup>+</sup>&#x3B1;&#x3B2;TCR<sup>+</sup>, CD3<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> CD4<sup>-</sup>&#x3B3;&#x3B4;TCR<sup>+</sup>, and CD3<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>-</sup> CD4<sup>-</sup>&#x3B3;&#x3B4;TCR<sup>+</sup> with CD16 and CD57 expression in a variable number of cases.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] Our patient had CD and chronic HBV in the background, and had smooth muscle antibodies (SMAs). There have been previous reports of LGL leukemia associated with CD and HBV;[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] there has also been an occasional report of reactive expansion of LGLs in HBV infection.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] In our patient, autoimmune features could be a manifestation of LGL leukemia or the expansion of LGLs might be secondary to CD or HBV or both. The differentiation of the clonal process from reactive proliferation requires analysis of T cell receptor (TCR) rearrangement by flow cytometry or Southern blot analysis or polymerase chain reaction (PCR). More commonly used PCR has a sensitivity of only 70-80%.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Our patient showed a persistent LGL (&gt;2000/&#x3BC;l) for nearly 2 years and had an abnormal immunophenotype of CD2<sup>+</sup> CD4<sup>-</sup> CD5<sup>-</sup> CD7<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>variable</sup> CD16<sup>+</sup> CD56<sup>-</sup> CD57<sup>variable</sup> &#x3B3;&#x3B4; TCR<sup>+</sup>. The BM involvement was similar to that described in the literature [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>] and was refractory to various modalities of treatment, all of which favor, though does not prove an indolent leukemic process over a reactive condition. Compared to &#x3B1;&#x3B2; T cell LGL leukemia, &#x3B3;&#x3B4; type is rare with up to 50% of them showing CD3<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> CD4<sup>&#x2212;</sup> CD16<sup>+</sup> CD57<sup>+</sup> phenotype, slightly more common than CD4<sup>-</sup> CD8<sup>-</sup> phenotype. Both subtypes have a similar clinical behavior.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Both &#x3B1;&#x3B2;TCR<sup>+</sup> and &#x3B3;&#x3B4;TCR<sup>+</sup> LGL leukemias are included under LGL leukemia in the World Health Organization (WHO) 2008 classification but &#x3B3;&#x3B4; TCR<sup>+</sup> LGL leukemias are a distinct class of &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T cell lymphomas with indolent clinical course in contrast to most other &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T cell lymphomas.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Various treatment options that are useful for LGL leukemias include steroids, low dose methotrexate, cycyclophosphamide, purine analogs, alemtuzumab (anti-CD52 monoclonal antibody), and stem cell transplantation.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</p>
      <p>In our case, large granular lymphocytosis probably would have contributed significantly to the development of PRCA. However, the role of HBV and CD in the expansion of LGLs and the subsequent development of PRCA are debatable. The clonality studies could not be performed in our case but it has to be highlighted that the demonstration of clonality may not always support a malignant process as oligoclonal and sometimes clonal expansions can be seen in various benign conditions including viral infections.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] The management of PRCA remains complicated by association with multiple diseases, especially HBV infection.</p>
      <p>Our case highlights the uncommon and complex association of multiple immunologically related diseases and large granular lymphocytosis; the overlapping spectrum of indolent LGL and &#x3B3;&#x3B4; T cell proliferations, and the difficulties in the diagnosis of indolent T cell lymphomas in the usual clinical settings as reflected in few case reports and a lack of any large series in the Indian literature.</p>
      <sec id="sec2-1">
        <title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
        <p>Nil.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2-2">
        <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
        <p>Authors declare that they have no conflict of interests.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dearden</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large granular lymphocytic leukaemia pathogenesis and management</article-title>
          <source>Br J Haematol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>152</volume>
          <fpage>273</fpage>
          <lpage>83</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21158751</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Malley</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>T-cell large granular leukemia and related proliferations</article-title>
          <source>Am J Clin Pathol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>850</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17509982</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bourgault-Rouxel</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loughran</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zambello</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Epling-Burnette</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Semenzato</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donadieu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical spectrum of gammadelta+ T cell LGL leukemia: Analysis of 20 cases</article-title>
          <source>Leuk Res</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17544120</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Couderc</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costello</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagn&#xE8;res</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vitton</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demoux</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Is pure red cell aplasia a new extra digestive manifestation of celiac disease?</article-title>
          <source>Rev Med Interne</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>336</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16527376</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ide</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sata</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nouno</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamashita</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakano</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanikawa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical evaluation of four cases of acute viral hepatitis complicated by pure red cell aplasia</article-title>
          <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8304314</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foucar</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morice</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Catovsky</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Swerldlow</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>NL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaffe</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pileri</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stein</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>T cell large granular lymphocytic leukemia</article-title>
          <source>WHO Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <publisher-loc>Lyon, France</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>IARC Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>272</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Malamut</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meresse</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verkarre</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaltenbach</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Montcuquet</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duong Van Huyen</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large granular lymphocytic leukemia: A treatable form of refractory celiac disease</article-title>
          <source>Gastroenterology</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>143</volume>
          <fpage>1470</fpage>
          <lpage>2.e2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22922421</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agostini</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zambello</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pontisso</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alberti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trentin</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siviero</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lymphoproliferative disease of granular lymphocytes in a patient with concomitant hepatitis B virus infection of CD4 lymphocytes</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>401</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2576027</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sandberg</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lima</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xE1;rcena</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szczepa&#xF1;ski</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>TCRgammadelta+ large granular lymphocyte leukemias reflect the spectrum of normal antigen-selected TCR gammadelta+ T-cells</article-title>
          <source>Leukemia</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>505</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16437145</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kingma</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaffe</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schrager</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Janik</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Flow cytometric immunophenotypic profiles of mature gamma delta T-cell malignancies involving peripheral blood and bone marrow</article-title>
          <source>Cytometry B Clin Cytom</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15973700</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
