<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Emerging Infect. Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25530077</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4285261</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14-0762</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2101.140762</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type">
          <subject>Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="TOC-title">
          <subject>Clinical, Environmental, and Serologic Surveillance Studies of Melioidosis in Gabon, 2012&#x2013;2013</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Clinical, Environmental, and Serologic Surveillance Studies of
Melioidosis in Gabon, 2012&#x2013;2013</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Melioidosis in Gabon,
2012&#x2013;2013</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wiersinga</surname>
            <given-names>W. Joost</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Birnie</surname>
            <given-names>Emma</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Weehuizen</surname>
            <given-names>Tassili A.F.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alabi</surname>
            <given-names>Abraham S.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huson</surname>
            <given-names>Micha&#xEB;la A.M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>in &#x2019;t Veld</surname>
            <given-names>Robert A. G. Huis</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mabala</surname>
            <given-names>Harry K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Adzoda</surname>
            <given-names>Gregoire K.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Raczynski-Henk</surname>
            <given-names>Yannick</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Esen</surname>
            <given-names>Meral</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lell</surname>
            <given-names>Bertrand</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kremsner</surname>
            <given-names>Peter G.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Visser</surname>
            <given-names>Caroline E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
            <given-names>Vanaporn</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peacock</surname>
            <given-names>Sharon J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>van der Ende</surname>
            <given-names>Arie</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Limmathurotsakul</surname>
            <given-names>Direk</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grobusch</surname>
            <given-names>Martin P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, the Netherlands (W.J. Wiersinga, E.
Birnie, T.A.F. Weehuizen, M.A.M. Huson, R.A.G. in &#x2019;t Veld, C.E. Visser, A. van
der Ende, M.P. Grobusch); </aff>
        <aff id="aff2">Albert Schweitzer Hospital, Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Gabon (A.S. Alabi,
H.K. Mabala, G.K. Adzoda, M. Esen, B. Lell, P.G. Kremsner, M.P. Grobusch); </aff>
        <aff id="aff3">Ex-Situ Silex Geoarchaeology, Leiden, the Netherlands (Y.
Raczynski-Henk); </aff>
        <aff id="aff4">University of T&#xFC;bingen, T&#xFC;bingen, Germany (M. Esen, B.
Lell, P.G. Kremsner, M.P. Grobusch); </aff>
        <aff id="aff5">Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand (V. Wuthiekanun, D.
Limmathurotsakul); </aff>
        <aff id="aff6">University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK (S.J. Peacock)</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: W. Joost Wiersinga, Center for Infection
and Immunity Amsterdam, Dept. of Internal Medicine, Academic Medical Center,
University of Amsterdam, Meibergdreef 9, Room G2-132, 1105 AZ Amsterdam, the
Netherlands; email: <email xlink:href="w.j.wiersinga@amc.uva.nl">w.j.wiersinga@amc.uva.nl</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>21</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>40</fpage>
      <lpage>47</lpage>
      <abstract abstract-type="toc">
        <p><italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> are
in the soil; a novel <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> sequence type causes lethal
septic shock.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract>
        <p><italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei,</italic> an environmental gram-negative bacillus,
is the causative agent of melioidosis and a bio-threat agent. Reports of <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> isolation from soil and animals in East and West Africa
suggest that melioidosis might be more widely distributed than previously thought.
Because it has been found in equatorial areas with tropical climates, we hypothesized
that <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> could exist in Gabon. During 2012&#x2013;2013,
we conducted a seroprevalance study in which we set up microbiology facilities at a
large clinical referral center and prospectively screened all febrile patients by
conducting blood cultures and testing for <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and
related species; we also determined whether <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> could be
isolated from soil. We discovered a novel <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> sequence
type that caused lethal septic shock and identified <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>
and <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> in the environment. Our data suggest that
melioidosis is emerging in Central Africa but is unrecognized because of the lack of
diagnostic microbiology facilities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords: </title>
        <kwd>Burkholderia pseudomallei</kwd>
        <kwd>Burkholderia thailandensis</kwd>
        <kwd>melioidosis</kwd>
        <kwd>epidemiology</kwd>
        <kwd>seroprevalance</kwd>
        <kwd>Africa</kwd>
        <kwd>Gabon</kwd>
        <kwd>soil</kwd>
        <kwd>sepsis</kwd>
        <kwd>bacteria</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>The Tier 1 bio-threat agent <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> is an environmental
gram-negative bacillus and the cause of melioidosis, a disease characterized by sepsis,
pneumonia, and abscess formation in almost any organ (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> is closely related to
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> but rarely causes disease in humans or animals; it is
usually distinguished from <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> by its ability to assimilate
arabinose (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><italic>6</italic></xref>). Melioidosis mainly affects those
who are in regular contact with soil and water and is associated with a mortality rate of
up to 40% in resource-poor environments. The major regions to which melioidosis is endemic
are Southeast Asia and tropical Australia (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>).
The northern tip of the Northern Territory in Australia and northeast Thailand represent
hot spots, where annual incidence is up to 50 cases per 100,000 persons (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>).</p>
    <p>The emergence of melioidosis in Brazil is an example of increasing recognition of the
disease in areas where it is probably endemic, and cases have become apparent as a result
of enhanced awareness and diagnostics (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>).
Human <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> infection has been reported from Malawi, Nigeria,
The Gambia, Kenya, and Uganda; however, human cases in Africa seem to be few and isolated,
although this finding could be the result of underrecognition and underreporting (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>). Although reports of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>
isolation from soil and animals in East and West Africa are limited, they suggest that
melioidosis could be widely distributed across this region (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><italic>13</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>).</p>
    <p>Given the equatorial tropical distribution of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and
<italic>B. thailandensis</italic>, we hypothesized that these bacteria are present in
the central African country of Gabon, potentially causing disease. By conducting a
seroprevalence study, an environmental survey, and setting up microbiology facilities for
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> detection at a large referral hospital, we detected
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> in soil and identified it as a cause of lethal
infection in Gabon. We also detected <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> in environmental
soil samples, indicating that this organism is also present in Gabon.</p>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Study Sites and Populations</title>
        <p>The study was performed in Moyen-Ogoou&#xE9; and Ngouni&#xE9; Provinces (combined
population 162,000) in central Gabon; these 2 provinces cover an area of 56,285
km<sup>2</sup> and consist of predominantly dense primary rain forest. For the
seroprevalence surveillance study, 304 serum samples were collected from healthy
nonfebrile school children (12&#x2013;20 years of age) living in and around
Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, the capital of Moyen-Ogoou&#xE9; Province; these children
also participated in a chemoprophylaxis study for malaria (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>). </p>
        <p>A prospective analysis of community-acquired bloodstream infections was performed at
Albert Schweitzer Hospital (which admits &#x2248;6,000 patients annually) in
Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9; (population 24,000), in the Central African rain forest on
the river Ogoou&#xE9;, Gabon. The rainy season starts in October and ends in June
(including a short dry season in December&#x2013;January). Mean annual rainfall is
1,981 mm (78 inches), which is equivalent to that in northeastern Thailand (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>). Studies were approved by
the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique et Technologique, Libreville, and
the scientific review committee of the Centre de Recherches M&#xE9;dicales de
Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Albert Schweitzer Hospital. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Prospective Analysis of Community-Acquired Bloodstream Infections</title>
        <p>To obtain data about the prevalence and causes of community-acquired bloodstream
infections in Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, we prospectively monitored all blood cultures
for febrile patients admitted to Albert Schweitzer Hospital for 1 year (June 1,
2012&#x2013;May 31, 2013) by using BacT/Alert PF (bioM&#xE9;rieux, Marcy
l'Etoile, France). Criteria for ordering blood cultures were left to the
discretion of the treating physician. Technicians and staff of the clinical
microbiology laboratory received additional training on sample handling and
processing (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>). All oxidase-positive,
gram-negative bacteria that were not <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> were
further tested to determine whether they were <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> by
using the subculture and identification methods described below. Antimicrobial drug
susceptibilities were determined by using Etest (bioM&#xE9;rieux) on
Mueller-Hinton-agar (bioM&#xE9;rieux); when available, break points were defined as
described (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> Antibody Detection by Indirect Hemagglutination
Assay </title>
        <p>During May 2012, presence and titer of antibodies to <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>
in healthy schoolchildren were determined using by the indirect hemagglutination
assay (IHA) as described (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><italic>21</italic></xref>), with pooled antigens prepared from 2 <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> isolates from Thailand. An antibody titer of &#x2265;1:40
was used as the cutoff value for seropositivity (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><italic>22</italic></xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Soil Sampling Study</title>
        <p>During July 2012&#x2013;September 2012, soil sampling to test for the presence of
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> was based on consensus guidelines, and direct
culture of soil in enrichment broth was performed (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><italic>23</italic></xref>). A total of 8 sites around the residences of children
were selected on the basis of local maps and consultations with inhabitants
throughout the provinces of Moyen-Ogoou&#xE9; (6 sites) and Ngouni&#xE9; (2
sites) and on known factors associated with the presence of <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> (e.g., wet soil such as rice paddies or land use such as
goat farming) (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Within each sampling area (50 &#xD7;
50 m<sup>2</sup>), a fixed-interval sampling grid was used to collect 100 samples per
field, 5 m apart. For each sample, 10 g of soil was collected from a depth of 30 cm,
stored away from direct sunlight, and processed within 3 h. </p>
        <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Environmental survey. A) Gabon, showing location of the 8 sites from which soil
was sampled to test for the presence of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>, July
2012&#x2013;September 2012. B) Soil sampling site no. H, a rice field near
Mouila village. </p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="14-0762_F1"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Isolation of potential <italic>Burkholderia</italic> spp. from soil was performed as
described (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><italic>23</italic></xref>). In brief, 10 g of soil was
diluted in 10 mL of threonine&#x2013;basal salt solution plus colistin at 50 mg/liter
(TBSS-C50 broth) containing crystal violet and was vortexed for 30 s before
incubation at &#x2248;42&#xB0;C for 48 h. Ten &#x3BC;L of supernatant was
subcultured onto Ashdown-agar and incubated and examined every 24 h for 7 days.
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> was identified by colony morphology, positive
oxidase test result, inability to assimilate arabinose, antimicrobial drug
susceptibility pattern (<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> is generally resistant to
gentamicin and colistin but susceptible to amoxicillin/clavulanic acid [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>]), and results of API 20NE (bioM&#xE9;rieux) and
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>&#x2013;specific (Bps) latex-agglutination tests
(<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><italic>25</italic></xref>). Positive results were confirmed with molecular
analysis. Soil type was determined by standard lithologic and pedologic analysis of
sediments; for this purpose, 2 extra samples were collected per site from a depth of
30 cm (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><italic>26</italic></xref>). Sediment
properties were compared with properties of other (typical) samples from the same
locations as described in the recently published Soil Atlas of Africa (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><italic>26</italic></xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Genetic and Phylogenetic Analyses</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted by using a DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (QIAGEN, Valencia,
CA, USA) to perform multilocus sequence typing (MLST) (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>). Primers used to amplify fragments of the 7
housekeeping genes were identical to those described at the
<italic>Burkholderia</italic> MLST website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bpseudomallei.mlst.net/misc/info2.asp">http://bpseudomallei.mlst.net/misc/info2.asp</ext-link>). For isolate <italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> D50, the primer narK-up was replaced by narK-upAMC
5&#x2032;-TCTCTACTCGTGCGCTGGGG-3&#x2032;. Sequences of the 7 gene fragments of
isolates from Africa were concatenated and combined with those from a selection of
971 sequence types (STs) representing all <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>,
<italic>B. mallei</italic>, and <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> isolates in the
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> MLST database. Concatenated sequences were
aligned and analyzed by using MEGA-6 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.megasoftware.net">http://www.megasoftware.net</ext-link>).
A phylogenetic tree was constructed by using a neighbor-joining algorithm and the
Kimura 2-parameter model. Bootstrap testing was performed for 500 repetitions.
Whole-genome sequencing was performed by using the MiSeq platform (Illumina, San
Diego, CA, USA) as described (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Community-Acquired Bloodstream Infections</title>
        <p>Of the 941 bacterial blood cultures, 77 (8.2%) were positive for bacteria. The most
prevalent isolate was <italic>Escherichia coli,</italic> responsible for 8 (10.0%)
bloodstream infections, followed by <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (6 [7.8%])
and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> (6 [7.8%], 5 of which were nontyphoidal
salmonellae). Other organisms that were isolated at least 5 times included
<italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> (5 [6.5%]), <italic>Klebsiella
pneumoniae</italic> (5 [6.5%]), and <italic>Enterobacter</italic> spp. (5 [6.5%]).
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> was isolated from 1 (1.4%) patient, described in
the case report.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case Report</title>
        <p>A 62-year-old Gabonese woman was hospitalized in January 2013 with a 7-day history of
fever, cough, weakness, headache, vomiting, and a painful knee. She did not report
coughing or shortness of breath. She had poorly controlled diabetes mellitus and was
taking glibenclamide. She had no history of cardiopulmonary or renal disease, was
receiving no long-term medications other than glibenclamide, and did not smoke. She
was a retired school teacher but still engaged in family farming. Physical
examination revealed blood pressure of 160/90 mm Hg, a pulse rate of 130 beats per
minute, and a temperature of 40.5&#xB0;C. She had a wound with an underlying
abscess on her right leg, together with diffuse tenderness of the right knee with
warmth, erythema, and limitation of active and passive ranges of motion because of
pain and effusion. Neurologic, cardiovascular, and respiratory examinations revealed
no abnormalities. Laboratory findings obtained at admission showed an elevated blood
glucose level of 24 mmol/L but values within reference range for creatinine (0.85
mg/dL), leukocytes (9,800 &#xD7; 10<sup>3</sup> mm<sup>3</sup>), and hemoglobin
(9.2 g/dL). No other blood or urine test was performed, and chest radiographs were
not taken. On hospitalization day 1, treatment with amoxicillin/clavulanic acid was
empirically initiated for sepsis. On day 2, the abscess was incised and drained, and
on day 3 antimicrobial drug therapy was switched to ceftriaxone. Cultures of blood,
wound, and synovial fluid grew identical gram-negative rods, which were initially
classified as <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. No other pathogens were detected. The
patient&#x2019;s clinical condition deteriorated, and she died of septic shock on day
8. A postmortem examination was not performed. </p>
        <p>After the patient&#x2019;s death, the <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> species was
classified as <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> (patient strain Gb100) and confirmed
by MLST and whole-genome sequencing. This isolate was later determined to be
susceptible to trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole, amoxicillin/clavulanic acid,
ceftazidime, and meropenem <bold>(</bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table
1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Antimicrobial drug susceptibility of <italic>Burkholderia
pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> strains from
Gabon, 2012&#x2013;2013*</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="103" span="1"/>
            <col width="79" span="1"/>
            <col width="103" span="1"/>
            <col width="95" span="1"/>
            <col width="99" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Drug</th>
                <th colspan="4" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">MIC,
mg/L<hr/></th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th valign="bottom" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Break point
resistance</th>
                <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> patient strain</th>
                <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> soil strain C2</th>
                <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> soil strain D50</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x2020;</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tobramycin</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x2020;</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moxifloxacin</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x2021;</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meropenem</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftazidime</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMP/SMX</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/19</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMC</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TZP</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/?&#xA7;</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloramphenicol</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracycline</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#xB6;</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polymyxin B</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA#</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,024</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>*Bacterial isolates were tested for their susceptibility to antimicrobial
agents. MIC (MICs; mg/L) were determined by E-test on Mueller-Hinton-agar. When
available break points were defined as described [19]. AMC,
amoxicillin/clavulanic acid; NA, not applicable; TMP/SMX,
trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole, TZP, piperacillin/
tazobactam.&#x2028;&#x2020;Break point for gentamicin was
used.&#x2028;&#x2021;Break point for ciprofloxacin was used.
&#x2028;&#xA7;Break point available for piperacillin
only.&#x2028;&#xB6;Break point for doxycycline was used. &#x2028;#Intrinsic
resistance. </p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Seroprevalence </title>
        <p>Of the 304 healthy schoolchildren for whom serum samples were tested for <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> antibodies, 143 (47.0%) were male. Details for this cohort
have been reported previously (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>). For 43 (14.1%) children, an IHA titer was
detectable; titers ranged from 1:10 to 1:80 (median 1:10, interquartile range
1:10&#x2013;1:20). For 5 (1.6%) children, IHA titer was
<underline>&gt;</underline>1:40, which has been used as the cutoff value for
seropositivity (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><italic>22</italic></xref>). None of
the children had an IHA titer &gt;1:160, which is considered by several centers in
Thailand to support a diagnosis of melioidosis in patients with clinical features
consistent with this diagnosis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Environmental Isolates</title>
        <p>The predominant soil type in this area of Gabon was ferralsol, which is red and
yellow weathered soil. The only exception was samples taken from a rice paddy near
Mouila village, where the soil was gleysol (clay, a hydric soil saturated with
groundwater long enough to develop a characteristic gleyic color pattern) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> was
isolated from 21 (3%) of 800 soil samples taken from 3 (38%) of the 8 sample sites;
the maximum number of positive samples for 1 site was 14 (14%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The biochemical profiles of all
isolates were in accordance with <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> (API 20NE code
1156576). The antibiogram of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> soil strain C2 is shown
in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. </p>
        <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Geographic features and distribution of <italic>Burkholderia
pseudomallei</italic> strains at 8 sampling sites in Moyen-Ogoou&#xE9; and
Ngouni&#xE9; Provinces, Gabon, 2012&#x2013;2013*</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="25" span="1"/>
            <col width="101" span="1"/>
            <col width="40" span="1"/>
            <col width="58" span="1"/>
            <col width="72" span="1"/>
            <col width="128" span="1"/>
            <col width="55" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="bottom" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</th>
                <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nearest village</th>
                <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevation, m</th>
                <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Land use</th>
                <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil type</th>
                <th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil description</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample holes positive, %</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Albert Schweitzer
Hospital; lat. S 00&#xB0;40&#x2032;40.5, long. E
010&#xB0;13&#x2032;49.7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Football (soccer) field</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferralsol</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellowish-brown, clay fluvial sediments, not
strongly humic, some gravel, poorly sorted sediment, decalcified</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Adouma; lat. S
00&#xB0;40&#x2032;50.2, long. E 010&#xB0;13&#x2032;31.5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riverbed that is dry most of the year</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferralsol,&#x2028;clay, orange, dry</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brownish yellow, clay fluvial sediments,
moderately humic, some gravel, strong indicators of human
interference</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Makouk&#xE9;; lat. S
00&#xB0;28&#x2032;30.8, long. E 010&#xB0;24&#x2032;34.7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cattle ranch</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferrasol, orange, little stones, hard,
rocky, less hard, orange</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellowish brown, clay fluvial sediments, not
strongly humic, some gravel, poorly sorted sediment, decalcified</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Adiwa; lat. S
00&#xB0;41&#x2032;06.0, long. E 010&#xB0;13&#x2032;43.5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Next to school (with Bps IHA
positivity)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferralsol</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brownish yellow, clay fluvial sediments,
moderately humic, some gravel, strong indicators of human
interference</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Petit Paris 3; lat.
S010&#xB0;42&#x2032;40.4, long. E 010&#xB0;15&#x2032;20.7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cattle ranch</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Savannah/ferralsol</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellowish gray, well-sorted clay, weakly
humic</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fougamou; lat. S 01&#xB0;18&#x2032;40.3,
long. E 010&#xB0;37&#x2032;14.4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Savannah, grassland</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Savannah/ferralsol</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellowish gray, well-sorted clay, weakly
humic</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Massika II; lat. S 00&#xB0;40&#x2032;40.7,
long. E 010&#xB0;13&#x2032;51.4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Football pitch</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ferralsol</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reddish brown, clay fluvial sediments, not
strongly humic, sediment, decalcified</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouila; lat. S 01&#xB0;51&#x2032;27.8,
long. E 011&#xB0;02&#x2032;37.7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rice paddy</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gleysol</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greyish yellow clay with ferric concretions,
gleyic features, probably associated with rice cultivation</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p>*lat., latitude; long., longitude.</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>The closely related <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> coexists with <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> in the soil in Southeast Asia and Australia and is generally
considered avirulent (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>). We also identified
<italic>B. thailandensis</italic> in the soil of Gabon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). This strain, termed <italic>B. thailandensis</italic>
soil strain D50, was positive by Bps latex agglutination. This <italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> strain, API 20NE code 1157577, was susceptible to
trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole, amoxicillin/clavulanic acid, ceftazidime, and
meropenem (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Phylogenetic tree of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> strains from Gabon, 2012&#x2013;2013. Phylogenetic
analysis by multilocus sequence typing amplification (MLST) of isolate Gb100
(from 62-year-old patient who died of melioidosis), <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> soil isolate C2 (sample collected at site C), and
<italic>B. thailandensis</italic> soil isolate D50 (sample collected at site
D), together with sequence types representing all <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>B. thailandensis</italic> isolate
accessible in the MLST database. Phylogenetic tree was constructed by using the
neighbor-joining algorithm with the Kimura 2-parameter model. Bootstrap test
was for 500 repetitions. Sequence type labels were omitted for simplicity.
Position of the isolates from Gabon, including their closest relatives, are
indicated.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="14-0762-F2"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Genetics and Phylogeny <italic>of Burkholderia</italic> spp. Strains </title>
        <p>The 3 isolates from Gabon contained previously described MLST alleles but belonged to
novel STs. The patient isolate Gb100 (ST1127) and soil isolate C2 (ST1128) were
single-locus variants and differed by 1 nt in the <italic>narK</italic> sequence
only. Patient isolate Gb100 was also a single-locus variant of ST707
(single-nucleotide substitution in <italic>ndh</italic>). The only <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> strain with ST707 in the database had been isolated in 2010
from a patient in the United Kingdom, 6 weeks after the patient had returned from a
trip to Nigeria (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>). The
soil isolate C2 (ST1128) was a single-locus variant of ST7 (single-nucleotide
substitution in <italic>ndh</italic>) and ST879 (single-nucleotide substitution in
<italic>lipA</italic>). ST7 was represented by 2 isolates in the MSLT database,
both isolated in 1963 from patients in Vietnam. The <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic>
ST879 strain was isolated in 2011 from a patient in Spain, who had returned from a
trip through Madagascar and 14 countries in West Africa (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>). The soil isolate D50 (ST1126) was a
single-locus variant of ST73. This ST is represented in the database by 2 <italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> strains, 1 isolated from a foal in France and 1 isolated
from the environment in Kenya. Phylogenetic analysis of the Gabon isolates together
with 971 STs obtained from the MLST database by using the aligned concatenated
sequences of the 7 loci in the neighbor-joining algorithm with the Kimura 2-parameter
model showed that the patient isolate Gb100 and soil isolate C2, found near the
community of the patient, grouped together with 7 STs. These 7 STs represented 10
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> strains isolated in Cambodia (2 strains), Vietnam
(2 strains), Niger, Nigeria, Spain (imported), France (2 strains [1 imported]), and
the United Kingdom (imported) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Again,
patient isolate Gb100 and soil isolate C2 are most closely related to ST879. Soil
isolate D50 grouped together with 3 STs representing 4 <italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> strains isolated from Kenya, France, the United States, and
Cambodia. Using this approach, we showed that the closest relatives of the strain
that infected and eventually killed the patient reported here were ST879 and the
strain isolated from soil around her community. Our whole-genome sequencing sample
data have been submitted to a project that is undertaking whole-genome sequencing on
a large number of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> isolates from around the world.
This approach is anticipated to offer superior resolution of the global phylogeny of
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We detected a case of melioidosis in a human in central Africa, confirmed the presence
of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> in the environment in Gabon, and isolated <italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> from an environmental sample from that part of the world. The
low rate of antibody seropositivity among healthy children combined with the low
prevalence of <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> cultured from blood of patients in a
local hospital, however, suggest that melioidosis is rare in this setting.</p>
      <p>Only 4 of the 13 melioidosis cases acquired by humans in Africa and reported in the
literature have been PCR confirmed (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><italic>29</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>). We show with phylogenetic analysis that the newly
identified patient isolate Gb100 groups with a <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> isolate
from a patient from Spain who had traveled across West Africa and Madagascar (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>). <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> seropositivity was reported during a World Health Organization
investigation into an outbreak of severe pneumonia in the northeastern of the Democratic
Republic of Congo (Eric Bertherat, pers. comm.) (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). However, in that study some of the <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic>&#x2013;seropositive cases diagnosed as melioidosis were later
diagnosed as plague, calling into question the value of serology-based testing in this
setting (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). The predominant
soil type at the sites from which <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> was isolated was
similar to the soil type from which <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> strains were
isolated in Cambodia (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><italic>26</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><italic>36</italic></xref>). The low rate of <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> positivity per site points toward a relatively low abundance of
<italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> in Gabon soil when compared with highly
melioidosis-endemic areas in Southeast Asia and Australia (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><italic>21</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>). The true distribution of melioidosis in Africa
remains uncertain, but we now can expand this area toward the central African country of
Gabon.</p>
      <p>The genus <italic>Burkholderia</italic> comprises &gt;30 species, of which <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>B. mallei</italic> are considered the most
pathogenic (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>). The isolation of <italic>B.
thailandenis</italic> from soil in Gabon extends our knowledge of the geographic
distribution of this species. This strain was positive by Bps latex agglutination; this
finding is in agreement with previous findings of a <italic>B. thailandensis</italic>
strain from Thailand with a Bps-like capsular polysaccharide variant that also had a
positive Bps latex-agglutination result (<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><italic>39</italic></xref>). Our phylogenic analysis shows a divergence between
the strain from Gabon and the original <italic>B. thailandenis</italic> E264 from
Thailand, which is the most studied strain (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Evidence of the presence of this bacterium in Africa
will have implications for bacterial identification in clinical laboratories, diagnostic
serology assays, and environmental studies.</p>
      <p>Our study has several limitations. <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> serology can be
misleading; false- positive results are a major concern (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><italic>40</italic></xref>). Clearly, for assessing exposure to <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic>, an accurate, inexpensive, simple serologic assay is needed. In
the interim, however, serologic evidence of exposure should be based on assays with
known sensitivity and specificity against culture-confirmed melioidosis, and, to our
understanding, the IHA is the best test for identifying melioidosis cases. Given the
nature of working in a resource-poor environment, only limited information is available
on the patient reported here (e.g., no imaging was performed to investigate the presence
of deeper abscesses). With regard to the environmental study, <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> is known for its capacity to survive in water and has been
reported to be present in the air during severe weather (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>); we, however did not investigate its presence in
water and air in Gabon in this study. Furthermore, we cannot dismiss the possibility of
error during soil sampling although guidelines for environmental sampling of <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> were followed (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>).</p>
      <p>In summary, we identified <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> in the Gabon environment and discovered a novel <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> ST that can cause lethal septic shock. <italic>B.
pseudomallei</italic> is probably an underrecognized cause of disease in central
Africa. We propose that melioidosis occurs in central Africa but that it is unrecognized
because of the lack of diagnostic microbiology facilities.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="citation">
        <p><italic>Suggested citation for this article</italic>: Wiersinga WJ, Birnie E,
Weehuizen TA, Alabi AS, Huson MA, Huis in &#x2019;t Veld RAG, et al. Clinical,
environmental, and serologic surveillance studies of melioidosis in Gabon,
2012&#x2013;2013. Emerg Infect Dis [Internet]. 2015 Jan [<italic>date
cited</italic>]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid2101.140762">http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid2101.140762</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="FN1">
        <label>1</label>
        <p>These authors contributed equally to this article.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank our colleagues in the field for fruitful discussions leading towards this
project, Sebastiaan Stolp for help with the logistics concerning the soil sampling
study, Katja de Jong and Jacqueline Lankelma for help in the laboratory, and Matt T.
Holden for help with the genetic analysis. </p>
      <p>This study was supported by the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (Veni
grant no. 91610008 to W.J.W.) and the Netherlands Organization for Health Research and
Development (ZonMW clinical fellowship grant no. 90700424 to W.J.W.). V.W. and D.L. work
at Mahidol-Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit funded by the Wellcome Trust of Great
Britain (no. 089275/Z/09/Z).</p>
    </ack>
    <bio id="d35e1288">
      <p>Dr. Wiersinga divides his time between patient care, teaching, and research at the
Academic Medical Center, Amsterdam. His research focus is sepsis.</p>
    </bio>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wiersinga</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Currie</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Peacock</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>.
<article-title>Melioidosis.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>367</volume>:<fpage>1035</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>44</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1204699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22970946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Currie</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melioidosis:
epidemiology, pathophysiology, and management.</article-title>
<source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>383</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>416</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.18.2.383-416.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831829</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Department of Health and Human Services, Centers
for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. Possession, use, and transfer of
select agents and toxins; biennial review. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://FedRegist.">Fed
Regist.</ext-link>
<year>2012</year>;77:61083&#x2013;115.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brett</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Deshazer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woods</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic>Burkholderia
thailandensis</italic> sp. nov., a <italic>Burkholderia
pseudomallei&#x2013;</italic>like species.</article-title>
<source>Int J Syst Bacteriol</source>.
<year>1998</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-48-1-317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9542103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Wiersinga</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de
Vos</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de
Beer</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://WielandCW">Wieland
CW</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://RoelofsJJ">Roelofs
JJ</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://WoodsDE">Woods
DE</ext-link>, et al. Inflammation patterns induced by different
<italic>Burkholderia</italic> species in mice. Cell Microbiol.
<year>2008</year>;10:81&#x2013;7.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Angus</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Arabinose assimilation
defines a nonvirulent biotype of <italic>Burkholderia
pseudomallei.</italic></article-title>
<source>Infect Immun</source>.
<year>1997</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>4319</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21</lpage>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9317042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Currie</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The epidemiology and
clinical spectrum of melioidosis: 540 cases from the 20 year Darwin prospective
study.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e900</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21152057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Rolim</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vilar</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sousa</surname>
<given-names>AQ</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://MirallesIS">Miralles
IS</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://deOliveiraDC">de
Oliveira DC</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HarnettG">Harnett
G</ext-link>, et al. Melioidosis, northeastern Brazil. Emerg Infect Dis.
<year>2005</year>;11:1458&#x2013;60.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Katangwe</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Purcell</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bar-Zeev</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://DenisB">Denis
B</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://MontgomeryJ">Montgomery J</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://AlaertsM">Alaerts
M</ext-link>, et al. Human melioidosis, Malawi, 2011. Emerg Infect Dis.
<year>2013</year>;19:981&#x2013;4.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Cuadros</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gil</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miguel</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Marab&#xE9;G">Marab&#xE9; G</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://G&#xF3;mez-HerruzTA">G&#xF3;mez-Herruz
TA</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://LoboB">Lobo
B</ext-link>, et al. Case report: melioidosis imported from West Africa to Europe.
Am J Trop Med Hyg. <year>2011</year>;85:282&#x2013;4.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Morosini</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Quereda</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gil</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://AndaP">Anda
P</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://N&#xFA;&#xF1;ez-MurgaM">N&#xFA;&#xF1;ez-Murga
M</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Cant&#xF3;nR">Cant&#xF3;n R</ext-link>, et al. Melioidosis in traveler from Africa to Spain.
Emerg Infect Dis. <year>2013</year>;19:1656&#x2013;9.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salam</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Malnick</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kenna</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dance</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klein</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melioidosis acquired
by traveler to Nigeria.</article-title>
<source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1296</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1707.110502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21762592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Batchelor</surname>
<given-names>BI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Trakulsomboon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mgongo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dance</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melioidosis survey in
Kenya.</article-title>
<source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>1994</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(94)90286-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7518617</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Currie</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dance</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The global
distribution of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> and melioidosis: an
update.</article-title>
<source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>S1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0035-9203(08)70002-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19121666</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Lell</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Faucher</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Missinou</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://BorrmannS">Borrmann
S</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://DangelmaierO">Dangelmaier O</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HortonJ">Horton
J</ext-link>, et al. Malaria chemoprophylaxis with tafenoquine: a randomised
study. Lancet. <year>2000</year>;355:2041&#x2013;5.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Suputtamongkol</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dance</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ChaowagulW">Chaowagul W</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://RajchanuvongA">Rajchanuvong A</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://SmithMD">Smith
MD</ext-link>, et al. The epidemiology of melioidosis in Ubon Ratchatani,
northeast Thailand. Int J Epidemiol. <year>1994</year>;23:1082&#x2013;90.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Limmathurotsakul</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dance</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://KaestliM">Kaestli
M</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://MayoM">Mayo
M</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://WarnerJ">Warner
J</ext-link>, et al. Systematic review and consensus guidelines for environmental
sampling of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> PLoS Negl Trop Dis.
<year>2013</year>;7:e2105.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Chantratita</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dance</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Limmathurotsakul</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Peacock</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>. SOP: latex agglutination technique
for the detection of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic>
<year>2012</year>
[cited 2014 May 1]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.melioidosis.info/download.aspx">http://www.melioidosis.info/download.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>19. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jenney</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lum</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Currie</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antibiotic
susceptibility of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> from tropical
northern Australia and implications for therapy of melioidosis.</article-title>
<source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source>.
<year>2001</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>13</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0924-8579(00)00334-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11165114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R20">
        <label>20. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alexander</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Huxsoll</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Warner</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shepler</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dorsey</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serological diagnosis
of human melioidosis with indirect hemagglutination and complement fixation
tests.</article-title>
<source>Appl Microbiol</source>.
<year>1970</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>825</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33</lpage>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5530276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R21">
        <label>21. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Pheaktra</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Putchhat</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://SinL">Sin
L</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://SenB">Sen
B</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://KumarV">Kumar
V</ext-link>, et al. <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> antibodies in
children, Cambodia. Emerg Infect Dis. <year>2008</year>;14:301&#x2013;3.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R22">
        <label>22. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>O'Brien</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Freeman</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lum</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Currie</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Indirect
hemagglutination assay in patients with melioidosis in northern
Australia.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>2006</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>330</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16474092</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R23">
        <label>23. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Limmathurotsakul</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Chantratita</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://WongsuvanG">Wongsuvan G</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://AmornchaiP">Amornchai P</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://DayNP">Day
NP</ext-link>, et al. <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> is spatially
distributed in soil in northeast Thailand. PLoS Negl Trop Dis.
<year>2010</year>;4:e694.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R24">
        <label>24. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Anuntagool</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>White</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sirisinha</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short report: a rapid
method for the differentiation of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> and
<italic>Burkholderia thailandensis.</italic></article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>2002</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>759</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>61</lpage>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12224587</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R25">
        <label>25. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Amornchai</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Chierakul</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://MahakhunkijcharoenY">Mahakhunkijcharoen Y</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://PhetsouvanhR">Phetsouvanh R</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://CurrieBJ">Currie
BJ</ext-link>, et al. Accuracy of <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic>
identification using the API 20NE system and a latex agglutination test. J Clin
Microbiol. <year>2007</year>;45:3774&#x2013;6.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R26">
        <label>26. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Jones</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Breuning-Madson</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Brossard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. Soil atlas of Africa. European
Commission. Luxembourg (Belgium): Publications Office of the European Union;
<year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R27">
        <label>27. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Godoy</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Randle</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Simpson</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://AanensenDM">Aanensen
DM</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://PittTL">Pitt
TL</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://KinoshitaR">Kinoshita R</ext-link>, et al. Multilocus sequence typing and evolutionary
relationships among the causative agents of melioidosis and glanders,
<italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>Burkholderia
mallei</italic> J Clin Microbiol. <year>2003</year>;41:2068&#x2013;79.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R28">
        <label>28. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brett</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Deshazer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woods</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characterization of
<italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> and <italic>Burkholderia
pseudomallei&#x2013;</italic>like strains.</article-title>
<source>Epidemiol Infect</source>.
<year>1997</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>48</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S095026889600739X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9129590</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R29">
        <label>29. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bremmelgaard</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bygbjerg</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoiby</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Microbiological and
immunological studies in a case of human melioidosis diagnosed in
Denmark.</article-title>
<source>Scand J Infect Dis</source>.
<year>1982</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>
.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7163779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R30">
        <label>30. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mabey</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Corrah</surname>
<given-names>PT</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A case of melioidosis
in West Africa.</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>.
<year>1985</year>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>424</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/152.2.424a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4031552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R31">
        <label>31. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Issack</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bundhun</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gokhool</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melioidosis in
Mauritius.</article-title>
<source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>40</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1101.040605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15705340</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R32">
        <label>32. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Martinet</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pac
Soo</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Knezynski</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Melioidosis: regarding
a case acquired in Madagascar and two nosocomial cases</article-title>
<comment>[in French]</comment>
<source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot</source>.
<year>2004</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R33">
        <label>33. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Borgherini</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Poubeau</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Paganin</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://PicotS">Picot
S</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://MichaultA">Michault
A</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ThibaultF">Thibault
F</ext-link>, et al. Melioidosis: an imported case from Madagascar. J Travel Med.
<year>2006</year>;13:318&#x2013;20.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R34">
        <label>34. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Amezyane</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Lecoules</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Algayres</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mycotic iliac aneurysm
associated with <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei.</italic></article-title>
<source>Int J Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>Suppl
3</issue>):<fpage>e381</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2009.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19897393</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R35">
        <label>35. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Bertherat</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Thullier</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shako</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://EnglandK">England
K</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Kon&#xE9;ML">Kon&#xE9; ML</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ArntzenL">Arntzen
L</ext-link>, et al. Lessons learned about pneumonic plague diagnosis from two
outbreaks, Democratic Republic of the Congo. Emerg Infect Dis.
<year>2011</year>;17:778&#x2013;84.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R36">
        <label>36. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Rattanavong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://AmornchaiP">Amornchai P</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://SirisoukJ">Sirisouk
J</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://PhetsouvanhR">Phetsouvanh R</ext-link>, et al. Randomized soil survey of the distribution of
<italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> in rice fields in Laos. Appl Environ
Microbiol. <year>2011</year>;77:532&#x2013;6.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R37">
        <label>37. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name><surname>Kaestli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mayo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Harrington</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://WardL">Ward
L</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://WattF">Watt
F</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://,">,
</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HillJV">Hill
JV</ext-link>, et al. Landscape changes influence the occurrence of the
melioidosis bacterium <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic> in soil in northern
Australia. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. <year>2009</year>;3:e364.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R38">
        <label>38. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ussery</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kiil</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Lagesen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sicheritz-Ponten</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bohlin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wassenaar</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The genus
<italic>Burkholderia</italic>: analysis of 56 genomic
sequences.</article-title>
<source>Genome Dyn</source>.
<year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>57</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000235768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19696499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R39">
        <label>39. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><string-name><surname>Hantrakun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Rongkard</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Amonchi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sarunporn</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Langla</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wuthiekanun</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal/> Presence of environmental
<italic>B. pseudomallei, B. thailandensis</italic> and putative <italic>B.
thailandensis</italic> with <italic>B. ps</italic>&#x2013;like CPS variant in east
Thailand. Abstract in: Proceedings of the 7th World Melioidosis Congress;
<year>2013</year> Sep 18&#x2013;20; Bangkok, Thailand.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R40">
        <label>40. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Peacock</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Currie</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dance</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The use of positive
serological tests as evidence of exposure to <italic>Burkholderia
pseudomallei.</italic></article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>1021</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2011.11-0114a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21633045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
