<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25889909</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4409782</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">575</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12957-015-0575-9</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A giant myxoma originating from the aortic valve causing severe left ventricular tract obstruction: a case report and literature review</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Prifti</surname>
            <given-names>Edvin</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>edvinprifti@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Ademaj</surname>
            <given-names>Fadil</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>fadilademaj-kosove@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kajo</surname>
            <given-names>Efrosina</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>ekajo@yahoo.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baboci</surname>
            <given-names>Arben</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>arbenbaboci@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Division of Cardiac Surgery, University Hospital Center of Tirana, Tirana, Albania </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Division of Cardiology, Regional Hospital of Gjakova, Rr. Prizren, Gjakova, Kosovo </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>13</volume>
      <elocation-id>151</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Prifti et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>The left ventricular localization of a myxoma is very rare, usually arising from the interventricular septum close to the left ventricular outflow tract, the mitral valve, the ventricular wall and extremely rarely the aortic valve.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 13-year-old male was admitted due to dyspnea and angina. Transesophageal echocardiography revealed left ventricular outflow tract obstruction with a mean gradient of 58 mmHg, and a mobile mass measuring 65&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;25 mm originating from the ventricular surface of the aortic valve was identified. The patient underwent urgent surgical excision and aortic valve replacement. Histopathological examination of the mass confirmed the diagnosis of a myxoma.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>In conclusion, a myxoma originating from the aortic valve remains a very rare localization. Total resection associated with aortic valve replacement seems to offer an excellent outcome.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Aortic valve</kwd>
        <kwd>Myxoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Left ventricular tract obstruction</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Most cardiac myxomas are located in the left atrium, attached to the interatrial septum. The left ventricular localization of a myxoma is very rare, usually arising from the interventricular septum close to the left ventricular outflow tract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], the mitral valve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], the left ventricular wall [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] and extremely rarely the aortic valve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Here we report a case of an aortic valve myxoma undergoing successful resection.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 13-year-old male patient was admitted due to dyspnea and angina. On physical examination, peripheral pulses were present and normal. An early diastolic murmur could be heard in the aortic valve area. The ECG showed a normal sinus rhythm with signs of mild left ventricular hypertrophy. Transesophageal echocardiography revealed a grade II/IV aortic incompetence and left ventricular outflow tract obstruction with a peak gradient of 110 mmHg and a mean gradient of 58 mmHg, and a giant mobile mass originating from the ventricular surface of the aortic valve was identified (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). LV function was normal. The other cardiac valves and cavities were free of lesions. The patient underwent urgent surgical excision through a median sternotomy under normothermic cardiopulmonary bypass. The aorta was clamped and an anterior cardioplegic solution was administered. An anterior oblique aortotomy was performed. The inspection of the aortic valve revealed a 65&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;25 mm mass, attached to the ventricular surface of the right and left coronary leaflets (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). The mass was gelatinous soft (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C) with multiple haemorrhagic areas and was totally excised (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D). The patient underwent standard aortic valve replacement with mechanical prosthesis. Histopathological examination demonstrated a sparse population of round and stellate cells mostly concentrating beneath the surface, with some cells forming solid cords and vascular channels (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A), surrounded by abundant myxoid stroma (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B) confirming the diagnosis of a myxoma. Mitosis, pleomorphism and necrosis were all absent. The postoperative course was uneventful. The patient was followed up for 3 years postoperatively with a series of echocardiography control. Non-tumour recurrence was diagnosed.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Transthoracic echocardiography, aortotomy, and excision and division of the mass. <bold>(A)</bold> Transthoracic echocardiography revealing a mass at the left ventricular outflow tract. <bold>(B)</bold> Aortotomy was performed and the mass visualized underneath the aortic valve. <bold>(C)</bold> The total excised mass. <bold>(D)</bold> The mass was divided and multiple haemorrhagic areas discovered.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2015_575_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Histopathological examination. <bold>(A)</bold> The myxoma cells with a stellate appearance proliferate in a myxoid background in nests and linear syncytia, which often appear to emanate from vascular structures (H-E, 10X). <bold>(B)</bold> The myxoma cells variably express endothelial cell markers (CD 34, 20&#xD7;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2015_575_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Myxomas of the left ventricle are very rare. Recently, a thorough literature review demonstrated only 71 cases with a reported left ventricular myxoma usually originating from the interventricular septum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Myxomas of the cardiac valves are very unusual, especially those of the aortic valve. To our knowledge, this is the tenth reported case of an aortic valve myxoma. The first was described as a <italic>post</italic>-<italic>mortem</italic> finding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. However, the patient in the present case is the youngest amongst them.</p>
      <p>The shape, the extension, the site of attachment, the involvement of valve leaflets and the functional obstruction of the LV outflow tract could promptly and easily be assessed by echocardiography. Transesophageal echocardiography enables the detection of an aortic valve myxoma; however, histopathology remains the gold standard method of diagnosis. Most of the tumours were larger than 1 cm; however, the present case had the greatest mass dimensions amongst the reported cases with an aortic valve myxoma.</p>
      <p>Our patient referred dyspnea and angina. The clinical presentations of the other seven reported cases included acute embolic stroke, acute embolic myocardial infarction, acute embolic lower limb ischaemia and aortic stenosis (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). An aortic valve myxoma has been described as arising from both the ventricular aspect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and the margin of the valve cusps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The right, left and non-coronary leaflets may be affected either together or individually (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In the other two reported cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], the right and left cusps were simultaneously affected as in our patient.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Clinical presentations of the reported cases and the present case</bold>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="top"><th>
<bold>Reference</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Age</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Clinical finding</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Size</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Complication</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Associated procedure</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Location</bold>
</th><th>
<bold>Comorbidity</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td>Kennedy <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td>23</td><td>Leg pain</td><td>1.5 cm</td><td>PVD</td><td>AVR</td><td>RCC and LCC</td><td>None</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Watarida <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td><td>58</td><td>Heart murmur</td><td>1.1&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;1 cm</td><td>None</td><td>AVR</td><td>RCC</td><td>HTN</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Ramsheyi <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td><td>32</td><td>Facial hemiparesis</td><td>1 cm</td><td>Stroke</td><td>AVR</td><td>RCC</td><td>None</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Okamoto <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]</td><td>61</td><td>Endocarditis</td><td>1&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;1 cm</td><td>None</td><td>None</td><td>LCC</td><td>HTN, DM</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Dyk <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td><td>15</td><td>Chest pain</td><td>4&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;1 cm</td><td>STEMI</td><td>None</td><td>NCC</td><td>None</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Koyalakonda <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>60</td><td>Paroxysmal A-fib</td><td>1&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;1 cm</td><td>Stroke</td><td>None</td><td>RCC</td><td>A-fib, HTN</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Kim <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td>72</td><td>Shortness of breath</td><td>1.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;0.8 cm</td><td>None</td><td>AVR</td><td>NCC</td><td>HTN, A-fib</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Fernandez <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</td><td>28</td><td>Hemiparesis</td><td>1.5&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;0.7 cm</td><td>Stroke</td><td>AVR</td><td>RCC and LCC</td><td>Epilepsy</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>Javed <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td><td>81</td><td>Leg pain</td><td>1.8&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;1.2 cm</td><td>AMI</td><td>CABG</td><td>LCC</td><td>HTN, AA</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td>This study</td><td>13</td><td>Dyspnea and angina</td><td>60&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;22 mm</td><td>None</td><td>AVR</td><td>RCC and LCC</td><td>None</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>AVR, aortic valve replacement; CABG, coronary artery bypass grafting; DM, diabetes mellitus; HTN, hypertension; LCC, left coronary cusp; NCC, non-coronary cusp; RCC, right coronary cusp; PVD, peripheral vascular disease; AMI, acute myocardial infarction; STEMI, ST segment elevation myocardial infarction.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Differential diagnosis of an aortic valve myxoma includes vegetations, papillary fibroelastoma and Lambl&#x2019;s excrescences. Microscopic and immunohistochemical characteristics allow the distinction between these entities. As we have observed, aortic valve myxomas are a potential source of emboli; therefore, surgical removal should be indicated as soon as the diagnosis is confirmed. Surgical excision should include not only the tumour but also the implantation site to minimize the risk of local recurrence. Tumour resection with conservation of the native valve should be intended, but sometimes due to a big tumour size and/or structural valve degeneration, replacement of the aortic valve may become necessary as in our case. These patients should be followed carefully due to a high probability of distal tumour growth at the site of previous embolization as well as local recurrence of the tumour.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>In conclusion, a myxoma originating from the aortic valve remains a very rare left ventricular localization of such a tumour. Total resection associated with aortic valve replacement seems to offer an excellent outcome.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient&#x2019;s legal guardian(s) for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>EP and AB performed the surgery. FA and EK performed the diagnosis and the manuscript writing including the literature review. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Natale</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minardi</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casali</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pulignano</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Musumeci</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Left ventricular myxoma originating from the interventricular septum and obstructing the left ventricular outflow tract</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Echocardiogr</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>84</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17379578</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rao</surname>
              <given-names>RV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walsh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stadnick</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sohmer</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veinot</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unusual cause of an ejection murmur: myxoma in the left ventricular outflow tract</article-title>
          <source>Can J Cardiol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1742.e13-5</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cjca.2013.07.799</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24404613</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garg</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Left ventricular myxoma in a child: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Echocardiogr</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>E23</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ejechocard/jeq182</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21239452</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keeling</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oberwalder</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schuchlenz</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anelli-Monti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rigler</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Left ventricular outflow tract obstruction due to valve myxoma</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>1590</fpage>
          <lpage>1</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(00)01182-6</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10881855</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>BW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryu</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choe</surname>
              <given-names>KO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myxoma attached to both atrial and ventricular sides of the mitral valve: report of a case and review of 31 cases of mitral myxoma</article-title>
          <source>Int J Cardiovasc Imaging</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>411</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1011986001058</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12025955</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abad</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Novoa</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delgado</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alonso</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myxoma of the left ventricle</article-title>
          <source>Tex Heart Inst J</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>395</fpage>
          <lpage>400</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14503/THIJ-13-3281</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25120392</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Javed</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zalawadiya</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kovach</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Afonso</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aortic valve myxoma at the extreme age: a review of literature</article-title>
          <source>BMJ Case Rep</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>2014</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wold</surname>
              <given-names>LE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lie</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cardiac myxomas: a clinico-pathologic profile</article-title>
          <source>Am J Pathol</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>219</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7446701</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Watarida</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katsuyama</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasuda</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magara</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Onoe</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nojima</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myxoma of the aortic valve</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>234</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(96)00771-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8993277</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramsheyi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deleuze</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D&#x2019;Attelis</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bical</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lefort</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aortic valve myxoma</article-title>
          <source>J Card Surg</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>491</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1540-8191.1998.tb01089.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10543466</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Okamoto</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kazui</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suzuki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koshima</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamashita</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aortic valve myxoma mimicking vegetation: report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Surg Today</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>927</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00595-006-3273-y</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16998689</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dyk</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Konka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Images in cardiothoracic surgery: unusual complication of aortic valve grape-like myxoma</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>1022</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2008.12.051</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19699953</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kennedy</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parry</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parums</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pillai</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myxoma of the aortic valve</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>1221</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-4975(94)00969-E</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7733728</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vega</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El-Diasty</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Su&#xE1;rez</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Myxoma of the aortic valve</article-title>
          <source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>560</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icvts/ivs117</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22617509</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koyalakonda</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mediratta</surname>
              <given-names>NK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ball</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Royle</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A rare case of aortic valve myxoma: an unusual cause of embolic stroke</article-title>
          <source>Cardiology</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000327081</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21540590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>SU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>WI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A rare case of aortic valve myxoma: easy to confuse with papillary fibroelastoma</article-title>
          <source>Korean Circ J</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>281</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4070/kcj.2012.42.4.281</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22563343</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
