<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25475024</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4289318</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1847</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7819-12-372</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Robotic pancreaticoduodenectomy in a case of duodenal gastrointestinal stromal tumor</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Parisi</surname>
            <given-names>Amilcare</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>amilcareparisi@virgilio.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Desiderio</surname>
            <given-names>Jacopo</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>djdesi85@hotmail.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trastulli</surname>
            <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>stefano.trastulli@hotmail.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grassi</surname>
            <given-names>Veronica</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>veronicagrassi@hotmail.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ricci</surname>
            <given-names>Francesco</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>f.fricci@libero.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Farinacci</surname>
            <given-names>Federico</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>federico.farinacci@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff11"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cacurri</surname>
            <given-names>Alban</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>albancacurri@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Castellani</surname>
            <given-names>Elisa</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>elisa.ecv@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Corsi</surname>
            <given-names>Alessia</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>alessia.cor@libero.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Renzi</surname>
            <given-names>Claudio</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>renzicla@virgilio.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Barberini</surname>
            <given-names>Francesco</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>francescobarberini@hotmail.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>D&#x2019;Andrea</surname>
            <given-names>Vito</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>vito.dandrea@uniroma1.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff13"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Santoro</surname>
            <given-names>Alberto</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>albert.santoro@tiscali.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff13"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cirocchi</surname>
            <given-names>Roberto</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>cirocchiroberto@yahoo.it</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff10"><label/>Department of Digestive and Liver Surgery Unit, St. Maria Hospital, Via Tristano di Joannuccio 1, Terni, 05100 Italy </aff>
        <aff id="Aff11"><label/>Mininvasive and Robotic Surgery, St. Maria Hospital, University of Perugia, Via Tristano di Joannuccio 1, Terni, 05100 Italy </aff>
        <aff id="Aff12"><label/>Department of General and Oncologic Surgery, University of Perugia, Piazzale Gambuli 1, Perugia, 06157 Italy </aff>
        <aff id="Aff13"><label/>Department of General Surgery, Sapienza University of Rome, Viale del Policlinico 155, Roma, 00161 Italy </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <elocation-id>372</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Parisi et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Laparoscopic pancreaticoduodenectomy is rarely performed, and it has not been particularly successful due to its technical complexity. The objective of this study is to highlight how robotic surgery could improve a minimally invasive approach and to expose the usefulness of robotic surgery even in complex surgical procedures.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>The surgical technique employed in our center to perform a pancreaticoduodenectomy, which was by means of the da Vinci&#x2122; robotic system in order to remove a duodenal gastrointestinal stromal tumor, is reported.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Robotic technology has improved significantly over the traditional laparoscopic approach, representing an evolution of minimally invasive techniques, allowing procedures to be safely performed that are still considered to be scarcely feasible or reproducible.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>pancreaticoduodenectomy</kwd>
        <kwd>robotic technology</kwd>
        <kwd>GIST</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2014</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Pancreaticoduodenectomy (PD) is one of the most complex interventions in abdominal surgery, still performed by experienced surgeons in specialized centers. The laparoscopic approach to distal pancreaticoduodenectomy has spread significantly, while its use in PD is very rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Since robotics in digestive surgery represents a recent evolution of the laparoscopic approach, its role and application over the traditional minimally invasive surgery is still debated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. A robotic pylorus-preserving pancreaticoduodenectomy performed in our center for the treatment of a duodenal gastrointestinal stromal tumor (GIST) is reported.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Case report</title>
        <p>A 68-year-old woman was admitted to our department with fatigue, anemia and positive fecal occult blood. The endoscopy showed an enlarged and ulcerated ampulla of Vater. The morphological and immunohistochemical findings were compatible with GIST. Computed tomography (CT) staging confirmed the presence of a parietal, stenotizing polypoid lesion without infiltration of the adjacent tissue. A pylorus-preserving pancreaticoduodenectomy (Traverso-Longmire procedure) using the da Vinci Si&#x2122; HD Surgical System robot was proposed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Technical notes</title>
        <p>A 20-degree anti-Trendelenburg position is preferred, slightly rotated 10 degrees to the left side. Trocars are placed through the umbilicus following a concave curved line. The optical trocar is inserted about 5&#xA0;cm to the right of the umbilical line. The first robotic trocar is positioned between the midaxillary and the transverse umbilical line, the second robotic trocar between the right axillary line and the transverse umbilical line, and the third robotic trocar in the right hypochondrium. A 12-mm extra-port is located between the umbilicus and the first robotic trocar. A robotic camera is inserted through the periumbilical trocar port. To access the retrocavity of the epiploon, the gastrocolic ligament is opened outside the gastroepiploic arch. The back wall of the stomach is identified. A Kocher maneuver is performed to release the second and the third portion of the duodenum and views of the inferior vena cava and of the left renal vein. The pancreatic isthmus is identified, a retropancreatic tunnel is created between the posterior face of the pancreas and the superior mesenteric vein (SMV). Then, a retrograde cholecystectomy is performed to allow further mobilization of the duodenal-pancreatic block and to identify the course of the main bile duct, which must be sectioned below the confluence of the cystic duct (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The course of the gastroduodenal artery is identified and the artery is sectioned Ultracision&#x2122; (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The duodenum is sectioned 3&#xA0;cm below the pylorus with a laparoscopic linear stapler. The retro-pancreatic tunnel is completed, and the pancreas is loaded on a tape. The upper and lower edges of the pancreatic isthmus are closed and a pancreatic dissection is performed with the robotic Ultracision&#x2122; (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). After the course of the SMV and the spleno-mesenteric confluence of the portal trunk are identified, a section of the retroportal pancreatic lamina is performed. A pancreaticogastrostomy is performed via a transgastric approach (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The anterior wall of the stomach is opened to allow access to the back wall and the residual pancreas is anastomosed with an interrupted suture technique. Finally, the gastric anterior wall is closed. Then, the ligament of Treiz is identified, and a section of the first jejunal loop is performed. The biliary-jejunal anastomosis is confectioned (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). A minilaparotomy is performed and a Lap Disc&#x2122; is positioned; the termino-lateral duodeno-jejunal anastomosis is closed, and the surgical specimen is retrieved. Two intra-abdominal drains are placed. Surgical time was 510&#xA0;minutes; blood loss was 250&#xA0;ml. The postoperative course was fast and smooth. No perioperative complication occurred. On the first post-operative day the Pain Visual Analog Scale (VAS) score was 3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. On the second day fluid intake was restored. Digestive function is recovered on day 3, allowing a solid diet. Bowel functions recovery in day 5 led to the removal of the abdominal drains. The patient was discharged on day 9. The Short Form-12 (SF-12) assessment scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] showed a quick return to daily activities. The histopathological examination was group 3 GIST, according to the classification by Miettinen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. At 18&#xA0;months after the operation, there was no recurrence of disease or complications.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>The bile duct is divided with robotic scissors.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2014_1847_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e441"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>After the gastroduodenal artery is identified, it is sectioned between the Hem-o-lok using the robotic Ultracision&#x2122;.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2014_1847_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e453"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>
<bold>The dissection of the pancreas is performed with robotic Ultracision&#x2122;.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2014_1847_Fig3_HTML" id="d30e465"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>
<bold>The pancreaticogastrostomy is performed with a transgastric approach.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2014_1847_Fig4_HTML" id="d30e477"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>
<bold>Execution of the biliary jejunal anastomosis.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2014_1847_Fig5_HTML" id="d30e489"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Technological advances in recent decades have resulted in significant development of minimally invasive techniques. However, PD still remains a highly demanding procedure and since 1994, when Gagner performed the first PD using a laparoscopic approach, only 146 cases have been reported in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The implementation of robotic systems applied to abdominal surgery has led surgeons keen to use minimally invasive surgery to test a new approach in those procedures. However, to date, robotic PD has not yet been standardized in the literature and the range of surgical techniques employed is wide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Several authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] have described a hybrid robotic-laparoscopic-open surgical procedure because robotics was seen initially as complementary to laparoscopy, especially to facilitate the implementation of the visceral anastomosis. Thus, the first procedures to be described in literature consisted in a laparoscopic approach first, with a subsequent robotic reconstructive time. The technique used derives from the one presented by Giulianotti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], consisting in a fully robotic demolitive and reconstructive time, called robot-assisted PD or simply robotic PD in contrast with the hybrid techniques already mentioned. We believe that the robotic approach is not just complementary, but represents a real evolution compared to the traditional laparoscopic approach, and it is applicable to all stages of PD. According to Giulianotti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], in robotic surgery the tactile feedback is replaced by visual feedback and the dissection of SMV from pancreatic parenchyma is performed safely and with great precision. The da Vinci&#x2122; robotic system increases the surgeon&#x2019;s dexterity, his ability to perform a precise dissection of the tissues and advanced sutures, and it can replace tactile feed-back with a visual feedback. In this way, it is possible to rebuild the gastrointestinal tract with biliary, pancreatic and gastric hand-sewn 3-4/0 PDS anastomosis and to extract the surgical specimen from a service laparotomy just 5&#xA0;cm long.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6" sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We believe that the development of robotic technology has increased the indications to perform a minimally invasive approach in complex interventions such as PD, which appears more feasible and safer in selected patients and to experienced surgeons within dedicated teams.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for the publication of this report and any accompanying images.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-list>
          <def-item>
            <term>CT</term>
            <def>
              <p>computed tomography</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
          <def-item>
            <term>GIST</term>
            <def>
              <p>gastrointestinal stromal tumor</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
          <def-item>
            <term>PD</term>
            <def>
              <p>pancreaticoduodenectomy</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
          <def-item>
            <term>SMV</term>
            <def>
              <p>superior mesenteric vein</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
          <def-item>
            <term>VAS</term>
            <def>
              <p>Visual Analog Scale</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
          <def-item>
            <term>SF-12</term>
            <def>
              <p>Short Form-12.</p>
            </def>
          </def-item>
        </def-list>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. Furthermore for the writing of this paper the authors didn&#x2019;t benefit of any source of funding.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>AP Concepted, drafted and revised the manuscript. JD designed and revised the manuscript. ST concepted and revised the manuscript. VG designed, drafted and revised the paper. FR concepted and revised the manuscript. FF designed, drafted and revised the manuscript. AC concepted and drafted the manuscript. EC drafted and revised the manuscript. AC drafted and revised the manuscript. CR designed, drafted and revised the manuscript. FB designed, concepted and revised the manuscript. VD concepted, designed and revised the manuscript AS designed, concepted and revised the manuscript. RC concepted, drafted and revised critically the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cirocchi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Partelli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coratti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desiderio</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parisi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falconi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Current status of robotic distal pancreatectomy: a systematic review</article-title>
          <source>Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>201</fpage>
          <lpage>207</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.suronc.2013.07.002</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23910929</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dulucq</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wintringer</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahajna</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Laparoscopic pancreaticoduodenectomy for benign and malignant diseases</article-title>
          <source>Surg Endosc</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1045</fpage>
          <lpage>1050</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00464-005-0474-1</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16736311</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Giulianotti</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coratti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Angelini</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sbrana</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cecconi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balestracci</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caravaglios</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Robotics in general surgery: personal experience in a large community hospital</article-title>
          <source>Arch Surg</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>138</volume>
          <fpage>777</fpage>
          <lpage>784</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archsurg.138.7.777</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12860761</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huskisson</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Measurement of pain</article-title>
          <source>J Rheumatol</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>768</fpage>
          <lpage>769</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6184474</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ware</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kosinski</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keller</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A 12-Item Short-Form Health Survey: construction of scales and preliminary tests of reliability and validity</article-title>
          <source>Med Care</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>220</fpage>
          <lpage>233</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005650-199603000-00003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8628042</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miettinen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lasota</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gastrointestinal stromal tumors: review on morphology, molecular pathology, prognosis, and differential diagnosis</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>1466</fpage>
          <lpage>1478</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17090188</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gagner</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pomp</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Laparoscopic pylorus-preserving pancreatoduodenectomy</article-title>
          <source>Surg Endosc</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>408</fpage>
          <lpage>410</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00642443</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7915434</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cirocchi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Partelli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trastulli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coratti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parisi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falconi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A systematic review on robotic pancreaticoduodenectomy</article-title>
          <source>Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>238</fpage>
          <lpage>246</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.suronc.2013.08.003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24060451</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>D&#x2019;Annibale</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orsini</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morpurgo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sovernigo</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>La chirurgia robotica. Considerazioni dopo 250 interventi</article-title>
          <source>Chir Ital</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>5</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16729603</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Narula</surname>
              <given-names>VK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mikami</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melvin</surname>
              <given-names>WS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Robotic and laparoscopic pancreaticoduodenectomy: a hybrid approach</article-title>
          <source>Pancreas</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>160</fpage>
          <lpage>164</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPA.0b013e3181bd604e</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910835</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Giulianotti</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sbrana</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bianco</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elli</surname>
              <given-names>EF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Addeo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caravaglios</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coratti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Robot-assisted laparoscopic pancreatic surgery: single-surgeon experience</article-title>
          <source>Surg Endosc</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1646</fpage>
          <lpage>1657</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00464-009-0825-4</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20063016</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
