<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rimtsp</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Revista do Instituto de Medicina Tropical de S&#xE3;o Paulo</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0036-4665</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-9946</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Instituto de Medicina Tropical</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26603236</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4660458</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0036-46652015000500015</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>FIRST CASE OF HUMAN INFECTION BY <italic>Bertiella</italic>
<italic>studeri</italic> (Blanchard, 1891) Stunkard,1940 (Cestoda; Anoplocephalidae) IN BRAZIL</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Primeiro caso de infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o humana por <italic>Bertiella studeri</italic> (Blanchard, 1891) Stunkard,1940 (Cestoda; Anoplocephalidae) no Brasil</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>LOPES</surname>
            <given-names>Valeriana Valadares</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>dos SANTOS</surname>
            <given-names>Hudson Andrade</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>da SILVA</surname>
            <given-names>Am&#xE1;lia Ver&#xF4;nica Mendes</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>FONTES</surname>
            <given-names>Gilberto</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>VIEIRA</surname>
            <given-names>Gabriela Lisboa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>FERREIRA</surname>
            <given-names>Arilton Carlos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>da SILVA</surname>
            <given-names>Eduardo Sergio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>(1)</label>Universidade Federal de S&#xE3;o Jo&#xE3;o del-Rei, Campus Centro-Oeste, CCO/UFSJ, Divin&#xF3;polis, MG, Brasil. E-mails: <email>valeriana@ufsj.edu.br, gilberto.fontes@pq.cnpq.br, tutalisboa@hotmail.com, professorariltonferreira@yahoo.com.br, silvaedu@ufsj.edu.br</email></aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>(2)</label>Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais, Laborat&#xF3;rio de Helmintologia Veterin&#xE1;ria do Departamento de Parasitologia, ICB/UFMG, Belo Horizonte, MG, Brasil. E-mail: <email>hudson@icb.ufmg.br</email></aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>(3)</label>Universidade FUMEC, Faculdade de Ci&#xEA;ncias Humanas, Sociais e Sa&#xFA;de, Belo Horizonte, MG, Brasil. E-mail: <email>avsilva@fumec.br</email></aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Gilberto Fontes. E-mail: <email>gilberto.fontes@pq.cnpq.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>57</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>447</fpage>
      <lpage>450</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>SUMMARY</title>
        <p>Cestodes of the <italic>Bertiella</italic> genus are parasites of non-human primates found in Africa, Asia, Oceania and the Americas. Species <italic>Bertiella studeri</italic> and <italic>Bertiella mucronata </italic>could, accidentally, infect human beings. The infection occurs from ingestion of mites from the Oribatida order containing cysticercoid larvae of the parasite. The objective of this report is to register the first case of human infection by <italic>Bertiella studeri</italic> in Brazil. Proglottids of the parasite, found in the stool sample of a two-and-a-half-year-old child, were fixed, stained and microscopically observed to evaluate its morphological characteristics. Eggs obtained from the proglottids were also studied. The gravid proglottids examined matched the description of the genus <italic>Bertiella</italic>. The eggs presented a round shape, with the average diameter of 43.7 &#xB5;m, clearly showing the typical pyriform apparatus of <italic>B. studeri</italic>. The authors concluded that the child was infected with <italic>Bertiella studeri, </italic>based on Stunkard's (1940) description of the species. This is the fifth case of human Bertiellosis described in Brazil through morphometric analysis of the parasite, the third in Minas Gerais State and the first diagnosed case of <italic>Bertiella studeri </italic>in Brazil. </p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <title>RESUMO</title>
        <p>Os cest&#xF3;deos do g&#xEA;nero <italic>Bertiella </italic>s&#xE3;o parasitos de primatas n&#xE3;o humanos, os quais s&#xE3;o encontrados na &#xC1;frica, &#xC1;sia, Austr&#xE1;lia, Oceania e Am&#xE9;ricas. As esp&#xE9;cies <italic>Bertiella studeri</italic> e <italic>Bertiella mucronata</italic> podem, eventualmente, vir a infectar os seres humanos e a infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o acontece pela ingest&#xE3;o acidental de &#xE1;caros da ordem Oribatida infectados com larvas cisticerc&#xF3;ides do parasito. O objetivo deste estudo foi relatar o primeiro caso humano por <italic>Bertiella studeri</italic> no Brasil. Proglotes do parasito, encontrado na amostra de fezes de uma crian&#xE7;a com idade de 2,5 anos, foram fixados, corados e observados ao microsc&#xF3;pio para avaliar as suas caracter&#xED;sticas morfol&#xF3;gicas. Ovos, obtidos a partir dos proglotes tamb&#xE9;m foram estudados. As proglotes gr&#xE1;vidas examinadas estavam de acordo com a descri&#xE7;&#xE3;o do g&#xEA;nero <italic>Bertiella</italic>. Os ovos apresentam forma arredondada com di&#xE2;metro m&#xE9;dio de 43,7 &#xB5;m, demonstrando claramente aparelho piriforme t&#xED;pico de <italic>B. studeri</italic>. Os autores conclu&#xED;ram que a crian&#xE7;a estava infectada com <italic>Bertiella studeri</italic>, de acordo com a descri&#xE7;&#xE3;o da esp&#xE9;cie por Stunkard (1940). Este &#xE9; o quinto caso de Bertiellose humana descrita no Brasil por meio de an&#xE1;lises morfom&#xE9;tricas do parasito, o terceiro em Minas Gerais e o primeiro caso de diagn&#xF3;stico por <italic>Bertiella</italic>
<italic>studeri</italic> no Brasil.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Bertiella</kwd>
        <kwd>Human bertiellosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Helminth</kwd>
        <kwd>Zoonosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="22"/>
        <page-count count="4"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>
<italic>Bertiella </italic>sp. is a cestode from the Anoplocephalidae family, common parasites in non-human primates, rodents and Australian marsupials, being the only representatives of the family with human infection case reports<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. Among the 29 species of this genus listed by SCHMIDT (1986)<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, two, <italic>Bertiella studeri</italic> (Blanchard, 1891) and<italic>Bertiella mucronata </italic>(Meyner, 1895) are the major causes of human bertiellosis, mainly in infants<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>. Cestodes of the genus <italic>Bertiella</italic> are heteroxenic parasites found in the small intestine of mammals, especially non-human primates. Their invertebrate hosts are mites of the Oribatida order<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>. DENEGRI (1993)<sup>6 </sup>showed several oribatid mites that can act as intermediate hosts of 14 genera and 27 species of anoplocephalid tapeworms. </p>
      <p>Human infection by <italic>Bertiella </italic>sp. is usually asymptomatic. However gastrointestinal disturbances, diarrhea, abdominal pain, anorexia, weight loss, vomit and constipation have been reported<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>. As this clinical presentation is common in numerous gastrointestinal pathologies, the bertiellosis diagnose is confirmed by parasitological stool examination<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>.</p>
      <p>BLANCHARD (1913)<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> described the first case of human bertiellosis in an eight-year-old-female patient from Mauritius, parasitized by <italic>Bertiella studeri. </italic>Since the initial records, over 50 cases of <italic>Bertiella</italic> sp. in humans have been reported around the world<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>. In Brazil, up to now, only four human cases were detected based on morphological and morphometric egg analysis<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. </p>
      <p>The objective of this paper is to report a case of human bertiellosis in Brazil originated in Perdigao, a city located in the Midwest region of Minas Gerais State.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>The patient was a Brazilian two and a half year old female, born and raised in the city of Perdigao, located in the midwest region of Minas Gerais State. The patient's prior history includes living on a farm inhabited by non-human primates. Since January 2011, the child started to present sporadic episodes of abdominal pain. A few months later, her parents noticed spontaneous elimination of proglottids in the feces. Fragments of the adult worm and stool samples were collected and parasitological examinations were carried out. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
      <p>Stool samples were collected and fixed in a 10% formalin solution for parasitological exams. Cestodes fragments and proglottids found in the feces were separated and washed in a 0.85% saline solution. Subsequently, the proglottids were pressed between two slides to flatten them uniformly, fixed in FAA (formalin-acetic acid-alcohol) solution, stained with alum acetocarmine solution, dehydrated in a crescent series of ethanol, diafanized in Faia's creosote and mounted in Canada balsam between a microscope slide and cover slip. The fecal samples were processed by KATO-KATZ<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and LUTZ (1919)<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> methods for parasitological exams. Micrometric studies were performed and microphotographs were taken using an optical microscope (Leika) equipped with a digital camera (AxioCam ERc 5s, Carl Zeiss). Measurements were made using an image analysis software (Axio Vision version 4.8, Carl Zeiss Vision).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <p>Three 1 cm segments with 15 imbricated proglottids measuring 0.8 cm in length and 1.0 cm in width were examined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1A</xref>). After staining progottid fragments, unilateral, irregularly alternated, genital pores located between the anterior and posterior margin of each proglottid were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1B</xref>). Similar structures to the muscular part of the cirrus pouch and masses of eggs can be observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1C</xref>. </p>
      <p>
<fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>
<bold>-</bold>
<italic>Bertiella</italic> sp. proglottids. A) Proglottids fixed segments in FAA; B) Proglottids stained with alum acetocarmine solution (muscular part of the cirrus pouch); C) Proglottids showing eggs and genital pores.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0036-4665-rimtsp-57-05-00447-gf01"/></fig>
</p>
      <p>Based on morphological features, the proglottids have been identified as <italic>Bertiella</italic> genus. Eggs observed by microscopic examination show spherical shape and an external rough membrane measuring 42 to 47.3 &#xB5;m in diameter (average of 43.77 &#xB5;m). The average dimension of the hexacant embryo with the pyriform apparatus was 24.5 &#xB5;m and the measurement of just the hexacant embryo was 15.75 &#xB5;m (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig. 2</xref>). Based on the morphometry of the eggs and the pyriform apparatus<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, the authors identified the species as <italic>Bertiella studeri.</italic>
</p>
      <p>
<fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>
<bold>-</bold>
<italic>Bertiella</italic> sp. eggs showing the pyriform apparatus. A) Eggs recovered from the patient's stool (200X); B) Eggs liberated from gravid proglottids (400X); C) Eggs washed with lactophenol of Amann (1000X).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0036-4665-rimtsp-57-05-00447-gf02"/></fig>
</p>
      <p>On the parasitological stool exams, the authors found only <italic>Bertiella</italic> sp. eggs. No other helminth or protozoan infections were detected.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The first report of human bertiellosis in Brazil was identified as <italic>Bertiella mucronata</italic> in an adult patient in the city of Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo State<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>. COSTA <italic>et al</italic>. (1967)<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> reported the second case of <italic>B. mucronata</italic> in an individual from the city of Formiga, Minas Gerais State. The third human infection by<italic> Bertiella</italic> sp. was diagnosed in a two-year-old infant from Goiania, Goias State<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>. SILVA <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> reported the fourth case of <italic>Bertiella </italic>sp. infection in an eight-year-old resident of the municipality of Caete, Minas Gerais State. This current report is the third case of human bertiellosis in Minas Gerais State, and the fifth case in Brazil.</p>
      <p>The proper bertiellosis diagnosis in humans is made by observing the morphological characteristics of the progottids and the scolex. In addition, the morphometric parameters of the eggs must be analyzed<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>.</p>
      <p>The authors defined the species as being <italic>Bertiella studeri </italic>by considering the morphological description of the proglottids and morphometry of the eggs. To their knowledge, this is the first case of <italic>B. studeri</italic> human infection reported in Brazil.</p>
      <p>This species is the main etiological agent of human bertiellosis in the world, except in South America, where infections were diagnosed to be caused by <italic>Bertiella</italic> sp. or by the species <italic>B. mucronata</italic>.</p>
      <p>The symptoms reported by the child's guardians are compatible with human bertiellosis. Following diagnosis, the patient was medicated orally with praziquantel (10 mg/Kg) in a single dose. After treatment, no further elimination of proglottids occurred and the symptoms disappeared.</p>
      <p>Probably, the infection described here was acquired by accidental ingestion of Oribatid mites, harbouring cysticercoid larva, present in the soil or contaminated food. This process was also described in the MALIK <italic>et al</italic>. (2013)<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> study.</p>
      <p>DENEGRI (1985)<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> has predicted that the introduction of monkeys, in places where <italic>Bertiella</italic> is endemic and there is close contact of monkeys and humans are the cause of parasite spreading. He also suggested that an epidemiological inquiry should be performed in humans to ascertain the true prevalence of this parasitosis. It is difficult to control and prevent this zoonosis since the intermediate hosts are cosmopolitan with a large distribution<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>.</p>
      <p>According to LOZANO <italic>et al</italic>. (2010)<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> several cases of human bertiellosis in non-endemic countries are currently reported. This reinforces the importance of correctly identifying the parasite in order to prevent misdiagnosis with other cestode infections. </p>
      <p>This report contributes to alerting the public health authorities of this helmintic zoonosis occurrence in humans.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <p>The authors are grateful to Eliana Maria Mauricio da Rocha for the critical reading of the manuscript, and English review, and Fl&#xE1;via Mauricio da Rocha Fontes for the English review. </p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Achir</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zait</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamrioui</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Infection humaine due &#xE0;<italic>Bertiella </italic>sp (Cestode: Anoplocephalidae) observ&#xE9;e en Alg&#xE9;rie chez un &#xE9;tudiant originaire du Y&#xE9;men</article-title>
          <source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>108</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18543702</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blanchard</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<italic>Bertiella satyri</italic>de l'Orang-outang, est aussi parasite de l'homme</article-title>
          <source>Bull Acad M&#xE9;d (Paris)</source>
          <year>1913</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>186</fpage>
          <lpage>296</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corr&#xEA;a</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brener</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novo caso humano de parasitismo por<italic>Bertiella mucronata </italic>(Meyner, 1895) Stiles &amp; Hassal, 1902 (Cestoda-Anoplocephalidae)</article-title>
          <source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source>
          <year>1967</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          <lpage>97</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5628742</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Denegri</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Consideraciones sobre sistem&#xE1;tica y distribuci&#xF3;n geogr&#xE1;fica del g&#xE9;nero<italic>Bertiella </italic>Stiles &amp; Hassall, 1902 (Cestoda-Anoplocephalidae) en el hombre y en primates no humanos</article-title>
          <source>Neotr&#xF3;pica</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Denegri</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Desarrollo experimental de<italic>Bertiella mucronata </italic>Meyner, 1895 (Cestoda-Anoplocephalidae) de origen humano en su hu&#xE9;sped intermediario</article-title>
          <source>Zbl Vet Med</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>498</fpage>
          <lpage>504</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Denegri</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Review of oribatid mites as intermediate hosts of tapeworms of the Anoplocephalidae</article-title>
          <source>Exp Appl Acariol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>567</fpage>
          <lpage>580</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Denegri</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perez-Serrano</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bertiellosis in man: a review of cases</article-title>
          <source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>123</fpage>
          <lpage>127</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9394527</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Denegri</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bernadina</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perez-Serrano</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodriguez-Caabeiro</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anoplocephalidae cestodes of veterinary and medical significance: a review</article-title>
          <source>Folia Parasitol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9516990</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>El-Dib</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Ruffaii</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>El-Badry</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Zoheiry</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdell-Aal</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human infection with<italic>Bertiella </italic>species in Saudi Arabia</article-title>
          <source>Saudi Pharm J</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>168</fpage>
          <lpage>169</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gal&#xE1;n-Puchades</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuentes</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simarro</surname>
              <given-names>PP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mas-Coma</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human<italic>Bertiella studeri </italic>in Equatorial Guinea</article-title>
          <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>680</fpage>
          <lpage>680</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9509178</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xF3;mez-Puerta</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>L&#xF3;pez-Urbina</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ocurrence of tapeworm<italic>Bertiella mucronata </italic>(Cestoda: Anoplocephalidae) in the Titi monkey<italic>Callicebus oenanthe </italic>from Peru: new definitive host and geographical record</article-title>
          <source>Vet Parasitol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>163</volume>
          <fpage>161</fpage>
          <lpage>163</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19414220</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chaves</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pellegrino</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A simple device for quantitative stool thick smear technique in schistosomiasis mansoni</article-title>
          <source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source>
          <year>1972</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>397</fpage>
          <lpage>400</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4675644</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lozano M del</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garc&#xED;a-Martos</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garc&#xED;a-Tapia</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fern&#xE1;ndez</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<italic>Bertiella studeri </italic>infection in a girl from Equatorial Guinea</article-title>
          <source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>652</fpage>
          <lpage>653</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20363057</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lutz</surname>
              <given-names>AO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<italic>Schistosomum mansoni</italic>e a shistomatose segundo observa&#xE7;&#xF5;es, feitas no Brasil</article-title>
          <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source>
          <year>1919</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>144</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Malik</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>K</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
              <suffix>Srivastava</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samantaray</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human bertiellosis from North India</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>258</fpage>
          <lpage>260</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22359199</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pa&#xE7;&#xF4;</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campos</surname>
              <given-names>DMB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ara&#xFA;jo</surname>
              <given-names>JLB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human bertiellosis in Goi&#xE1;s, Brazil: a case report on human infection by<italic>Bertiella</italic>sp. (Cestoda: Anoplocephalidae)</article-title>
          <source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>161</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12870066</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pessoa</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sobre um caso de parasitismo humano por cestoide anoplocephalideo do g&#xEA;nero<italic>Bertiella</italic>
</article-title>
          <source>Bol Soc Med Cirurg</source>
          <year>1930</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>158</fpage>
          <lpage>162</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>GD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Handbook of tapeworm identification</source>
          <publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>
          <year>1986</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AVM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arruda</surname>
              <given-names>FCS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bertielose humana: segundo relato em Minas Gerais, Brasil</article-title>
          <source>Rev Patol Trop</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>185</fpage>
          <lpage>189</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stunkard</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The morphology and life history of the cestode,<italic>Bertiella studeri</italic>
</article-title>
          <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
          <year>1940</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>305</fpage>
          <lpage>333</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fang</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>XZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>XM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>
<italic>Bertiella studeri </italic>infection, China</article-title>
          <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>176</fpage>
          <lpage>177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16634184</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xuan</surname>
              <given-names>LT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anantaphruti</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tuan</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tu</surname>
              <given-names>LX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hien</surname>
              <given-names>TV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The first human infection with<italic>Bertiella studeri </italic>in Vietnam</article-title>
          <source>Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>298</fpage>
          <lpage>300</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12971553</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
