<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amjcaserep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The American Journal of Case Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1941-5923</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>International Scientific Literature, Inc.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27052496</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4829126</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/AJCR.896944</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">896944</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Periampullary Diverticula Misdiagnosed as Cystic Pancreatic Lesions: A Review of 3 Cases</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ng</surname>
            <given-names>Chee Hui</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-17-224">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="c1-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="corresp"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Chau Hung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-amjcaserep-17-224">
            <sup>E</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="af1-amjcaserep-17-224">Department of Radiology, Tan Tock Seng Hospital, Singapore, Singapore</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn>
          <p>Authors&#x2019; Contribution:</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn1-amjcaserep-17-224">
          <label>A</label>
          <p>Study Design</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn2-amjcaserep-17-224">
          <label>B</label>
          <p>Data Collection</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn3-amjcaserep-17-224">
          <label>C</label>
          <p>Statistical Analysis</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn4-amjcaserep-17-224">
          <label>D</label>
          <p>Data Interpretation</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn5-amjcaserep-17-224">
          <label>E</label>
          <p>Manuscript Preparation</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn6-amjcaserep-17-224">
          <label>F</label>
          <p>Literature Search</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn7-amjcaserep-17-224">
          <label>G</label>
          <p>Funds Collection</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn8-amjcaserep-17-224">
          <p><bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> None declared</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="c1-amjcaserep-17-224">Corresponding Author: Chee Hui Ng, e-mail: <email>powerlee_1999@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>07</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <fpage>224</fpage>
      <lpage>230</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Am J Case Rep, 2016</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license>
          <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>
          <bold>Case series</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Patient: Female, 67 &#x2022; Male, 69 &#x2022; Female, 65</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Final Diagnosis: Periampullary diverticulum</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Symptoms: &#x2014;</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Medication: &#x2014;</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Clinical Procedure: Magnetic Resonance Imaging</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Specialty: Radiology</bold>
        </p>
        <sec>
          <title>Objective:</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Diagnostic/therapeutic accidents</bold>
          </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>Cystic lesions on the pancreatic head can mimic fluid-filled duodenal or periampullary diverticula. We reviewed a series of cases in which periampullary diverticula were misdiagnosed as cystic pancreatic lesions.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case Report:</title>
          <p>Case 1. A Chinese woman presented to the surgical outpatient clinic for intermittent upper abdominal discomfort. Contrast-enhanced MRI of the abdomen revealed a cystic-appearing lesion in the region of the pancreatic head, which was reported as a cystic pancreatic lesion. A follow-up scan showed this lesion to be filled with fluid, gas, and debris, suggestive of a periampullary diverticulum. Review of a prior CT scan confirmed a periampullary diverticulum. Case 2. A Chinese man with a history of chronic hepatitis B infection underwent an MRI of the liver, which revealed a cystic-appearing lesion in the region of the pancreatic head, reported as a cystadenoma or pseudocyst. The patient underwent an endoscopic ultrasound. A large periampullary diverticulum was discovered but there was no pancreatic head lesion. Case 3. A Chinese woman with a history total hysterectomy and bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy for ovarian malignancy underwent an MRI of the abdomen and pelvis. A cystic-appearing lesion was found in the region of the pancreatic head, which was reported as a cystadenoma or intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm. Follow-up magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography showed a signal void within, suggestive of gas within a periampullary diverticulum. Review of a prior CT scan showed a periampullary diverticulum.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions:</title>
          <p>Periampullary diverticula, when fluid-filled, can be confused with cystic lesions in the pancreatic head. Radiologists should be aware of this potential pitfall.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>MeSH Keywords:</title>
        <kwd>Diagnostic Errors</kwd>
        <kwd>Diverticulum</kwd>
        <kwd>Duodenum</kwd>
        <kwd>Pancreatic Cyst</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Cystic pancreatic lesions are increasingly diagnosed with increasing use of computed tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) in clinical practice. These lesions are often incidentally detected and common entities include intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms, cystadenomas, and pseudocysts. Periampullary diverticula are outpouchings of the duodenal wall occurring about 2&#x2013;3 cm from of the ampulla of Vater, and typically lie along the medial wall of the duodenum. Cystic lesions on the pancreatic head can be confused with fluid-filled duodenal or periampullary diverticula due to location and potentially similar imaging features. We review a series of cases in which periampullary diverticula were misdiagnosed as cystic lesions in the pancreatic head on MRI, and discuss how to avoid such misdiagnosis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Case1</title>
        <p>A 67-year-old Chinese woman presented to the surgical out-patient clinic due to intermittent upper abdominal discomfort of a few weeks duration. She had a history of colonic polyps. An abdominal ultrasound scan was unremarkable. Contrast-enhanced MRI of the abdomen was then performed. There was a lesion in the region of the pancreatic head. It was very hyperintense on T2-weighted sequence, similar to fluid intensity, measuring about 1.2&#xD7;0.7 cm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 1</xref>). It was hypointense on T1-weighted sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 2</xref>). There was no restricted diffusion, with &#x201C;T2 shine-through&#x201D; on ADC map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 3</xref>). After administration of intravenous contrast, there was no enhancement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 4</xref>). No other significant finding was noted in the MRI scan. The lesion was reported as a cystic lesion in the pancreatic head, possibly an intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm.</p>
        <p>A follow-up scan 3 months later showed this lesion to be filled with fluid, gas, and debris, communicating with the medial aspect of the second part of the duodenum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 5</xref>). This suggested a periampullary diverticulum. A review of the patient&#x2019;s CT scan performed a few years before confirmed the presence of a periampullary diverticulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 2</title>
        <p>A 69-year-old Chinese man with a history of chronic hepatitis B infection underwent an MRI of the liver to evaluate a hepatic lesion detected on screening ultrasound. MRI confirmed findings of a hepatocellular carcinoma. A lesion was also detected in the region of the pancreatic head, measuring 3.8&#xD7;2.6 cm. It was slightly hyperintense on T2-weighted sequence with internal hypointense areas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 7</xref>). It was hypointense on T1-weighted sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 8</xref>). After intravenous administration of contrast, there was no enhancement, but internal debris was demonstrated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 9</xref>). The lesion was reported as a cystic pancreatic head lesion with debris within, probably a cystadenoma or pseudocyst.</p>
        <p>The patient underwent an endoscopic ultrasound for further characterization of the lesion. A large periampullary diverticulum was discovered, but there was no pancreatic head lesion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f10-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 10</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 3</title>
        <p>A 65-year-old Chinese woman with a history of total hysterectomy and bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy for ovarian malignancy underwent an MRI of the abdomen and pelvis for staging. There was no evidence of nodal or distant metastases, but there was a cystic lesion in the region of the pancreatic head with internal debris on T2-weighted sequence, measuring about 2.5&#xD7;2 cm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f11-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 11</xref>). After intravenous administration of contrast, no enhancement was noted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f12-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 12</xref>). This lesion was reported as a cystic pancreatic head lesion, possibly a cystadenoma or intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm.</p>
        <p>Magnetic resonance cholangiopancreaticography (MRCP) was performed 1 week later to evaluate for communication with the pancreatic duct. The cystic structure appeared smaller, with a void within, suggestive of gas within a periampullary diverticulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f13-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 13</xref>). A review of a CT abdomen study performed a few years before showed a gas-filled periampullary diverticulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f14-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 14</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Cystic pancreatic lesions, such as intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms (IPMN), cystadenomas, and pseudocysts, are increasingly diagnosed with the increasing use of CT and MR in clinical practice, and are often incidental [<xref rid="b1-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. On MRI, such lesions show high T2-signal, sometimes with internal septations or locules, and, in cases of IPMN, there is communication with the pancreatic duct [<xref rid="b2-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. On imaging, periampullary diverticula are typically seen in the second part of the duodenum along the medial wall, and, when large, they can bulge into the region of the pancreatic head or uncinate process. When completely filled with fluid, they can appear as cystic structures on MRI and can be confused with cystic lesions in the pancreatic head.</p>
      <p>There are various reports of fluid-filled periampullary diverticula mimicking cystic lesions in the pancreatic head [<xref rid="b3-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="b5-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In our case series, all 3 periampullary diverticula were misdiagnosed as cystic pancreatic neoplasms on MRI. This reflects the challenge in actual practice in differentiating a fluid-filled periampullary diverticulum from cystic pancreatic neoplasm on MRI compared to CT, possibly because communication of the diverticulum with the adjacent duodenum and small amounts of intradiverticular gas can be more difficult to appreciate on MRI compared to CT. Moreover, cysts and intradiverticular fluid often show similar signal intensities on MRI and can be difficult to distinguish. For comparison, we show an example of another patient with a known intraductal papillary neoplasm in the pancreatic head. In this case, the lesion was also hyper-intense on T2-weighted sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f15-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 15</xref>), hypointense on T1-weighted sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f16-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 16</xref>), and did not show enhancement after administration of intravenous contrast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f17-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 17</xref>). These MRI features, together with location medial to the duodenum, are similar to the periampullary diverticula illustrated in our series. However, a 3-dimensional heavy-T2-weighted MRCP sequence showed communication with the main pancreatic duct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f18-amjcaserep-17-224">Figure 18</xref>), indicating an intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm.</p>
      <p>There are certain clues that may help to distinguish periampullary diverticulum from cystic neoplasms in the pancreatic head on MRI. The presence of intradiverticular gas with air-fluid level is one of the most important and easily recognized features [<xref rid="b6-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This is best seen on axial T2-weighted sequences, where there is stark contrast between the hyperintense fluid and the signal void of non-dependent gas. A tiny amount of gas may appear as a crescent of signal void, and careful evaluation is required. The presence of dependent debris within also suggests a diverticulum (containing bowel material) rather than a cystic pancreatic neoplasm. This appears as hypointense areas or dependent layering; however, this is also seen in pancreatic pseudocysts [<xref rid="b7-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Occasionally, periampullary diverticula can be seen to change morphology between MRI sequences or they may become gas-filled, making the diagnosis obvious. Alternatively, oral administration of water or shifting the patient&#x2019;s position can alter its morphology to increase diagnostic confidence [<xref rid="b5-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In retrospect, 2 of the present cases (case 1 and 3) had prior CT scans that confirmed presence of a periampullary diverticulum, while in 1 case (case 2), a communication with the duodenum was suggested on careful review of the images. In 2 cases (case 2 and 3), hypointense foci were noted within the lesions, which could have suggested intradiverticular debris rather than a true cystic pancreatic lesion. From our case series it is also clear that review of prior cross-sectional imaging is helpful in the diagnosis.</p>
      <p>When a periampullary diverticulum is suspected, further investigation can be done to confirm it. A barium follow-through study will show barium filling the diverticulum and this is usually diagnostic [<xref rid="b4-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Pineapple juice has also been studied as a negative oral contrast agent in MRI and can help in diagnosis of periampullary diverticula. Its superparamagnetic component results in shortening of T2-relaxation time and suppression of fluid signal from the diverticulum on MRI, distinguishing it from a cystic pancreatic lesion [<xref rid="b8-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Solitary periampullary diverticula generally do not require active management because most are asymptomatic. Indications for surgical resection include recurrent abdominal pain, cholangitis, pancreatitis, large diverticula causing mass effect (e.g., biliary or duodenal obstruction), or complications such as bleeding, perforation, or diverticulitis [<xref rid="b9-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Management of symptoms and complications is either medical or surgical. Medical management includes analgesia for abdominal pain and antibiotics for diverticulitis, as well as bed-rest and fluids. Surgical management includes diverticulectomy, embolization of bleed via endovascular techniques, or endoscopic hemostasis [<xref rid="b10-amjcaserep-17-224" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Periampullary diverticula, when fluid-filled, can be confused with cystic lesions in the pancreatic head. Radiologists should be aware of this potential pitfall. However, there are clues that are useful in avoiding misdiagnosis and further unnecessary investigation or intervention. Although the cases presented here were initially misdiagnosed as cystic pancreatic lesions, careful scrutiny of images, as well as review of prior studies, could have finalized the diagnosis.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn9-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <p><bold>Statements</bold>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest. No external funding was involved in our study.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The authors declare no involvement of human participants or animals.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Institutional review board approval was not required as our study did not involve direct patient care or interaction, and only required review of imaging studies that were already performed, and all patient identifiers were removed.</p></list-item></list></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="b1-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kalb</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarmiento</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kooby</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MR imaging of cystic lesions of the pancreas</article-title>
          <source>Radiographics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>1749</fpage>
          <lpage>65</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19959519</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sahani</surname>
              <given-names>DV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kadavigere</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saokar</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cystic pancreatic lesions: A simple imaging-based classification system for guiding management</article-title>
          <source>Radiographics</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>1471</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16284129</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mallappa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiao</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Juxtapapillary duodenal diverticulum masquerading as a cystic pancreatic neoplasm</article-title>
          <source>JRSM Short Rep</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>89</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22140615</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Macari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazarus</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Israel</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Megibow</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Duodenal diverticula mimicking cystic neoplasm of the pancreas: CT and MR imaging findings in seven patients</article-title>
          <source>Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>180</volume>
          <fpage>195</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490502</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hariri</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siegelman</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hruban</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Duodenal diverticulum mimicking a cystic pancreatic neoplasm</article-title>
          <source>Br J Radiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>562</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15900065</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>&#xD6;zy&#xFC;rek</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozkavukcu</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haliloglu</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erden</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MRCP findings of incidentally detected juxtapapillary diverticular in patients with pancreaticobiliary symptoms</article-title>
          <source>ECR Educational Exhibit</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <comment>Poster No.: C&#x2013;0011</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Macari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Finn</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differentiating pancreatic cystic neoplasms from pancreatic pseudocysts at MR imaging: Value of perceived internal debris</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>251</volume>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19332847</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mazziotti</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ascenti</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MR cholangiopancreatography diagnosis of juxtapapillary duodenal diverticulum simulating a cystic lesion of the pancreas: usefulness of an oral negative contrast agent</article-title>
          <source>Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>185</volume>
          <fpage>432</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16037516</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of juxta-ampullary duodenal diverticulum</article-title>
          <source>Clin Invest Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>298</fpage>
          <lpage>303</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10-amjcaserep-17-224">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>CW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>YY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yen</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soon</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Successful double balloon endteros-copy treatment for bleeding jejuna diverticulum: A case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J Laparoendosc Adv Surg Tech A</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>637</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19489675</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T2-weighted fat-saturated sequence showing a fairly homogeneous hyperintense lesion in the region of the pancreatic head (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T1-weighted (dual-echo out-of-phase) sequence showing the lesion to be hypointense (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>On ADC map, the lesion demonstrates &#x201C;T2 shine-through&#x201D; with hyperintense signal, indicating absence of restricted diffusion (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Post-contrast T1-weighted fat-saturated sequence did not show enhancement of the lesion (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f5-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 5.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Follow-up MRI, T2-weighted sequence showed the lesion to contain fluid and hypointense contents (arrow), as well as non-dependent crescent of signal void, suggestive of gas (arrowhead) and suggesting the possibility of a periampullary diverticulum.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g005"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f6-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 6.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Prior CT scan confirmed the presence of a periampullary diverticulum containing gas (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g006"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f7-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 7.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T2-weighted sequence shows a predominantly hyperintense lesion in the region of the pancreatic head, with internal hypointense foci suggestive of internal debris (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g007"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f8-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 8.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T1-weighted (dual-echo in-phase) sequence showing the lesion to be hypointense (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g008"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f9-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 9.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Post-contrast T1-weighted fat-saturated sequence did not show significant enhancement of the lesion (arrow), although internal debris was again noted.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g009"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f10-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 10.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Endoscopic ultrasound found a large periampullary diverticulum. Distal common bile duct was identified (arrow) and no cystic lesion was noted in the region of the pancreatic head.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g010"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f11-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 11.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T2-weighted fat-saturated sequence showing a hyperintense lesion in the region of the pancreatic head with internal hypointense foci, suggestive of debris (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g011"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f12-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 12.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Post-contrast T1-weighted fat-saturated sequence did not show enhancement of the lesion (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g012"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f13-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 13.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Subsequent MRCP, T2-weighted fat-saturated sequence showing the lesion to have slightly decreased in size (arrow) and a crescent of non-dependent signal void was noted (arrowhead), suggesting the possibility of a periampullary diverticulum.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g013"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f14-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 14.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Prior CT scan confirmed the presence of a periampullary diverticulum containing gas (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g014"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f15-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 15.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T2-weighted fat-saturated sequence showing a fairly homogeneous hyperintense lesion in the region of the pancreatic head (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g015"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f16-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 16.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>T1-weighted (dual-echo out-of-phase) sequence showing the lesions to be hypointense (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g016"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f17-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 17.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Post-contrast T1-weighted fat-saturated sequence did not show enhancement of the lesion (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g017"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f18-amjcaserep-17-224" position="float">
      <label>Figure 18.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>3-D heavy-T2-weighted MRCP shows a communication of this cystic lesion with the main pancreatic duct (arrow), confirming an intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasm in the pancreatic head.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-224-g018"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
