<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Res Notes</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Res Notes</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Research Notes</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1756-0500</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25947008</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4430924</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1139</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-015-1139-3</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Recurrence of Merkel cell carcinoma in the gastrointestinal tract: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Tuktamyshov</surname>
            <given-names>Rasikh</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>rasikh.tuktamyshov@ynhh.org</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jain</surname>
            <given-names>Dhanpat</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>dhanpat.jain@yale.edu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ginsburg</surname>
            <given-names>Philip M</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>pginsburg@gastrocenter.org</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Yale New Haven Hospital, 1450 Chapel Street, New Haven, CT 06511 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Pathology, Yale University, 310 Cedar Street, New Haven, 208023 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label/>Yale-New Haven Hospital, 2200 Whitney Avenue, Suite 360, Hamden, New Haven, CT 06518 USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>7</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>7</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>8</volume>
      <elocation-id>188</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Tuktamyshov et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Merkel cell carcinoma is a rare and aggressive skin malignancy that arises from primary neural cells and has a tendency for local recurrence and regional lymph node metastases. There are only a few cases in the literature reporting metastases of Merkel cell carcinoma to the gastrointestinal tract.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>We present a 70&#xA0;year old Caucasian female with distant history of Merkel cell carcinoma who presented with iron-deficiency anemia. Colonoscopy performed later for the evaluation of anemia revealed 1&#xA0;cm polyp in ascending colon which turned out to be the recurrence of Merkel cell carcinoma.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Metastatic Merkel cell carcinoma to the gastrointestinal tract or any other organ should be considered in patients with a history of Merkel cell carcinoma.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Merkel Cell carcinoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Polyp</kwd>
        <kwd>Colonoscopy</kwd>
        <kwd>Colon</kwd>
        <kwd>Metastasis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Merkel cell carcinoma (MCC) is a rare condition. Earlier studies suggested that MCC originates from Merkel cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] which are mechanoreceptors located at stratum basale of the epidermis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, MCC probably arises from some kind of progenitor cell of the skin as substantial differences exist between MCC and Merkel cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Clinically, patients with MCC typically present with a rapidly growing, painless, firm, nontender, shiny, flesh-colored or bluish-red, intracutaneous nodule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. After resection, local recurrence is common but a review of the literature found only a few cases of documented metastases to gastrointestinal (GI) tract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. We present a case of Merkel cell carcinoma of the skin that recurred in the colon.</p>
      <sec id="Sec2">
        <title>Case Presentation</title>
        <p>A 70-year-old Caucasian female was evaluated for a one month history of progressively worsening low back pain and weakness. She had no gastrointestinal tract complaints. Her past medical history was significant for multiple basal and squamous cell cancers, as well as Merkel cell carcinoma 5&#xA0;years previously, at which time she presented with a lump in her left groin. After local resection, she was treated with radiation and carboplatin. There was no recurrence and a subsequent abdominal CT (computed tomography) scan 3&#xA0;years later showed no evidence of metastatic disease. The primary site was thought to be an inguinal lymph node.</p>
        <p>On physical exam she had a 5&#xA0;mm mobile lymph node in the left supraclavicular area. There were no focal neurological deficits. Stool tested guaiac negative. Labs revealed hemoglobin 7.1&#xA0;g/dL, hematocrit 21.1%, iron level 15 mcg/dL, total iron binding capacity 330&#xA0;mg/dL, and transferrin saturation 5%, consistent with severe iron-deficiency anemia. A contrast enhanced abdominal CT scan showed bulky retroperitoneal adenopathy encompassing the renal arteries, aorta, inferior vena cava as well as circumferentially thickened loop of small bowel in the left hemiabdomen (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). A small bowel series was negative. The decision was made to perform a colonoscopy.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>CT scan. Extensive bulky retroperitoneal lymphadenopathy (lymph node of 35.4&#xA0;mm is marked on the picture).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2015_1139_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>The findings at colonoscopy (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) revealed a semi-sessile ascending colon polyp measuring approximately 1&#xA0;cm in size. The polyp was smooth and pale, with regular margins, and normal surrounding mucosa. It was resected as a single piece using hot snare polypectomy technique, and all tissue was recovered into a sterile trap and submitted for routine histology. Post-resection appearances suggested complete removal of all polypoid mucosa. Pathological examination of the specimen showed a small blue cell neoplasm involving both the mucosa and submucosa (Figures&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The tumor cells were relatively small with scanty cytoplasm and hyperchromatic round nuclei. Immunostain for cytokeratin 20 showing perinuclear dot like cytoplasmic and surface positivity. Immunostaining for endocrine markers chromogranin and synaptophysin showed strong cytoplasmic positivity. The findings are typical of MCC and were similar to the patient&#x2019;s previous groin tumor. The patient was diagnosed with stage IV MCC based on the presence of a distant metastasis.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Colonoscopy, 10&#xA0;mm sessile polyp.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2015_1139_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Low magnification photograph showing the tumor infiltrating into the submucosa as well as overlying mucosa. The tumor cells are diffusely infiltrating the tissues without any specific arrangement or pattern.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2015_1139_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Higher magnification to show tumor cells that are small with hyperchromatic nuclei and scanty cytoplasm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2015_1139_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Immunostain for cytokeratin 20 showing diffuse cytoplasmic and surface positivity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2015_1139_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Immunostain for endocrine markers chromogranin and synaptophysin were similar and showed strong cytoplasmic positivity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13104_2015_1139_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
        <p>The patient was treated with 4&#xA0;cycles of cisplatin and etoposide (VP-16). Five months later, a CT of the abdomen showed increase in abdominal lymphadenopathy and a midjejunal small bowel mass that was felt to represent a metastatic focus. She received an additional 8&#xA0;cycles of chemotherapy with cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin and vincristine and a follow-up positron emission tomography scan showed resolution of the previous multifocal lymphadenopathy in the chest, abdomen, and pelvis with no new lesions.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Merkel cell cancer is a rare skin malignancy. In the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) database a total of 1665 cases were identified between 1973 and 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The cause is unknown. Sunlight has been implicated as a causative factor, in view of its predilection for sun-exposed regions of the body and geographic distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. In one prospective study, the highest age adjusted incidence among a Caucasian population was in Hawaii, the geographic location with the highest ultraviolet B index [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Immunosuppression has been associated with MCC, and linked with organ transplantation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Cases of MCC were reported among patients taking immunosuppressing medications like tumor necrosis factor inhibitors, including etanercept (Enbrel&#xAE;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and adalimumab (Humira&#xAE;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In 2008, a previously unknown polyomavirus was detected in 80% of patients with MCC in a series of 10 patients, suggesting a possible role in the pathogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p>
      <p>On light microscopy MCC may be confused with poorly differentiated small-cell tumors such as small-cell lung cancer, lymphoma, neuroblastoma and other &#x201C;small round blue cell tumors&#x201D;, which are characterized by a superficially very blue appearance on routine H &amp; E stained sections due to the cells having a single large hyperchromatic nucleus with evenly distributed granular chromatin and a thin rim of cytoplasm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. This appearance is shared by many tumors including small cell carcinoma, lymphoma, Ewing sarcoma and rhabdomyosarcoma, amongst others. The pathologic differential diagnosis of Merkel cell carcinoma includes other small round blue cell tumors, particularly lymphoma and small cell carcinoma when encountered in the GI tract. The immunohistochemical profile of the tumor is very typical with perinuclear punctate or dot-like positivity for CK20 (cytokeratin 20) and endocrine markers. This is in contrast to small cell carcinomas which, although frequently positive for endocrine markers, are negative for CK20. The small cells carcinomas in addition often show positivity of TTF-1 (thyroid transcription factor-1) or less commonly CDX-2 (caudal homeobox 2 protein) in the GI tract. Lymphomas can be easily differentiated by positivity for various leukocyte markers and lack of keratins and endocrine markers.</p>
      <p>Our case report presents a patient with MCC metastatic to colon. The jejunal mass and lymphadenopathy seen on the initial abdominal CT before the colonoscopy were most likely metastasis of MCC but not confirmed by tissue biopsy. The patient responded well to chemotherapy.</p>
      <p>The patient in our case had nodal disease without an apparent primary site, and this was the case for about 2% of initial presentations out of 661 cases published by Tai <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]<italic>.</italic> The patient also had previous basal and squamous cell carcinomas of the skin. The risk of development of MCC is increased in patients with other malignancies including skin cancers and melanoma. Moreover, MCC is a risk factor for development of another primary cancer with the highest risk for salivary gland tumors, bladder cancer, and multiple myeloma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>There are only a few cases in the literature reporting MCC metastases to the GI tract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and only three cases to our knowledge with metastasis to the large intestine. One of them describes a case with metastases to the colon, duodenum and stomach 6&#xA0;years after the excision of a skin lesion on the neck that was initially diagnosed as basal cell carcinoma but reevaluation of the specimen confirmed MCC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The second one reports the case of a patient who presented with hematochezia from MCC in the rectum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. A third case reports primary head and neck MCC with metastasis to the colon who survived for 6&#xA0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p>
      <p>There are more cases that report MCC metastatic to other parts of GI tract. One of them describes a patient with acute upper GI bleeding from a gastric metastasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Krasagakis <italic>s</italic>. presented the case of a patient who had widely spread metastatic disease including the stomach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Another case presented the recurrence of MCC at ileocecal valve 18&#xA0;months after resection of a tumor on the neck [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>MCC is a rare disease that rarely metastasizes to the gastrointestinal tract and may mimic other small blue round cell tumors. The morphology combined with immunostaining profile helps to establish the correct diagnosis. Metastatic disease should be in the differential diagnosis when evaluating GI symptoms in a patient with a history of MCC.</p>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Consent</title>
        <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient's next-of-kin for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>MCC</term>
          <def>
            <p>Merkel cell carcinoma</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>GI</term>
          <def>
            <p>Gastrointestinal tract</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CT</term>
          <def>
            <p>Computed tomography</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CK20</term>
          <def>
            <p>Cytokeratin 20</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>TTF-1</term>
          <def>
            <p>Thyroid transcription factor-1</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CDX-2</term>
          <def>
            <p>Caudal homeobox 2 protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>All the authors participated in the literature search, interpretation of the articles reviewed and analysis of the data and review of the manuscript. All the authors have read and approved the final version of the manuscript. DJ provided pathology images with their descriptions.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goessling</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McKee</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayer</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel cell carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>588</fpage>
          <lpage>98</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.20.2.588</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11786590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dinh</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feun</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elgart</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Savaraj</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel Cell Carcinomas</article-title>
          <source>Hematol Oncol Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>527</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hoc.2007.04.008</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17548038</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Czapiewski</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Biernat</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel cell carcinoma - recent advances in the biology, diagnostics and treatment</article-title>
          <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>536</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocel.2014.04.023</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24811434</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hitchcock</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bland</surname>
              <given-names>KI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laney</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
              <suffix>3rd</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franzini</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Copeland</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
              <suffix>3rd</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neuroendocrine (Merkel cell) carcinoma of the skin. Its natural history, diagnosis, and treatment</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>207</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>201</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-198802000-00015</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3277546</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mojica</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ellenhorn</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adjuvant radiation therapy is associated with improved survival in Merkel cell carcinoma of the skin</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>1043</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2006.07.9319</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17369567</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agelli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clegg</surname>
              <given-names>LX</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiology of primary Merkel cell carcinoma in the United States</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>832</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0190-9622(03)02108-X</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576661</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Penn</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>First</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel's cell carcinoma in organ recipients: report of 41 cases</article-title>
          <source>Transplantation</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>1717</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007890-199912150-00015</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10609948</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Giorgi</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benemei</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grazzini</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lotti</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geppetti</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rapid growth of Merkel cell carcinoma during etanercept treatment of psoriatic arthritis: cause or coincidence?</article-title>
          <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>354</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2340/00015555-1038</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21369689</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krishna</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel cell carcinoma in a patient treated with adalimumab: case report</article-title>
          <source>Cutis</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>81</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21416774</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Feng</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shuda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clonal integration of a polyomavirus in human Merkel cell carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>319</volume>
          <issue>5866</issue>
          <fpage>1096</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1152586</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18202256</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rajwanshi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srinivas</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Upasana</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant small round cell tumors</article-title>
          <source>J Cytol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0970-9371.54861</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21938141</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tai</surname>
              <given-names>PT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tonita</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilchrist</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel cell carcinoma of the skin</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Med Surg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>186</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11231196</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Howard</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dores</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Curtis</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Travis</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel cell carcinoma and multiple primary cancers</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1545</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-05-0895</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16896047</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shalhub</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morgan</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metastatic Merkel cell carcinoma masquerading as colon cancer</article-title>
          <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>856</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0016-5107(04)02173-X</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15557979</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>WS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>PY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>IL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chin</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metastatic Merkel cell carcinoma in the rectum: report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Dis Colon Rectum</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>1992</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10350-006-0879-5</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17713819</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Veness</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howle</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel cell carcinoma metastatic to the transverse colon: disease free after six years - cure or just prolonged remission?</article-title>
          <source>Australas J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>295</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-0960.2011.00782.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22070707</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Canales</surname>
              <given-names>LI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parker</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kadakia</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Upper gastrointestinal bleeding from Merkel cell carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1464</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1415105</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krasagakis</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almond-Roesler</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zouboulis</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tebbe</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wartenberg</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolff</surname>
              <given-names>KD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Merkel cell carcinoma: report of ten cases with emphasis on clinical course, treatment, and in vitro drug sensitivity</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>727</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0190-9622(97)80325-8</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9146534</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cheung</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Purkayastha</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ziprin</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ileocaecal recurrence of Merkel cell carcinoma of the skin: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Med Case Rep</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-1947-4-43</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20181112</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
