<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin J Gastroenterol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin J Gastroenterol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Clinical Journal of Gastroenterology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1865-7257</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1865-7265</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Japan</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27003801</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4829617</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">640</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12328-016-0640-0</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Endoscopic antralplasty for severe gastric stasis after wide endoscopic submucosal dissection in the antrum</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ohara</surname>
            <given-names>Yoshiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Toyonaga</surname>
            <given-names>Takashi</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+81-78-382-5774</phone>
            <email>toyonaga@med.kobe-u.ac.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tanabe</surname>
            <given-names>Akiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Takihara</surname>
            <given-names>Hiroshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baba</surname>
            <given-names>Shinichi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Inoue</surname>
            <given-names>Taro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ono</surname>
            <given-names>Wataru</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kawara</surname>
            <given-names>Fumiaki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tanaka</surname>
            <given-names>Shinwa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Azuma</surname>
            <given-names>Takeshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Division of Gastroenterology, Department of Internal Medicine, Graduate School of Medicine, Kobe University, Kobe, Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Endoscopy, Kobe University Hospital, 7-5-1 Kusunoki-cho, Chuo-ku, Kobe, Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label/>Department of Endoscopy, Kishiwada Tokushukai Hospital, Kishiwada, Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Gastroenterology, Ikoma City Hospital, Ikoma, Japan </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <fpage>63</fpage>
      <lpage>67</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2016</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>A 75-year-old female underwent esophagogastroduodenoscopy, revealing a widely spreading tumor occupying the anterior wall, lesser curvature, and posterior wall of the antrum and lower body. Endoscopic submucosal dissection was performed and resulted in more than five-sixths circumferential antral mucosal resection. One month later, she complained of nausea, vomiting, and abdominal distention. Endoscopy showed residual food in the stomach and deformation of the antrum with traction toward the contracted scar in the lesser curvature. The pyloric ring could not be seen from the antrum although the endoscope was able to pass easily beyond the area of deformation and the pyloric ring was intact. Despite repeated endoscopic balloon dilations, the patient&#x2019;s symptoms remained refractory. The problem was speculated to be not due to any potential stricture but to antrum deformation resulting from the traction force toward the healing ulcer. We hypothesized that an additional countertraction force opposite the previous ESD site might resolve the problem, and ESD of approximately 2.5&#xA0;cm size was performed in the greater curvature of the antrum. Along with development of a scar, traction toward the greater curvature was added, and the pyloric ring could be observed&#xA0;on repeat esophagogastroduodenoscopy. The symptoms were also gradually ameliorated. Afterwards, the endoscopic findings have now been unchanged during 7&#xA0;years of follow-up.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Endoscopic antralplasty</kwd>
        <kwd>Endoscopic submucosal dissection</kwd>
        <kwd>Gastric stasis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Japanese Society of Gastroenterology 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Endoscopic submucosal dissection (ESD) techniques have recently been improving and have been increasingly applied for the treatment of non-neoplastic diseases, such as perioral endoscopic myotomy (POEM) for achalasia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], anti-reflux mucosectomy (ARMS) for reflux esophagitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], and gastric perioral endoscopic myotomy (G-POEM) for pyloric stenosis and gastroparesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. These new treatment modalities have gradually replaced the surgical treatments that used to be done for these diseases.</p>
      <p>We experienced a case in which severe gastric stasis was caused after wide ESD in the antrum and lower body of the stomach because of antral deformation by a contracted scar. The patient was successfully treated with additional ESD on the contralateral side of the &#xA0;original ESD scar. We present this case as the first report of a new and promising method&#xA0;to treat gastric stasis after antral ESD.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 75-year-old female consulted a nearby clinic because of abdominal pain. She underwent esophagogastroduodenoscopy, which revealed a widely spreading tumor occupying the anterior wall, lesser curvature, and posterior wall of the antrum and lower body (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b). The biopsy showed a large, well-differentiated adenocarcinoma&#xA0;with no sign of deep submucosal invasion. ESD was indicated, and the patient underwent ESD using the Flush knife-BT (DK2618JB; Fujifilm Medical Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], without any intraoperative adverse events. The procedure took 79&#xA0;min. The mucosal defect in the antrum and the lower body spanned more than five-sixths of the antral circumference (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). Histopathological observation showed a well-differentiated adenocarcinoma, 88&#xA0;mm in size, invading 200&#xA0;&#x3BC;m deep into the submucosa (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d). The resected margin was tumor-negative. Although the resection was non-curative according to the JGES criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], the patient did not choose to undergo additional surgery and was closely observed. One month later, the patient complained of symptoms of gastric stasis, including nausea, vomiting, abdominal distention, and loss of appetite. Endoscopy showed deformation of the antrum with traction toward the contracted scar in the lesser curvature and residual food in the stomach (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a&#x2013;c). The pyloric ring could not be seen from the antrum; however, the endoscope was able to pass easily beyond the area of deformation, which suggested that there was no severe physical stricture. The pyloric ring was also confirmed to be intact. Despite repeated endoscopic balloon dilations (EBDs), the patient&#x2019;s symptoms did not improve. Two months later, she suffered from a full thickness tear in the upper stomach after vomiting, which was cured conservatively by gastric decompression and fasting. However, gastroparesis continued. These episodes suggested that the problem was not due to physical antrum stricture but due to deformation of the antrum resulting from the traction force toward the lesser curvature generated by the healing ESD induced ulcer. We hypothesized that an additional counter-traction force might resolve the problem. With the aim of releasing the deformation, ESD of approximately 2.5&#xA0;cm in size was performed in the great curvature of the antrum (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Along with development of a scar, traction toward the great curvature was added, and the pyloric ring could be observed from the antrum 1 month later (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). The symptoms also gradually ameliorated, and finally resolved. During subsequent 7 years of follow up, the endoscopic findings have not changed (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b, c), and no tumor recurrence or gastric stasis symptom has been observed.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold> Widely spreading tumor in the antrum and lower body. <bold>b</bold> Indigo carmine staining of the tumor. <bold>c</bold> Artificial ulcer after ESD with a mucosal defect of more than five-sixths circumference in the antrum and lower body. <bold>d</bold> Resected specimen measuring 110&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;70&#xA0;mm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12328_2016_640_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold> Ulcer 1 month after ESD. The antrum is deformed, and the pyloric ring cannot be seen from the antrum. <bold>b</bold> Residual food in the stomach because of deformation of the antrum. <bold>c</bold> Ulcer scar at 4 months after ESD. The pyloric ring still cannot be visually confirmed from the antrum because of the deformation</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12328_2016_640_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>ESD was performed on the greater curvature in the antrum 4 months after the first ESD</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12328_2016_640_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold> Endoscopic view 1 month after the endoscopic antralplasty. The ulcer added traction toward the great curvature, and the pyloric ring became observable from the antrum. <bold>b</bold> Endoscopic view 1&#xBD; years after the antralplasty. <bold>c</bold> Endoscopic view 7 years after the antralplasty</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12328_2016_640_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Stricture can develop after ESD for large esophageal and prepylorus lesions, and EBD is widely recognized as an effective strategy for its treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. On the other hand, in the antrum, deformation after ESD can lead to gastric stasis even when the stricture is mild&#xA0;or not present, as was observed in the present case. Our case demonstrates that the antral deformation can be treated by additional ESD on the contralateral side&#xA0;from the original ESD, with maintenance of this endoscopic and clinical effect for a significant amount of time.</p>
      <p>A previous report suggested that contralateral mucosal incision and steroid injection were useful for treatment of stenosis after wide ESD in the antrum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The authors suggested that the strategy&#x2019;s mechanism depended on induction of granulation by the incision and steroid injection aiding in the widening of the antrum, which differed from the mechanism of the present method. The authors also mentioned that a combination with oral steroid administration resulted in a better prognosis. However, steroid treatments may sometimes be problematic; specifically steroid injections to the ulcer may raise the risk of late perforation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], and oral steroid administration after ESD may cause severe infectious disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p>
      <p>The present method utilizes conventional ESD techniques with no use of steroids. Creation of a counter-traction force against the original contracted ESD scar may help resolve the deformity and gastric stasis secondary to wide ESD.</p>
      <p>It must be noted that the limitation of the present method is that it has only been performed in one case. It remains to be confirmed whether the present method can be applied to other patients, including those who undergo wide ESD in the greater curvature of the antrum, or whether there are potential complications such as a risk of developing stricture.</p>
      <p>However, endoscopic antralplasty may be an alternative therapeutic option for post-ESD gastric stasis and worth considering prior to surgery because of its reduced invasiveness and ability to preserve the stomach compared with surgery. This method may help patients suffering from gastric stasis after wide ESD and avoid unneeded surgery.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <notes notes-type="conflict-interest">
      <title>Compliance with ethical standards</title>
      <sec id="FPar1">
        <title>Conflict of Interest</title>
        <p>Dr. Toyonaga invented the Flush knife-BT in conjunction with Fujifilm and receives royalties from its sale.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="d30e431">
        <title>Human Rights:</title>
        <p>All procedures followed have been performed in accordance with the ethical standards laid down in the 1964 Declaration of Helsinki and its later amendments.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="d30e436">
        <title>Informed Consent:</title>
        <p>Informed consent was obtained from the patient for being included in the study.</p>
      </sec>
    </notes>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Inoue</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minami</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Peroral endoscopic myotomy (POEM) for esophageal achalasia</article-title>
          <source>Endoscopy</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>265</fpage>
          <lpage>271</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1244080</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20354937</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Inoue</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikeda</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anti-reflux mucosectomy for gastroesophageal reflux disease in the absence of hiatus hernia a pilot study</article-title>
          <source>Ann Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>346</fpage>
          <lpage>351</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25330784</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chaves</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Moura</surname>
              <given-names>EG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mestieri</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endoscopic pyloromyotomy via a gastric submucosal tunnel dissection for the treatment of gastroparesis after surgical vagal lesion</article-title>
          <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>164</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gie.2014.03.045</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836745</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khashab</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stein</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>JO</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gastric peroral endoscopic myotomy for refractory gastroparesis: first human endoscopic pyloromyotomy (with video)</article-title>
          <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>764</fpage>
          <lpage>768</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gie.2013.07.019</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24120337</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Toyonaga</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Man</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujita</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The performance of a novel ball-tipped Flush knife for endoscopic submucosal dissection: a case-control study</article-title>
          <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>908</fpage>
          <lpage>915</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2036.2010.04425.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20839389</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ono</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujishiro</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Guidelines for endoscopic submucosal dissection and endoscopic mucosal resection for early gastric cancer</article-title>
          <source>Dig Endosc</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/den.12518</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26234303</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ono</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujishiro</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niimi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Predictors of postoperative stricture after esophageal endoscopic submucosal dissection for superficial squamous cell neoplasms</article-title>
          <source>Endoscopy</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>661</fpage>
          <lpage>665</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1214867</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19565442</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iizuka</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kakizaki</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sohara</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stricture after endoscopic submucosal dissection for early gastric cancers and adenomas</article-title>
          <source>Dig Endosc</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>282</fpage>
          <lpage>288</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1443-1661.2010.01008.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21175480</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mori</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobara</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rafiq</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel method for the management of stenosis after gastric endoscopic submucosal dissection: mucosal incision with steroid injection contralateral to the severely contracted scar</article-title>
          <source>Dig Endosc</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>622</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/den.12400</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25369879</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ishida</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morita</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoshi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Disseminated nocardiosis during systemic steroid therapy for the prevention of esophageal stricture after endoscopic submucosal dissection</article-title>
          <source>Dig Endosc</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>388</fpage>
          <lpage>91</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/den.12317</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24889691</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
