<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann R Coll Surg Engl</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann R Coll Surg Engl</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rcse</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Annals of The Royal College of Surgeons of England</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0035-8843</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1478-7083</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Royal College of Surgeons</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23484980</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4098601</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/003588413X13511609955931</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">955931</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Online Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Neurofibroma of the bile duct: a rare cause of obstructive jaundice</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="lrh">Neurofibroma of the bile duct: a rare cause of obstructive jaundice</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>De Rosa</surname>
            <given-names>A</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gomez</surname>
            <given-names>D</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zaitoun</surname>
            <given-names>AM</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Cameron</surname>
            <given-names>IC</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="C1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="AF0001">
          <addr-line>Nottingham University Hospitals NHS Trust,</addr-line>
          <country>UK</country>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="C1"><addr-line>Department of Hepatobiliary and Pancreatic Surgery, E Floor, West Block, Queen&#x2019;s Medical Centre, Derby Road, Nottingham NG7 2UH,</addr-line><country>UK</country> E: <email>iain.cameron@nuh.nhs.uk</email><phone>+ 44(0)115 924 9924</phone></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>95</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>e38</fpage>
      <lpage>e40</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2013 Royal College of Surgeons</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neurofibromas of the common bile duct are extremely rare. The lack of specific clinical or radiological features makes preoperative diagnosis in the absence of histology difficult. We report the case of a female patient who presented with obstructive jaundice and evidence of a common bile duct stricture on imaging. She underwent an exploratory laparotomy, and intraoperative frozen section confirmed clear margins and a benign lesion. Excision of the extrahepatic bile duct and A Roux-en-Y hepaticojejunostomy was performed. We discuss the clinical features and management of neurofibromas of the bile duct in light of the literature.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Neurofibroma</kwd>
        <kwd>Jaundice</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Neurofibromas of the common bile duct are extremely rare. The lack of specific clinical or radiological features makes preoperative diagnosis in the absence of histology difficult.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> In addition, patients tend to present with clinical symptoms and signs suggestive of underlying malignancy. We report a case of neurofibroma of the common bile duct, and discuss the surgical treatment and histopathological findings.</p>
    <sec id="ch6_sau1">
      <title>Case history</title>
      <p>A 70-year-old Caucasian woman with no significant alcohol consumption presented with a 4-week history of painless jaundice, anorexia and pruritus. She did not have any significant past medical history or family history of hereditary diseases. Clinical examination revealed she was jaundiced with no palpable masses or skin lesions. There was a right subcostal surgical scar from an open cholecystectomy performed two years previously. Laboratory analysis revealed deranged liver function tests suggestive of an obstructive presentation, with an elevated bilirubin level of 74&#x3BC;mol/l (normal range: 1&#x2013; 21&#x3BC;mol/l) and alkaline phosphatase of 379iu/l (normal range: 40&#x2013;130iu/l). Contrast enhanced computed tomography (CT) of the abdomen and pelvis identified a stricture at the mid-common bile duct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig 1</xref>) with no evidence of a mass lesion, vascular invasion or enlarged lymph nodes.
<fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Coronal section of contrast-enhanced computed tomography of the abdomen and pelvis demonstrating a stricture at the mid-common bile duct (arrow)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9502-e6-01"/></fig>
</p>
      <p>Following case discussion at the multidisciplinary team meeting, the patient underwent an exploratory laparotomy. At laparotomy, thickening of the mid-upper third of the common bile duct suspicious of malignancy was observed. There were no palpable lymph nodes or surrounding fibrosis suggestive of local invasion and no evidence of distant metastases. Intraoperative frozen sections were performed, both proximal and distal to the stricture to ensure margin clearance, which demonstrated characteristics of a benign lesion. The patient underwent excision of the extrahepatic bile duct and a Roux-en-Y hepaticojejunostomy.</p>
      <p>The postoperative histological findings were consistent with a neurofibroma, with the presence of long spindle cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig 2</xref>) and positive immunohistochemistry for S100, a marker for neurofilament protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig 3</xref>). Following surgery, the patient made an uneventful recovery and was clinically well at the four-week follow-up appointment.
<fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Haematoxylin and eosin stained section of the bile duct wall showing spindle cell proliferation (4&#xD7; magnification)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9502-e6-02"/></fig>
<fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Positive staining of the lesion with S100, a marker for neurofilament protein (10&#xD7; magnification)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rcse9502-e6-03"/></fig>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="ch6_sau2">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Neurofibromas are rare benign tumours arising from Schwann cells of nerve sheaths. Solitary neurofibromas may occur but they occur most frequently as part of neurofibromatosis, an autosomal dominant disease characterised by multiple tumours throughout the nervous system with or without skin lesions. Bile duct neurofibromas arise from the sympathetic and parasympathetic nerve fibres in the wall of the common bile duct and are extremely rare, with a limited number of cases reported in the literature. These tumours are characterised pathologically by the presence of long spindle cells, whose neurogenic properties are demonstrated by positive immunohistochemistry for S100, a marker for neurofilament protein.</p>
      <p>The most common primary tumours of the biliary tract are cholangiocarcinomas, most of which are adenocarcinomas. Surgery is the only curative treatment with a 9&#x2013;18% five-year survival rate for proximal bile duct lesions and a 20&#x2013;30% five-year survival for distal lesions.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> Curative surgical resection is an option for only a minority of patients as the majority of patients present late when the lesion is unresectable. The five-year survival rate for inoperable disease is less than 5%.<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref> Benign tumours of the biliary tract, most commonly adenomas or papillomas, account for only 6% of all biliary tumours.<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
</p>
      <p>In the absence of neurofibromatosis, almost all cases of neurofibromas of the common bile duct are secondary to operative trauma following a cholecystectomy,<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> where traumatic rupture of the epineurium results in proliferation of the nerve fibres in the connective tissue surrounding the nerve. Solitary primary neurofibromas of the common bile duct may also occur, in which axonal proliferation is confined to the inside of the epineurium, and are thought to be the result of chronic inflammatory lesions, infection or foreign bodies such as biliary stones.</p>
      <p>Symptomatic neurofibromas usually present with jaundice, with or without abdominal pain and/or fever. Such patients are investigated radiologically with CT as in this case, with or without endoscopic ultrasonography (EUS).<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> The appearances of a homogenous mass or stricture are non-diagnostic in both imaging modalities and the use of EUS to investigate this patient would have not altered the subsequent management. The non-specific clinical and radiological features make it extremely difficult to differentiate between a neurofibroma and a malignant bile duct lesion preoperatively, and diagnosis is achieved only by histological examination.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> We emphasise the importance of intraoperative frozen section examination not only to ensure clear resection margins but also to rule out malignancy and avoid extensive surgical resection for benign disease, which could be associated with higher morbidity.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="ch6_sau3">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Neurofibromas of the bile duct are rare, and the lack of specific clinical and radiological features makes preoperative diagnosis difficult. The diagnosis should be considered in patients presenting following previous bile duct trauma such as a cholecystectomy. An exploratory laparotomy should include the use of intraoperative frozen section to ensure clear margins and confirm benign disease, to enable the most appropriate surgical management to be instituted.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name>
<surname>Ray</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Das</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mridha</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Khamrui</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Neurofibroma of the common bile duct: a rare cause of obstructive jaundice</article-title>. <source>Am J Surg</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>202</volume>: <fpage>e1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>e3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21741514</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name>
<surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Davidson</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Goldin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of cholangiocarcinoma: consensus document</article-title>. <source>Gut</source><year>2002</year>; <volume>51</volume> Suppl <issue>6</issue>: <fpage>vi1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>vi9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name>
<surname>Farley</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nagorney</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>&#x2018;Natural history&#x2019; of unresected cholangiocarcinoma: patient outcome after noncurative intervention</article-title>. <source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><year>1995</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7537346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name>
<surname>Burhans</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Myers</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Benign neoplasms of the extrahepatic biliary ducts</article-title>. <source>Am Surg</source><year>1971</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5548431</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name>
<surname>Peyr&#xE9;</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wakim</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mateo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name><italic>et al.</italic><article-title>Unusual cases of jaundice secondary to non-neoplastic bile duct obstruction</article-title>. <source>Am Surg</source><year>2004</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>620</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15279187</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
