<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Res Notes</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Res Notes</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Research Notes</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1756-0500</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27145827</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4857409</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2063</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-016-2063-x</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Resistant tuberculosis in Maranh&#xE3;o, Brazil: a case series</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Maia</surname>
            <given-names>Kenia Regina Oliveira</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>krmaia@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>de Castro Viana</surname>
            <given-names>Gra&#xE7;a Maria</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>gracaviana@globo.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>da Silva</surname>
            <given-names>Marcos Antonio Cust&#xF3;dio Neto</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>marcos_antonio456@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Soares Brand&#xE3;o Nascimento</surname>
            <given-names>Maria do Desterro</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>cnsd_ma@uol.com.br</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Souza</surname>
            <given-names>Victor Lima</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>victorlima_s@yahoo.com.br</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Monteiro</surname>
            <given-names>Silvio Gomes</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>silvio_gm@yahoo.com.br</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>Graduate Program in Parasitic Biology, University CEUMA, S&#xE3;o Lu&#xED;s, MA Brazil </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Nucleus of Basic and Applied Immunology, Department of Pathology, Federal University of Maranh&#xE3;o, S&#xE3;o Lu&#xED;s, MA Brazil </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label/>Medicine School, Federal University of Maranh&#xE3;o, Scientific Scholarship of CNPq, S&#xE3;o Lu&#xED;s, MA Brazil </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label/>Graduate Program in Adult and Child Health, Nucleus of Basic and Applied Immunology, Department of Pathology, Federal University of Maranh&#xE3;o, S&#xE3;o Lu&#xED;s, MA Brazil </aff>
        <aff id="Aff5"><label/>Medicine School, Federal University of Maranh&#xE3;o, S&#xE3;o Lu&#xED;s, MA Brazil </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <elocation-id>260</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Maia et al. 2016</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> multidrug resistance, especially against rifampicin and isoniazid, places pulmonary tuberculosis in the list of emerging diseases. The misuse of therapeutic regimens is one of its main predisposing factors.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>Four clinical cases (three were brown and one black) with multidrug-resistant tuberculosis, treated in a reference hospital in the state of Maranh&#xE3;o, Brazil, were reported to evaluate the importance of radiological framework on disease evolution.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The clinical framework showed a bad evolution and drug resistance, while radiology showed lung lesions, ranging from exudative infiltrates to lung parenchyma disintegration.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Tuberculosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Anti-tuberculosis drugs</kwd>
        <kwd>Resistance</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>The adverse effects of anti-tuberculosis drugs are related to the high incidence of noncompliance to treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Bacillus&#x2019; resistance to anti-tuberculosis drugs is related to wild strain mutations and the mutant selection process during treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] in cases related to discontinuation or irregular treatment with standard regimens. Cases that led to primary resistance or acquired resistance, without contact, have also been found upon using specific drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Cavitary tuberculosis cause outbreaks with higher resistance and mutant frequency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>This paper shows four clinical cases of patients with multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) assisted in a reference hospital in the state of Maranh&#xE3;o, Brazil. In addition, the radiological framework importance on disease evolution was assessed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>This paper consists of a retrospective study with 41 confirmed MDR-TB cases in 2003&#x2013;2010. Only four cases are described in this series, as they had a complete supporting documentation.</p>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Case 1</title>
        <p>A 33-year-old man, brown, married, was admitted in October 2006, with a history of Scheme III failure (indicated for therapeutic failure; 2&#xA0;months with streptomycin, ethionamide, ethambutol and pyrazinamide, and 4&#xA0;months with ethionamide and ethambutol) and resistance to rifampicin, isoniazid and streptomycin; negative HIV test; chest radiograph showed a right hemithorax fissure rectification and an exudative bronchiectasis lesion in the hemithorax. One&#xA0;year and 1&#xA0;month later, fibro-atelectatic lesions were observed in the right upper lobe. The patient initiated the MDR-TB treatment 3&#xA0;years later, having a positive sputum smear for acid-fast bacilli (AFB), confirmed by culture, with an oscillating pattern, and two positive cultures for <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, with resistance to isoniazid, rifampicin, streptomycin and ethambutol. MR scheme for MR-X was conducted with ciprofloxacin, clarithromycin and pyrazinamide. Terizidone and bacilloscopies continued with an oscillating pattern. During 2&#xA0;years and 6&#xA0;months, two negative cultures were performed, with clinical resolution and radiological pattern of healing (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Case 2</title>
        <p>A 27-year-old woman, brown, single, student, with a history of irregular treatment with regimen I in 2005 (indicated for new pulmonary and extra-pulmonary tuberculosis cases, except tuberculous meningitis; 2&#xA0;months with rifampicin, isoniazid and ethambutol, and 4&#xA0;months with rifampicin and isoniazid). HIV was negative. After 6&#xA0;months, the patient developed productive cough, fatigue, fever episodes and gastrointestinal symptoms, then resumed with the tuberculostatic medication. The radiological framework showed residual pleural injury. Three years later, a cavitary lesion in the left upper lobe and bilaterally diffuse alveolar infiltrates were found when the enhanced scheme I was repeated, as having a positive sputum smear for AFB. A month later, bilateral lesions were found with cavities in the right upper lobe, positive smear and culture, and then the MDR-TB treatment began. Three months later, the positive culture remained, and a bilateral parenchymal fibrosis to the right was observed. A month later, the radiological examination showed bilaterally diffuse interstitial-alveolar infiltrate. Two months later, the radiological examination showed alveolar lesions in the apices, an atelectasis band to the right and a positive culture. Four years later, decreased lung size, atelectasis bands and cavitary lesions in the upper lobes were found. Three months later, bilateral bronchiectasis areas were observed. After three months, the patient was in a severe general condition. Five years later, a positive smear was found and an alternative scheme began. A month later, bilateral cavitation areas were observed, with right lung reduction. Three months later, radiological pattern persisted and positive smear with sensitivity tests indicating isoniazid and rifampicin resistance were found. Although the patient was treated, the severity evolved without improvement and the patient died 2&#xA0;months later (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Case 3</title>
        <p>A 38-year-old woman, black, homemaker. Chest radiography showed diffuse interstitial-alveolar infiltrates with pulmonary parenchyma, bubbles and bronchiectasis in the upper lobes. The treatment with scheme I began in 2006. It was abandoned, and the patient resumed treatment 1&#xA0;year later with an enhanced scheme I. After a few months, the patient stopped taking medication, and the treatment resumed with the MDR-TB regimen. Three months later, being the smear positive, a positive culture for <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> was observed in the susceptibility test, showing resistance to isoniazid and rifampicin. Six months later, <italic>Mycobacterium hodleri</italic> was identified by PCR. Seven months later, a radiograph showed large pneumatoceles in the upper lobes, left apical bronchiectasis, and fibro-exudative and cavitary lesions in the upper segments of lower lobes. Three months later, the patient was discharged after the cure of MDR-TB, returning repeatedly for 10&#xA0;months, when the AFB smear was positive. Chest radiograph showed bubbles, bronchiectasis and fibrous residual lesions in the upper lobes (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Case 4</title>
        <p>An 18-year-old woman, brown, single, peasant. She started the regimen I treatment in 2003, and abandoned it. One year later, the treatment was resumed with the enhanced scheme I, showing therapeutic failure. One year later, the MDR-TB treatment began. Two years later, the patient was treated for MDR-X tuberculosis. Bacilloscopy oscillated during the course of treatment. The culture trials conducted during treatment were positive for <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>, showing a resistance to isoniazid, rifampicin and ethambutol. Six months later, a chest radiograph showed alveolar infiltrates in the left lung base. A year and 10&#xA0;months later, the radiograph showed left lung parenchymal destruction, with cavitary lesions in the right upper lobe (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Clinical characteristics of patients with documented multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Patient</th><th align="left">Age</th><th align="left">Tuberculosis duration, years</th><th align="left">Drugs to which the patient was resistant<sup>a</sup>
</th><th align="left">Severe CXR findings<sup>b</sup>
</th><th align="left">Time to smear conversion, months</th><th align="left">Adverse reactions to the treatment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">33</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">INH, Rif, Eth, Stm</td><td align="left">No</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">27</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">INH, Rif</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left">GI</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">38</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">INH, Rif</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left">None</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">INH, Rif, Eth</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left">None</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>CXR</italic> chest radiograph, <italic>Eth</italic> ethambutol, <italic>INH</italic> isoniazid, <italic>Rif</italic> rifampin, <italic>Stm</italic> streptomycin, <italic>GI</italic> gastrointestinal</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>Patients were tested for resistance to Eth, INH, Rif, PZA, Stm, Km, Cm, and Tha, as well as resistance to ciprofloxacin and cycloserine</p><p>
<sup>b</sup>Cavitary and bilateral lesions</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Although the literature describes a high toxicity of drugs used in the MDR-TB treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], adverse effects were only observed in one case (25&#xA0;%).</p>
      <p>Through the report of four cases, the presence of severe pulmonary lesions with irreversible characteristics was radiographically evident, usually beginning with exudative lesions and parenchymal lung destruction. Case 3 shows a concomitant infection by <italic>M. hodleri</italic>, with very exuberant lung lesions. All patients described abandoned treatment, and had cavitary and fibro residual lesions and treatment failure, and showed no HIV coinfection, which is an association commonly described in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
      <p>Chest radiography predicts tuberculosis prognosis by evaluating pulmonary lesions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], and it is still the most used imaging method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Cavitary lesions and residual fibrosis found related to multidrug resistance corroborate the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>In this study, 7.3&#xA0;% of MDR-TB and 2.4&#xA0;% of XDR were found, values lower than those reported for the USA. Marks et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] found a prevalence of 36&#xA0;% of MDR-TB and 56&#xA0;% of XDR-TB in 2005&#x2013;2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Regarding drugs, resistance to rifampicin and isoniazid, as well as age (young adults), supported the findings of a study conducted in Congo [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p>
      <p>In summary, MDR-TB is a major public health problem in Brazil, especially in poor areas such as the Brazilian North and Northeast.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>AFB</term>
          <def>
            <p>acid-fast bacilli</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>HIV</term>
          <def>
            <p>human immunodeficiency virus</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MDR-TB</term>
          <def>
            <p>multidrug-resistant tuberculosis</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>XDR</term>
          <def>
            <p>extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ack>
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>KROM participated in data collection and interpretation, critically revised the manuscript and contributed to the writing of the manuscript. GMCV participated in data collection and interpretation, contributed to the writing of the manuscript and critically revised the manuscript. SGM participated in data collection and interpretation and critically revised the manuscript. MACNS contributed to the writing and drafting of the manuscript, and critically revised the manuscript. MDSBN contributed to the writing and drafting of the manuscript and critically revised the manuscript. VLS contributed in drafting the manuscript and critically revised it. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      <sec id="FPar1">
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <p>We would like to thank Presidente Vargas Hospital for providing the data from patients involved in this study.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar2">
        <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
        <p>The data supporting the conclusions of this paper are included in the paper (and its additional files).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar3">
        <title>Competing interests</title>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar4">
        <title>Ethics (and consent)</title>
        <p>A free and informed consent was obtained from all patients that participated in this study. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the State Department of Health, according to the Resolution no. 466/2012 of the National Health Council.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar5">
        <title>Publishing consent</title>
        <p>A written informed consent was obtained from all patients concerning the publication of the case report and accompanying tables from all four patients. In the case of patients that died, a written informed consent was obtained for the publication of this case report and any accompanying tables from the next of kin of the patients.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maciel</surname>
              <given-names>ELN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guidoni</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Favero</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hadad</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molino</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jonhson</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dietze</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Efeitos adversos causados pelo novo esquema de tratamento de tuberculose preconizado pelo Minist&#xE9;rio da Sa&#xFA;de do Brasil</article-title>
          <source>J Bras Pneumol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>232</fpage>
          <lpage>238</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1806-37132010000200012</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20485945</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Campos</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> resistente, de onde vem a resist&#xEA;ncia?</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras An&#xE1;l Cl&#xED;n</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <lpage>161</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>EAT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruffino-Netto</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrade</surname>
              <given-names>SMO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Drug rsistance profile of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in the state of Mato Grosso do Sul, Brazil, 2000&#x2013;2006</article-title>
          <source>J Bras Pneumol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>224</fpage>
          <lpage>231</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20485944</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cunha</surname>
              <given-names>EAT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leite</surname>
              <given-names>CQF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Junqueira</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ar&#xE3;o</surname>
              <given-names>CAB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>IP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The contribution of the public health central laboratory of Mato Grosso do Sul to the diagnosis of tuberculosis and identification of antituberculosis drug-resistance</article-title>
          <source>BBAC</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>191</fpage>
          <lpage>196</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rocha</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dacolmo</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borga</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fedele</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marques</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tuberculose multirresistente</article-title>
          <source>Pulm&#xE3;o RJ</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>27</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shim</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jo</surname>
              <given-names>KW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Medical treatment of pulmonary multidrug-resistant tuberculosis</article-title>
          <source>Infect Chemother.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          <lpage>374</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3947/ic.2013.45.4.367</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24475350</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santa Cruz</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Albuquerque</surname>
              <given-names>MFPM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Campelo</surname>
              <given-names>ARL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>EJC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mazza</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Menezes</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kosminsky</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary tuberculosis: association between extent of residual pulmonary lesion and alteration in the lung function</article-title>
          <source>Rev Assoc Med Bras.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>406</fpage>
          <lpage>410</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18989560</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bombarda</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Figueiredo</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Funari</surname>
              <given-names>MBG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soares</surname>
              <given-names>JRJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seiscento</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terra</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Imagem em tuberculose pulmonar</article-title>
          <source>J. Pneumol.</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>340</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-35862001000600007</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marks</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flood</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seaworth</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirsch-Moverman</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armstrong</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mase</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salcedo</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graviss</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colson</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armitige</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Revuelta</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheeran</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <collab>TB Epidemiologic Studies Consortium</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment practices, outcomes, and costs of multidrug-resistant and extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis, United States, 2005&#x2013;2007</article-title>
          <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>812</fpage>
          <lpage>821</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2005.131037</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24751166</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kaswa</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bisuta</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kabuya</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lunguya</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ndongosieme</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muyembe</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Deun</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boelaert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multi drug resistant tuberculosis in mosango, a rural area in the democratic republic of congo</article-title>
          <source>PLoS ONE</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>e94618</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094618</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24732233</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
