<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24419876</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4073340</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13-0526</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.13-0526</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Pathology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Note</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Systemic <italic>Streptococcus dysgalactiae</italic> Subspecies
<italic>equisimilis</italic> Infection in a Yorkshire Pig with Severe
Disseminated Suppurative Meningoencephalomyelitis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>KASUYA</surname>
            <given-names>Kazufumi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>YOSHIDA</surname>
            <given-names>Eiji</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>HARADA</surname>
            <given-names>Rieko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>HASEGAWA</surname>
            <given-names>Mio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>OSAKA</surname>
            <given-names>Hiroyuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>KATO</surname>
            <given-names>Masaharu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SHIBAHARA</surname>
            <given-names>Tomoyuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Pathological and Physiochemical Examination Division,
Laboratory Department, Animal Quarantine Service, 11&#x2013;1 Haramachi, Isogo, Yokohama,
Kanagawa 235&#x2013;0008, Japan</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>Animal Inspection Division, Quarantine Department, Animal
Quarantine Service, 11&#x2013;1 Haramachi, Isogo, Yokohama, Kanagawa 235&#x2013;0008, Japan</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3)</label>Pathology and Pathophysiology Research Division, National
Institute of Animal Health, 3&#x2013;1&#x2013;5 Kannondai, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305&#x2013;0856, Japan</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Kasuya, K., Pathological and
Physiochemical Examination Division, Laboratory Department, Animal Quarantine Service,
11&#x2013;1 Haramachi, Isogo, Yokohama, Kanagawa 235&#x2013;0008, Japan. e-mail: <email xlink:href="kasuyaka@aqs.maff.go.jp">kasuyaka@aqs.maff.go.jp</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>76</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>715</fpage>
      <lpage>718</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2014 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>ABSTRACT</title>
        <p>An 18-week-old female breeding Yorkshire pig displayed symptoms of astasia and
subsequently died. Histologically, severe disseminated suppurative
meningoencephalomyelitis was detected, as were numerous myocardial microabscesses.
Gram-positive cocci were detected in these suppurative lesions, and these cocci reacted
with an antibody against <italic>Streptococcus</italic> C group species. Gram-positive
cocci were isolated from the liver, spleen, kidney, heart, lungs, pleural abscess and
articular fluid of the right tarsal joint. The isolates were &#x3B2;-hemolytic, categorized into
Lancefield group C and were identified as <italic>Streptococcus dysgalactiae</italic>
subspecies <italic>equisimilis</italic> by analysis of the 16S ribosomal DNA sequence.
This is the first report of systemic <italic>S. equisimilis</italic> infection in a pig
with severe disseminated suppurative meningoencephalomyelitis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd><italic>Streptococcus dysgalactiae</italic> subspecies <italic>equisimilis</italic></kwd>
        <kwd>swine</kwd>
        <kwd>systemic infection</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Swine streptococcosis is an important infectious disease caused by
<italic>Streptococcus</italic> species. <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic>,
<italic>Streptococcus dysgalactiae</italic> and <italic>Streptococcus porcinus</italic> are
indigenous bacteria isolated from the tonsils, intestinal tracts and genital organs of
clinically healthy pigs. However, they are also opportunistic pathogens capable of causing
swine streptococcosis [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], the symptoms of which include
sepsis, meningitis, arthritis, endocarditis, cervical abscess, pneumonia, abortion and
lymphadenitis [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Recently, endocarditis-associated
brain lesions were detected in slaughter pigs with left-sided valvular endocarditis, and most
cases were caused by <italic>S. suis</italic> [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
    <p><italic>S. dysgalactiae</italic> can be divided into two subspecies based on whole-cell
protein profiles and biochemical properties [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The
first is <italic>S. dysgalactiae</italic> subsp. <italic>dysgalactiae</italic>(<italic>S.
dysgalactiae</italic>), which includes &#x3B1;-, &#x3B2;- and non-hemolytic strains of animal origin,
belonging to Lancefield group C or L. The second is <italic>S. dysgalactiae</italic> subsp.
<italic>equisimilis</italic>(<italic>S. equisimilis</italic>), which includes &#x3B2;-hemolytic
strains of human origin, belonging to Lancefield serogroup C or G.</p>
    <p><italic>S. equisimilis</italic> is usually isolated from pigs with verrucous endocarditis
showing no other clinical signs of disease, and lesions are usually diagnosed at the time of
inspection at the slaughterhouses [<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. <italic>S. equisimilis</italic>-associated human
streptococcosis, including severe invasive infections, has also been reported [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. However, its virulence is not completely understood,
because of insufficient bacterial analysis. Additional research should be carried out into
these bacteria as they are important in public health and also in the field of veterinary
medicine.</p>
    <p>The purpose of this study was to describe systemic <italic>S</italic>.
<italic>equisimilis</italic> infection accompanied by suppurative meningoencephalomyelitis
in a Yorkshire pig.</p>
    <p>Sixty-eight 9&#x2013;18-week-old female breeding Yorkshire pigs were imported from Canada into Japan
by airplane. At the time of arrival in Japan, a 15-week-old pig was unable to stand, and the
right tarsal joint was swollen and warm. The white cell count revealed leukocytosis (WBC:
26,900/<italic>&#xB5;l</italic>). The pig gradually
weakened and died at 18 weeks of age in quarantine. No clinical abnormalities were observed in
the remaining 67 pigs.</p>
    <p>The pig was vaccinated against swine erysipelas, porcine circovirus type 2 (PCV-2) and
Glasser&#x2019;s disease during the departure quarantine period in Canada. In addition, in compliance
with animal health requirements, the animal had been treated with oxytetracycline (Liquamycin
LA-200; Pfizer, New York, NY, U.S.A.) for leptospirosis.</p>
    <p>A necropsy was performed, and tissue samples from major organs were fixed in 10%
neutral-buffered formalin and embedded in paraffin wax. Tissue sections (approximately 3
<italic>&#xB5;</italic>m thick) were stained with hematoxylin and eosin (HE) and Gram stained for
histological examination.</p>
    <p>For immunohistochemistry analysis, rabbit polyclonal antibodies against
<italic>Streptococcus</italic> C group bacteria (Denka Seiken, Tokyo, Japan) and PCV-2
[<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] were used with a commercial kit
(<italic>N</italic>-Histofine Simple Stain MAX PO (R); Nichirei Bioscience Inc., Tokyo,
Japan).</p>
    <p>The liver, spleen, kidney, heart, lungs, articular fluid of the right tarsal joint and
pleural abscess were used for bacterial isolation. A simple identification kit (API 20 STREP;
bioMerieux SA, Marcy-l&#x2019;&#xC9;toile, France) and a Strept LA &#x201C;SEIKEN&#x201D; <italic>Streptococcus</italic>
grouping kit (Denka Seiken) were used to identify the isolates.</p>
    <p>For genetic tests, genomic DNA was extracted from bacterial colonies using a DNA extraction
kit (InstaGene Matrix; Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, U.S.A.). Polymerase chain reaction
(PCR) was employed to detect the genes encoding streptolysin O (<italic>slo</italic>) [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], streptolysin S (<italic>sagA</italic>) [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and streptokinase (pSTKP8) [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p>
    <p>To test antibiotic susceptibility, the disk diffusion method was performed on <italic>S.
equisimilis</italic> isolated from the heart, using antibiotic disks (SN disk; Nissui
Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). The antibiotics tested were ampicillin, erythromycin,
clindamycin, tetracycline and chloramphenicol.</p>
    <p>An ~500 bp region of the 16S ribosomal RNA gene (16S rDNA) region was amplified and sequenced
using a MicroSeq 500 16S rDNA PCR/Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems Life Technologies,
Carlsbad, CA, U.S.A.) [<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p>
    <p>Grossly, the right tarsal joint was swollen, and cloudy effusion had accumulated in the
articular cavity. An abscess (approximately 2 cm in diameter) was found in the pleura of the
6th costovertebral joint. No gross abnormalities were found in other organs, including the
brain and spinal cord.</p>
    <p>Histologically, severe (cerebrum and brainstem) to moderate (cerebellum and spinal cord)
disseminated suppurative meningoencephalomyelitis was detected. The lesions were also
characterized by focal microabscesses in the parenchyma of the central nervous system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1a</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>a. Microabscesses in the cerebrum. HE. Bar=50 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m. b. Moderate to
severe neutrophilic infiltrations are detected around the blood vessel in the heart. HE.
Bar=100 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m. c. A few Gram-positive cocci (arrows) are detected in the
neutrophilic cytoplasm in the cerebrum. Gram stain. Bar=10 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m. d. The
cocci in the microabscess in the cerebrum react with the antibody against
<italic>Streptococcus</italic> C group bacteria (arrows). HE (left).
Immunohistochemistry for <italic>Streptococcus</italic> C group bacteria counterstained
with hematoxylin (right). Bar=20 <italic>&#xB5;</italic>m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-76-715-g001"/></fig>). Small numbers of neutrophils had infiltrated into the subarachnoid cavity and cranial
pia mater and around the blood vessels of the cerebrum. Vasculitis, with moderate to severe
neutrophilic infiltrations, was detected in the heart (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig.
1b</xref>). Numerous microabscesses were also detected in the myocardium. Moderate
lymphoplasmacytic and slight neutrophilic infiltrations were detected in the stroma of the
kidney. Slight neutrophilic infiltrations were also detected in the hepatic lobular connective
tissue, in the splenic pulp and around the bronchus of the lung. A few Gram-positive cocci
were detected in the suppurative lesions of the cerebrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1c</xref>), brainstem, heart, liver, spleen, kidney and pleural abscess, and some
cocci were also detected in the blood vessels. The cocci reacted with an antibody against
<italic>Streptococcus</italic> C group bacteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig.
1d</xref>), but no positive reactions to an antibody against PCV-2 were observed in tissue
sections.</p>
    <p>Neutralization tests for classical swine fever and Aujeszky&#x2019;s disease, indirect enzyme-linked
immunosorbent assay for porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome, a tube agglutination
test for brucellosis and viral isolation for swine influenza virus from a nasal swab were
conducted as a routine serological and virological examination for imported pigs, and the
results were all negative.</p>
    <p>Gram-positive cocci were isolated from the liver, spleen, kidney, heart, lungs, articular
fluid of the right tarsal joint and pleural abscess. The isolates were &#x3B2;-hemolytic,
catalase-negative and oxidase-negative and were identified as <italic>S. equisimilis</italic>
by the simple identification kit (profile number 11132041100, 57.2% identity). The bacteria
were categorized into Lancefield group C by the <italic>Streptococcus</italic> grouping kit.
The <italic>sagA</italic> and pSTKP8 genes, but not the <italic>slo</italic> gene, were
positively identified in the isolates, which also showed resistance to erythromycin,
clindamycin and tetracycline. Sequencing of the amplified 16S rDNA region confirmed the
Gram-positive cocci as <italic>S. equisimilis </italic>(ATCC 35666, 99.2% identity).</p>
    <p><italic>S. equisimilis</italic> was isolated from the liver, spleen, kidney, heart, lungs and
pleural abscess. Furthermore, because Gram-positive cocci reacting with the antibody against
<italic>Streptococcus</italic> C group bacteria were detected in the suppurative lesions,
the present case was diagnosed as systemic streptococcosis caused by <italic>S.
equisimilis</italic> infection. Streptococci are regularly found in the tonsils of pigs, and
immunosuppressed pigs are more likely to develop streptococcosis [<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In this case, the stress of
long-distance transportation and environmental changes associated with importation were
considered to be relevant to the pathogenesis. The present findings suggested that sepsis
occurred and that the causative cocci were transferred hematogenously from the tonsils to the
systemic organs, including the central nervous system and joints. Next, suppurative lesions
formed in the systemic organs. Suppurative encephalomyelitis in pigs is common [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], but this is the first report of severe systemic
<italic>S. equisimilis</italic> infection with disseminated suppurative
meningoencephalomyelitis in pigs.</p>
    <p>Although the present isolates were identified as <italic>S. equisimilis</italic> by the
simple identification kit, the percent identity was not high (57.2%). This low identity may
have been caused by the negative result for alkaline phosphatase activity. The biochemical
properties used to identify <italic>Streptococcus</italic> species by the simple
identification kit are difficult to reproduce consistently [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In this case, species identification by 16S rDNA sequence was beneficial.</p>
    <p>The <italic>S. equisimilis</italic> strain isolated in this case was categorized into
Lancefield group C, which is consistent with a report that <italic>S. equisimilis</italic>
isolated from pigs with endocarditis and arthritis is frequently categorized into group C
[<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In
addition, the pattern of virulence genes was <italic>slo</italic>(&#x2212;), <italic>sagA</italic>(+)
and pSTKP8 (+). <italic>S. equisimilis</italic> of human origin has been reported to contain
all three genes [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], indicating that the pig isolate
identified in the current case differs from those of human origin. Furthermore, the isolates
were susceptible to ampicillin, indicating that penicillin antibiotics would still be
effective, but were resistant to the macrolide erythromycin and tetracycline. This result was
consistent with a report that the susceptibility of <italic>S. equisimilis</italic> to
macrolide and tetracycline antibiotics was lower than that to penicillin antibiotics [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors thank Mr M. Kobayashi and Ms M. Shimada for histopathological
assistance.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bert</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert-Zechovsky</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year>
<article-title>Analysis of a case of recurrent
bacteraemia due to group A <italic>Streptococcus equisimilis</italic> by pulsed-field
gel electrophoresis</article-title>.
<source><italic>Infection</italic></source><volume>25</volume>:
<fpage>250</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>251</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01713156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9266266</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Caballero</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lottenberg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year>
<article-title>Cloning, expression, sequence analysis,
and characterization of streptokinases secreted by porcine and equine isolates of
<italic>Streptococcus equisimilis</italic></article-title>. <source><italic>Infect.
Immun.</italic></source><volume>67</volume>: <fpage>6478</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6486</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10569766</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>J. A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katic</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandler</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year>
<article-title>Taxonomic studies on streptococci of
serological groups E, P, U, and V; Description of <italic>Streptococcus
porcinus</italic> sp. nov</article-title>. <source><italic>Syst. Appl.
Microbiol.</italic></source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>413</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0723-2020(84)80041-7</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McShan</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adjic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savic</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Primeaux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sezate</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suvorov</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Najar</surname><given-names>F. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>
<article-title>Complete genome sequence of an M1 strain
of <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic></article-title>. <source><italic>Proc. Natl.
Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source><volume>98</volume>:
<fpage>4658</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4663</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.071559398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11296296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiya</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunji</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuma</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Antimicrobial susceptibilities and
resistant genes in &#x3B2;&#x2013;hemolytic Streptococci isolated from endocarditis in slaughtered
pigs</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Jpn. Vet. Med.
Assoc.</italic></source><volume>66</volume>:
<fpage>138</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>142</lpage> (in
Japanese). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12935/jvma.66.138</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Ikebe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isobe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsukawa</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamaru</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujinaga</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> and Working Group for Streptococci in Japan. <year>2004</year>
<article-title>Surveillance of severe invasive group-G streptococcal infections and
molecular typing of the isolates in Japan</article-title>. <source><italic>Epidemiol.
Infect.</italic></source><volume>132</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>149</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268803001262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14979600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gyllensten</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leifsson</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agerholm</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boye</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aalb&#xE6;k</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year>
<article-title>Histologic and bacteriologic findings in
valvular endocarditis of slaughter-age pigs</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet.
Diagn. Invest.</italic></source><volume>22</volume>:
<fpage>921</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>927</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/104063871002200611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21088176</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Karstrup</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>H. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aalb&#xE6;k</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leifsson</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boye</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agerholm</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>
<article-title>Endocarditis-associated brain lesions in
slaughter pigs</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Comp.
Pathol.</italic></source><volume>144</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>295</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcpa.2010.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21168147</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Katsumi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiramune</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year>
<article-title>Biochemical and serological examination
of beta-hemolytic streptococci isolated from slaughtered pigs</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Vet. Med. Sci.</italic></source><volume>60</volume>:
<fpage>129</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>131</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.60.129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9492374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kilpper-Balz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schliefer</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year>
<article-title><italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> sp.
nov., nom. rev</article-title>. <source><italic>Int. J. Syst.
Bacteriol.</italic></source><volume>37</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>162</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-37-2-160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">11.<person-group><name><surname>Maxie</surname></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year> Cardiovascular system. pp. 27&#x2013;30. <italic>In</italic>:
Pathology of Domestic Animals, 5th ed. (Maxie, G. ed.), Saunders Elsevier,
Edinburgh.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabali</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibahara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>
<article-title>Systemic <italic>Actinobacillus
suis</italic> infection in a piglet</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Jpn. Vet. Med.
Assoc.</italic></source><volume>64</volume>:
<fpage>381</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>384</lpage> (in
Japanese).</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sunaoshi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aburahashi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuzumi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ubukata</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>
<article-title><italic>Emm</italic> typing by genetic
identification of <italic>Streptococcus dysgalactiae</italic> subsp.
<italic>equisimilis</italic> and susceptibility to oral antibiotics</article-title>.
<source><italic>Kansenshogaku Zasshi</italic></source><volume>80</volume>:
<fpage>488</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>495</lpage> (in
Japanese). <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17073261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Therese</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deepa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangaiyarkarasi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dajcs</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>H. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>DNA sequencing by Microseq kit targeting
16S rRNA gene for species level identification of mycobacteria</article-title>.
<source><italic>Indian J. Med. Res.</italic></source><volume>129</volume>:
<fpage>176</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>181</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19293445</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pot</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falsen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kersters</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devriese</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year>
<article-title>Taxonomic study of Lacefield
streptococcal Groups C, G, and L (<italic>Streptococcus dysgalactiae</italic>) and
proposal of <italic>S. dysgalactiae</italic> subsp. equisimilis subsp.
nov</article-title>. <source><italic>Int. J. Syst.
Bacteriol.</italic></source><volume>46</volume>: <fpage>774</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>781</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-46-3-774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8782689</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
