<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26312687</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4540521</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20153455</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Granulomatosis with polyangiitis, a new nomenclature for Wegener's
Granulomatosis - Case report<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Lima</surname>
            <given-names>Alexandre Moretti</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Torraca</surname>
            <given-names>Pedro de Freitas Silva</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>da Rocha</surname>
            <given-names>Sheila Pereira</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Santiago</surname>
            <given-names>Carmelia Matos Reis</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ferraz</surname>
            <given-names>Fabio Humberto Ribeiro Paes</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label>Universidade Federal de Mato Grosso do Sul (UFMS) - Campo
Grande (MS), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label>Private clinic - Bras&#xED;lia (DF), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label>Hospital Regional da Asa Norte (HRAN) - Bras&#xED;lia (DF),
Brazil.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">MAILING ADDRESS: Alexandre Moretti de Lima, 2165, Doutor Arthur Jorge
Street, Apt 601, Monte Castelo, 79010210 - Campo Grande - MS, Brazil. Email:
<email>morettilima@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>Conflict of Interest: None.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>May-Jun</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>90</volume>
      <issue>3 Suppl 1</issue>
      <fpage>101</fpage>
      <lpage>103</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2015 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The granulomatosis with polyangiitis, initially known as Wegener's granulomatosis, is
a small and medium vessels vasculitis. It's classic form presents a triad:
necrotizing granuloma of respiratory tract, necrotizing cutaneous vasculitis and
glomerulonephritis. This vasculitis has cytoplasmic antineutrophil antibodies as
signal. This work illustrates a case, of multisystemic rare disease, in which the
segment and treatment were considered satisfactory for symptoms remission.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic antibody-associated vasculitis</kwd>
        <kwd>Granulomatosis with Polyangiitis</kwd>
        <kwd>Vasculitis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Initially described by Klinger in 1931 and by Wegener in 1936, Wegener's granulomatosis
is a small and medium vessels vasculitis. <sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> After 2012, with the
advent of a new Chapel Hill Consensus Conference (CHCC 2012), it was renamed
granulomatosis with polyangiitis (GP).<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
      <p>With an unknown etiology, GP is a rare multisystem disease, with no gender preferences,
common in Caucasians, with undetermined worldwide incidence.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> In the United
States it is estimated 3 cases per 100,000 people, and in the United Kingdom, 109 cases
per million inhabitants.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> It is characterized by necrotizing
granulomatous inflammation, primarily of kidney, upper and lower respiratory
tract.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Davies, in 1982, and Van der Woude, in 1985, showed anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic
antibodies of cytoplasmic pattern (C-ANCA), in GP, with a specificity of 99.3% for the
disease. <sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> The present study consists
of a GP case report, highlighting its skin and systemic involvement, and its new
nomenclature.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Woman, 18 years old, Caucasian, coming from Ceil&#xE2;ndia (DF), with tumor on the left side
of face and on right lower limb, which progressed to ulceration associated with ptosis
of the left eyelid, bilateral epistaxis, purulent otorrhea in the left ear, palatal
ulcer, anasarca and oliguria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). Personal history: asthma since the age of eight.
Physical examination: good general condition, pale; palate with painful ulceration in
healing phase, ptosis of the left eyelid and two ulcers with infiltrative borders of 2cm
and 3cm, clean background, on left zygomatic area; wheezing at lung bases; extremity
with edema and ulcer of 5 cm located in the right leg.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Ulcerative crusty lesions on the left side of the face</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-03-s1-0101-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Fibrin-covered ulcer in the right lower limb</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-03-s1-0101-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Imaging tests: chest X-ray with mixed standard condensation foci at left lung base;
cranial x-ray showing frontal sinus with increased volume, hyper transparent image in
frontal region; sinus radiography with opacification and fluid levels in maxillary
sinuses; cranial tomography with focal area of edema in the left frontal lobe compatible
with cerebritis, infectious subdural collection and mastoiditis; abdominal ultrasound
showing kidneys with corticomedullary demarcation poorly defined, increased cortical
echogenicity, suggestive of parenchymal nephropathy.</p>
      <p>Renal anatomopathological examination of clusters with increasing cell, fibrinoid
necrosis foci, partial sclerosis of glomeruli and immunofluorescence with no deposits of
immunoglobulins, complement fraction and fibrinogen, compatible with related standard
c-ANCA.</p>
      <p>Laboratory tests showed leukocytosis with neutrophilia of 89% and C-ANCA 1:20.
Anatomopathological examination of skin ulcer biopsy showed loose granulomatous
infiltrate in the dermis, with multinucleate cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>). After confirmation of the diagnosis of GP, it was started the
pulse therapy with methylprednisolone 0.5g/day for 5 days and maintenance prednisone at
initial dose of 1mg/kg/day (gradually reduced) and cyclophosphamide 2 mg/kg/day. Patient
showed improvement of renal involvement, with a decrease in anasarca, serum creatinine,
urea and upper respiratory symptoms, as well as accelerated healing of skin ulcers.</p>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Anatomopathological examination of skin ulcer biopsy showing infiltrate, loose
granulomas in the dermis, with multinucleated giant cells (40x)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-03-s1-0101-g03"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Classified as necrotizing granulomatous vasculitis of small and medium vessels,
granulomatosis with polyangiitis (GP) is a rare multisystem disease. <sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Presence of its triad - necrotizing
granulomatous inflammation of the respiratory tract, cutaneous necrotizing vasculitis
and glomerulonephritis - observed in our case guides the diagnosis, however these
clinical manifestations may not occur simultaneously. <sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Since 2013, due to the recommendations of the American College of Rheumatology (ACR),
the American Society of Nephrology (ASN) and the European League Against Rheumatism
(EULAR), a new Chapel Hill Consensus Conference (CCHC2012) updated the classification of
Wegener's granulomatosis to granulomatosis with polyangiitis. The main purpose of this
modification is to optimize the official system of classification of vasculitis in order
to suggest more identifiable criteria for classification and diagnosis, thus avoiding
eponyms. <sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The involvement of the upper respiratory tract occurs in 50-80% of cases, and mainly in
the form of chronic sinusitis. <sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>
Studies show that skin manifestations may appear in 16% to 77% of cases and with varied
presentations. <sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Papulonecrotic lesions represent the most common injuries
and they occur mainly in the lower limbs. <sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Involvement of skin and
mucosa, alone, feature a rare variant called localized granulomatosis. <sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Renal vasculitis, necrotizing and granulomatous, happens in less than 50% of cases of
GP. These vasculitis are late and don't occur in the limited form of the disease. The
most frequently observed renal damage (75% to 80% of patients), though not decisive in
GP, is the focal and segmental necrotizing glomerulonephritis and it may, in some cases,
evolve into generalized glomerulonephritis. Vasculitis, in its granulomatous form in the
renal tissue, is very rare. <sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>An important aspect in the diagnosis of GP is its antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody
profile. Originally these antibodies are associated with necrotizing vasculitis and they
can be subdivided according to its stimulating antigen. <sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> There are
currently 2 main classifications for this class of antibodies: specific pattern for
protein myeloperoxidase (MPO-ANCA) of perinuclear presentation (p-ANCA) and the specific
pattern for proteinase 3 (PR3-ANCA) of cytoplasmic display (c-ANCA). <sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> The c-ANCA standard is the marker in GP
and it was shown in laboratory tests of our case with a rate of 1:20.</p>
      <p>Early treatment of remission induction is crucial to reverse the renal damage, and it is
performed in 40% of cases within the first 3 months of symptoms, relying on the use of
corticosteroids and cyclophosphamide.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>
Before introduction of cyclophosphamide, patients' outcome was invariably fatal, with a
mean survival rate of 5 months and mortality rate of 82% in one year, reaching 90% in 2
years of the disease. Using this association, Mc Donald and Remee reviewed 411 treated
cases, and observed a mean survival rate of 75% in 5.8 years.<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Currently, hopes are directed towards immunobiological
agents. Among them, the most studied is rituximab, which found a place in the current
EULAR recommendations as an alternative drug for refractory disease, being used at a
dose of 375 mg/m<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>/week for 4
weeks.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Another alternative in
the treatment of remission is methotrexate 15-25 mg/week combined with folic acid.
Maintenance can be done with azathioprine 2 mg/kg/day; leflunomide 20-30 mg/day or
rituximab 1g IV every 6 months for 2 years. <sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In the presented case, pulse corticosteroids therapy was the chosen treatment, showing
clinical and laboratorial remission, but cyclophosphamide was not administered in the
form of pulse therapy due to a suspicion of pulmonary infection, which would worsen the
clinical condition.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>Financial Support: None.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p><bold>How to cite this article:</bold> Lima AM, Torraca PFS, Rocha SP, Santiago CMR,
Paes-Ferraz FHR. Granulomatosis with polyangiitis, a new nomenclature for Wegener's
Granulomatosis - case report.. An Bras Dermatol. 2015;90 (3 Suppl 1):S101-3.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other" id="fn01">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Study performed at Hospital Regional da Asa Norte (HRAN) - Bras&#xED;lia (DF), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>NH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jorizzo</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bourke</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Savage</surname>
              <given-names>COS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Vasculitis, neutrophilic dermatoses and related
disorders</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Burns</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breathnach</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Griffiths</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Rook's textbook of dermatology</source>
          <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Wiley Blackwell</publisher-name>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>2417</fpage>
          <lpage>2419</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kea</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fiorentino</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Cutaneous vasculitis</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bolognia</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jorizzo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rapini</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Dermatology</source>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>360</fpage>
          <lpage>361</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jennette</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falk</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bacon</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Basu</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cid</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrario</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>2012 Revised International Chapel Hill Consensus Conference
Nomenclature of Vasculitides</article-title>
          <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23045170</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taborda</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taborda</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Granulomatose de Wegener</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brandt</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arnone</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valente</surname>
              <given-names>NY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sotto</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Criado</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Medium and large vessel vasculitis</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19377760</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>Emedicine.Medscape.com</collab>
          </person-group>
          <comment>[Internet]</comment>
          <source>Dermatologic manifestations of Wegener granulomatosis, Inc.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">updated 2013 Oct 23</date-in-citation>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited 2014 Jan 29</date-in-citation>
          <comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1085290">http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1085290</ext-link></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandes</surname>
              <given-names>NC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cardoso</surname>
              <given-names>ICL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Serpa</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rettore</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macieira</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Granulomatose de Wegener localizada: relato de caso</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandes</surname>
              <given-names>NC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castilho</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paes</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macieira</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Granulomatose de Wegener localizada com manifesta&#xE7;&#xE3;o ocular: relato de
caso</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>110</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dey</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arunabha</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sudipta</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Susmita</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mita</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A young lady presented with limited pulmonary Weneger's
Granulomatosis</article-title>
          <source>Lung India</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>168</fpage>
          <lpage>171</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21264088</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lutalo</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D'Cruz</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and classifcation of granulomatosis with polyangiitis (aka
Wegener's granulomatosis)</article-title>
          <source>J Autoimmun</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>48-49</volume>
          <fpage>94</fpage>
          <lpage>98</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24485158</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
