<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rimtsp</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Revista do Instituto de Medicina Tropical de S&#xE3;o Paulo</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0036-4665</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-9946</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Instituto de Medicina Tropical</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26603238</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4660460</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0036-46652015000500017</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>PROTECTIVE LEVELS OF VARICELLA-ZOSTER ANTIBODY DID NOT EFFECTIVELY PREVENT CHICKENPOX IN AN X-LINKED AGAMMAGLOBULINEMIA PATIENT</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>N&#xED;vel s&#xE9;rico adequado de anticorpo contra o v&#xED;rus da varicela-zoster n&#xE3;o foi suficiente para prevenir a infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o em crian&#xE7;a com agamaglobulinemia ligada ao X</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>NOBRE</surname>
            <given-names>Fernanda Aim&#xE9;e</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>GONZALEZ</surname>
            <given-names>Isabela Garrido da Silva</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de MORAES-PINTO</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Isabel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>COSTA-CARVALHO</surname>
            <given-names>Beatriz Tavares</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>(1)</label>Universidade Federal de S&#xE3;o Paulo, Departmento de Pediatria, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brasil. E-mails: <email>aimeenobre@yahoo.com.br; belinhagonzalez@hotmail.com; m.isabelmp@uol.com.br; beacarvalho@terra.com.br</email></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Correspondence to: </bold>Fernanda Aim&#xE9;e Nobre, Departmento de Pediatria, Universidade Federal de S&#xE3;o Paulo, Rua dos Otonis 725, 04025-002 S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brasil. Tel: +55 11 5084-0285; Fax: +55 11 56787090. E-mail: <email>aimeenobre@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
        <fn id="fn01" fn-type="conflict">
          <p>
<bold>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</bold>None declared.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>57</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>455</fpage>
      <lpage>457</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>SUMMARY</title>
        <p>We describe the case of an eight-year-old boy with X-linked agammaglobulinemia who developed mild varicella despite regular intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) therapy. He maintained protective antibody levels against varicella and the previous batches of IVIG that he received had adequate varicella-specific IgG levels. The case illustrates that IVIG may not prevent VZV infection.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <title>RESUMO</title>
        <p>Relatamos o caso de uma crian&#xE7;a com agamaglobulinemia ligada ao X, sexo masculino, oito anos de idade, que desenvolveu quadro de varicela leve, apesar do tratamento regular com imunoglobulina intravenosa (IVIG). O paciente mantinha n&#xED;veis adequados de imunoglobulina (IgG) contra varicela, assim como, os &#xFA;ltimos lotes de IVIG por ele recebido tamb&#xE9;m apresentavam n&#xED;veis adequados do anticorpo espec&#xED;fico. O caso ilustra que o tratamento regular com IVIG n&#xE3;o &#xE9; suficiente para prevenir a infec&#xE7;&#xE3;o pelo v&#xED;rus da varicela-zoster.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Chickenpox</kwd>
        <kwd>Immunoglobulin</kwd>
        <kwd>Intravenous</kwd>
        <kwd>Agammaglobulinemia</kwd>
        <kwd>Immunodeficiency disorders</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="1"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="18"/>
        <page-count count="3"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Patients who have immunodeficiency disorders rely on immunoglobulin prophylaxis to prevent common infectious diseases. Intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) products are prepared from pools of plasma collected from a large number of healthy donors and, therefore, contain antibodies against many infectious agents preventing a variety of bacterial and viral infections, such as varicella, in patients with impaired antibody production<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>.</p>
      <p>X-linked agammaglobulinemia (XLA) is a hereditary immunodeficiency, characterized by absence of mature B cells, resulting in very low levels of all immunoglobulin isotypes. The mainstay of therapy for these patients is immunoglobulin replacement<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>.</p>
      <p>Varicella is a disease caused by the primary infection with the varicella-zoster virus (VZV). Clinical manifestations of the disease depend on age, immune and vaccination status, and type of exposure <xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>. As a result of immunization, in some countries, chickenpox is no longer a common illness<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>. In Brazil, however, this disease is still endemic.</p>
      <p>The majority of primary VZV infections involve uncomplicated chickenpox. However, in newborns and inadequately protected immunosuppressed patients, exposure to VZV can lead to severe illness<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>.</p>
      <p>In this study, we report a case of chickenpox in a child with XLA who is being treated with regular intravenous immunoglobulin. Although the patient developed a mild disease, this case shows that regular intravenous immunoglobulin therapy did not effectively prevent chickenpox. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>An eight-year-old boy was diagnosed with XLA at the age of four, and presented 0.5% of B lymphocytes and serum IgG, IgA and IgM levels of 149 mg/dL, 1 mg/dL and 11 mg/dL, respectively. T lymphocyte numbers were normal. He started treatment with IVIG (600 mg/kg, every four weeks) with excellent compliance and good outcome, keeping IgG levels over 600 mg/dL.</p>
      <p>He was admitted to our clinic with a one-day history of skin lesions on trunk and abdomen that had started 19 days after his last IVIG infusion and was diagnosed with a mild varicella (less than 50 lesions at various stages - red papules, vesicles and broken vesicles leaving a crust). There was no history of fever or other symptoms. He was treated with oral acyclovir for five days and received an extra dose of standard IVIG. He recovered without any complication.</p>
      <p>Total serum IgG levels, varicella-zoster IgG levels, and avidity, assessed on day 1 of varicella, are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>. VZV antibodies and VZV IgG avidity were also assessed from serum samples collected five, ten, sixteen and twenty months before varicella (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>). Varicella-specific IgG levels from the batch of IVIG that was administered to the patient for the last three months before varicella were determined (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <p>
<table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title> a Varicella-specific IgG levels and its avidity, and total IgG levels obtained from the serum of the patient. b Varicella-specific IgG levels from the batch of IVIG that patient received over the last three months before VZV infection. Samples were tested for varicella-specific IgG levels by ELISA<sup>5,14</sup>
</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Varicella-specific IgG titer (IU/mL)</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Varicella-specific IgG avidity (%)</bold>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IgG (mg/dL)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 1 of varicella<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">718</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Five months before varicella<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ten months before varicella<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sixteen months before varicella<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Twenty months before varicella<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IVIG<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN01"><p>Protective IgG levels are considered when higher than 0.1 IU/mL<sup>8,9</sup>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>At the time of varicella infection, the patient's CD4+ and CD8+ T lymphocyte counts were 2388 cells/mm<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and 1293 cells/mm<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, respectively. Fifteen days after infection, both CD4+ and CD8+ T cells expressed CD25 upon <italic>in vitro </italic>stimulation with VZV specific antigens<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      <p>
<fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>
<bold>- </bold>CD25 expression on CD4+ and CD8+ T lymphocytes after incubation with VZV specific antigens. The final value of positive cells was obtained by subtracting the percentage of cells stimulated with cell supernatant of non-VZV-infected cells (negative control) from the percentage of cells from the culture in presence of the stimulus (VZV antigen). Adapted from VIANA<italic> et al</italic>., 2010<sup>18</sup>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0036-4665-rimtsp-57-05-00455-gf01"/></fig>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The aim of IVIG replacement therapy in hypogammaglobulinemic patients is to protect them from potentially preventable infections.</p>
      <p>However, it is well known that many factors may have an impact on the quality and quantity of antibodies in IVIG preparations, and there are differences in immunoglobulin content from brand to brand as well as from batch to batch<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>.</p>
      <p>Assessment of current IVIG preparations showed that they contain high levels of VZV specific IgG, despite the changing epidemiology of varicella due to vaccine introduction<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>. A study published in 2000 showed that patients receiving monthly IVIG at 400 mg/kg may be protected against varicella and probably do not require varicella-zoster immune globulin (VZIG) if the last dose of IVIG was given three weeks or less before exposure<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>. That is in agreement with the fact that antibodies for some virus and bacteria in IVIG preparations seems to have a half-life longer than 20 days<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>.</p>
      <p>In 2009, we had two other patients, one with common variable immunodeficiency (CVI) and another with XLA who also presented with mild varicella while on regular IVIG replacement therapy, similar to the patient in this case. In this current report, we showed that the previous-batches of IVIG that the patient received had adequate varicella-specific IgG levels and our patient maintained protective antibody levels against varicella during the previous months (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>). </p>
      <p>Specific antibody levels have been correlated with protection against several diseases. Antibody levels that correlate with protection are generally derived from studies with healthy population wherein observations have been shown that individuals with a certain level of antibody are always or nearly always protected from disease<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. However, these protective levels are usually determined after active immunization. There has been no study that has defined what level of varicella-specific antibody provides adequate protection in passive prophylaxis usage. What would be the protective antibody levels for a patient who does not produce antibodies?</p>
      <p>Humoral immunity is very important for VZV neutralization of the cell-free virus and cellular immunity is essential for limiting the extent of primary infection with VZV<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>. XLA patients have normal T cells function and these cells from our patient responded to VZV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1</xref>) which could explain his favorable evolution. However, certain groups of patients, such as those with impaired T cell-mediated immunity or with antibody deficiency but taking immunosuppressive drugs can develop severe complications<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and must be protected.</p>
      <p>Although the efficacy of IVIG in the prevention of several diseases is well established<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, we have to be aware that this therapy cannot be totally effective for some diseases in certain situations. Maybe IVIG is effective in modifying varicella infection but not in preventing the disease. </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn02" fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>
<bold>FUNDING</bold>None.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn03" fn-type="other">
        <p>
<bold>ETHICAL APPROVAL</bold>Not required.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Albin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunningham-Rundles</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An update on the use of immunoglobulin for the treatment of immunodeficiency disorders</article-title>
          <source>Immunotherapy</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>1113</fpage>
          <lpage>1126</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25428649</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>American Academy of Pediatrics</collab>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Varicella-zoster infections</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pickering</surname>
              <given-names>LK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baker</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kimberlin</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Long</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Red Book: 2012 report of the Committee on Infectious Diseases</source>
          <sup>th</sup>
          <publisher-loc>Elk Grove Village</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>American Academy of Pediatrics</publisher-name>
          <year>2012</year>
          <fpage>774</fpage>
          <lpage>789</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Audet</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Virata-Theimer</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beeler</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frazier</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mikolajczyk</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Measles-virus-neutralizing antibodies in intravenous immunoglobulins</article-title>
          <source>J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>194</volume>
          <fpage>781</fpage>
          <lpage>789</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16941344</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berger</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Principles of and advances in immunoglobulin replacement therapy for primary immunodeficiency</article-title>
          <source>Immunol Allergy Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>437</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424340</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Ory</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Echevarr&#xED;a</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kafatos</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anastassopoulou</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrews</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Backhouse</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>European seroepidemiology network 2: standardization of assays for seroepidemiology of varicella zoster virus</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Virol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          <lpage>118</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16616612</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gelfand</surname>
              <given-names>EW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differences between IGIV products:impact on clinical outcome</article-title>
          <source>Int Immunopharmacol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>592</fpage>
          <lpage>599</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16504921</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gershon</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gershon</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breuer</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levin</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oaklnder</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Griffiths</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Advances in the understanding of the pathogenesis and epidemiology of herpes zoster</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Virol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
          <fpage>S2</fpage>
          <lpage>S7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20510263</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keller</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stiehm</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Passive immunity in prevention and treatment of infectious diseases</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>602</fpage>
          <lpage>614</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11023960</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maarschalk-Ellerbroek</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoepelman</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ellerbroek</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immunoglobulin treatment in primary antibody deficiency</article-title>
          <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>396</fpage>
          <lpage>404</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21276714</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mankarious</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fischer</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pyun</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ochs</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oxelius</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The half-lives of IgG subclasses and specific antibodies in patients with primary immunodeficiency who are receiving intravenously administered immunoglobulin</article-title>
          <source>J Lab Clin Med</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>634</fpage>
          <lpage>640</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3183495</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maranich</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rajnik</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Varicella-specific immunoglobulin G titers in commercial intravenous immunoglobulin preparations</article-title>
          <source>Pediatrics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>124</volume>
          <fpage>e484</fpage>
          <lpage>e488</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19706589</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nobre</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
              <given-names>IGS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sim&#xE3;o</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moraes-Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa-Carvalho</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Antibody levels to tetanus, diphtheria, measles and varicella in patients with primary immunodeficiency undergoing intravenous immunoglobulin therapy: a prospective study</article-title>
          <source>BMC Immunol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>26</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24952415</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Notarangelo</surname>
              <given-names>LD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary immunodeficiencies</article-title>
          <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <issue>2 Suppl 2</issue>
          <fpage>S182</fpage>
          <lpage>S194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20042228</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ono</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lafer</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weckx</surname>
              <given-names>LY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Granato</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Moraes-Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A simple and cheaper in house varicella zoster virus antibody indirect ELISA</article-title>
          <source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>168</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15286822</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pichichero</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Booster vaccinations: can immunologic memory outpace disease pathogenesis?</article-title>
          <source>Pediatrics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>124</volume>
          <fpage>1633</fpage>
          <lpage>1641</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19933727</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Plebani</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soresina</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rondelli</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amato</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azzari</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cardinale</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical, immunological, and molecular analysis in a large cohort of patients with X-linked agammaglobulinemia: an Italian multicenter study</article-title>
          <source>Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <fpage>221</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12217331</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sartori</surname>
              <given-names>AMC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A review of the varicella vaccine in immunocompromised individuals</article-title>
          <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <lpage>270</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15325594</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Viana</surname>
              <given-names>PO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ono</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyamoto</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salomao</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa-Carvalho</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weckx</surname>
              <given-names>LY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Humoral and cellular immune responses to measles and tetanus: the importance of elapsed time since last exposure and the nature of the antigen</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Immunol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>574</fpage>
          <lpage>582</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20405177</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
