<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chin Med J (Engl)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chin. Med. J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Chinese Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0366-6999</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26831246</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4799588</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CMJ-129-374</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0366-6999.174495</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Correspondence</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Epidermoid Cyst Located in Facies Convexa Cerebri with Atypical Images</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zeng</surname>
            <given-names>Han-Hai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Jing-Sen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gu</surname>
            <given-names>Chi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Gao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Neurosurgery, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou, Zhejiang 310009, China</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Prof. Gao Chen, Department of Neurosurgery, The Second Affiliated Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, 88<sup>th</sup> Jiefang Road, Hangzhou, Zhejiang 310009, China E-Mail: <email xlink:href="d-chengao@zju.edu.cn">d-chengao@zju.edu.cn</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>05</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>129</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>374</fpage>
      <lpage>375</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; 2016 Chinese Medical Journal</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>To the Editor: Epidermoid cyst, was first described by an artist in a French medical school in 1807,[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] is a kind of congenital disease characterized by a stratified epithelial capsule and laminated keratin debris contents. It accounts for approximately 1% of all intracranial tumors and commonly locates in the cerebellopontine angle, parasellar region, and the fourth ventricle. Cerebrospinal fluid density on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) with nonenhancing is their typical images. However, epidermoid cysts occurring in an uncommon location with atypical MRI may cause the difficult diagnosis. While the radiological and pathological features of atypical epidermoid cysts have still been unclear, we reported an epidermoid cyst that was located in facies convexa cerebri and presented with atypical images.</p>
    <p>A 17-year-old girl was experienced for few minutes&#x2019; unconsciousness, three times in recent 3 months. Each time before faint, she could feel intermittent numbness in both lower limbs, developing from distal to proximal, following some moderate to intense exercise. No positive family history was obtained. Physical examination revealed that the only neurological positive sign was hypoesthesia in her left lower extremity. Lesion showed block mass in parietal lobe closed to the parietal bone with iso- or hypo-intensity on T1-weighted MRI, and hyperintensity on T2-weighted MRI. There was no empty shadow in the lesion due to the absence of vascular flow and the boundary remained clear. Middle structure shifting was not found. Simultaneously, remarkable enhancing was not discovered after Gd-diethylenetriamine pentaacetic acid administration [Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1a</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1c</xref>]. Lesion also showed the hyperintense signal on diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI). Meanwhile, magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) showed low creatine, choline, N-acetylaspartate (creatine and N-acetylaspartate were obvious), and inverted peak of lactate.</p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(a) Axial view showed lesion in parietal lobe with iso- or hypo-intensity on T1-weighted magnetic resonance imaging, (b) Hyperintensity on T2-weighted magnetic resonance imaging. (c) No remarkable contrast enhancement on T1-weighted magnetic resonance imaging after contrast-medium administration. (d) Remarkable keratosis and squamous epithelium with hemorrhage in tumor as arrows pointing in routine pathology (H and E staining, magnification, &#xD7;20).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="CMJ-129-374-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <p>The patient underwent surgery by right parietal approach to the parietal lobe. Tumor with pearly appearance, approximately 3 cm &#xD7; 3 cm &#xD7; 3 cm, was in facies convexa cerebri. Taking attention to protecting superior sagittal sinus and avoiding rupture of the cyst, the neurosurgeon totally resected the tumor. Yellow and cheese-like cyst contents emerged after splitting the tumor. Intraoperative frozen pathology declared keratosis and squamous epithelium with the consideration of epidermoid cyst.</p>
    <p>Slight numbness in the left leg was left over without any other neurological deficits after operation. During the hospitalization, unconsciousness was not relieved. The patient was discharged on the 7<sup>th</sup> day after surgery without any neurological deterioration. On the day of discharge, postoperative pathology also confirmed diagnosis of epidermoid cyst according to remarkable keratosis and squamous epithelium. Moreover, it showed hemorrhage in tumor as arrows pointing [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1d</xref>]. Followed up for 6 months, the symptom of the patient had improved without any unconsciousness.</p>
    <p>Intracranial epidermoid cysts are slow-growing benign tumors, arising from the inclusion of ectodermal tissue during the neural tube closure or formation of the secondary cerebral vesicles. So far, this is the first case of epidermoid cyst that was located in the facies convexa cerebri with atypical images. In preoperative MRI, iso- or hypo-intensity on T1-weighted and hyperintensity on T2-weighted without conspicuous enhance offered little hint of actual diagnosis. Nevertheless, with the help of histopathology, we speculated that atypical MRI was due to hemorrhage in the epidermoid cyst. In general, atypical MRI in intracranial epidermoid cysts may be attributed to factors of high proteinaceous content or abundance of polymorphonuclear leukocytes in the cyst, creamy texture or nonsolid of the cyst contents, and calcification and hemorrhage within the cyst.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Hemorrhage of epidermoid cyst can lead to atypical images in the form of variable signal intensity on MRI, according to the age of the bleed.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] In 2013, Ren <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] verified hemorrhage in 21 patients of 24 atypical intracranial epidermoid cysts. Accordingly, we confirmed that atypical MRI rests ascribable to spontaneous hemorrhage in the case.</p>
    <p>Moreover, we also conducted MRS and DWI before operation. DWI images showed markedly restricted diffusion with high signal intensity, the same as typical DWI findings. MRS images demonstrated low creatine, choline, N-acetylaspartate (creatine and N-acetylaspartate were obvious), and inverted peak of lactate, differing with widely accepted typical spectrum of an intracranial epidermoid cyst, which presents with a high lactate peak at 1.3 ppm with a virtual absence of the normal brain metabolites (N-acetylaspartate, creatine, and choline).[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] In 2013, Schoors <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] described that glycolysis had influence on activating and restraining pathological neovascularization. As MRS images prompted reduced glycolysis, we inferred the lesion had pathological neovascularization in the progress of this case.</p>
    <p>In intracranial epidermoid cyst, total removal of lesion is the definitive and ideal treatment. Simultaneously, to reach none chemical inflammation and better outcome, clearing free pieces of tumor and protecting important vessels and functional region become indispensable. As a result, a good outcome of our patient was affirmed in follow-up.</p>
    <p>In brief, epidermoid cyst presenting with atypical images located in facies convexa cerebri is very rare. Atypical magnetic resonance findings can be caused by hemorrhage within epidermoid cysts. Fluctuation of lactate in lesion gives hint of pathological neovascularization. To achieve good outcome, thorough preoperative magnetic resonance examination and intraoperative total resection become necessary in similar cases.</p>
    <sec disp-level="2" id="sec2-1">
      <title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
      <p>Nil.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec disp-level="2" id="sec2-2">
      <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
      <p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="edited-by">
        <p><bold>Edited by:</bold> Peng Lyu</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>R<sc>EFERENCES</sc></title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grant</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Austin</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidermoids: Clinical evaluation and surgical results</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1950</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>190</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <comment>doi: 10.3171/jns.1950.7.3.0190</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15415775</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Savardekar</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rane</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Radotra</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Atypical features of a midline pre-pontine epidermoid cyst</article-title>
          <source>Br J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>390</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <comment>doi: 10.3109/02688697.2012.741734</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23171146</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luo</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sui</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical, radiological, and pathological features of 24 atypical intracranial epidermoid cysts</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>611</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          <comment>doi: 10.3171/2011.10.JNS111462</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22175719</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahktar</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delgado</surname>
              <given-names>PN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lowe</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging and proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy of intracranial epidermoid tumors</article-title>
          <source>Crit Rev Comput Tomogr</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>389</fpage>
          <lpage>427</lpage>
          <comment>doi: 10.3109/10408370490903543</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15747577</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schoors</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Bock</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cantelmo</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Georgiadou</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghesqui&#xE8;re</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cauwenberghs</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Partial and transient reduction of glycolysis by PFKFB3 blockade reduces pathological angiogenesis</article-title>
          <source>Cell Metab</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <comment>doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2013.11.008</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24332967</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
