<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arq. Bras. Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cardiologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0066-782X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-4170</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25352512</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4206369</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/abc.20140141</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinicoradiological Session</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Case 6 / 2014 - Five-year Old Child with Scimitar Syndrome and Pulmonary
Sequestration of Right Lower Lobe</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Atik</surname>
            <given-names>Edmar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff01">Instituto do Cora&#xE7;&#xE3;o do Hospital das Cl&#xED;nicas da
Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de S&#xE3;o Paulo, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP -
Brazil</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing Address: Edmar Atik,</bold> Rua Dona Adma Jafet, 74, conj.73, Bela
Vista. Postal Code 01308-050, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP - Brazil. E-mail:
<email>eatik@cardiol.br</email>, <email>conatik@incor.usp.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>103</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>e45</fpage>
      <lpage>e47</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Scimitar syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart murmurs</kwd>
        <kwd>Bronchopulmonary sequestration</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><bold>Clinical data:</bold> Heart murmur was auscultated in routine examination in a
two-year old male child, who remained asymptomatic and without use of specific
medication.</p>
    <p><bold>Physical examination:</bold> Eupneic, acyanotic, normal pulse. Weight: 18.6 Kg,
Height: 109 cm, BP: 100/60 mmHg, HR: 90 bpm, saturation O<sub>2</sub>= 99%. Aorta was not
palpable in furcula.</p>
    <p>In precordium, <italic>ictus cordis</italic> was not palpable and there were no systolic
impulses. Heart sounds were normophonetic, but audible on the right sternal border, and the
second heart sound was constant and with mild systolic murmur, +/++ of intensity, harsh, in
the aortic area, irradiated to the right sternal border, larger than the left one. Liver
was palpable at 1 cm from the right costal margin.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Complementary tests</title>
      <p><bold>Electrocardiogram:</bold> Showed sinus rhythm and RS morphology in right
precordial and rs in V6 compatible with right ventricular overload. Ventricular
repolarization was normal. AP: +20&#xBA;, AQRS: +250&#xBA;, AT: +30&#xBA;.</p>
      <p><bold>Chest radiography:</bold> Shows hypoplasia of right lung with increased cardiac
area positioned to the right and increased pulmonary vascular markings. There were signs
of vascular imaging on the right side of the retrocardiac image with an outlining that
resembled a scimitar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Chest radiography shows the increased heart area to the right with increased
pulmonary vascular markings and venous vessel in the hypoplastic right lung,
simulating the shape of scimitar, in the retrocardiac image (arrows).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-103-04-0e45-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p><bold>Bi-Doppler echocardiogram:</bold> showed a clear enlargement of right cavities,
dilation of the pulmonary trunk and left pulmonary artery. 5 mm <italic>ostium
secundum</italic> interatrial communication with shunt from the left to the right.
Pulmonary veins on the left normally drain in normal left atrium and right veins on the
dilated inferior vena cava, next to the right atrium. Measurements: RV = 26, LV = 31, PT
= 21, RPA = 7, LPA = 13, annulus T = 22, annulus M = 16, annulus P = 15 annulus Ao = 15
mm, RVSP = 37 mmHg, LVEF = 66%, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Angiography in right upper pulmonary vein enhances the Scimitar shape of right
common pulmonary vein (arrows) towards lower vena cava in A, Left Pulmonary Vein
(LPV) in the Left Atrium (LA) in continuity of the Left Ventricle (LV) and Aorta
(Ao) in B and systemic-to-pulmonary vessel of descending aorta to right lower lobe
in C. Echocardiographic images show the increased right cavities in apical view of
4 chambers in D, the large increase of right ventricle in cross-sectional view in
E and dilated pulmonary trunk and left pulmonary artery in cross-sectional view in
F.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-103-04-0e45-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <p><bold>Cardiac catheterization</bold> confirmed the diagnosis of Scimitar syndrome with
abnormal draining of right pulmonary veins in inferior vena cava and interatrial
communication. It was verified with an injection of contrast agent in the descending
aorta the presence of systemic-to-pulmonary collateral vessel which was being directed
to the right lower lobe (pulmonary sequestration) and underwent embolization by placing
four spring coils (Figure 2). Pressures: RA = 11, RV = 40/12, PT = 36/8-17, PC = 16, LA
= 12, LV = 82/17, Ao = 90/60-70 mmHg.</p>
      <p><bold>Clinical diagnosis:</bold> Scimitar Syndrome in hypoplasia of the right lung and
interatrial communication, with shunt from left to right, and pulmonary sequestration of
the right lower lobe, in asymptomatic child.</p>
      <p><bold>Clinical reasoning:</bold> Clinical elements were compatible with the diagnosis of
interatrial communication and abnormal drainage of right pulmonary veins on the lower
vena cava in hypoplasia of the right lung, indicating Scimitar syndrome. Pulmonary
sequestration on the right side was established by the cardiac catheterization.</p>
      <p><bold>Differential diagnosis:</bold> Clinical findings and complementary tests,
characteristic of Scimitar syndrome, have not found differentials similar to other
abnormalities. These elements must be always highlighted and remembered in the presence
of hypoplasia of the right lung. Under these circumstances, the associated pulmonary
sequestration must also be remembered.</p>
      <p><bold>Conduct:</bold> Surgery for redirection of right pulmonary veins to the left
atrium and closure of interatrial communication is supported by the effects
repercussion, given the right heart cavities large increase, motivated by shunt from
left to right at the atrial level.</p>
      <p><bold>Comments:</bold> Scimitar syndrome published by Cooper<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> in 1836, and therefore designated by Neill, given the
morphologic analogy with the Turkish curved in 1960<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, is systematically associated with homonymous pulmonary hypoplasia
to the right and sometimes with pulmonary sequestration, congenital cardiopathies (more
commonly IAC) and other defects known as "venolobar syndrome". The clinical status is
similar to that of an interatrial communication, which is repercussion when pulmonary
hypoplasia is not significant. Otherwise, the more hypoplastic the lung is, the more
reduced the pulmonary flow is to the right and clinical manifestation is frustrated, to
a point of not having a benefit from surgical correction. In association with pulmonary
sequestration, it is always recommended the embolization of systemic-to-pulmonary vessel
in order to avoid complications of pulmonary hemorrhage and localized pulmonary
hypertension, in addition to pulmonary infection.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case of malformation of the thoracic viscera consisting of imperfect
development of the right lung and transposition of the heart</article-title>
          <source>London Med Gas</source>
          <year>1836</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>600</fpage>
          <lpage>601</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Neill</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferenca</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sabiston</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheldon</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The familial occurence of hypoplastic right lung with systemic
arterial supply and venous return, "Scimitar Syndrome"</article-title>
          <source>Bull Johns Hopkins Hosp</source>
          <year>1960</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14426379</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
