<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev. Inst. Med. Trop. Sao Paulo</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rimtsp</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Revista do Instituto de Medicina Tropical de S&#xE3;o Paulo</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0036-4665</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-9946</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Instituto de Medicina Tropical</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27074328</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4826087</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1678-9946201658034</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="other">00403</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>BRAIN ABSCESS DUE TO <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> OF
CRYPTOGENIC SOURCE IN AN HIV-1 INFECTED PATIENT IN USE OF ANTIRETROVIRAL
THERAPY</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de OLIVEIRA</surname>
            <given-names>Anna Paula Romero</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>PAPPALARDO</surname>
            <given-names>Mara Cristina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>DANTAS</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>LINS</surname>
            <given-names>Diogo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>VIDAL</surname>
            <given-names>Jos&#xE9; Ernesto</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Instituto de Infectologia Em&#xED;lio Ribas, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Universidade de S&#xE3;o Paulo, Faculdade de Medicina, Hospital das Cl&#xED;nicas,
LIM 49, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brazil</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Anna Romero de Oliveira. Instituto de Infectologia
"Emilio Ribas". Avenida Dr. Arnaldo 165, 01246-000 S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brasil. Fone: 55 11
38961200. E-mail:<email>annaminczuk@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>58</volume>
      <elocation-id>34</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The spectrum of neurological complications associated with human immunodeficiency
virus type 1 (HIV-1) infection is broad. The most frequent etiologies include primary
diseases (caused by HIV itself) or secondary diseases (opportunistic infections or
neoplasms). Despite these conditions, HIV-infected patients are susceptible to other
infections observed in patients without HIV infection. Here we report a rare case of
a brain abscess caused by <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in an HIV-infected
patient. After drainage of the abscess and treatment with oxacilin, the patient had a
favorable outcome. This case reinforces the importance of a timely neurosurgical
procedure that supported adequate management of an unusual cause of expansive brain
lesions in HIV-1 infected patients.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Brain abscess</kwd>
        <kwd>HIV</kwd>
        <kwd>Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Staphyloccocus aureus</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="1"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="16"/>
        <page-count count="1"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>The spectrum of neurological complications associated with human immunodeficiency virus
type 1 (HIV-1) infection is extremely heterogeneous and includes primary diseases
(caused by HIV itself) or secondary (opportunistic infections or neoplasms).
Opportunistic neurological manifestations can be classified according to the predominant
neurological syndrome involved in meningeal or encephalic syndrome. The encephalic
syndrome can be classified in focal or with diffuse involvement and focal brain lesions
may or may not show mass effect<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>. Cerebral
toxoplasmosis represents the most frequent cause of expansive brain lesions in
HIV-infected patients. In Brazil, focal forms of the central nervous system (CNS)
tuberculosis (particularly tuberculomas and rarely abscesses) constitute the main
differential diagnosis of cerebral toxoplasmosis. Primary CNS lymphomas are uncommon in
our setting<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>. Several other infections may
occasionally present with focal lesions in HIV-infected patients, including Nocardia
species, Varicella-zoster virus, Aspergillus species, <italic>Listeria
monocytogenes</italic>, <italic>Treponema pallidum</italic>, <italic>Histoplasma
capsulatum</italic>, and <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>. Some of these
microorganisms are more commonly causes of meningitis, but they may cause focal
processes<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. </p>
      <p>In addition to neurological complications associated with HIV-1 infection, these
patients can present etiologies that are not commonly associated with immunossupression.
In this report, we present the case of a HIV-1 infected patient with a brain abscess
caused by <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and discuss several challenging issues
about the management of expansive brain lesions in this kind of host. </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 76-year-old man was admitted to the emergency room after being found disoriented by
his family. He experienced episodes of fever (38-39.5 &#xB0;C) in previous days. There were
no other complaints including headache or seizures. His prior history included an HIV-1
infection diagnosed 10 years before, pulmonary tuberculosis, hypertension and
hyperthyroidism. His medications included zidovudine, lamivudine, efavirenz, tiamazol,
and captopril. The last laboratorial results showed a CD4 cell count of 668
cells/mm<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and HIV viral load &lt; 50
copies/mL. At admission, the physical examination showed a patient in good general
conditions, moderately dehydrated and pale, afebrile, and hemodynamically stable. The
neurological exam showed disorientation in time and space with a Glasgow Coma Scale of
14. The rest of the examination was normal. Laboratorial tests showed leukocytosis with
left shift and no other alterations. A brain computed tomography scan showed a single
low attenuation lesion with a uniform ring enhancement in the left temporal region
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1A</xref>). At this moment, empiric treatment
for toxoplasmosis with parenteral trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (5/ 25 mg/ kg twice a
day) was initiated. Seven days later, the patient's level of consciousness worsened,
presenting disorientation and confusion. At this moment, after a review of the prior
images, the hypothesis of bacterial or mycobacterial brain abscess was considered and
ceftriaxone (2 g twice a day) and metronidazole (500 mg three times a day) were started.
A lumbar puncture showed 1 cell/dL, 56 mg/dL of glucose, and 40 mg/dL of proteins. The
cerebrospinal fluid direct exam and bacteria, fungus and mycobacteria cultures were all
negative. The latex agglutination test for <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans,Streptococcus
pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>Neisseria meningitides</italic> and<italic>Haemophylus
influenzae</italic> type B, and the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for these
bacteria as well as for <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> were also all
negative. Blood cultures performed by automated microbiology growth and detection system
for aerobic, anaerobic and fungi resulted negative. The patient underwent trepanation,
and drainage of the lesion was performed. Purulent material was obtained and sent to
culture, which resulted in the growth of methicillin-sensitive <italic>S.
aureus</italic>. Anti-<italic>Toxoplasma</italic> treatment was discontinued and
antibiotic scheme was changed to oxacillin (2 g six times a day). The patient received
eight weeks of this medication, improved progressively, clinically and radiologically
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1B-C</xref>) and was discharged to home. The
patient underwent dental examination, with no evidence of dental infection. At
transesophageal echocardiography the valves and left atrium were free of thrombi and
vegetations, and there was no evidence of infection in thechest radiography and also in
the abdominal ultrasound. In the daily assessment, measures of capillary glycemia were
normal. Despite intensive efforts, no predisposing condition leading to the brain
abscess, including trauma or surgery, intravenous drug use, skin or soft tissue
infection, empyema, lung or intraabdominal abscess, bacterial endocarditis, dental
infection, sinusitis or mastoiditis, were identified.</p>
      <p>
<fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>- Evolution of contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) of an
HIV-infected patient with a brain abscess due to <italic>Staphylococcus
aureus</italic>. <bold>A</bold> , pre-trepanation CT showing a single
expansive brain lesion in the left temporal area. <bold>B</bold>, after one
week of trepanation, CT scan demonstrates a marked diminution in the size of
the lesion, residual enhancement and a residual degree of edema. <bold>C</bold>
, ten months after trepanation, CT scan reveals only post-surgical changes.
</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0036-4665-rimtsp-00034-gf01"/></fig>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Here, we report a rare case of a brain abscess due to <italic>S. aureus</italic> in an
HIV-infected patient.We found only two case reports of brain abscesses caused
by<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in HIV-infected patients. The first case
report has been criticized because the pathogen was isolated only from sputum cultures
and skin samples, without any proof of the invasive disease such as the isolation of the
bacterium from blood or from the brain abscess<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>.
The second case reported an HIV-infected patient with a CD4 count of 85 cells/mm<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, who presented an expansive lesion in the frontal
lobe that did not show any improvement with empiric therapy for cerebral toxoplasmosis.
Stereotactic biopsy of the lesion was performed and purulent material was found. Gram
staining and culture revealed a methicillin-sensitive, cotrimoxazole-resistant
<italic>S.aureus</italic>. Hematogenous dissemination from a cutaneous portal of
entry was strongly suspected, because of a recent history of furunculosis<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>.</p>
      <p>Current standard management for HIV-infected patients presenting with CNS mass lesions
is to initiate empiric anti-toxoplasmosis therapy because CNS toxoplasmosis is the most
frequent cause of HIV-associated intracranial lesions<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<italic>.</italic> The definitive diagnosis of cerebral toxoplasmosis requires the
presence of tachyzoites of the parasite in cerebral tissue<xref rid="B06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, but the availability and risks related to the brain biopsy
precludes its routine use. Thus, if no clinical and radiological response is evident
after 10 to 14 days of empiric therapy, other causes (infectious or non-infectious)
should be considered<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>. It should be noted that if
at admission or during the empirical treatment there is a high index of suspicion for an
alternative diagnosis to cerebral toxoplasmosis, an early brain biopsy should be
considered<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>. </p>
      <p>In addition, it is important to consider other diagnoses than cerebral toxoplasmosis in
HIV-infected patients under immunological and virological control, including etiologies
of patients without HIV infection, for example, bacterial brain abscesses or tumors that
are not related to immunossupression. </p>
      <p>In ageneral population, bacterial brain abscesses can develop from three sources: first,
because of the spread of infection from a pericranial contiguous focus (such as the
sinuses, middle ear, or dental infection) in 25-50% of cases; second: from a distant
focus of infection (such as a lung abscess or empyema, endocarditis, skin, or the
intra-abdominal cavity), resulting in hematogenous spread in 15-30% of cases; and third,
from a direct inoculation such as a head trauma or neurosurgery in 8-19% of cases<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>. The origin of brain abscess formation remains
unknown (cryptogenic brain abscess) in 20-30% of cases<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>. In a general population, a wide range of pathogens can cause brain
abscesses and <italic>Streptococci</italic> are the most common pathogens, comprising
about 70% of isolates<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
<italic>.</italic>
</p>
      <p>
<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> accounts for 10% 20% of isolates of brain
abscesses in a general population, usually reported in patients with cranial trauma or
endocarditis, and it is often isolated in culture. Some cases caused by
community-associated methicillin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> have been
reported. Population-based studies have identified male gender and very young and
elderly individuals as being at increased risk for <italic>S. aureus</italic>infections.
Moreover, two studies showed that the most important risk factor is dialysis, either
peritoneal (relative risk [RR], 150 to 204) or hemodialysis (RR, 257 to 291). Other
conditions that increase the risk of invasive <italic>S. aureus</italic> infections
include diabetes (RR, 7), cancer (RR, 7.1 to 12.9), rheumatoid arthritis (RR, 2.2 to
9.2), HIV infection (RR, 23.7), intravenous drug use (RR, 10.1), or alcohol abuse (RR,
8.2)<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>. However, one of the most important factors
that is independently associated to brain abscess is chronic <italic>S. aureus</italic>
nasal carriage<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>. </p>
      <p>The status of HIV infection increases the chances of having invasive staphylococcal
disease<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, but it is difficult to establish a
cause-effect relationship in the present case. </p>
      <p>The purpose of this article is to highlight the need of timely diagnosis of expansive
brain lesions in HIV-infected patients, including brain abscess, because it is a
potentially fatal disease. Several studies have evaluated the findings of brain biopsies
in the context of HIV infection and bacterial brain abscess contributes to a small
percentage of the cases<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, reinforcing the rarity of this medical
condition in this setting.These studies highlight the utility of brain biopsy to uncover
erroneous diagnostic hypotheses<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>. </p>
      <p>In conclusion, although rare, <italic>S. aureus</italic> should be included in the
differential diagnosis of expansive brain lesions in HIV-infected patients, despite the
absence of classical risk factors to invasive disease caused by this bacterium. Timely
neurosurgical procedure, adequate identification and susceptibility pattern of the
microorganism, and an appropriate antibiotic, supported the favorable outcome in the
present case.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vidal</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Penalva de Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Altera&#xE7;&#xF5;es neurol&#xF3;gicas: parte I</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lindoso</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>da Eira</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casseb</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mello e Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Infectologia ambulatorial: diagn&#xF3;stico e tratamento</source>
          <publisher-loc>S&#xE3;o Paulo</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Sarvier</publisher-name>
          <year>2008</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vidal</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dauar</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Utility of brain biopsy in patients with acquired immunodeficiency
syndrome before and after introduction of highly active antiretroviral
therapy</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurgery</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <elocation-id>34</elocation-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Skiest</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Focal neurological disease in patients with acquired immunode: ciency
syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>115</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731953</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>NP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gazzard</surname>
              <given-names>BG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cerebral abscesses in a patient with AIDS caused by
methicillin-resistant Sthaphylococcus aureus (MRSA)</article-title>
          <source>Int J STD AIDS</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>460</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9228595</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Denoeud</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pacanowski</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Welker</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moulignier</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Girard</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Staphylococcus aureus brain abscess in an HIV-infected patient exposed
to enfuvirtide</article-title>
          <source>J Int Assoc Physicians AIDS Care (Chic)</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>219</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18701426</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira-Chiocolla</surname>
              <given-names>VL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vidal</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Toxoplasma gondii infection and cerebral toxoplasmosis in HIV-infected
patients</article-title>
          <source>Future Microbiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>1363</fpage>
          <lpage>1379</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995194</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Skolasky</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dal Pan</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olivi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenz</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abrams</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McArthur</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>HIV-associated primary CNS lymorbidity and utility of brain
biopsy</article-title>
          <source>J Neurol Sci</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>163</volume>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10223407</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mathisen</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brain abscess</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>763</fpage>
          <lpage>779</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9356788</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Derber</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Troy</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Head and neck emergencies: bacterial meningitis, encephalitis, brain
abscess, upper airway obstruction, and jugular septic
thrombophlebitis</article-title>
          <source>Med Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <fpage>1107</fpage>
          <lpage>1126</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23102480</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobsson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dashti</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wahlberg</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The epidemiology of and risk factors for invasive Staphylococcus
aureus infections in western Sweden</article-title>
          <source>Scand J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17366006</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Laupland</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Church</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mucenski</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutherland</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davies</surname>
              <given-names>HD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Population-based study of the epidemiology of and the risk factors for
invasive Staphylococcus aureus infections</article-title>
          <source>J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>187</volume>
          <fpage>1452</fpage>
          <lpage>1459</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12717627</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van Rijen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonten</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wenzel</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kluytmans</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mupirocin ointment for preventing Staphylococcus aureus infections in
nasal carriers</article-title>
          <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>CD006216</fpage>
          <lpage>CD006216</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18843708</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Laupland</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ross</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gregson</surname>
              <given-names>DB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Staphylococcus aureus bloodstream infections: risk factors, outcomes,
and the influence of methicillin resistance in Calgary, Canada,
2000-2006</article-title>
          <source>J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>198</volume>
          <fpage>336</fpage>
          <lpage>343</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18522502</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gildenberg</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gathe</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stereotactic biopsy of cerebral lesions in AIDS</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>491</fpage>
          <lpage>499</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10722433</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gjerris</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pedersen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>FK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagn</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brain biopsy in AIDS. Diagnostic value and consequence</article-title>
          <source>Acta Neurochir (Wien)</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>99</fpage>
          <lpage>102</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7942191</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Micheletti</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tostes</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meneses</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva-Vergara</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neuropathology of AIDS: an autopsy review of 284 cases from Brazil
comparing the findings pre- and post-HAART (Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy)
and pre- and postmortem correlation</article-title>
          <source>AIDS Res Treat</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>2012</volume>
          <fpage>186850</fpage>
          <lpage>186850</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22461978</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
