<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Med. Sci</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26256491</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4751124</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">15-0116</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.15-0116</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Surgery</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Note</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A canine case with cystic meningioma showing miraculous reduction of the
cystic lesion</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>WADA</surname>
            <given-names>Masae</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>HASEGAWA</surname>
            <given-names>Daisuke</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>HAMAMOTO</surname>
            <given-names>Yuji</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>ASAI</surname>
            <given-names>Atsushi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SHOUJI</surname>
            <given-names>Akane</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>CHAMBERS</surname>
            <given-names>James</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>UCHIDA</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuyuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>FUJITA</surname>
            <given-names>Michio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Department of Clinical Veterinary Medicine, Nippon
Veterinary and Life Science University, Tokyo 180&#x2013;8601, Japan</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>ORM Co., Ltd., Saitama 330&#x2013;0803, Japan</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3)</label>Animal Medical Plaza Sekiya, Niigata 951&#x2013;8165, Japan</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><label>4)</label>Department of Veterinary Pathology, The University of Tokyo,
Tokyo 113&#x2013;8657, Japan</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Hasegawa, D., Department of Clinical
Veterinary Medicine, Nippon Veterinary and Life Science University, 1&#x2013;7&#x2013;1 Kyounancho,
Musashino, Tokyo 180&#x2013;8602, Japan. e-mail: <email xlink:href="disk-hsgw@nvlu.ac.jp">disk-hsgw@nvlu.ac.jp</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>78</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>101</fpage>
      <lpage>104</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2016 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>A 12-year-old spayed female Labrador retriever was presented with forebrain
signs. Brain MRI revealed a huge cystic lesion with the thickened falx in the frontal
region. The brain parenchyma surrounding the lesion showed significant signs of a mass
effect and also increased intracranial pressure. However, the dog suddenly became lucid
after about two weeks, and an MRI scan one month after the initial study revealed a
dramatically shrunken cystic lesion. The dog survived for over a year until it was
euthanized for other reasons, and the brain lesion was diagnosed as a cystic meningioma
histologically. To the authors&#x2019; knowledge, this is the first report that described the
reduction of the cystic lesion of a cystic meningioma in dogs.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>dog</kwd>
        <kwd>cystic meningioma</kwd>
        <kwd>MRI</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Meningiomas are the most common primary brain tumor in dogs: the incidence of canine cystic
meningioma has been reported to be 12.5&#x2013;32% [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. It is not uncommon for a cystic lesion to be larger
than a tumor [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Sometimes, increased intracranial pressure (ICP) is caused by cyst expansion
rather than tumoral growth. We report and discuss a rare case of cystic meningioma that showed
a significant reduction of the cystic component, resulting in long-term survival. To the
authors&#x2019; knowledge, no reports have described the reduction of the cystic lesion associated
with a meningioma either in veterinary medicine or in human medicine.</p>
    <p>A 12-year-old spayed female Labrador retriever was presented to a private clinic with cluster
seizures, circling towards the left and decreased mental status (day 0). The owner reported
that the dog had one seizure 2 months previously. CBC, serum chemistry, urine analysis,
thoracic and abdominal radiographs, heart and abdominal ultrasound, and ECG were within normal
range. A neurological examination found depression, left circling and decreased postural
reactions of the right side, which suggested left forebrain dysfunction.</p>
    <p>To confirm the lesion, an initial MRI scan was performed using a 0.4-tesla (T) system (day
10). The MRI revealed a large cystic lesion showing hyperintensity on T2-weighted images
(T2W), and hypointensities on T1-weighted (T1W) and fluid-attenuated inversion recovery
(FLAIR) images extending from the left parafalx olfactory bulb to the frontal region that
somewhat extended to the right (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>The first MRI. (A) Sagittal T2W image showing a large, hyperintense structure occupying
the frontal lobe. (B) Transverse post-contrast T1W image at the level of the falx
cerebri. The contrast-enhanced and slightly thickened falx was suggestive of a
meningioma. (C) Dorsal post-contrast T1W image revealing an enhanced lesion adhering to
the falx cerebri. There was no enhancement of the cystic wall. Uncleared sulci
(narrowing subarachnoid space) of the cerebrum indicated increased ICP.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-78-101-g001"/></fig>). The left side of the cerebral falx was included within the cystic lesion, and was
slightly thickened and hyperintense on T2W, isointense on T1W and clearly enhanced on
Gadolinium-enhanced T1W (Gd-T1W). The outer wall of the cystic lesion was not enhanced. The
maximum diameter of the cyst, including the parenchymal lesion of the falx, was 2.0 cm &#xD7; 2.2
cm &#xD7; 4.2 cm. The cerebral parenchyma surrounding the lesion showed a significant mass effect
and other increased ICP findings consisting of cerebral sulci effacement, displacement of the
lamina quadrigemina, deformation of the interthalamic adhesion, rostral cerebellar contour
flatting, third ventricle compression and suprapineal recess compression; however,
perilesional edema and brain herniation were not observed [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These MR findings reminded a cystic meningioma as a top of the differential
diagnoses that included subarachnoid cyst, brain abscess and other tumors with cystic lesion.
Based on the clinical findings and brain MRI, there was concern about the risk of brain
herniation, so emergency surgical decompression was recommended. Although the owner wanted the
surgery to be done as soon as possible, there was a 1-month wait until it could be performed
at the university teaching hospital. During this waiting period, the dog was medically managed
with phenobarbital (Phenobal; Daiichi-Sankyo, Tokyo, Japan) (1.25 mg/kg, BID), zonisamide
(Excegran; Dainippon-Sumitomo, Osaka, Japan) (4.1 mg/kg, BID), isosorbide (Isobide; Kowa,
Tokyo, Japan) (0.5 m<italic>l</italic>/kg, BID) and prednisolone (Predonine; Shionogi, Osaka,
Japan) (0.3 mg/kg, SID).</p>
    <p>On the day of the operation (day 38), the surgeon expected that the dog might be unable to
walk or stand normally and would have a decreased level of consciousness due to increased ICP,
but the dog walked herself into the consultation room and was alert. On neurological
examination, the dog showed a decreased menace response in the right eye and a delayed
proprioceptive positioning in the right pelvic limbs, but everything else was unremarkable.
The owner had said that the dog had suddenly become lucid about two weeks previously.</p>
    <p>On the same day, a second MRI scan was performed using a 3.0-T system for preoperative
evaluation. Although there was no change in the contrast-enhancing lesion of the falx, the
cystic lesion was 1.2 cm &#xD7; 2.1 cm &#xD7; 3.5 cm, indicating a significant reduction in volume.
There was no signal change on the T2W and T1W images; however, the signal intensity of the
cyst was increased on FLAIR images (i.e., unsuppressed fluid signal), suggesting inflammation
or hemorrhage. In addition, the increased ICP findings observed on the first MRI had
disappeared. Because of the improvements in clinical signs and in MRI findings, the surgery
was cancelled, and the dog was continued on medical therapy. Hydroxyurea (Hydrea;
Bristol-Myers, Tokyo, Japan) (10 mg/kg, SID) was added to the current regimen of medications
stated above (from day 40).</p>
    <p>Subsequently, orofacial focal seizures and generalized seizures were observed several times,
but there was no progression of neurological abnormalities. A follow-up (third) MRI scan was
performed 45 days after hydroxyurea was started (day 85) using a 0.4-T system. The cyst
continued to decrease, reaching a final diameter of 1.0 cm &#xD7; 1.9 cm &#xD7; 2.2 cm. In addition, the
signal intensity of the cyst on FLAIR images had recovered to hypointensity.</p>
    <p>The dog lived for more than a year without any obvious neurological progression, but she
developed perianal adenocarcinoma. Because it became difficult for the dog to defecate, it was
euthanized on day 544. Just before the dog was euthanized, a final MRI scan (0.4-T) was
performed with the owner&#x2019;s consent. As compared with the third scan, there was no significant
change in the size of the tumor or that of the cyst (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig.
2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Comparison with the time course of the MRI findings. Transverse post-contrast T1W
images at the level of the falx cerebri: (A) first (day 10); (B) second (day 38); (C)
third (day 85); and (D) fourth (day 544). Comparing images A and B, there was a
significant reduction in the cystic lesion and spreading into the subarachnoid spaces.
There was no obvious change between images C and D.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-78-101-g002"/></fig>). The autopsy was performed after euthanasia.</p>
    <p>Histological examination of the brain revealed that the cystic lesion was connected to the
falx and consisted of proliferating tumor cells in the left frontal region. The thickened falx
and cystic wall, which comprised proliferating multilayered (stratified) meningeal epithelial
cells, led to the diagnosis of meningothelial meningioma, cystic type. Because the wall of an
arachnoid cyst is generally composed of monolayer epithelium, we judged that this multilayered
wall was a neoplastic cyst. The cystic lesions were supposed to dehisce to the midline region
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Histopathological appearance of the cystic lesion. (A) The over view of the frontal
cortex with cystic lesion (Cy, Arrow), H&amp;E, &#xD7; 10. (B) The cystic tumor was not
directly connected with the lateral ventricle (LV), H&amp;E, &#xD7; 200. (C) Tumor cells of
the cystic lesions were mostly polygonal-shaped with wide, clear to eosinophilic
cytoplasm, H&amp;E, &#xD7; 400. Their nuclei were round to oval-shaped with indistinct
nucleoli.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jvms-78-101-g003"/></fig>).</p>
    <p>Meningiomas account for 33&#x2013;49% of primary brain tumors in dog [<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In addition, Labrador retrievers are predisposed to developing brain
tumors [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Although the cyst, which seemed to be the cause
of the clinical signs (increased ICP), was significantly larger than the parenchymal
component, a cystic meningioma was clinically diagnosed based on the MRI findings. Nauta
<italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] classified cystic
formation associated with meningiomas into four types: those located centrally within the
tumor, such that the cyst surrounded by macroscopic tumor throughout (type I); those located
peripherally within the tumor, but still wholly within the margins of the tumor, such that
there is a microscopically visible attenuated rim of tumor cells along the peripheral margins
of the cyst (type II); those within the adjacent brain, such that they actually lie within the
adjacent brain rather than within the tumor itself (type III); and those at the interface of
the tumor and brain, as a loculation of CSF in the subarachnoid space, such that they do not
appear within either the tumor or the brain itself (type IV). Because the cyst wall was not
enhanced by gadolinium in MR imaging, the tumor in this case was thought to be classified as
type III or IV [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, the histopathological diagnosis was type II.</p>
    <p>On the first MRI, the brain parenchyma surrounding the lesion showed a mass effect, and there
were findings of increased ICP. On the second MRI, significant reduction of the cystic lesion
had occurred even though the tumoral parenchyma (i.e., enhanced falx) was not changed
obviously, and increased ICP findings were no longer observed. Furthermore, the dog had
improved clinically. Although it is undeniable that clinical improvement was caused by
medication (i.e., isosorbide and prednisolone), because the owner reported that the symptoms
improved suddenly, it is unlikely that the medications alleviated them. It is likely that the
cyst had ruptured miraculously due to for some reason.</p>
    <p>Typically, excessive expansion of cystic lesions in the forebrain may increase ICP and might
lead to transtentorial herniation. In the present case, however, we hypothesized that the cyst
wall was too thin and vulnerable to such a high ICP and ruptured before a transtentorial
herniation occurred. The unsuppressed intensity of the intracystic fluid on FLAIR in the
second MRI, which may be indicative of minor inflammatory/hemorrhage due to rupture, supports
this hypothesis. Because the intracystic fluid probably leaked into the subarachnoid space
from the hiatus, the dog could survive. In addition, the present case had a larger cystic
volume than mass volume, causing a brain herniation as reported previously [<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Therefore, if the cystic lesion of the present case
was parenchymatous, it would undoubtedly have caused a transtentorial herniation. On the other
hand, many reports have described the spontaneous reduction of an arachnoid cyst in human
medicine [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. These reports suggest that physiologic transient
elevation of ICP (breath hold, cough or sports activities, etc.), minor head trauma,
meningitis and hemorrhage may cause spontaneous rupture of the arachnoid cyst [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Therefore, although the present case was classified as
cystic meningioma type II, the possibility that similar events had occurred cannot be ruled
out. However, because there is no history of trauma or other findings, it is most likely that
the cyst had ruptured miraculously due to extremely high ICP.</p>
    <p>Because the clinical behavior of meningiomas progresses slowly and the survival duration
tends to be longer as compared with other tumors [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], cyst reduction may bring about longer survival
like as observed in the present case. However, the circumstances of this case are thought to
be extremely rare, and the authors think that surgical resection or decompression is still the
first choice for the treatment of cystic meningiomas.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bagley</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornegay</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thrall</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year>. <article-title>Cystic meningiomas in 2
dogs</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet. Intern.
Med.</italic></source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>72</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>75</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.1996.tb02030.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8683483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bagley</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year>. <article-title>Clinical signs associated with brain
tumors in dogs: 97 cases (1992&#x2013;1997)</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Am. Vet. Med.
Assoc.</italic></source><volume>215</volume>: <fpage>818</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>819</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10496135</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Bittermann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henke</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorgas</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging signs of
presumed elevated intracranial pressure in dogs</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet.
J.</italic></source><volume>201</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>108</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2014.04.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24888678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Brearley</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year>. <article-title>Hypofractionated radiation therapy of
brain masses in dogs: a retrospective analysis of survival of 83 cases
(1991&#x2013;1996)</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet. Intern.
Med.</italic></source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>412</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10499721</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging and
diffusion-weighted images of cystic meningioma: correlating with
histopathology</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin.
Imaging</italic></source><volume>28</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0899-7071(03)00032-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14996441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Cokluk</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Senel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Celik</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erg&#xFC;r</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>. <article-title>Spontaneous disappearance of two
asymptomatic arachnoid cysts in two different locations</article-title>.
<source><italic>Minim. Invasive Neurosurg.</italic></source><volume>46</volume>:
<fpage>110</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>112</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2003-39337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12761683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Fortuna</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrante</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acqui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guglielmi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastronardi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year>. <article-title>Cystic meningiomas</article-title>.
<source><italic>Acta Neurochir. (Wien)</italic></source><volume>90</volume>:
<fpage>23</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01541262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3344623</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Heidner</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornegay</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodge</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thrall</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year>. <article-title>Analysis of survival in a retrospective
study of 86 dogs with brain tumors</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet. Intern.
Med.</italic></source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>226</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.1991.tb00952.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1941756</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanayama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year>. <article-title>Cystic meningioma in a
dog</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Small Anim.
Pract.</italic></source><volume>43</volume>: <fpage>272</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>274</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2002.tb00073.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12074294</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year>. <article-title>Cystic meninigioma</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Clin. Neurosci.</italic></source><volume>14</volume>:
<fpage>856</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>859</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocn.2006.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17596946</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year>. <article-title>Spontaneous disappearance of a
suprasellar arachnoid cyst: case report and review of the literature</article-title>.
<source><italic>Childs Nerv. Syst.</italic></source><volume>23</volume>:
<fpage>99</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>104</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00381-006-0161-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16944178</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandara</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skerritt</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>. <article-title>Canine and feline intracranial
meningiomas: an updated review</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet.
J.</italic></source><volume>192</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>165</lpage>. doi:
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2011.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22104505</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Nauta</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horsey</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilbao</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonsalves</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1979</year>. <article-title>Xanthochromic cysts associated with
meningioma</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Neurol. Neurosurg.
Psychiatry</italic></source><volume>42</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>535</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.42.6.529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">469560</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Odake</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year>. <article-title>Cystic meningioma: report of three
patients</article-title>.
<source><italic>Neurosurgery</italic></source><volume>30</volume>:
<fpage>935</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>940</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/00006123-199206000-00023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1614600</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tropea</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuffrida</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuffr&#xE8;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year>. <article-title>Cystic meningiomas. Report of seven
cases</article-title>. <source><italic>J.
Neurosurg.</italic></source><volume>64</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>38</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/jns.1986.64.1.0035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3941348</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Rengachary</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batnitzky</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kepes</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morantz</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x2019;Boynick</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1979</year>. <article-title>Cystic lesions associated with
intracranial meningiomas</article-title>.
<source><italic>Neurosurgery</italic></source><volume>4</volume>:
<fpage>107</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>114</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1227/00006123-197902000-00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">440541</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shofer</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Winkle</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Massicotte</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>Canine intracranial primary neoplasia:
173 cases (1986&#x2013;2003)</article-title>. <source><italic>J. Vet. Intern.
Med.</italic></source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>675</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16734106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Sturges</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koblik</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kass</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kortz</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernau</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knipe</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecouteur</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging and
histological classification of intracranial meningiomas in 112 dogs</article-title>.
<source><italic>J. Vet. Intern. Med.</italic></source><volume>22</volume>:
<fpage>586</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>595</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2008.00042.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18466258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Walmsley</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrtage</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>The relationship between clinical signs
and brain herniation associated with rostrotentorial mass lesions in the
dog</article-title>. <source><italic>Vet. J.</italic></source><volume>172</volume>:
<fpage>258</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>264</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2005.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16014332</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>. <article-title>MRI finding of intracranial cystic
meningiomas</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin
Radiol.</italic></source><volume>64</volume>: <fpage>792</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>800</lpage>.
doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crad.2009.04.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19589418</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
