<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26496258</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4620829</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000001577</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">01577</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>5700</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report (CARE Compliant)</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Severe Hypoglycemia Caused by Recurrent Sarcomatoid Carcinoma in the Pelvic Cavity</article-title>
        <subtitle>A Case Report</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fang</surname>
            <given-names>Chao</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
            <given-names>Chuan Wen</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Yong Yang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Cun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Lie</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Yuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mo</surname>
            <given-names>Xian Ming</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Zong Guang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD, FACS</degrees>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Sierzega.</surname>
            <given-names>Marek</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>From the Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, P.R. China (CF, CWF, YYY, CW, LY, ZGZ) and Institute of Digestive Surgery, State Key Laboratory of Biotherapy, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, P.R. China (CF, CWF, YL, ZGZ); and Laboratory of Stem Cell Biology, State Key Laboratory of Biotherapy, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, P.R. China (XMM).</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Correspondence: Zong Guang Zhou, No. 37, Guoxue Lane, Chengdu 610041, P.R. China (e-mail: <email>zhou767@163.com</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>94</volume>
      <issue>42</issue>
      <elocation-id>e1577</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-94-e1577.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>Nonislet cell tumor hypoglycemia (NICTH) is a paraneoplastic syndrome characterized by persistent, severe hypoglycemia in different tumor types of mesochymal or epithelial origin; however, NICTH is infrequently induced by sarcomatoid carcinoma (SC). Despite some sarcomatoid and epithelioid characteristics in few cases of malignancies from epithelium, NICTH induced by recurrent SC in pelvic cavity in this report is extremely rare.</p>
        <p>We report a case in which NICTH caused by recurrence and pulmonary metastases from SC in the pelvic cavity, and the computed tomography scan revealed multiple pelvic masses and multiple large masses in the pulmonary fields. During the treatment of intestinal obstruction, the patient presented paroxysmal loss of consciousness and sweating. Her glucose even reached 1.22&#x200A;mmol/L while the serum glycosylated hemoglobin was normal and previous history of diabetes or use of oral hypoglycemic agents and insulin denied.</p>
        <p>The laboratory examination showed that the low level of insulin, C-peptide, and growth hormone levels in the course of hypoglycemic episodes suggesting to the diagnosis of hypoglycemia induced by nonislet cell tumor, and the decreased levels of insulin-like growth factor (IGF)-I and IGFBP3 and the high expression of big IGF-II in the serum further confirmed the diagnosis of NICTH. Because of the widely pelvic recurrence and pulmonary metastases were unresected, the patient was discharged from the hospital after 2 weeks treatment with dexamethasone and glucose and unfortunately died 1 week later.</p>
        <p>NICTH caused by SC in the pelvic cavity is extremely rare case in clinical. The aim of this report was to present the importance to examine big IGF-II expression in patient's serum in order to reach the diagnosis of NICTH in cases of intractable cancer-associated hypoglycemia.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Nonislet cell tumor hypoglycemia (NICTH) is a paraneoplastic syndrome characterized by recurrent fasting hypoglycemia, which is thought to be caused by the excessive secretion of incompletely processed precursors of insulin-like growth factor (IGF)-II (high molecular weight IGF-II or big IGF-II) by the tumor into the circulation.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> IGF-II-induced NICTH typically occurs in patients with large slow-growing neoplasm. In particular, it has been rarely reported in tumors of epithelial origin, while mesochymal tumors account for more than 50% of such cases.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Sarcomatoid carcinoma (SC) is an uncommon malignant neoplasm of primitive epithelial cell origin that displays both malignant epithelial and mesochymal characteristics.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Clinically, they are usually aggressive tumors with early occurrence of distant metastasis. To our knowledge, SCs rarely occur in the pelvic cavity, with only 1 case reported in literature.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Here, we report an extremely rare case in which NICTH caused by recurrence and pulmonary metastases from SC in the pelvic cavity. We also confirmed that the big IGF-II was associated with the hypoglycemia.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 69-year-old woman received resection of pelvic mass at West China Hospital, Sichuan University in August 2013, following admission with difficult defecation and numbness of lower limb for 3 months. MRI scan at the time was showed in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A left and right. Postoperative histological examination revealed SC/undifferentiated carcinoma without invasion of rectum. The diagnosis was confirmed by immunohistochemical results (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B).</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Diagnosis of PCSC. A: Abdominal MRI scan revealed a large (30&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;25&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;15&#x200A;cm) heterogeneous pelvic mass and seemed to be widely adherent to rectum, posterior vaginal wall, and partial pelvic wall. B: Immunohistochemical results identified the diagnosis of sarcomatoid carcinoma/undifferentiated carcinoma (positive for PCK, weakly positive for EMA and CK7 and negative for CD125, WT1, D2-40, HMB-45, Caldesmon, Desmin, S100, DOG1, and CD117). MRI = magnetic resonance imaging; PCSC = SC in the pelvic cavity.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e1577-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Postoperatively, the patient first received 2 cycles of TP regimen chemotherapy (cisplatin&#x200A;+&#x200A;paclitaxel); however, imaging assessment gave hints of disease progression with pelvic recurrence and pulmonary metastases. Thus, 2 cycles of second line MAID regimen (mesna&#x200A;+&#x200A;ifosfamidum&#x200A;+&#x200A;epirubicin hydrochloride for injection&#x200A;+&#x200A;dacarbazine) was given which also resulted in disease progression. At this point, the patient and family refused further chemotherapy and discharged.</p>
      <p>Twelve months later, the patient was admitted into the emergency because of intestinal obstruction. Computed tomography (CT) scan revealed multiple pelvic masses and multiple large masses in the pulmonary fields (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A left and right). This was treated by gastrointestinal decompression and parenteral nutrition. During this course, the patient presented paroxysmal loss of consciousness and sweating. Her glucose even reached 1.22&#x200A;mmol/L while the serum glycosylated hemoglobin was normal (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) and previous history of diabetes or use of oral hypoglycemic agents and insulin denied. Successive synchronous blood measurements during hypoglycemic episodes showed low insulin, C-peptide, growth hormone (GH), IGF-I, and IGF-binding protein-3 (IGFBP3) levels in favor of NICTH (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Diagnosis of NICTH. A: Abdominal CT scan revealed the pelvic recurrence and pulmonary metastases. B: Lane 3 showed that IGF-II was mainly detected as high molecular weight band in the sample from the patient, and lanes 2 and 3 showed the concentration of total IGF-II (ie, mature and big) of the patient's serum was higher than that in the control subject. CT = computed tomography; IGF-II = insulin-like growth factor II; NICTH = nonislet cell tumor hypoglycemia.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e1577-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>TABLE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Laboratory Examination for the Patient</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-94-e1577-g003"/>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Later on, western blot of serum sample was conducted with an anti-IGF-II antibody which detected a high percentage of high molecular weight band IGF-II. Moreover, compared with control, the concentration of total IGF-II (ie, mature and big) was higher (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B, lanes 2 and 3).</p>
      <p>Because of the widely pelvic recurrence and pulmonary metastases were unresected, treatment with oral dexamethasone (2&#x200A;mg/day) and continuous intravenous infusion of glucose (150&#x200A;g/day) were conducted. Dexamethasone and glucose doses were administrated to 1&#x200A;mg/day and 200&#x200A;g/day, respectively, to prevent recurrent hypoglycemia. The patient was discharged from the hospital and unfortunately died 1 week later.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Hypoglycemia not associated with diabetes and/or its therapy is an uncommon clinical disorder, and tumor-induced hypoglycemia (TIH) caused by different mechanisms is a rare clinical entity.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> TIH usually appears as a result of insulin hypersecretion by pancreatic islet &#x3B2;-cell tumor (insulinoma), and can also be developed by other nonpancreatic tumors (NICTH).<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> The serum glycemia, insulin, C-peptide levels could be used for the diagnosis of insulinoma, and the serum GH, IGF-I, IGFBP3, and IGF-II, especially big IGF-II levels could be used for the diagnosis of NICTH.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
      <p>NICTH is a paraneoplastic syndrome characterized by persistent, severe hypoglycemia with various tumor types of mesochymal or epithelial origin.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> It can result in an emergent and life-threatening condition, which should be suspected when a patient with various solid tumors suffered from hypoglycemia.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Although few cases of malignancies with both sarcomatoid and epithelioid characteristics were reported, such as renal cell carcinoma<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> and thyroid carcinoma,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> a case of NICTH with recurrent PCSC in the present report is extremely rare. Moreover, further laboratory examination showed normalized serum glycosylated hemoglobin and low insulin, C-peptide, GH, IGF-I, and IGFBP3 levels which were in accordance with NICTH.</p>
      <p>Nevertheless, the crucial event in the development of NICTH has been linked to the aberrant secretion of big IGF-II, the alterations in the somatotroph axis and the levels of circulating IGF binding proteins (IGFBPs).<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Detection of a high percentage of IGF-II as big IGF-II would guarantee the diagnosis of NICTH.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Here in this report, the expression of big IGF-II was significantly more than the mature isoform. Theoretically, both IGF-I and IGF-II are capable of decreasing glucose levels, but, they fail to do so because they are normally trapped within the vascular vessel in a high molecular weight protein complex with IGFBP3 and acid-labile subunit (ALS).<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The big IGF-II reside in the binary complex with IGFBP3 which was considered to be capable of crossing the endothelial barrier, resulting in a persistent insulin-like activity and leading to severe hypoglycemia.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup></p>
      <p>It is well known that NICTH often occurs in patient with large tumors and it might be necessary for big IGF-II to reach a certain level in causing hypoglycemia.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> In this case, hypoglycemia never occurred when the primary PCSC was &gt;30&#x200A;cm in diameter. Instead, the recurrence and pulmonary metastases with a diameter of &lt;11&#x200A;cm led to NICTH. Interestingly, such phenomenon was also observed in renal cell carcinoma<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> and thyroid carcinoma,<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> which was caused by the over-expressed big IGF-II in both recurrent tumor and the primary tumor.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, this is an extremely rare case of SC in the pelvic cavity with the NICTH syndrome caused by inhibition of the somatotroph axis resulting from excessive secretion of big IGF-II. It is important to examine big IGF-II expression in patient's serum in order to reach the diagnosis of NICTH in cases of intractable cancer-associated hypoglycemia.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <p>We thank the participant and her families for their kind cooperation, generosity, and patience. The authors appreciate Guiling Tian (Xinjiang Medical University, Urumqi, China) for diligent language checking of the manuscript.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: ALS = acid-labile subunit, CT = computed tomography, IGF = insulin-like growth factor, IGFBP3 = IGF-binding protein-3, MRI = magnetic resonance imaging, NICTH = nonislet cell tumor hypoglycemia, PCSC = SC in the pelvic cavity, SCs = arcomatoid carcinoma, TIH = tumor-induced hypoglycemia.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="equal">
        <p>CF and CWF have contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>The relevant institutional ethics committees approved this study.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>This study was supported by Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81402446, to CWF).</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsuzuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hypoglycemia caused by recurrent renal cell carcinoma as result of production of high molecular weight insulin-like growth factor 2</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Oncol</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <comment>[Epub ahead of print] (published online on April 7, 2014; DOI:10.1200/JCO.2013.49.5374)</comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikushima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A case of a giant phyllodes tumor of the breast with hypoglycemia caused by high-molecular-weight insulin-like growth factor II</article-title>. <source><italic>Breast Cancer</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19259766</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rikhof</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Non-islet cell tumour-induced hypoglycaemia: a review of the literature including two new cases</article-title>. <source><italic>Endocr Relat Cancer</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>993</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18045950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morioka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Non-islet cell tumor-induced hypoglycemia associated with macronodular pulmonary metastases from poorly differentiated thyroid carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Thyroid</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>399</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23697382</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McWhorter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Evidence for colorectal sarcomatoid carcinoma arising from tubulovillous adenoma</article-title>. <source><italic>World J Gastroenterol</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>4389</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4394</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18666331</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sarcomatoid carcinoma in the pelvic cavity</article-title>. <source><italic>Int J Clin Exp Pathol</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>797</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23573329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maki</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Small is beautiful: insulin-like growth factors and their role in growth, development, and cancer</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Oncol</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>4985</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4995</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20975071</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bodnar</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietropaolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Management of non-islet-cell tumor hypoglycemia: a clinical review</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>713</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>722</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24423303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iglesias</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Diez</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Management of endocrine disease: a clinical update on tumor-induced hypoglycemia</article-title>. <source><italic>Eur J Endocrinol</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>170</volume>:<fpage>R147</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>R157</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24459236</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The role of insulin-like growth factors and their binding proteins in tumor hypoglycemia</article-title>. <source><italic>Horm Res</italic></source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8950621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertherat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Logie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gicquel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Alterations of the 11p15 imprinted region and the IGFs system in a case of recurrent non-islet-cell tumour hypoglycaemia (NICTH)</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</italic></source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>220</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931103</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zachariah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brackenridge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shojaee-Moradie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The mechanism of non-islet cell hypoglycaemia caused by tumour-produced IGF-II</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>637</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>638</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17581259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Setoyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Horimatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Bioactive insulin-like growth factors as a possible molecular target for non-islet cell tumor hypoglycemia</article-title>. <source><italic>Cancer Biol Ther</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1588</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1592</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25535894</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daughaday</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapadia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Significance of abnormal serum binding of insulin-like growth factor II in the development of hypoglycemia in patients with non-islet-cell tumors</article-title>. <source><italic>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</italic></source>
<year>1989</year>; <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>6778</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6782</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2771956</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dynkevich</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rother</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitford</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Tumors, IGF-2, and hypoglycemia: insights from the clinic, the laboratory, and the historical archive</article-title>. <source><italic>Endocr Rev</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>798</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>826</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23671155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoekman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gloudemans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hypoglycaemia associated with the production of insulin-like growth factor II and insulin-like growth factor binding protein 6 by a haemangiopericytoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf)</italic></source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10468998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
