<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25830996</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4371675</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20153214</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Bed bug dermatitis, description of two cases in Rio de Janeiro,
Brazil<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></sup></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bernardes</surname>
            <given-names>Fred</given-names>
            <suffix>Filho</suffix>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Quaresma</surname>
            <given-names>Maria Vict&#xF3;ria</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Avelleira</surname>
            <given-names>Jo&#xE3;o Carlos Regazzi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Azulay</surname>
            <given-names>David Rubem</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Azulay-Abulafia</surname>
            <given-names>Luna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff04">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bastos</surname>
            <given-names>Amanda Queiroz</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff05">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gon&#xE7;alves</surname>
            <given-names>Teresa Cristina Monte</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff06">6</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label>Instituto de Dermatologia Professor Rubem David Azulay,
Santa Casa da Miseric&#xF3;rdia do Rio de Janeiro (IDPRDA-SCMRJ) - Rio de Janeiro (RJ),
Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label>Pontif&#xED;cia Universidade Cat&#xF3;lica do Rio de Janeiro (PUC
RJ) - Rio de Janeiro (RJ), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label>Funda&#xE7;&#xE3;o T&#xE9;cnico-Educacional Souza Marques - Rio de
Janeiro (RJ), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff04"><label>4</label>Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro (UERJ) - Rio de
Janeiro (RJ), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff05"><label>5</label>Universidade Federal Rural do Rio de Janeiro (UFRRJ).
Instituto Oswaldo Cruz/ Laborat&#xF3;rio de Transmissores de Leishmanioses, Setor de
Entomologia M&#xE9;dica e Forense (Fiocruz) - Rio de Janeiro (RJ), Brazil</aff>
      <aff id="aff06"><label>6</label>Instituto Oswaldo Cruz/Laborat&#xF3;rio de Transmissores de
Leishmanioses, Setor de Entomologia M&#xE9;dica e Forense (Fiocruz) - Rio de Janeiro
(RJ), Brazil</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">MAILING ADDRESS: Fred Bernardes Filho, Marqu&#xEA;s de Caxias, n&#xB0; 9
Sobrado - Centro, 24030-050 - Niter&#xF3;i - RJ Brazil. E-mail:
<email>f9filho@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Mar-Apr</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Mar-Apr</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>90</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>240</fpage>
      <lpage>243</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2015 by Anais Brasileiros de
Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any
medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bed bugs are hematophagous insects which due to their morphological and
biological characteristics are able to easily adapt themselves to human
households. The authors describe two cases of dermatitis caused by bed bug bites
in the city of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Patients presented linear lesions in the
usual "breakfast, lunch and dinner" arrangement, suggesting this diagnosis. A
visit to their dwellings showed infestation of insects identified as
<italic>Cimex hemipterus</italic>. The knowledge of these insects by the
dermatological community will contribute to an accurate diagnosis as well as
subsidize the dissemination of information aiming for prevention.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Arthropods</kwd>
        <kwd>Bed bugs</kwd>
        <kwd>Cimicidae</kwd>
        <kwd>Prurigo</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Cimicidae, or bed bugs, are hematophagous insects that have been associated with man
and bats since prehistorical age.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>
Morphological and biological characteristics such as their minuscule size,
dorsoventrally flattened body, absence of developed wings, short life cycle (30 to
45 days) and obligatory hematophagy enable them to hide in crevices and holes,
dispersed in a passive way, easing their adaptation to human households, reaching
high levels of infestation and acquiring this way economic, medical and
epidemiological importance.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Global dispersion of these insects increased due to international travel, commerce
and migrations. Additionally, the attention turned to the application and
indiscriminate use of insecticides for specific pests, not only decreased their
predecessors but also made possible their silent proliferation.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In Latin America, the concern with the reemergence of bed bugs was raised in the
debates that occurred during the International Lecture on Bed Bugs, where the
difficulty of promoting adequate measures became evident considering the lack of
knowledge.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In Brazil, <italic>Cimex lectularius</italic> is marked as having predominant
distribution in the south region associated with the intensive European immigration;
however, there are foci in tropical cities such as Belo Horizonte.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>
<italic>Cimex hemipterus</italic> was marked as the species with greater occurrence
in Brazil, with tropical distribution in populous centers and rural areas.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The bite of these insects disturbs night rest, causing discomfort when in high rates
of infestation.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> A study regarding the efficiency of the feeding
process shows that <italic>Cimex lectularius</italic> is avid and can reach high
levels of infestation when compared to <italic>Cimex hemipterus.</italic><sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Bites are painless and bed bugs are not noticed unless they are present in great
numbers. The pattern of biting distribution is in a linear sequence, in number of
three, characteristic, named "breakfast, lunch and dinner" and suggesting the
diagnosis.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The clinical picture depends on previous exposure to the insect and the degree of
immune response of the patient, which can present from cutaneous reactions, whose
lesion morphology includes macules, papules and seropapules, pustules, blisters and
nodules, to systemic reactions, such as urticaria and anaphylaxis.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>This report aims at registering the occurrence of bed bug dermatitis in the city of
Rio de Janeiro, through the description of two cases.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p><bold>Case 1:</bold> Male patient, 48 years old, presented pruritic lesions on upper
and lower limbs with one month of evolution. The onset of symptoms coincided with
the move to a new household, in the Lapa neighborhood, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</p>
      <p>At the dermatological examination, there were excoriated papules and pomphoid lesions
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1A</xref>). Some were grouped, in a
linear distribution, reminding us of the "breakfast, lunch and dinner" pattern
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1B</xref>). Fleas, bed bugs or tick bites
hypotheses were raised, however with no confirmation. Upon return, the patient
presented bed bugs collected from his house, confirming this way the diagnosis of
bed bug dermatitis (dermatosis caused by bed bug bite).</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A.</bold> Erythematous edematous lesion on the left flank, erythematous
papules with excoriated surface and hyperchromic macules on the back and
upper left limb; <bold>B.</bold> Pomphoid lesions over an erythematous base,
in a linear distribution</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0240-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In a visit by the first author to the site, a cluster of nymphs and adults was
observed close to the eggs and traces of feces added to the characteristic odor of
the bed bugs confirmed the infestation picture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Video 1</xref>). This
clustering is explained by the need of insects to search for sites where the body
surface is in contact with the substract, characteristic behavior of organisms
endowed with positive thigmotaxis.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Presence of Cimicidae eggs, nymphs, adult insects and feces over the
patient's bed - case 1</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0240-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <boxed-text position="float" orientation="portrait">
        <p>
<inline-graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0240-g06.jpg"/> Video available
online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.anaisdedermatologia.org.br/">http://www.anaisdedermatologia.org.br/</ext-link></p>
        <fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Video 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>It is possible to observe the presence of nymphs, adult bed bugs and
feces over the patient's bed - case 1</p>
          </caption>
          <media mimetype="video" mime-subtype="avi" xlink:href="abd-90-02-0240-m01.avi" orientation="portrait" id="d35e320" position="anchor"/>
        </fig>
      </boxed-text>
      <p>The identification of the specimen, made by the two last authors, was confirmed as
belonging to the order Hemiptera, suborder Heteroptera, family Cimicidae, species
<italic>Cimex hemipterus</italic>.</p>
      <p>The infestation was notified to the competent health authorities as an unusual event
and forwarded to the Environment Monitoring Agency. After fumigation of the house
and use of an antihistamine, topical corticoid and icaridin repellant, the patient
showed improvement.</p>
      <p><bold>Case 2:</bold> Male patient, 51 years old, presented diffuse pruritic lesions
over the body with 15 days of evolution. He reported that it started two days after
he moved to a hotel in the Catete neighborhood, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. At the
dermatological examination, he presented erythematous papules all over the body
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figure 3</xref>). Some lesions were grouped in a
linear sequence, in the "breakfast, lunch and dinner" pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>). In an initial examination were raised hypotheses of
bites by bed bugs or fleas.</p>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous edematous lesions on upper limbs</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0240-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous papules, some with the peculiar &#x201C;breakfast, lunch and dinner&#x201D;
pattern</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0240-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <p>A visit to the hotel where the patient was lodged was made by the first author, and
the presence of Cimicidae eggs, nymphs and adult insects was confirmed, as well as
traces of feces on the bed and walls added to the characteristic odor of bed bugs,
confirming this way the infestation of the premises and the diagnosis of bed bug
dermatitis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Presence of Cimicidae eggs, nymphs, adult insects and feces over the
patient's bed - case 2</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-02-0240-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Specimens were identified, by the two last authors, as <italic>Cimex
hemipterus</italic>, the same species of Case 1.</p>
      <p>The infestation was notified and antihistamine, topical corticoid and icaridin
repellant were prescribed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The increase in infestations by bed bugs in the 21<sup>st</sup> century occurs due to
a lack of knowledge of its importance in public health and basic knowledge about the
biology of the insect.</p>
      <p>The combating of these insects has been done with natural pyrethrins and synthetic
pyrethroids due to their low toxicity. However, they do not possess residual effect
and present resistance in laboratorial tests. This way, the fight against Cimicidae
must be done in a wider context where chemical control must be associated with
environmental management, like washing bed linen daily with hot water, vacuum clean
rooms and bed linens and steam clean furniture, that is, sanitation of housing
conditions and household hygiene, associated with information.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In recent years the increase of infestation cases and negligence with which it is
being treated is worrisome. In Brazil, little attention is paid to these insects
which can justify them being unknown and consequently the nonexistence of pest
control programs.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The presence of some lesions in linear form characterized as "breakfast, lunch and
dinner" suggests the occurrence of interruptions and new attempts at feeding, since
this is done directly at the blood vessel, whose caliber seems to influence
repast.<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The cases presented confirm the "silent" occurrence of these insects in neighborhoods
of Rio de Janeiro. Thus, it is believed that the knowledge of these insects by the
dermatological community will contribute to a precise diagnosis, as well as give
subsidies to the dissemination of information, aiming for prevention.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of Interests: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial Support: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>How to cite this article: Bernardes Filho F, Quaresma MV, Avelleira JCR, Azulay
DR, Azulay-Abulafia L, Bastos AQ, Gon&#xE7;alves TCM. Bed bug dermatitis, description
of two cases in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. An Bras Dermatol. 2015;90(2):240-7.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other" id="fn01">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Work performed at Instituto de Dermatologia Professor Rubem David Azulay, Santa
Casa da Miseric&#xF3;rdia do Rio de Janeiro (IDPRDA-SCMRJ) - Rio de Janeiro (RJ),
Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Usinger</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Monograph of Cimicidae (Hemiptera - Heteroptera).Thomas Say
Foundation</source>
          <volume>Vol. 7</volume>
          <publisher-loc>Maryland</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Entomological Society of America, College Park</publisher-name>
          <year>1966</year>
          <size units="pages">85 p</size>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reinhardt</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siva-Jothy</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biology of the Bed bugs</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>351</fpage>
          <lpage>374</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968204</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nascimento</surname>
              <given-names>LGG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Investiga&#xE7;&#xE3;o da ocorr&#xEA;ncia de infesta&#xE7;&#xE3;o por Cimicidae (Heteroptera:
Cimicomorpha) na Regi&#xE3;o Metropolitana de S&#xE3;o Paulo, no per&#xED;odo de 2004 a
2009 [disserta&#xE7;&#xE3;o]</source>
          <publisher-loc>S&#xE3;o Paulo (SP)</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Universidade de S&#xE3;o Paulo</publisher-name>
          <year>2010</year>
          <size units="pages">144p</size>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coto</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Curso Internacional sobre chinche de cama, organizado por HC
Consultores</article-title>
          <source>Revista Plagas Ambiente y Salud</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          <lpage>34</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Negromonte</surname>
              <given-names>MRS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Linardi</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagem</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Preval&#xEA;ncia de Cimex lectularius (Hemiptera: Cimicidae) em uma
comunidade de Belo Horizonte</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras Entomol</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>715</fpage>
          <lpage>720</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Araujo</surname>
              <given-names>RN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>FS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gontijo</surname>
              <given-names>NF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gon&#xE7;alves</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The feeding process of Cimex lectularius (Linnaeus 1758) and
Cimex hemipterus (Fabricius 1803) on different bloodmeal
sources</article-title>
          <source>J Insect Physiol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>1151</fpage>
          <lpage>1157</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712677</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Criado</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Criado</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bedbugs (Heteroptera, Cimicidae): an etiology of pruritus to be
remembered</article-title>
          <source>An Bras Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>164</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21437544</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goddard</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>deShazo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bed bugs (Cimex lectularius) and clinical consequences of their
bites</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>301</volume>
          <fpage>1358</fpage>
          <lpage>1366</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19336711</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Forattini</surname>
              <given-names>OP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Os cimic&#xED;deos e sua import&#xE2;ncia em Sa&#xFA;de P&#xFA;blica (Hemiptera-
Heteroptera; Cimicidae)</article-title>
          <source>Rev Sa&#xFA;de P&#xFA;bl S&#xE3;o Paulo</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>37</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Potter</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The History of Bed Bug Management - With Lessons from the
Past</article-title>
          <source>Am Entomol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>14</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
