<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Emerging Infect. Dis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24963722</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4073870</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13-1654</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2007.131654</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Letters to the Editor</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type">
          <subject>Letter</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Zoonotic Filariasis Caused by Novel <italic>Brugia</italic> sp. Nematode, United States, 2011</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Zoonotic Filariasis Caused by Novel <italic>Brugia</italic> Nematode</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Paniz-Mondolfi</surname>
            <given-names>Alberto Enrique</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>G&#xE1;rate</surname>
            <given-names>Teresa</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stavropoulos</surname>
            <given-names>Christine</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
            <given-names>Wen</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gonz&#xE1;lez</surname>
            <given-names>Luis Miguel</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Eberhard</surname>
            <given-names>Mark</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kimmelstiel</surname>
            <given-names>Fred</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sordillo</surname>
            <given-names>Emilia Mia</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut, USA (A.E. Paniz- Mondolfi); </aff>
        <aff id="aff2">St. Luke&#x2019;s-Roosevelt Hospital Center of Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, New York, USA (A.E. Paniz-Mondolfi, C. Stavropoulos, W. Fan, F. Kimmelstiel, E.M. Sordillo); </aff>
        <aff id="aff3">Servicio Autonomo Instituto de Biomedicina/Instituto Venezolano de los Seguros Sociales, Caracas, Venezuela (A. Paniz Mondolfi);</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"> Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Madrid, Spain (T. G&#xE1;rate, L.M. Gonz&#xE1;lez); </aff>
        <aff id="aff5">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, USA (M. Eberhard)</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: Alberto E. Paniz-Mondolfi, Yale&#x2013;New Haven Hospital, Microbiology Laboratory (PS656), 55 Park St, New Haven, CT 06511, USA; email: <email xlink:href="albertopaniz@yahoo.com">albertopaniz@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>20</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>1248</fpage>
      <lpage>1250</lpage>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <title>Keywords: </title>
        <kwd>Brugia sp. Nov</kwd>
        <kwd>zoonotic filariasis</kwd>
        <kwd>North America</kwd>
        <kwd>New York</kwd>
        <kwd>United States</kwd>
        <kwd>parasites</kwd>
        <kwd>nematode</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><bold>To the Editor:</bold> Zoonotic brugian filariasis is an incidental infection of humans with <italic>Brugia</italic> spp. nematodes that primarily parasitize nonhuman vertebrates, rarely humans (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). In contrast to classical lymphatic filariasis caused by <italic>B. malayi</italic> and <italic>B. timori</italic>, which are found in Asia, most zoonotic <italic>Brugia</italic> infections have been reported from the northeastern United States (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>) or South America (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). We report a case of symptomatic brugian infection in a New York City resident who had not traveled to the Eastern Hemisphere.</p>
    <p>In 2011, a 53-year-old White man first noted tenderness and swelling behind his penis and in his right groin after having fallen 3 months earlier. The tenderness was relieved by nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs, but the swelling continued; an oral antimicrobial drug, prescribed for presumed cellulitis, produced no improvement. At the time of examination, the patient had no fever or other signs or symptoms. Only a 3.0-cm &#xD7; 3.0-cm firm, nonfixed right inguinal nodule without warmth or tenderness was noted. Laboratory findings were remarkable for total leukocytes of 6.4 &#xD7; 10<sup>9</sup>, eosinophilia (12%, 600 cells/mm<sup>3</sup>), decreased hemoglobin level (10.0 g/dL), and low hematocrit of 31.2%. An excisional biopsy sample revealed intralymphatic adult nematodes with viable-appearing microfilaria (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Technical Appendix</xref> Figure).</p>
    <p>The patient had been born and raised in Champlain, Illinois, and had resided in the Bronx, New York, since 1979; he had no history of travel to filariasis-endemic regions. Characteristics of the adult worms and microfilaria were most consistent with those of <italic>Brugia</italic> spp., which was surprising because classical brugian lymphatic filariasis seems to be limited to Asia (<italic>B. malayi</italic>) and Indonesia (<italic>B. timori</italic>) (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>). However, the adult filariae were smaller than expected for <italic>B. malayi</italic> or <italic>B. timori</italic> nematodes, prompting consideration of zoonotic filariasis (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><italic>6</italic></xref>). The adult worms and microfilaria seemed to be viable, although zoonotic <italic>Brugia</italic> spp. in histologic sections often appear degenerated (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><italic>6</italic></xref>). The diameters of the adult worms were similar to those reported from South America (females 90&#x2013;100 &#x3BC;m, males 50 &#x3BC;m) (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>) rather than those from North America (females 35&#x2013;75 &#x3BC;m, males 32&#x2013;52 &#x3BC;m) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Peripheral blood was repeatedly negative for microfilaria. Serum sent to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (Atlanta, GA, USA) for ELISA testing for <italic>B. malayi</italic> anti-filarial IgG 4 showed optical density of 0.13, below the ELISA cutoff for filariasis.</p>
    <p>Because micromorphologic information was not adequate for species identification, paraffin-embedded biopsy specimens were submitted for molecular testing. Genomic DNA extracted from paraffin-embedded tissue with the QIAamp DNA&#x2013;formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tissue procedure was amplified by using the primer sets DiBu-F(5&#x2032;-GCTAGATATGCTACCAACAAAA-3&#x2032;)/ITS1 R(5&#x2032;-CTCAATGCGTCTGCAATTCGC-3&#x2032;) and BuF2-(5-CATTTATGCTAGATATGCTACCAAC-3&#x2032;)/ITS1-R. The products were fractionated on 2% agarose gel and stained with ethidium bromide. The internal transcribed spacer (ITS) 1 PCR product (182 bp) was automatically sequenced by using the same primers used for PCR. Lasergene software (DNASTAR, Madison, WI, USA) was used to align the sequences obtained with <italic>Brugia</italic> spp. sequences deposited in GenBank; detailed sequence comparison identified the isolate as a novel <italic>Brugia</italic> (Nematoda: Onchocercidae) species closely related to <italic>B. pahangi</italic> and <italic>B. malayi</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure</xref>). The ITS-1 sequence was submitted to the EMBL Nucleotide Sequence Database (accession no. HE856316).</p>
    <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
      <label>Figure</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Pile-up of partial ribosomal DNA sequences from <italic>Brugia</italic> NY strain (HE856316) and from other related <italic>Brugia</italic> spp. strains and clones, <italic>B. malayi</italic> BM28 (JQ327146), <italic>B. malayi</italic> C27Cat5 (EU373624), <italic>B. pahangi</italic> C61CAT5 (EU419348), <italic>B. pahangi</italic> C14Cat6 (EU373632), <italic>B. pahangi</italic> C7Cat6 (EU373630), <italic>B. pahangi</italic> Bp-1 (AY621469), <italic>B. pahangi</italic> C46CAT5 (EU419351), and <italic>B. pahangi</italic> C27Cat7 (EU373647). The <italic>Brugia</italic> NY strain (HE856316) is enclosed in a red box; asterisks (*) indicate conserved residues; periods (.) indicate nucleotide changes; colons (:) indicate nucleotide changes just in the <italic>Brugia</italic> NY isolate; hyphens (-) are included in the sequences to maximize the comparisons among the 9 DNA molecules. Italicized numbers in parentheses indicate the percentage of similarity with the <italic>Brugia</italic> NY isolate. </p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="13-1654-F"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Removal of an affected lymph node without additional treatment is often considered sufficient treatment for zoonotic filariases. However, for the patient reported here, persistence of inguinal swelling prompted a repeat biopsy 4 months later; the specimen again demonstrated reactive follicular hyperplasia, although no parasites were seen. Because the patient&#x2019;s initial clinical signs and subsequent persistent adenopathy were reminiscent of unilateral lymphadenitis, lymphangitis, and induration that are typical of <italic>B. malayi</italic> or <italic>B. timori</italic> filariasis, and the microfilariae in the original biopsy sample appeared to be viable, we empiricially prescribed a standard dosage of oral doxycycline for 6 weeks, followed by single doses of ivermectin at 400 &#x3BC;g/kg and 800 mg albendazole. The patient has been well, without further adenopathy or eosinophilia, for &gt;2 years. Because adult filariae can live for &gt;10 years, the place of acquisition cannot be stated with certainty.</p>
    <p>The prevalence of zoonotic infection with <italic>Brugia</italic> spp. nematodes is unknown. Many reported cases are asymptomatic or diagnosed incidentally during evaluation for persistent adenopathy (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Conversely, differentiation of zoonotic from classical filariasis is unlikely in disease-endemic areas; most cases published since the initial 1962 case report (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>) occurred in the United States. Most case-patients were from the Northeast, including New York (8 cases), Massachusetts, Pennsylvania, Connecticut, and Rhode Island (3 cases each) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>); single cases have been identified in Michigan, Ohio, North Carolina, Oklahoma, New Jersey, Louisiana, Florida, and California (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>). Four other cases have been reported: 3 in South America (Colombia, Brazil, Peru) (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>) and 1 in Africa (Ethiopia) (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>). Only a few <italic>Brugia</italic> species have been identified, including <italic>B. leporis</italic>, found in rabbits in the northeastern United States (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>); <italic>B. beaveri</italic>, found in raccoons and bobcats in the southern United States; and <italic>B. guyanensis</italic>, found in coatimundi and other vertebrates in South America (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>). Definitive identification with molecular techniques will better identify causative species and help clarify many of the ecologic and epidemiologic questions surrounding zoonotic filarial infections.</p>
    <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
      <caption>
        <title>Technical Appendix</title>
        <p>Histocytologic appearance of <italic>Brugia</italic> nematodes in 53-year-old White man from New York, USA.</p>
      </caption>
      <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="13-1654-Techapp-s1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e410" position="anchor"/>
    </supplementary-material>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="citation">
        <p><italic>Suggested citation for this article</italic>: Paniz-Mondolfi AE, G&#xE1;rate T, Stavropoulos C, Fan W, Gonz&#xE1;lez LM, Eberhard M, et al. Zoonotic filariasis caused by novel <italic>Brugia</italic> sp. nematode, United States, 2011 [letter]. Emerg Infect Dis [Internet]. 2014 Jul [<italic>date cited</italic>]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid2007.131654">http://dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid2007.131654</ext-link></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <p>This work was supported by the Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Fondo de Investigaci&#xF3;nes Sanitarias, through the sixth national plan of research plus development plus innovation (2008&#x2013;2011), Instituto de Salud Carlos III -General Sub-Direction of Networks and Centers for Collaborative Research (Red Tem&#xE1;tica de Investigaci&#xF3;n Cooperativa&#x2013;Red de Investigaci&#xF3;n Cooperativa en Enfermedades Tropicales, grant no. RD12/0018/003).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Orihel</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eberhard</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Zoonotic filariasis.</article-title>
<source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>81</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9564568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eberhard</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>DeMeester</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>BW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lammie</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Zoonotic <italic>Brugia</italic> infection in western Michigan.</article-title>
<source>Am J Surg Pathol</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1058</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>61</lpage> . <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000478-199310000-00012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8372943</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Orihel</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beaver</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Zoonotic <italic>Brugia</italic> infections in North and South America.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>638</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>47</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2662786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoerauf</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bockarie</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Lymphatic filariasis and onchocerciasis.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>376</volume>:<fpage>1175</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>85</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60586-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20739055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aguilera</surname>
<given-names>XP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barbosa da Silva Junior</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ault</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Najera</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martinez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Elimination of neglected diseases in Latin America and the Caribbean: a mapping of selected diseases.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e964</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21358810</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gutierrez</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnostic features of zoonotic filariae in tissue sections.</article-title>
<source>Hum Pathol</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>514</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0046-8177(84)80004-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6539296</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kozek</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reyes</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ehrman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garrido</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nieto</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Enzootic <italic>Brugia</italic> infection in a two-year old Colombian girl.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6696186</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Baird</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neafie</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>South American brugian filariasis: report of a human infection acquired in Peru.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3407837</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Men&#xE9;ndez</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouza</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic>Brugia</italic> species in a man from western Ethiopia.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>90</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3407838</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10. </label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Beaver</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orihel</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Human infection with filariae of animals in the United States.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1965</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1010</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>29</lpage> .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5891453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
