<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neurosciences (Riyadh)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Neurosciences (Riyadh)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Neurosciences</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Neurosciences</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1319-6138</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Riyadh : Armed Forces Hospital</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Saudi Arabia</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26492117</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4727625</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Neurosciences-20-368</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17712/nsj.2015.4.20150142</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Parry-Romberg syndrome</article-title>
        <subtitle>Physical, clinical, and imaging features</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ayd&#x131;n</surname>
            <given-names>Hasan</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yologlu</surname>
            <given-names>Zeynel</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sarg&#x131;n</surname>
            <given-names>Husamettin</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Metin</surname>
            <given-names>Melike Rusen</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <italic>From the Radiology Department (Aydin, Yologlu), Onkoloji Education and Research Hospital, and the Radiology Department (Sargin), Egerad Private Medical Imaging Center, and the Radiology Department (Metin), Ataturk Education and Research Hospital, Ankara, Turkey</italic>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">
          <italic>Address correspondence and reprint request to: Dr. Hasan Ayd&#x131;n, Radiology Department, Onkoloji Education and Research Hospital, PO Box 215, Ankara 06110, Turkey. Tel. +90 (312) 3360909. E-mail: <email xlink:href="dr.hasanaydin@hotmail.com">dr.hasanaydin@hotmail.com</email></italic>
        </corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>20</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>368</fpage>
      <lpage>371</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Neurosciences</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license>
          <license-p>Neurosciences is an Open Access journal and articles published are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial License (CC BY-NC). Readers may copy, distribute, and display the work for non-commercial purposes with the proper citation of the original work.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Progressive hemifacial atrophy also known as Parry-Romberg syndrome is an acquired, slowly progressive disorder, occurring more in women, primarily affecting one side of the face, mainly characterized by unilateral atrophy, and loss of skin and subcutaneous tissues of face, muscles, and bones. Ocular and neurologic involvements are common. The possible etiology is unclear without any known cure. We report a rare case of Parry-Romberg syndrome with classical features. The clinical features, radiological imaging findings, differential diagnosis, and available treatment options are discussed in this report.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Parry-Romberg syndrome (PRS), also named as progressive hemifacial atrophy is an acquired, sporadic neurocutaneous disorder that is mainly characterized by unilateral self-limited atrophy and loss of skin and subcutaneous tissue of the face.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> It was first reported by Parry, and then elaborated as a syndrome by Romberg.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> It is a slowly progressive disorder, occurring more in women, primarily affecting one side of the face, including skin, subcutaneous tissue, muscles, cartilage, and bones.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> The onset of this syndrome generally occurs in the first and second decades of life with skin changes resembling scleroderma, which is usually accompanied by this neurological effects of PRS, including seizures, migraine, trigeminal neuralgia and darkening of skin; partial seizures are the most common neurologic complication.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Ocular involvement is common, and the most frequent manifestation is enophthalmos.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Its origin is unclear without any known cure. Several possible causes have been postulated (encephalitis, trauma, scleroderma, vasculitis, migraine, infections, genetic and hereditary factors, autoimmunity, and so forth) but a multifactorial pathogenesis may be the first etiology.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Possible neuroimaging findings of PRS in CT and MR imaging are; atrophy of skin and subcutaneous tissue of face, intracranial calcifications, cerebral atrophy, deep and subcortical white matter lesions, encephalomalacia, hydrocephalus, meningeal, and leptomeningeal enhancement, aneurysms, cortical thickening and dysgenesis, infarctions in the corpus callosum, and so forth.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> We describe a rare case of PRS with classical features, associated with alopecia, hyperpigmentation around the left globe and eyebrows, and unilateral asymmetric loss of subcutaneous fat in left lower leg. Our objective in presenting this particular case is to highlight the classical neurologic, skin and ocular findings of PRS with addition of subcutaneous fat loss in long extremities.</p>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 48-year-old female with complaints of prominence of left forehead and asymmetric left-sided hemifacial atrophy, alopecia, asymmetric thinning of left lower leg, without any history of trauma, presented to the Dermatology Department of our hospital. She also had slight skin pigmentation over the left eyebrow and the left palpebral conjunctiva. Her symptoms started around 6 years ago with mild hemifacial atrophy on the left forehead, and progressed slowly with alopecia. The asymmetric thinning of her left lower leg had started around one year before. No facial motor and sensory deficits were noted physically with normal tongue movements, without any enophthalmus or ptosis of the left upper eyelid. Her neurologic and fundus examinations were both normal with normal psychomotor attitudes. The right face appeared completely normal. On physical examination, the left-sided facial and forehead asymmetry was detected mainly due to subcutaneous fatty loss with prominent bony ridges on the left forehead and left maxillary region. Intra and extraoral examination revealed normal physical yields without any atrophy of chewing muscles and/or tongue. Paranasal sinus x-ray examination also presented a normal frontal and maxillary sinus on the left side. There was asymmetric prominent subcutaneous fat and tissue loss in the left cruris region on inspection (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>, Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref></bold>). She had several normal brain CT scans and electromyographic approaches during the first 6 years. Following consultation, she was admitted as inpatient admission to the Surgery Department, then referred to Egerad private medical imaging center for brain MRI. The brain MRI revealed asymmetric, prominent fatty loss in the dural and galeal parts of the left frontal region. No cortex or deep white matter involvement, including white matter hyperintensities-cortical atrophy was indicated (<bold>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">C</xref></bold>).</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>An image showing: <bold>A</bold>) general physical appearance of the patient; and <bold>B</bold>) left sided facial hemiatrophy and left forehead prominence with bony ridges.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="Neurosciences-20-368-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>An image of the patient showing; <bold>A</bold>) asymmetric fatty loss and thinning of left lower leg; and <bold>B</bold>) non-homogenous alopecia.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="Neurosciences-20-368-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>An image showing: <bold>A</bold>) fatty loss of the scalp and galeal subcutaneous fatty tissue of the left frontal area, seen in T2 weighted (W) axial image; <bold>B</bold>) tissue loss of the scalp of the left frontal region, presented in T2W coronal image; and <bold>C</bold>) calvarial fat and soft tissue loss in left frontal side, shown in T1W axial image.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="Neurosciences-20-368-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Laboratory results for a complete blood count and biochemistry revealed hemoglobin: 13.58 [normal value (NV): 12-16 g/dl], hematocrit: 41.3 [NV: 37-50 g/dl], mean corpuscular volume: 90.2 [NV: 80-99 g/dl], mean corpuscular hemoglobin 28.5 [NV: 33-37 g/dl], white blood count (4700/&#xB5;lt [NV: 4800-10800/&#xB5;lt], C-reactive protein 2.23 mg/dL [NV: 0-10 mg/dL], sedimentation 38/hour [NV: 0-20/hour], and mild thrombocytosis (430.000 g/dl) were indicated. Prothrombin time, and activated partial thromboplastin time were normal with negative hepatitis B surface antigen, anti hepatitis B surface antibodies, hepatitis C virus, and human immunodeficiency virus. The triiodothyronine - thyroxine - thyroid stimulating hormone levels were within normal range. Urine analysis was normal, CSF analysis showed mildly elevated protein (16 mg/dL; NV: 0-10 mg/dL), normal glucose and no pleocytosis. In the differential diagnosis, scleroderma or connective tissue disorders were considered, however, she had negative HLA-B27 with normal glucose and electrolyte levels in serum blood. Based on the clinical findings and history, a diagnosis of Parry-Romberg syndrome was made. Alloplastic aesthetic surgery with autologous fat injection to the atrophied left forehead was suggested to our patient by a plastic surgeon, but due to financial difficulties, she declined any surgical management. The treatment plan excluding the surgical management of our patient was physical and clinical follow-up in our research hospital; the follow up included physical rehabilitation including sports and exercise, use of a chin mask, and/or analgesic use.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Parry-Romberg syndrome is an uncommon; rare pathology of poorly understood etiology. It is characterized by a slow progressive unilateral atrophy of the face, including skin-soft tissue, muscles and bones, which were present in our case.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The extension of the atrophy is frequently limited to one side of the face, and ipsilateral facial involvement is rare (10-20% of cases were reported bilaterally).<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The early hemifacial asymmetry progresses over years to extreme loss of subcutaneous tissues, resulting in a sunken and wrinkled face on one side.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The incidence of PRS is not well-established, the average onset of disease is around 10 years of age; however, onset can be found as late as 40-50 years in some patients;<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> our patient was a 48-year-old female. The severity of PRS with late onset, including facial atrophy-asymmetry, neurological and ocular findings and so forth, may be less than PRS in younger ages, probably due to the complete development of craniofacial and nervous structures.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> To date around 150 cases of PRS had been reported in the literature.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> This syndrome is more prevalent in females without any precise geographical distribution. It mostly manifests on the left side of the face, and can occur in any members of the same family.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Characteristically, hemifacial atrophy is usually self-limited and stabilizes in most of the patients after 5-10 years duration.<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Guerrerosantos et al<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> classified PRS into 4 types: Type 1 and 2 involve a decrease in the facial soft tissue, type 3 and 4 also involve thinning of soft tissue, as well as bone and cartilage atrophy. Type 1 is the mildest form, and type 4 is the most severe, and most serious form.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Our patient is considered to be type 3 due to thinning of the subcutaneous soft tissue in the left face and cruris region.</p>
      <p>Electromyography, blink reflex, and trigeminal evoked potential abnormalities may indicate false implications through the brain stem as the etiology of the disease, and hyperactivity of the brain stem sympathetic centers, which may be caused by autoimmune processes, may lead to the cutaneous and subcutaneous atrophy in PRS.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Clinically, dry and hyperpigmented skin may be the first sign, also present in our patient, and in some cases, a demarcated line between normal and abnormal skin can be seen, known as the en coup de sabre that means &#x201C;cut of the sword&#x2019;&#x2019;, can also be shown in a localized form of scleroderma.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Ocular involvement is common, such as progressive enophthalmos, pseudoptosis, uveitis, pupillary disturbances, heterochromia, and restrictive strabismus. The most frequent opthalmic manifestation is enophthalmos due to loss of fat around the affected orbit, which was not observed in our patient.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Alopecia and thinning of the ear due to fat atrophy on the involved side are also frequent signs; alopecia was present in our case.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p>
      <p>Neurological complications of PRS are trigeminal neuralgia, facial paresthesia, migraine, and seizures. Epilepsy, especially contralateral epilepsy may also occur occasionally,<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> however, except for headache, other findings were not found in our patient. Atrophy of the tongue on the affected side, deviation of the mouth and nose to the affected side, atrophy of the upper lip leading to an exposition of teeth, small teeth with short roots on the involved side are the other important features of PRS, which were absent in our patient.<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Although the pathophysiology of this disease is not well known, some authors have proposed that the primary cause is neurologic disturbance of fat metabolism, resulting from a trophic malformation of the cervical sympathetic nervous system.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Parry-Romberg syndrome may have strong correlation with autoimmune disorders, endocrine, and hereditary disturbances, scleroderma, and Rasmussen encephalitis.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Neuroimaging findings of PRS may be intracranial calcifications, cerebral and cerebellar atrophy, deep white matter lesions, encephalomalacia, heterogeneous meningeal enhancement and so forth.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> The brain MR imaging of our patient showed asymmetric, prominent fatty loss in the dura and galea of the left frontal side without any deep white matter and cortical involvement of the cerebrum and cerebellum. There is no curative therapy for PRS and treatment options are limited, symptomatic treatment including pain relief, anticonvulsant drugs, and reconstructive surgery are the main management modalities; steroid and immunosuppressive therapy have also been tried in some cases.<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Surgical treatment is usually based on the reposition of fat on the atrophied side, autogenous fat and cartilage grafts, silicon injections and prostheses, bovine collagen and inorganic implants are the alternatives of aesthetic surgical correction of fatty atrophy.<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p>
      <p>Our case had left face asymmetry with slight left facial hemiatrophy, a prominent left forehead with bony ridges due to subcutaneous fatty tissue loss, slight pigmentation over the left eyebrow and conjunctiva, and alopecia, which are the classical features of PRS in previous reports.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> She had normal neurologic and ocular findings, with normal psychomotor functions, and brain MRI revealed an asymmetric fatty loss in the left frontal side without any cortex or deep white matter involvement. She also had subcutaneous fatty loss in the left lower leg, resulting in an asymmetric thinning of the left cruris, which on literature review, is a previously unknown feature of PRS.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p>
      <p>Due to the non-existence of a precise cure, affected patients should be managed by a multidisciplinary team of physicians, surgeons, dentists, and psychologists to alleviate all possible difficulties related to PRS. Fat and dermis grafts are the most appropriate for type 1 and 2 PRS, whereas panfacial volumization with autologous fat-cartilage and bone graft-galeal flap injection is an excellent tool for replacing volume and restoring contour to the aging face in type 3 and 4 PRS.<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Alloplastic aesthetic surgical implantation with lipoinjection was suggested for our patient, but she declined.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, PRS is a rare disease that manifests with facial hemiatrophy and subcutaneous fatty loss on the affected side; its pathophysiology remains unknown. No definite curative treatment exists for PRS, and the most widely available treatment approach is based upon plastic aesthetic surgery.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p><italic>The authors thank Dr. Volkan Kizilgoz for confirming the figures and his help in writing this manuscript</italic>.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>
<boxed-text position="float"><caption><title>Disclosure</title></caption><p>The authors declare no conflicting interests, support or funding from any drug company.</p></boxed-text>
</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chiu</surname>
              <given-names>EY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vora</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maheshwari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A significant proportion of children with morphea en coup de sabre and Parry-Romberg syndrome have neuroimaging findings</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Dermatol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>738</fpage>
          <lpage>748</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23106674</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fornwalt</surname>
              <given-names>BE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Altman</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Parry-Romberg syndrome in an adult: report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Ear Nose Throat J</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bharatha</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antonyshyn</surname>
              <given-names>OM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aviv</surname>
              <given-names>RI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Symons</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case 178: Parry-Romberg syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>262</volume>
          <fpage>721</fpage>
          <lpage>725</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22282187</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rangare</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Babu</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shetty</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Parry-romberg syndrome: a rare case report</article-title>
          <source>J Oral Maxillofac Res</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>e5</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Budrewicz</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koszewicz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koziorowska-Gawron</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szewczyk</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Podemski</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>S&#x142;otwi&#x144;ski</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Parry-Romberg syndrome: clinical, electrophysiological and neuroimaging correlations</article-title>
          <source>Neurol Sci</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>423</fpage>
          <lpage>427</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909746</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duymaz</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karabekmez</surname>
              <given-names>FE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keskin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tosun</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Parry-Romberg syndrome: facial atrophy and its relationship with other regions of the body</article-title>
          <source>Ann Plast Surg</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>457</fpage>
          <lpage>461</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19745718</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Balaji</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Subdermal fat grafting for Parry-Romberg syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Ann Maxillofac Surg</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24987600</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Paula</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
              <given-names>BN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bahia</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
              <given-names>RN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Carvalho</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Parry-Romberg syndrome: findings in advanced magnetic resonance imaging sequences - case report</article-title>
          <source>Radiol Bras</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>186</fpage>
          <lpage>188</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25741077</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Balan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gogineni</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shetty</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D'souza</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Three-dimensional imaging of progressive facial hemiatrophy (Parry-Romberg syndrome) with unusual conjunctival findings</article-title>
          <source>Imaging Sci Dent</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232729</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guerrerosantos</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guerrerosantos</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orozco</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Classification and treatment of facial tissue atrophy in Parry-Romberg disease</article-title>
          <source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>424</fpage>
          <lpage>434</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17700981</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
