<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Surg</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Surgery</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2482</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25481274</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4268889</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">541</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2482-14-103</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Spontaneous complete migration of suture material after subcuticular continuous suture in cesarean section: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ryu</surname>
            <given-names>Ki-Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>ryukj@korea.ac.kr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ahn</surname>
            <given-names>Ki Hoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>akh1220@hanmail.net</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Hong</surname>
            <given-names>Soon Cheol</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>novak082@naver.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, College of Medicine, Korea University and Korea University Medical Center, 126-1, 5-Ga Anam-Dong, SeongBuk-Gu, Seoul, 136-705 Republic of Korea </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <elocation-id>103</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Ryu et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Skin closure during cesarean section is often performed with subcuticular running sutures by using a nonabsorbable suture material. However, this material has the risk of incomplete removal after wound healing and can migrate to other sites in rare cases.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 34-year-old Korean woman who had undergone a cesarean section 5&#xA0;months prior presented with a fine, blue object visible through the skin on her left lower abdomen. No pain or any other signs of inflammation were observed. The foreign body was revealed to be 10-cm-long suture material that had migrated laterally approximately 15&#xA0;cm in intradermal layer during the previous 5&#xA0;months, without tangling of the entire length.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Small remnants of suture materials in the subcutaneous tissue are known to migrate toward the superficial layer. The mechanism of these migrations is often thought to be related to foreign body immune reaction or the force generated in wound contracture. Long-distance migration of relatively long suture materials, as in the present case, has not been reported yet. Such a steady tension in a uniform direction within a human tissue layer cannot be explained clearly by the previously described mechanisms. That migration might have occurred in superficial subcutaneous tissue layers through the horizontal flow or movement of those layers during the recovery process that have not been revealed yet.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
          <p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/1471-2482-14-103) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Suture material migration</kwd>
        <kwd>Subcuticular suture</kwd>
        <kwd>Wound recovery</kwd>
        <kwd>Cesarean section</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2014</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>A transverse suprapubic (Pfannenstiel) incision is widely used during cesarean section, and the skin closure is often performed with a subcuticular running suture, which might be associated with a low risk of wound complications compared to staples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Either absorbable or nonabsorbable sutures can be used. Nonabsorbable sutures do not leave buried knots that can be associated with complications such as granulomas or abscesses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, the material of these sutures has a risk of incomplete removal after wound healing and can migrate to other sites in rare cases.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 34-year-old, para 1, Korean woman underwent emergent cesarean section at 34&#xA0;weeks of gestation in the Korea University Medical Center Anam Hospital in March 2012 because of preterm premature rupture of the membrane and breech presentation. Her body mass index (BMI) was 22.1&#xA0;kg/m<sup>2</sup>. She was diagnosed with a uterus didelphys and vaginal septum but had no other medical or surgical history. A transverse suprapubic (Pfannenstiel) incision was performed during the cesarean section. A 2.42-kg male baby was delivered, without perioperative complications. After closure of the subcutaneous layer, the skin was closed with subcuticular running sutures by using a 3-0 nonabsorbable monofilament nylon suture (AILEE Inc., Busan, South Korea). The distal part of that string was snapped during the wound dressing on postoperative day 4, and the resident ordered the discharge of the patient on the next day without removal of the remaining string. Five months after the patient was discharged, she presented to the outpatient clinic with a fine, blue object visible on the left lower quadrant of her abdomen. A 10-cm thread-like foreign body showed through her skin. It was situated transversely; the medial end was located approximately 5&#xA0;cm horizontally from the scar of the previous cesarean section, and the lateral end reached the upper lateral margin of the anterior superior iliac spine (Figures&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> [arrows] and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). No pain or any other sign of inflammation was observed around the region. We discovered that the foreign body was the nonabsorbable suture material that had not been removed completely during the hospital stay. We thought that the remnant suture material had migrated laterally approximately 15&#xA0;cm in dermis layer during the previous 5&#xA0;months without any symptoms. Under local anesthesia with lidocaine, the material was removed easily through a 2-mm incision (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Video 1). The nylon suture material was confirmed, without the knot portion (Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The patient was discharged without any complications.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>
<bold>The 10-cm thread-like object in the left lower quadrant of the abdomen (arrows).</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12893_2014_541_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e264"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>The fine, blue foreign body showing through the skin.</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12893_2014_541_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e276"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>
<bold>The foreign body removed through a 2-mm skin incision.</bold> The nylon suture material was confirmed, without the knot portion.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12893_2014_541_Fig3_HTML" id="d30e288"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Small remnants of nonabsorbable suture materials in the dermis or hypodermis (subcutaneous tissue) are known to migrate toward the superficial layer or occasionally to other sites within the human tissue. The phenomenon can be associated with complications, as reported in plastic surgeries such as blepharoptosis repair [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The mechanism of the migration was often thought to be related to foreign body immune reaction or to the force generated in wound contracture. However, no clear explanation has been proposed. To our knowledge, migration of relatively long suture materials, as in the present case, has not been reported yet. We retrieved related literature via PubMed by using keywords &#x201C;migration&#x201D;, &#x201C;movement&#x201D;, and &#x201C;suture material&#x201D;. In our case, the 10-cm length of the nylon suture migrated transversely to a relatively long distance (approximately 15&#xA0;cm) within the dermis layer, without remarkable tangling of the entire length of the suture. Previously described mechanisms do not explain such uniform steady tension. Moreover, among suture materials, the nylon is known to have the least tissue reaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Some cases of migration of subcutaneous catheters, which are larger than suture materials, have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], but the mechanism of these migrations might be a shift in the subcutaneous fat pad due to position change, which is not applicable to the transverse migration of suture material.</p>
      <p>Subcuticular skin sutures usually penetrate the dermis or superficial subcutaneous tissue. The subcutaneous tissue layer supports the mobility of dermal and epidermal skin layers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The horizontal migration of the nonabsorbable suture in the present case might have occurred between the dermis and superficial subcutaneous tissue layers through the horizontal flow or movement of those layers, from the midline to the lateral side, during the recovery process or via mechanisms that have not been revealed yet.</p>
      <p>More cases and studies are needed to explain the mechanism of the transverse migration of long suture materials. The results of these studies may provide evidence to better understand the movement of human tissues during wound recovery. Finally, practitioners need to be mindful that remnant suture materials can migrate to distant sites in rare cases. Careful exploration around the surgical wound might be helpful in these situations.</p>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Ethics</title>
        <p>We obtained approval of this study from the institutional review board of the Korea University Anam Hospital Clinical Trial Center (reference No. 2014-05-0009).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Consent</title>
        <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for the publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent form is available for review by the editor of this journal.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
          <media xlink:href="12893_2014_541_MOESM1_ESM.wmv">
            <caption>
              <p>Additional file 1: Video 1: The migrated suture material identified and removed through a skin incision. A 10-cm-long, fine, blue material is seen transversely in the left lower quadrant of the abdomen; the medial end is located approximately 5&#xA0;cm horizontally from the scar of the previous cesarean section, and the lateral end has reached the upper lateral margin of the anterior superior iliac spine. No sign of inflammation is observed around the region. Under local anesthesia with lidocaine, the material is removed easily through a 2-mm incision. (WMV 11 MB)</p>
            </caption>
          </media>
        </supplementary-material>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors&#x2019; contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>All of the authors participated in the design of the study, acquisition, and interpretation of data, and drafting of the manuscript. All of the authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tuuli</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rampersad</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carbone</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stamilio</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macones</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Odibo</surname>
              <given-names>AO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Staples compared with subcuticular suture for skin closure after cesarean delivery: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
          <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>682</fpage>
          <lpage>690</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AOG.0b013e31820ad61e</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21343772</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Genders</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamminga</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kukutsch</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Securing the subcuticular running suture</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1722</fpage>
          <lpage>1724</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1524-4725.2012.02488.x</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22804818</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Foster</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>John</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castro</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meisler</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Blepharoptosis surgery complicated by late suture migration</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>116</fpage>
          <lpage>117</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9394(00)00467-0</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11004269</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Postlethwait</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Willigan</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ulin</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human tissue reaction to sutures</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <volume>181</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>144</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-197502000-00003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">122890</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagasaka</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikeda</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsugeno</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okamoto</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Subcutaneous migration of distal ventriculoperitoneal shunt catheter caused by abdominal fat pad shift: three case reports</article-title>
          <source>Neurol Med Chir</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>80</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2176/nmc.50.80</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Junqueira</surname>
              <given-names>LCUA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carneiro</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Contopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Basic histology</article-title>
          <source>A concise medical library for practitioner and student</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <publisher-loc>Los Altos: Calif</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lange Medical Publications</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref-list id="BSec1">
        <title>Pre-publication history</title>
        <ref id="CR7">
          <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2482/14/103/prepub">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2482/14/103/prepub</ext-link></mixed-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
