<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Bras Ter Intensiva</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev Bras Ter Intensiva</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Revista Brasileira de Terapia Intensiva</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0103-507X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1982-4335</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Associa&#xE7;&#xE3;o Brasileira de Medicina intensiva</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25295827</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4188469</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/0103-507X.20140044</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome in patients presenting enlarged aortic
root: case report and literature review</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>S&#xED;ndrome de platipneia-ortode&#xF3;xia em aorta ect&#xE1;sica: relato de caso e
revis&#xE3;o da literatura</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Townsend</surname>
            <given-names>Raquel da Silva</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Costa</surname>
            <given-names>Ana L&#xFA;cia Martins</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gib</surname>
            <given-names>Marcelo C&#xFA;rcio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff02">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dexheimer Neto</surname>
            <given-names>Felippe Leopoldo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff03">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label> Adult Intensive Care Unit, Hospital Ernesto Dornelles - Porto Alegre
(RS), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff02"><label>2</label> Cardiovascular Surgery Service, Hospital Ernesto Dornelles - Porto
Alegre (RS), Brazil.</aff>
      <aff id="aff03"><label>3</label> Postgraduate Program in Pulmonology, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande
do Sul - Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Felippe Leopoldo Dexheimer Neto, Hospital Ernesto
Dornelles, Unidade de Terapia Intensiva, Avenida Ipiranga, 1.801, Zip code: 90160-092
- Porto Alegre (RS), Brazil, E-mail: <email>fldneto@me.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Jul-Sep</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Sep</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>26</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>313</fpage>
      <lpage>316</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We describe herein a case of a patient who, when in orthostatic positions, had severe
hypoxemia and ventilatory dysfunction. Although the severity of symptoms required
hospitalization in an intensive care setting, the initial tests only identified the
presence of enlarged aortic root, which did not explain the condition. The
association of these events with an unusual etiology, namely intracardiac shunt,
characterized the diagnosis of platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome. The literature review
shows that, with advancing research methods, there was a progressive increase in the
identification of this condition, and this association should be part of the
differential diagnosis of dyspnea in patients with enlarged aortic root.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <p>Descrevemos aqui o caso de um paciente que, ao assumir posi&#xE7;&#xF5;es de ortostatismo,
apresentava hipoxemia e disfun&#xE7;&#xE3;o ventilat&#xF3;ria grave. Embora a gravidade dos sintomas
tenha determinado a necessidade de interna&#xE7;&#xE3;o em ambiente de terapia intensiva, os
exames iniciais identificaram apenas a presen&#xE7;a de ectasia da aorta, sem, no entanto,
justificar o quadro. A associa&#xE7;&#xE3;o dessas manifesta&#xE7;&#xF5;es a uma etiologia incomum, o
shunt intracard&#xED;aco, caracterizou o diagn&#xF3;stico da s&#xED;ndrome de platipneia-ortode&#xF3;xia.
A revis&#xE3;o da literatura demonstra que, com o avan&#xE7;o dos m&#xE9;todos de investiga&#xE7;&#xE3;o,
houve progressivo aumento na identifica&#xE7;&#xE3;o desse quadro, devendo essa associa&#xE7;&#xE3;o
fazer parte do diagn&#xF3;stico diferencial de dispneia em pacientes com aorta
ect&#xE1;sica.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Aortic diseases</kwd>
        <kwd>Respiratory insufficiency</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart septal defects</kwd>
        <kwd>Aortic aneurysm</kwd>
        <kwd>Case reports</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>Coordena&#xE7;&#xE3;o de Aperfei&#xE7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#xED;vel
Superior</funding-source>
          <award-id>9868-13-1</award-id>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Dyspnea and severe hypoxemia exacerbated by orthostatic position are rare events, often
related to pulmonary disease or intracardiac shunts.<sup>(<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup> This report
describes the research and diagnosis of an unusual etiology: intracardiac shunt
secondary to acquired anatomic factors, characterizing platypnea-orthodeoxia
syndrome.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>The patient is female, 86 years old, complaining of dyspnea, productive cough and dorsal
thoracic pain, not ventilator-dependent and without radiation, with a progressive
condition for more than 7 days. The patient presented with 89% saturation in room air,
with no changes upon physical examination. The laboratory tests were normal, as were her
electrocardiogram and her chest X-ray. The initial diagnosis was respiratory infection,
which was treated with antibiotic therapy. After stabilization, the patient was
transferred to the inpatient unit.</p>
      <p>At the hospital, the patient suffered hypoxemic respiratory failure, which required a
transfer to the intensive care unit (ICU) and the initiation of invasive mechanical
ventilation. A chest computerized tomography (CT) and pulmonary CT angiography were
performed, which showed no pulmonary embolism and no alteration that justified the
condition. The investigation continued with transthoracic echocardiography, which
identified a hypertrophic left ventricle, ejection fraction of 68%, changed relaxation
pattern, increased left atrial size (4.7mm), an enlarged aortic root with an inner
diameter of 45mm, and mild aortic and tricuspid valve regurgitation, with an estimated
right ventricular/right atrial gradient of 35mmHg. The diagnostic hypothesis was a
decompensated diastolic heart failure due to an infection. The patient progressed with
rapid improvement and was discharged from the ICU.</p>
      <p>The investigation continued, and the patient underwent cardiac catheterization, which
showed normal coronary arteries and ruled out pulmonary arterial hypertension.</p>
      <p>However, after 48 hours, the patient had a new episode of hypoxic respiratory failure,
which was managed in the ICU with noninvasive mechanical ventilation. At that time, the
marked worsening of hypoxemia and ventilatory dysfunction that occurred when the patient
was sitting or in a more upright position drew attention. This worsening was confirmed
through arterial blood gas analyses in both positions, revealing marked orthostatic
desaturation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Results of sequential arterial blood gas analyses collected with the patient in
different positions</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#xA0;</th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Supine position</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Sitting position</bold>
              </th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PaO<sub>2</sub> (mmHg)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen saturation (%)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O<sub>2</sub> concentration</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>When the possibility of hypoxemia secondary to a right-to-left shunt was suggested, a
transesophageal Doppler echocardiography (TEE) was performed with the patient in the
supine position with the head tilted 45&#xBA;. In addition to the finding of enlarged aortic
root, this examination revealed the presence of an atrial septal aneurysm and a patent
foramen ovale (PFO) with significant and early microbubble flow from the right to the
left atrium. During the evaluation, we observed that this flow increased significantly
increased when the head of the patient was elevated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Transesophageal echocardiography. Atrial septal aneurysm with high permeability at
microbubble contrast.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="rbti-26-03-0313-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p>After the diagnosis of platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome, the patient underwent
percutaneous PFO closure. The patient exhibited good clinical progress and was
discharged with no symptoms seven days after the procedure.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>We report herein the clinical case of a patient with postural accentuation of a
right-to-left intracardiac shunt, characteristic of platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome,
characterized by dyspnea and hypoxemia exacerbated or triggered by orthostasis. This
syndrome is caused by a limited number of clinical conditions that produce pulmonary
arteriovenous shunt (arteriovenous malformation and hepatopulmonary syndrome) or
right-to-left intracardiac shunt (PFO and/or related atrial septal defects).<sup>(<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup></p>
      <p>The prevalence of this syndrome is underestimated because it requires a high degree of
suspicion to be identified. However, relatively simple tests (comparison of arterial
blood gas analyses performed with the patient in different positions) can confirm the
diagnosis, combined with a correct evaluation of the clinical information.<sup>(<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>)</sup>
Moreover, the possibility of a right-to-left intracardiac shunt should be evaluated by a
transesophageal echocardiography with contrast in the supine and upright position. This
procedure is a minimally invasive option and provides relatively sensitive
diagnosis.<sup>(<xref rid="B01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup></p>
      <p>PFO is usually asymptomatic because the left atrial pressure tends to keep it closed,
through a valve mechanism of the <italic>septum secundum</italic>, and is found in up to
30% of the adult population.<sup>(<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>)</sup>
However, in situations of increased pressure in the right heart chambers or redirected
venous flow toward the face of the PFO, aimed at the right atrium, right-to-left shunt
may occur. When a shunt occurs due to changes in the pressure gradient (higher pressure
in the right atrium than in the left), neither dyspnea nor hypoxemia is influenced by
the position of the patient.<sup>(<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>)</sup></p>
      <p>In platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome, right-to-left shunt is not related to increased
pressure in the right heart chambers. For shunt to occur, other factors must be present
to change the intracardiac anatomical relationships and to orient the venous flow toward
the atrial septum, causing the venous blood to cross the PFO toward the left atrium.
Thus, atrial shunt is caused or potentiated by orthostatism, manifesting in
platypnea-orthodeoxia complaints.<sup>(<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>-<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)</sup></p>
      <p>There are two groups of proposed anatomical factors that, by coexisting with PFO, may
determine intracardiac shunt with normal pressure, namely congenital (persistence of
fetal circulation) and acquired factors. Examples of congenital factors include the
Chiari network and the redundant Eustachian valve (present in the anterior inferior face
of the inferior vena cava). The following acquired factors have been described:
pneumonectomy, atelectasis, diaphragm paralysis, kyphoscoliosis, and enlarged aortic
root/aneurysm.<sup>(<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>-<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup> In theory, the
mediastinal remodeling that occurs with acquired factors would change the conformation
(tending to stretch it) and the position of the atrial septum, favoring the passage of
blood from the right to the left side in the presence of PFO. Thus, orthostatism would
contribute to directing the blood flow from the inferior vena cava to the atrial septum,
thereby extending the shunt.<sup>(<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>-<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</sup></p>
      <p>An association between enlarged aortic root and the development of right-to-left shunt
has been described in various populations.<sup>(<xref rid="B02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</sup> In 2005, Eicher et al.
retrospectively evaluated a series of 19 patients with platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome
due to intracardiac shunt and found aortic root dilation in 63% of them.<sup>(<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup> The researchers also revealed that in
42% of cases, there was no other thoraco-pulmonary change that could justify the
syndrome; thus, enlarged aortic root was the only likely etiological agent.<sup>(<xref rid="B08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup> In 2007, Bertaux et al. described
changes in the conformation, size and mobility of the atrial septum determined by the
presence of aortic root aneurysm in a prospective study.<sup>(<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</sup> Bertaux et al. found that the higher the dilation of the
aortic root, the smaller and more mobile the atrial septum becomes; they also found that
in the presence of PFO, this change would potentiate (proportionally to the ectasia
size) the right-to-left shunt.<sup>(<xref rid="B09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</sup></p>
      <p>Platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome greatly affects the quality of life of patients. Thus,
repairing the atrial septal defect is essential for the relief of symptoms. In the
literature, both percutaneous and surgical treatments are indicated to be effective.
However, percutaneous PFO closure is associated with high success rates when implanting
the prosthesis and with a low risk of complications.<sup>(<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>)</sup> This technique may be more highly recommended in some
situations, such as in the case of our patient, because it avoids the morbidity and
mortality and higher costs associated with open heart surgery.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>Platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome secondary to a right-to-left shunt in the absence of
increased pressure in the heart chambers is a presumably underdiagnosed event. We
emphasize that one of the proposed pathophysiological mechanisms, namely enlarged aortic
root, has a high prevalence and tends to increase progressively. Thus,
platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome should be considered in the differential diagnosis of
causes for hypoxemia and ventilatory dysfunction in patients with enlarged aortic
root.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> None.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p><bold>Responsible editor:</bold> Gilberto Friedman</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <p>Felippe Leopoldo Dexheimer Neto is a fellow of the <italic>Coordena&#xE7;&#xE3;o de
Aperfei&#xE7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#xED;vel Superior</italic> - CAPES, process n&#xBA;
9868-13-1.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seward</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenow</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
              <suffix>3rd</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reeder</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Platypnea-orthodeoxia: clinical profile, diagnostic workup,
management, and report of seven cases</article-title>
          <source>Mayo Clin Proc</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>221</fpage>
          <lpage>231</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6708599</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Popp</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melek</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garnett</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Platypnea-orthodeoxia related to aortic elongation</article-title>
          <source>Chest</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1682</fpage>
          <lpage>1684</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9404772</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Herregods</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timmermans</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frans</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Decramer</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daenen</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Geest</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnostic value of transesophageal echocardiography in
platypnea</article-title>
          <source>J Am Soc Echocardiogr</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>624</fpage>
          <lpage>627</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8311971</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smeenk</surname>
              <given-names>FW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Postmus</surname>
              <given-names>PE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interatrial right-to-left shunting developing after pulmonary
resection in the absence of elevated right-sided heart pressures. Review of the
literature</article-title>
          <source>Chest</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>528</fpage>
          <lpage>531</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8432148</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chopard</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meneveau</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Right-to-left atrial shunting associated with aortic root aneurysm: a
case report of a rare cause of platypnea-orthodeoxia syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Heart Lung Circ</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>71</fpage>
          <lpage>75</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22999442</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lisboa</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Furian</surname>
              <given-names>TQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vieira</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Shunt direita-esquerda atrav&#xE9;s de forame oval patente
sem hipertens&#xE3;o pulmonar</article-title>
          <source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>e10</fpage>
          <lpage>e12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17364103</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baptista</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castro</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Monteiro</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Provid&#xEA;ncia</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title xml:lang="pt">Aneurisma da aorta ascendente e foramen ovale patente:
uma causa rara de platipneia-ortode&#xF3;xia</article-title>
          <source>Rev Port Cardiol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>445</fpage>
          <lpage>450</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21815525</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eicher</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonniaud</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baudouin</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petit</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bertaux</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donal</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hypoxaemia associated with an enlarged aortic root: a new
syndrome?</article-title>
          <source>Heart</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1030</fpage>
          <lpage>1035</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15761046</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bertaux</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eicher</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petit</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dobs&#xE1;k</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolf</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anotomic interaction between the aortic root and the atrial septum: a
prospective echocardiographic study</article-title>
          <source>J Am Soc Echocardiogr</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>409</fpage>
          <lpage>414</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17400121</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gu&#xE9;rin</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lambert</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Godart</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Legendre</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petit</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bourlon</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transcatheter closure of patent foramen ovale in patients with
platypnea-orthodeoxia: results of a multicentric French registry</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>164</fpage>
          <lpage>168</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15719178</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
