<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amjcaserep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The American Journal of Case Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1941-5923</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>International Scientific Literature, Inc.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26939861</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4780268</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/AJCR.895661</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">895661</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Positive TTF-1 Expression in Malignant Mesothelioma: A Case Report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Richter</surname>
            <given-names>Georg</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>A</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn3-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>C</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>D</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>E</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn6-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>F</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn7-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>G</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-amjcaserep-17-133"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Heidersdorf</surname>
            <given-names>Holger</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>A</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>D</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>E</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hirschfeld</surname>
            <given-names>Dieter</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>A</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>D</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Krebbel</surname>
            <given-names>Friedhelm</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>A</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>E</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-amjcaserep-17-133">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1-amjcaserep-17-133"><label>1</label>Institute of Pathology, Hameln, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="af2-amjcaserep-17-133"><label>2</label>Department of Radiology, Sana Klinikum Hameln-Pyrmont, Hameln, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="af3-amjcaserep-17-133"><label>3</label>Department of Radiation Therapy &amp; Radiation Oncology, Hanover-Hildesheim-Hameln, Hamelin, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="af4-amjcaserep-17-133"><label>4</label>Department of Oncology, Sana Klinikum Hameln-Pyrmont, Hameln, Germany</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn>
          <p>Authors&#x2019; Contribution:</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn1-amjcaserep-17-133">
          <label>A</label>
          <p>Study Design</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn2-amjcaserep-17-133">
          <label>B</label>
          <p>Data Collection</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn3-amjcaserep-17-133">
          <label>C</label>
          <p>Statistical Analysis</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn4-amjcaserep-17-133">
          <label>D</label>
          <p>Data Interpretation</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn5-amjcaserep-17-133">
          <label>E</label>
          <p>Manuscript Preparation</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn6-amjcaserep-17-133">
          <label>F</label>
          <p>Literature Search</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn7-amjcaserep-17-133">
          <label>G</label>
          <p>Funds Collection</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn8-amjcaserep-17-133">
          <p><bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> None declared</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="c1-amjcaserep-17-133">Corresponding Author: Georg Richter, e-mail: <email>richter@pathologie-richter.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>04</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <fpage>133</fpage>
      <lpage>136</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Am J Case Rep, 2016</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license>
          <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>
          <bold>Patient: Female, 70</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Final Diagnosis: Malignant mesothelioma</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Symptoms: &#x2014;</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Medication: &#x2014;</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Clinical Procedure: Radiation/Chemotherapy</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Specialty: Oncology</bold>
        </p>
        <sec>
          <title>Objective:</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Rare co-existance of disease or pathology</bold>
          </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>The histopathological diagnosis of malignant mesothelioma is based mainly on the immunohistological profile of the neoplasia, using different immunohistochemical markers to distinguish between a malignant mesothelioma and a carcinoma.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case Report:</title>
          <p>A female patient presented with a right paravertebral rapidly growing tumor and severe pain. Based on the immunohistochemical findings, we present the first case of a malignant mesothelioma with immunohistochemical expression of thyroid transcription factor-1.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions:</title>
          <p>The detection of a positive reaction for thyroid transcription factor-1 in the tumor cells may not exclude a malignant mesothelioma.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>MeSH Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Diagnosis, Differential</kwd>
        <kwd>Mesothelioma</kwd>
        <kwd>Pathology, Surgical</kwd>
        <kwd>Pleural Diseases</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Malignant mesothelioma is a rare malignant disease, but its incidence is increasing worldwide, strongly associated with amphibole asbestos exposure [<xref rid="b1-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="b3-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. It is thought that the parietal pleura are the basis for malignant mesothelioma; however, there are rare cases of primary peritoneal mesothelioma [<xref rid="b4-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="b6-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The localized malignant mesothelioma is a very rare tumor that grossly appears as a distinctly localized nodular lesion without gross or microscopic evidence of diffuse pleural spread. There are many immunohistochemical markers known to distinguish between a malignant mesothelioma and a carcinoma, including pancytokeratin, cytokeratin 5/6, calretinin, WT-1, D2-40, BG8, MOC-31, EpCAM (BerEP4), Claudin, and TTF-1 [<xref rid="b7-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="b10-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The expression of thyroid transcription factor-1 (TTF-1) is positive in about 85% of lung adenocarcinoma and in thyroid carcinoma cases. Other tumors rarely show TTF-1 expression; for example, 10% of colorectal cancers show this expression, but so far none have been described in malignant mesothelioma [<xref rid="b10-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 70-year-old white female presented with a right paravertebral rapidly (within 4 weeks) growing tumor and severe pain, for which morphine was administered. Since 2003, the patient had been under observation because of stable B-cell chronic lymphocytic leukemia (B-CLL), Rai staging 0, and slowly advancing Alzheimer disease. A cerebral metastasis had been excluded by computerized tomography (CT). The patient was employed as a commercial clerk without particular work-related exposure to noxa, such as asbestos or radiation. In the clinical examination, an approximately 4-cm lesion expansion, painful when pressed, was found in the area of the upper third paravertebral right of the thoracic spine. Further tumor manifestations were excluded clinically and by CT. The CT showed a 6&#xD7;5 cm large lesion expansion with the beginning of shallow erosion of the 4<sup>th</sup> rib dorsal right. The lesion expansion extended continuously from the pleura (there was a pleura swelling approximately 1.5 cm large and 4.0 cm long) through the thorax wall in between the ribs to the margo lateralis scapulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-amjcaserep-17-133">Figure 1</xref>). A vicinal triangular subpleural atelectasis and smaller pleural effusion were secondary findings.</p>
      <p>Using a rechargeable pistol from Barth with insertable Trucut needles (14G), tissue cylinders from the lesion expansion were obtained for histological assessment. The sonography-guided puncture under sterile conditions is preferable, because with a one-person one-hand puncture necessary corrections can be performed quickly.</p>
      <p>The specimens were routinely fixated in 4% buffered formalin, embedded in paraffin, and sectioned into 3&#x2013;4 &#xB5;m thick sections. Then they were routinely stained with hematoxylin and eosin. They were also immunohistochemically stained with primary antibodies cytokeratin 5/6 (Cell Marque, Cell Marque Corporation, Rocklin, California, USA), cytokeratin 7 (Roche Diagnostics International AG, Rotkreuz, Switzerland), cytokeratin 20 (Roche Diagnostics International AG, Rotkreuz, Switzerland), calretinin (Roche Diagnostics International AG, Rotkreuz, Switzerland), and TTF-1 (Roche Diagnostics International AG, Rotkreuz, Switzerland) using the ultra-view&#x2122; universal alkaline phosphatase red detection kit (Roche Diagnostics International AG, Rotkreuz, Switzerland) on a Benchmark XT device (Ventana Medical Systems, Inc). In addition, on-slide positive controls were used.</p>
      <p>Microscopical examination showed monotonous growth with uniform flat or cuboidal medium-size cells with round nuclei and eosinophilic cytoplasm [<xref rid="b11-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Moreover, mitotic activity and giant cells could be detected. A lymphocytic inflammatory infiltrate was verifiable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-amjcaserep-17-133">Figure 2</xref>). There was a verifiable negative immunohistochemical reaction in the tumor cells for cytokeratin 7 and cytokeratin 20. A positive reaction was detected in the tumor cells for cytokeratin 5/6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-amjcaserep-17-133">Figure 3</xref>), calretinin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-amjcaserep-17-133">Figure 4</xref>), and TTF-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-amjcaserep-17-133">Figure 5</xref>). In addition, the tumor cells showed an immunohistochemical positive reaction for D2-40 and WT-1 (not shown).</p>
      <p>The treatment consisted of a combination of radiation/chemotherapy: Cisplatin weekly 20 mg/m<sup>2</sup>, cumulative dose 240 mg. In addition, the patient was treated in a palliative setting [<xref rid="b12-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="b13-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] with a 6 MV photon beam [<xref rid="b14-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="b15-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] from a linear accelerator. The single dose was 2.5 Gray (Gy), 5 times a week, and the total dose 50.0 Gy. Target volume was the dorsolateral thoracic wall. At the end of this therapy, a sonographically measured 50% tumor reduction was achieved. Four months later, no growth gain was detected. The patient required no analgesic.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We present the first report of a malignant mesothelioma with immunohistochemical positive expression of TTF-1. There are many immunohistochemical markers known to distinguish between a malignant mesothelioma and a carcinoma, including pancytokeratin, cytokeratin 5/6, calretinin, WT-1, D2-40, BerEP4, MOC-31, BG8, Claudin, and TTF-1. The expression of TTF-1 is positive in about 85% of lung adenocarcinoma cases and in thyroid carcinoma. Some other tumors rarely show an expression of TTF-1; for example, 10% of colorectal cancers show this expression, but so far none have been described in malignant mesothelioma. TTF-1 is a transcription factor essential for the morphogenesis and differentiation of several organs, including the lungs, ventral forebrain, and thyroid [<xref rid="b16-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. TTF-1 is necessary for the expression of some genes in the thyroid, lungs, and central nervous system. Human TTF-1 is located on chromosome 14 [<xref rid="b17-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In the lungs, TTF-1 controls the expression of surfactant proteins that are essential for lung stability and, until now, TTF-1 was deemed to be negative in mesothelioma [<xref rid="b18-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="b20-amjcaserep-17-133" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. We detected a localized malignant mesothelioma with a positive reaction for TTF-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-amjcaserep-17-133">Figure 5</xref>) in the tumor cells. This was confirmed by the internationally renowned Professor A. Tannapfel, director of the German mesothelioma register of Ruhr University Bochum, who provided scientific consultations. This finding is important for prospective pathological diagnosis of mesothelioma because a positive reaction for TTF-1 may not exclude a malignant mesothelioma.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We present the first report of a malignant mesothelioma with immunohistochemical positive expression of TTF-1. Until now, the detection of TTF-1 seems to have ruled out the diagnosis of a malignant mesothelioma, but now a positive reaction for TTF-1 may no longer exclude a malignant mesothelioma.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors thank the patient described in this study and the patient&#x2019;s daughter for her consent for this article. The authors thank Professor Andrea Tannapfel of Ruhr University Bochum, Germany for her support. Also, the authors thank Mrs. Claudia Noble-Pyott for her relentless and excellent work on this case report.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn9-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <p>
          <bold>Conflict of interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publishing of this paper.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="b1-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sleggs</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marchand</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diffuse pleural mesothelioma</article-title>
          <source>Br J Ind Med</source>
          <year>1960</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>260</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13782506</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Neumann</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>L&#xF6;seke</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nowak</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant pleural mesothelioma &#x2013; incidence, etiology, diagnosis, treatment and occupational health</article-title>
          <source>Dtsch Arztebl Int</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>319</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23720698</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sezer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>S&#xFC;mb&#xFC;l</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abal&#x131;</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant pleural mesothelioma: A single-center experience in Turkey</article-title>
          <source>Med Sci Monit</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>825</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24842043</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frontario</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loveitt</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldenberg-Sandau</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary peritonael mesothelioma resulting in small bowel obstruction: A case report and review of literature</article-title>
          <source>Am J Case Rep</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>496</fpage>
          <lpage>500</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26222965</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tentes</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zorbas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pallas</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fiska</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multicystic peritonael mesothelioma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Case Rep</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>262</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23569544</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ellapparadja</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madhavan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slater</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant pleural mesothelioma with spinal fracture &#x2013; a case report</article-title>
          <source>Am J Case Rep</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>408</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Husain</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colby</surname>
              <given-names>TV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ordnez</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Guidelines for pathologic diagnosis of malignant mesothelioma</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>1317</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19653732</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tischoff</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tannapfel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pathologic and anatomic evidence of peritonael metastases</article-title>
          <source>Chirurg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>1085</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <fpage>1088</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18030433</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Penman</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Downie</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roberts</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Positive immunostaining for Thyroid-transcription factor-1 in primary and metastatic colonic adenocarcinoma: a note of caution</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Pathol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>663</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731609</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dongfeng</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zander</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immunohistochemistry for assessment of pulmonary and pleural neoplasms: A review and update</article-title>
          <source>Int J Clin Exp Pathol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18784820</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Churg</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fiber counting and analysis in the diagnosis of asbestos related diseases</article-title>
          <source>Hum Pathol</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>381</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6281166</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rawluk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hen&#xDF;</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waller</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mesotheliome</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Berger</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Engelhardt</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mertelsmann</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Das Rote Buch: H&#xE4;matologie und Internistische Onkologie</source>
          <edition>5th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>ecomed MEDIZIN</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
          <fpage>796</fpage>
          <lpage>801</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parker</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiggins</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant mesothelioma</article-title>
          <source>Orphanet J Rare Dis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19099560</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Opitz</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of malignant pleural mesothelioma &#x2013; The European experience</article-title>
          <source>J Thorac Dis</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>Suppl.2</issue>
          <fpage>S238</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24868442</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dhalluin</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scherpereel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chemotherapy and radiotherapy for mesothelioma</article-title>
          <source>Rec Res Cancer Res</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>189</volume>
          <fpage>127</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Felice</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Di Lauro</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid development and its disorders: Genetics and molecular mechanisms</article-title>
          <source>Endocr Rev</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>722</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kishimoto</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozaki</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kato</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Malignant pleural mesothelioma in parts of Japan in relationship to asbestos exposure</article-title>
          <source>Ind Health</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>435</fpage>
          <lpage>39</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15540627</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ordonez</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Immunohistochemical diagnosis of epithelial mesothelioma: an update</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>129</volume>
          <fpage>1407</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16253021</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ordonez</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The diagnostic utility of immunohistochemistry and electron microscopy in distinguishing between peritoneal mesothelioma and serous carcinoma: a comparative study</article-title>
          <source>Pathology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20-amjcaserep-17-133">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thatcher</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pickering</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasleton</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sensitivity and specificity of immunohistochemical markers used in the diagnosis of epitheloid mesothelioma: A detailed systematic analysis using published data</article-title>
          <source>Histopathol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>223</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1-amjcaserep-17-133" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Axial CT scan showing an expansive lesion with the beginning of shallow erosion of the 4. rib dorsal right.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-133-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2-amjcaserep-17-133" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Micrograph hematoxylin and eosin staining (original magnification &#xD7;200).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-133-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3-amjcaserep-17-133" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Micrograph immunohistochemical positive reaction for cytokeratin 5/6 (original magnification &#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-133-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4-amjcaserep-17-133" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Micrograph immunohistochemical positive reaction for calretinin (original magnification &#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-133-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f5-amjcaserep-17-133" position="float">
      <label>Figure 5.</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Micrograph immunohistochemical positive reaction for TTF-1 (original magnification &#xD7;400).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-17-133-g005"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
