<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26375230</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4560550</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20153212</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Wells syndrome associated with chronic lymphocytic leukemia<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stuhr</surname>
            <given-names>Petra Maria de Oliveira Duarte</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>do Vale</surname>
            <given-names>Everton Carlos Siviero</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff01"><label>1</label>Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG) - Belo
Horizonte (MG), Brazil.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01">MAILING ADDRESS: Petra Maria de Oliveira Duarte Stuhr, Alameda Alvaro
Celso 55, Santa Efig&#xEA;nia, 30150-260 Belo Horizonte, MG. E-mail:
<email>petraduarte@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Jul-Aug</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jul-Aug</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>90</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>571</fpage>
      <lpage>574</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2015 by Anais Brasileiros de
Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eosinophilic cellulitis or Wells syndrome is an uncommon skin condition of unknown
etiology that can occur alone or associated with other conditions. Typically, it
presents with recurrent pruritic, erythematous and edematous plaques, but it can also
show clinical polymorphism. Besides the cutaneous lesions, patients can experience
systemic manifestations like fever, malaise, arthralgia and peripheral blood
eosinophilia. We describe a case of this rare syndrome that presented with
polymorphic cutaneous lesions associated with a serious systemic disease, which was
revealed through the investigation of the cutaneous disease.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Cellulitis/diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Eosinophilia</kwd>
        <kwd>Leukemia/complications</kwd>
        <kwd>Skin manifestations</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Eosinophilic cellulitis, first described by Wells in 1971 as recurrent granulomatous
dermatitis with eosinophilia, also known as Wells Syndrome (WS), is a rare inflammatory
dermatosis observed in all age groups, without preference for gender and race.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Its causes are not completely understood, but some authors believe it may be a local
hypersensitivity reaction triggered by different factors such as insect bites, vaccines
containing thimerosal, immunobiological medications, viral infections and parasitic
infestations, among others. It may occur as an isolated condition or associated with
other diseases, with sporadic reports of familial cases.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Although it may present a polymorphic clinical picture, recurrent pruritic, erythematous
and edematous plaques are typical, affecting more frequently the trunk, face, arms and
neck, that tend to regress with hyperpigmentation.<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> The lesions may be
preceded by local pain and a burning sensation, associated with fever, malaise,
arthralgia and liver function abnormalities, besides peripheral blood eosinophilia in up
to 50% of cases.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Laboratory evaluation of patients with suspected WS should include a complete blood cell
count, metabolic panel, stool examination when intestinal parasitic infestation is
suspected, and a cutaneous lesion biopsy.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The histopathological examination may show three different stages. The acute phase is
characterized by edema in superficial and middle dermis, with dense and diffuse
eosinophilic inflammatory infiltrate. Eventually, the papillary dermal edema may be
intense enough to result in cleavage and formation of subepidermal blisters. In the
subacute or granulomatous phase it is possible to identify "flame figures" in the
dermis, formed by collagen fibers covered by eosinophil granule proteins and surrounded
by histiocytes and eosinophils. The regression phase exhibits gradual reduction of
eosinophils, persistence of histiocytes and the appearance of giant cells around
deposits of collagen, forming microgranulomas. None of the stages shows
vasculitis.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A mestizo female 62-year-old patient, being treated for hypertension and without other
comorbidities, had presented intensely pruritic lesions on the upper and lower limbs for
18 months, without identification of a triggering factor. During the dermatological
examination, erythematous papular plaques were observed, some of them with superposition
of serohemorrhagic vesicles and erosions located on limbs and back, besides papular
purpuric lesions on the lower limbs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> to
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">3</xref>). Cervical, supraclavicular and axillary hard
and adherent lymphadenopathies could also be noticed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A:</bold> Diffuse erythema and edema, with numerous microvesicles;
<bold>B</bold> - Papules and plaques, vesicles and erosions isolated and in
groups</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-04-0571-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Papular purpuric lesions on the legs</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-04-0571-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Cervical and supraclavicular masses</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-04-0571-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The use of hydrochlorothiazide had been suspended after a prior cutaneous biopsy at
another service, suggesting drug skin eruption, without improvement; prednisone 80mg per
day was introduced, achieving only partial control of the clinical picture.</p>
      <p>The hypotheses of dermatitis herpetiformis, linear IgA bullous dermatosis,
leukocytoclastic vasculitis, Sweet's syndrome and probable systemic lymphoma were
considered and a cutaneous biopsy was performed for histological examination and direct
immunofluorescence (DIF). A laboratory review and interconsultation with hematology were
requested and an antihistamine was started for pruritus control.</p>
      <p>During follow-up, the patient maintained periods of remission and exacerbation of the
cutaneous clinical picture. After lymph node biopsy, the chronic lymphocytic leukemia
diagnosis was confirmed by the hematology team.</p>
      <p>The histopathologic examination showed hyperkeratosis, acanthosis, papillary dermal
edema with cleavage and subepidermal blisters; a moderate, lymphohistiocytic and
eosinophilic diffuse dermal inflammatory infiltrate, extending to the hypodermis,
besides the typical "flame figures" in the middle and deep dermis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">6</xref>). DIF was
negative and the immunohistochemical examination ruled out neoplastic skin
infiltration.</p>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A:</bold> Papillary dermal edema, leading to formation of extensive
subepidermal blisters and diffuse dermal inflammatory infiltrate (HE 100x);
<bold>B</bold> - Detail of inflammatory infiltrate, rich in eosinophils (HE
400x)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-04-0571-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Typical flame figure, showing degenerated collagen fibers surrounded by histiocyte
and eosinophil infiltrate (HE 400x)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-04-0571-g06"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The clinical and pathological correlation allowed the WS diagnosis, with complete
resolution of the cutaneous clinical picture after chemotherapy for leukemia
treatment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>With a polymorphic clinical presentation and relative rarity, WS is a diagnostic
challenge for the dermatologist. It should always be considered in cases with a
diagnosis of bacterial cellulitis which do not respond to antibiotic therapy. Another
important differential diagnosis is the hypereosinophilic syndrome (HES), a
multisystemic disease that may be fatal and presents persistent eosinophilia in
peripheral blood, in addition to the involvement of internal organs.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Other differential diagnoses, mainly due to the histological similarity of the
inflammatory infiltrate rich in eosinophils, are reactions to drugs, Churg-Strauss
syndrome (CSS) and bullous pemphigoid, the latter especially important in cases with
subepidermal blisters. In both CSS and WS there may be eosinophilia, increased IgE
levels, increased eosinophil cationic protein, in addition to "flame figures" and
formation of granulomas at the histopathological examination; what differentiates the
two syndromes histologically is necrotizing vasculitis of small and middle vessels
present in CSS, besides clinical findings such as sinusitis, asthma, mononeuritis and
pulmonary infiltration. Some authors believe that WS, CSS and HES are part of the
spectrum of eosinophilic disorders; therefore, they suggest that patients with WS be
investigated and periodically monitored due to the risk of developing CSS and
HES.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The histopathologic finding of "flame figures" is typical of the disease, although
unspecific. They can be observed in arthropod bites, parasitic infestations and drug
reactions. Leiferman et al consider their presence mandatory for a WS
diagnosis.<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p>
      <p>It is believed that this syndrome is a local hypersensitivity reaction triggered by
different factors. Although the pathogenesis is still not completely understood, there
is evidence that interleukin 5 production is increased, which would be responsible for
migration of eosinophils from the bone marrow to the skin and their degranulation,
resulting in tissue damage. The activated eosinophils apparently also secrete eosinophil
cationic protein, a ribonuclease that is toxic for bacteria and helminths, which might
contribute to the skin lesion.</p>
      <p>In view of the diversity of triggering factors and possible association with severe
diseases like lymphoproliferative disorders, systemic vasculitides and neoplasms, a
thorough clinical evaluation of the patients becomes mandatory.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In general corticotherapy allows good control of cases of isolated syndrome<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> with prednisone in a 10-60mg/day dose,
but the cases associated with other conditions are most often resolved only with
treatment for the basic disease. Other treatments described are ciclosporin, azatioprin,
dapsone and tacrolimus. A spontaneous resolution of the clinical picture is also
possible.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Financial Support: None.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>Financial Support: None.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p><bold>How to cite this article:</bold> Stuhr PMOD, Vale ECS. Wells syndrome
associated with chronic lymphocytic leukemia. An Bras Dermatol. 2015;90(4):571-4</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other" id="fn01">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Study carried out at the Dermatology Service of the Teaching Hospital of Universidade
Federal de Minas Gerais (HC-UFMG) - Belo Horizonte (MG), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moossavi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehregan</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wells' syndrome: a clinical and histopathologic review of seven
cases</article-title>
          <source>Int J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>62</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12581147</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Powell</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramsdell</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rothman</surname>
              <given-names>IL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Eosinophilic cellulitis (Wells syndrome) in a pediatric patient: a
case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Cutis</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>191</fpage>
          <lpage>194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22611749</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ratzinger</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zankl</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zelger</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wells syndrome and its relationship to Churg-Strauss
syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Int J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>949</fpage>
          <lpage>954</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23786445</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boura</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarantopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lefaki</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skendros</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Papadopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Eosinophilic cellulitis (Wells' syndrome) as a cutaneous reaction to
the administration of adalimumab</article-title>
          <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>839</fpage>
          <lpage>840</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16699060</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maiberger</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maher</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>JAAD Grand Rounds quis. Pruritic, recurrent, erythematous
plaques</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>214</fpage>
          <lpage>216</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167424</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Caputo</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marzano</surname>
              <given-names>AV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vezzoli</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lunardon</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wells syndrome in adults and children: a report of 19
cases</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>142</volume>
          <fpage>1157</fpage>
          <lpage>1161</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16983003</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spinelli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frigerio</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cozzi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garutti</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garavaglia</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Altomare</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bullous Wells' syndrome associated with non-Hodgkin's lymphocytic
lymphoma</article-title>
          <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>530</fpage>
          <lpage>531</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18779905</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gleich</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leiferman</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The hypereosinophilic syndromes: current concepts and
treatments</article-title>
          <source>Br J Haematol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>145</volume>
          <fpage>271</fpage>
          <lpage>285</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19243381</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leiferman</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reflections on eosinophils and flame figures</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>142</volume>
          <fpage>1215</fpage>
          <lpage>1218</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16983010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakazato</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujita</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamade</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nemoto-Hasebe</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sugita</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishie</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wells' syndrome associated with chronic myeloid
leukaemia</article-title>
          <source>Acta Derm Venereol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>375</fpage>
          <lpage>376</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23147913</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>FIGURE 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Diffuse erythema and confluent vesicles with central erosion on lower limb</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-04-0571-g02"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
