<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25184920</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4155959</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20143095</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A rare clinical presentation of Desmoplastic Trichilemmoma mimicking
Invasive Carcinoma<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">*</xref>
</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sano</surname>
            <given-names>Daniela Tiemi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Jeane Jeong Hoon</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tebcherani</surname>
            <given-names>Antonio Jos&#xE9;</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bazzo</surname>
            <given-names>Luiz Arthur de Paula Machado</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff> Complexo Hospitalar Padre Bento de Guarulhos (CHPBG) - Guarulhos (SP),
Brazil.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><italic>MAILING ADDRESS:</italic> Daniela Tiemi Sano, Secretaria da Dermatologia. Av.
Em&#xED;lio Ribas,1819. Bairro Gopouva - Guarulhos - S&#xE3;o Paulo - SP, 07051-000, Brazil.
E-mail: <email>danitsano@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>89</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>796</fpage>
      <lpage>798</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2014 by Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted
non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trichilemmoma is a benign neoplasm from the outer sheath of the pilosebaceous
follicle. Desmoplastic trichilemmoma, a rare variant, is histologically characterized
by a central area of desmoplasia that can clinically mimic an invasive carcinoma,
requiring histopathological examination to define the diagnosis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Hair diseases</kwd>
        <kwd>Hair follicle</kwd>
        <kwd>Skin neoplasms</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>The trichilemmoma is a benign solid tumor originating from external sheath cells of
pilosebaceous follicles, and the desmoplastic trichilemmoma is a rare benign
histological variant.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Clinically, it
may look like other cutaneous lesions.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Among the differential diagnoses, we can cite basal-cell carcinoma,
squamous cell carcinoma and viral lesions; the histopathological examination is
necessary for diagnostic confirmation. We report here a case of desmoplastic
trichilemmoma in a rare clinical presentation, simulating an invasive
carcinoma.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Male patient, 78 years old, white, mentioned onset of a lesion in the right
retroauricular region for 4 years, with progressive increase, associated with the
presence of central ulceration and local bleeding. He denied pain and association with
other signs and systemic symptoms. Previously hypertensive and diabetic, with a history
of cerebrovascular accident 1 year ago. Ex-smoker for 40 years. He denied alcoholism. He
denied similar cases in relatives. He mentioned a trauma next to the lesion site
approximately 50 years ago, unrelated with the onset of current lesion. At the
dermatological examination, he presented erythematous tumor with shiny borders and
central ulceration, measuring approximately 2 cm along the largest diameter in the right
retroauricular region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">2</xref>). Diagnostic hypotheses were produced for basalcell
carcinoma, squamous-cell carcinoma and keratoacanthoma. It was opted to remove the
lesion by surgery. The anatomopathological examination was compatible with the diagnosis
of desmoplastic trichilemmoma, without the presence of malignant processes, and
associated with nevus sebaceous of Jadassohn in the periphery of the lesion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Figures 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">4</xref>,
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">6</xref>).
Patient is still under outpatient follow-up, with good clinical evolution and no relapse
of lesion.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Erythematous growth with shiny edges and central ulceration, measuring
approximately 2 cm along its biggest diameter in the right retroauricular
region</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-05-0796-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Detail of lesion in the right retroauricular region</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-05-0796-g02"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>HE. 40x. Panoramic view, evidencing the connection of the lesion to a hair
follicle</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-05-0796-g03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>HE 400x. Histological aspect of clear cells, with the peripheral palisade</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-05-0796-g04"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>HE 40x. Adjacent epidermis with papillomatosis, sebaceous hyperplasia</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-05-0796-g05"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>FIGURE 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>HE 400x. Epithelial basaloid projections of epidermis, involved by fibroblasts</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abd-89-05-0796-g06"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>The trichilemmoma is a benign tumor originating from external root sheath cells of
pilosebaceous follicles, described for the first time by Headington and French in 1962.
In 1990, Hunt and colleagues described a clinical variant of the neoplasm, the
desmoplastic trichilemmoma, characterized by a central zone of desmoplasia, which can
clinically simulate an invasive carcinoma.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The desmoplastic trichilemmoma is a rare trichilemmoma variant and is predominant in
women, usually after the fifth decade of life.<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> A tumor suppressor gene
named PTEN/MMAC1 has been reported as the causal agent.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Some authors consider it to be a kind of viral wart based
on the findings of conventional microscopic sections. However, molecular genetic studies
usually do not demonstrate papilloma virus in these lesions and thus a viral cause does
not seem probable.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Clinically, it is characterized by a papule or nodule usually skin colored or
erythematous, asymptomatic, with a dome-like appearance and a smooth or keratotic
surface, frequently located on the face, possibly involving other locations such as
neck, scalp, thorax and vulva. It presents a slow and progressive growth. The lesion
evolution time can vary from months to years. Occasionally, it presents pearly edges and
ulceration on its surface. It rarely exceeds 1 cm in diameter.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The trichilemmomas are small and circumscribed lobular or multilobular proliferations
composed mainly of pale cells from the external sheath containing glycogen in its
interior, usually with wide connection to the epidermal surface. The clear aspect of
cells is due to the accumulation of glycogen, which can be evidenced by the combination
of PAS stains with or without diastase. A papillomatous surface is common and there may
be acute verrucous hyperplasia with hypergranulosis. Squamous swirls are also common.
There is a palisade of small and compact basal keratinocytes at the periphery of a lobe,
usually with a thickened adjacent basal membrane and periodic acid-Schiff with positive
diastase (PAS-D). In desmoplastic trichilemmoma, histology is similar to trichilemmoma
with central desmoplastic stroma.<sup><xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> The
center is composed of irregular cords and nests of basaloid cells embedded in a dense
collagenous sclerotic stroma. Usually, the lesion mimics an invasive carcinoma. However,
nuclear atypia and mitotic activity are not normally present.<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The desmoplastic aspect of the lesion, characterized by cords of cells wrapped in
fibrosis, can be observed in this case. The knowledge of this desmoplastic variant is
important due to the possible confusion with basal-cell carcinoma. In this case, we also
found acanthosis and pappilomatosis in the lesion periphery, in addition to sebaceous
hyperplasia and small basaloid epidermal projections, configuring an associated nevus
sebaceous of Jadassohn. This variant, known as desmoplastic trichilemmoma, is especially
common in this context.</p>
      <p>Cases of multiple facial trichilemmomas, with sclerotic fibromas and acrokeratosis
verruciformis, may represent an important marker for the Cowden syndrome. Patients with
Cowden syndrome show a tendency to develop internal malignancies, especially in the
breasts, thyroid and gastrointestinal tract. It is important, in these cases, to carry
out an investigation of possible systemic involvement.<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Due to non-specific clinical presentations of desmoplastic trichilemmoma, it may look
similar to other cutaneous lesions. Among the differential diagnoses we can cite
basal-cell carcinoma, trichilemmal carcinoma, cutaneous horn, papilloma, intradermal
nevus, seborrheic keratosis, sebaceous carcinoma, invasive carcinoma and squamous cell
carcinoma. Histopathologic examination is required for diagnostic
confirmation.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Indeed, it is important to consider the histological analysis of desmoplastic
trichilemmoma, for it simulates trichilemmal carcinoma, squamous-cell carcinoma and
basal-cell carcinoma, with direct implication in misdiagnosed cases.<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Immunohistochemical methods can be used
to differentiate the desmoplastic trichilemmoma from other tumors with follicular
differentiation.<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> The
trichilemmoma expresses marker BCL-2 in the most peripheral portion of neoplastic cells.
In this case, marker Ki67 was measured, which evidenced a low cell proliferation rate
(30%), more intense in the periphery of the lesion, which favors the profile of a benign
process.</p>
      <p>Since it is a benign neoplasia, surgical excision of desmoplastic trichilemmoma is not
necessary. However, as it is a rare cutaneous neoplasm and easily mistaken for other
invasive cutaneous neoplasms, a complete surgical excision is advised for
histopathological examination and diagnostic definition. There are also reports of
association of desmoplastic trichilemmoma with atypical basaloid proliferations, such as
basal-cell carcinoma, maintaining the importance of diagnostic confirmation by
histopathological analysis of the lesion.<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>Conflict of Interests: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Financial Support: none</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>How to cite this article: Sano DT, Yang JJH, Tebcherani AJ, Bazzo LAPM. A rare
clinical presentation of Desmoplastic Trichilemmoma mimicking Invasive Carcinoma. An
Bras Dermatol. 2014;89(5):796-8.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn01" fn-type="other">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Work performed at Complexo Hospitalar Padre Bento de Guarulhos (CHPBG) - Guarulhos
(SP), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schweiger</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spann</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weinberg</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ross</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A Case of Desmoplastic Trichilemmoma of the Lip Treated with Mohs
Surgery</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>1062</fpage>
          <lpage>1064</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15209802</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCalmont</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title xml:lang="pt">Neoplasias anexiais</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bolognia</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jorizzo</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rapini</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source xml:lang="pt">Dermatologia</source>
          <edition>2 ed.; traduzida</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
          <fpage>1699</fpage>
          <lpage>1700</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sampaio</surname>
              <given-names>SAP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rivitti</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title xml:lang="pt">Tumores Epiteliais Benignos</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Sampaio</surname>
              <given-names>SAP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rivitti</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source xml:lang="pt">Dermatologia</source>
          <edition>3 ed</edition>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>1151</fpage>
          <lpage>1151</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Topping</surname>
              <given-names>NC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chakrabarty</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edrich</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henderson</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Desmoplastic trichilemmoma of the upper eyelid</article-title>
          <source>Eye (Lond)</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>593</fpage>
          <lpage>594</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10692942</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perone</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaddu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kerl</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title xml:lang="pt">Tumores Anexiais e Hamartomas da Pele</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Wolff</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldsmith</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilchrest</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paller</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leffell</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source xml:lang="pt">Fitzpatrick Tratado de Dermatologia</source>
          <edition>7 ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Revinter Ltda</publisher-name>
          <year>2011</year>
          <fpage>1084</fpage>
          <lpage>1085</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crowson</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magro</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Basal cell carcinoma arising in association with desmoplastic
trichilemmoma</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermatopathol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8721590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rapini</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title xml:lang="pt">Neoplasias Foliculares</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rapini</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source xml:lang="pt">Dermatopatologia Pr&#xE1;tica</source>
          <publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Editora Dilivros</publisher-name>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>290</fpage>
          <lpage>291</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Afshar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Desmoplastic Trichilemmoma - A Report of Successful Treatment with
Mohs Micrographic Surgery and a Review and Update of the
Literature</article-title>
          <source>Dermatol Surg</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>1867</fpage>
          <lpage>1871</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22805188</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pierson</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodman</surname>
              <given-names>OG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trichilemmoma</article-title>
          <source>J Dermatol Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>58</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">759462</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simpson</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Collin</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Benign hair-follicle derived tumours in the differential diagnosis of
basal-cell carcinoma of the eyelids: a clinicopathological
comparison</article-title>
          <source>Br J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>347</fpage>
          <lpage>353</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2730855</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
