<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Card Anaesth</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ann Card Anaesth</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ACA</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Annals of Cardiac Anaesthesia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0971-9784</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0974-5181</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26750694</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4900378</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ACA-19-162</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0971-9784.173040</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Heart to Heart Blog Interesting Images</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cardiac papillary fibroelastoma; when, how, why?</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baikoussis</surname>
            <given-names>Nikolaos G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dedeilias</surname>
            <given-names>Panagiotis</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Argiriou</surname>
            <given-names>Michalis</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Argiriou</surname>
            <given-names>Orestis</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vourlakou</surname>
            <given-names>Christina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Prapa</surname>
            <given-names>Efstathia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Charitos</surname>
            <given-names>Christos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">Department of Cardiovascular and Thoracic Surgery, Evangelismos General Hospital, Athens, Greece</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Surgery, Metaxa General Hospital, Athens, Greece</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Evangelismos General Hospital, Athens, Greece</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>3</label>Department of Cardiology, Evangelismos General Hospital, Athens, Greece</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Nikolaos G. Baikoussis, 45-47 Ipsilantou Street, Kolonaki, Athens, Greece. E-mail: <email xlink:href="nikolaos.baikoussis@gmail.com">nikolaos.baikoussis@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jan-Mar</season>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>162</fpage>
      <lpage>165</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; 2016 Annals of Cardiac Anaesthesia</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We would like to present an interesting case operated on in our department and discuss the international bibliography about this issue. We also present some interesting images of this case. Our material is composed from a 68-year-old woman treated by the authors. She presented with a small murmur in the auscultation while she was asymptomatic and then she diagnosed with a tumor on of the left coronary cusp of the aortic valve with the characteristics of papillary fibroelastoma. On the basis of the potential embolic risk either of the mass itself or of associated thrombus and the possibility of further enlargement, the patient although asymptomatic at the time of diagnosis was referred for elective surgical excision of the mass. She underwent on median sternotomy and through extracorporeal circulation the mass has been excised with the preservation of the well-functioning valve. Through this case, we would like to discuss the bibliography for the decision making in these cases. Hence, the aim of our study is that we have to keep in mind that this kind of friable mass may be the cause of embolism, stroke or coronary artery occlusion and must be excided in a conservative setting, sparing the aortic valve.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Aortic insufficiency</kwd>
        <kwd>Aortic valve</kwd>
        <kwd>Cardiac tumor</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart tumor</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart valve disease</kwd>
        <kwd>Myocardial infarction</kwd>
        <kwd>Myxoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Papillary fibroelastoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Stroke</kwd>
        <kwd>Valve surgery</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Cardiac neoplasms are rare, constituting only 0.001&#x2013;0.28% of autopsy cases.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] They are divided into primary cardiac tumors, metastatic cardiac tumors,[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and intracardiac tumors originated from infradiaphragmatic organs.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Primary cardiac tumors can be either benign or malignant neoplasms arising from the endocardium, heart valves or myocardium.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] Papillary fibroelastomas account for &lt;10% of all cardiac tumors, representing the most common tumor of the valves and the second most common cardiac benign tumor, following myxomas.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] The clinical presentation of papillary fibroelastoma varies from asymptomatic to severe embolic complications with stroke or myocardial infarction.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Cardiac fibroelastomas occur sporadically, exhibit a wide distribution of age, with predominance between the fourth and eight decades of life and it is more frequent in the male sex.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] They are generally small, friable, and slow growing tumors with multiple avascular papillary fronds made of collagen, elastic fibers, and proteoglycans. Their pathogenesis remains yet uncertain.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Although histologically benign, papillary fibroelastomas have the potential to lead in life-threatening complications from embolization of fragments into the coronary arteries, systemic circulation, and pulmonary circulation depending on their dimension, mobility, and location. Cerebral and retinal arteries are typically affected through embolization of fibrin thrombus or parts of the tumor giving genesis to the most common presenting symptoms of neurologic impairment ranging from transient ischemic attack to real stroke. Papillary fibroelastomas can also cause angina, myocardial infarction or even sudden death through direct occlusion of the coronary arteries. It can also cause embolization of visceral and peripheral vessels.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Surprisingly, although commonly valvular, they are rarely associated with valvular dysfunction.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] We would like to present a case diagnosed incidentally with papillary fibroelastoma and underwent surgical excision of the tumor with the use of the extracorporeal circulation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec1-2">
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 68-year-old asymptomatic woman was referred to our hospital after an aortic valve mass was detected on transthoracic echocardiography after a heart murmur was found on routine auscultation. Her medical history was free. At transthoracic echocardiography, a mass 10.5 mm &#xD7; 4.6 mm attached to the left coronary cusp was detected. The mass was a pedunculated, mobile, round, echo dense, and stipple in texture structure, with well-demarcated borders, features typical of a fibroelastoma. It projected into the arterial lumen of the aorta without causing any aortic insufficiency while the rest echocardiographic examination revealed an estimated left ventricular ejection fraction of 0.50 without other valvular abnormalities [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>]. Because of the gross appearance and the location of the lesion, a working diagnosis of papillary fibroelastoma was made. On the basis of the potential embolic risk either of the mass itself or of associated thrombus and the possibility of further enlargement, the patient although asymptomatic at the time of diagnosis was referred for elective surgical excision of the mass in our department. This is confirmed by the international bibliography[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] other than our experience. A median sternotomy and a standard cardiopulmonary bypass were established. After the aortotomy a pedunculated flower-like tumor was found [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>]. A valve-sparing technique with simple shave excision of the tumor was undertaken with particular care in avoiding embolization and ensuring that no remnants from fragmentation of this friable tumor were left behind both locally on the cusp and in the vicinity of ascending aorta and left ventricle. The resected lesion had a flower-like appearance with frond-like projections deriving from the tumor. The lesion was histologically diagnosed as a papillary fibroelastoma [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>]. The patient's postoperative course was uncomplicated. She discharged the 6<sup>th</sup> postoperative day in optimal clinical conditions. A follow-up echocardiogram at 2 weeks did not demonstrate any tumor recurrence or aortic regurgitation or dysfunction. The patient will be followed-up in 3 months with repeat echocardiography.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The mass was a pedunculated, mobile, round, echo dense, and stipple in texture structure, with well-demarcated borders, features typical of a fibroelastoma. It projected in the arterial lumen of the aorta without causing any aortic insufficiency</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ACA-19-162-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>After the aortotomy a pedunculated flower-like tumor was found</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ACA-19-162-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The histological appearance of the papillary fibroelastoma</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ACA-19-162-g003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-3">
      <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
      <p>Therapeutic decisions should take into consideration not only the presence of symptoms but also the potential of life-threatening complications. Although histologically benign, papillary fibroelastomas have the potential to lead in life-threatening complications from embolization of fragments into the coronary arteries, systemic circulation and pulmonary circulation depending on their size, mobility, and location. Cerebral and retinal arteries are typically affected through embolization of fibrin thrombus or parts of the tumor giving origin to the most common presenting symptoms of neurologic impairment ranging from stroke to transient ischemic attack. Papillary fibroelastomas can also cause angina, myocardial infarction, or even sudden death through direct occlusion of the coronary arteries or embolization to a coronary vessel as well as heart failure and peripheral embolization.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Surprisingly, although commonly valvular, they are rarely associated with valvular regurgitation or dysfunction.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] It has also been described multiple left and right ventricle papillary fibroelastomas other than on tricuspid valve localization.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] The left side and mainly the location on the aortic valve are the lesion more dangerous for embolic events.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] The transthoracic, as well as transoesophageal echocardiography it is generally the only imaging, examination required preoperatively except for the cases where the presence of coronary disease must be evaluated. Coronary angiography is associated with an added risk because the catheter may dislodge a fragment of the tumor and lead to embolism coronary or systemic embolization.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Patients with localization of the tumor in the aortic valve will probably need a noninvasive modality like computed tomography angiography or scintigraphy to evaluate the coronary anatomy and avoid the high cardioembolic risk. This in accordance with the bibliography.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] Therapeutic decisions should take into consideration not only the presence of symptoms but also the potential of life-threatening complications. There is a general consensus that symptomatic patients should be referred for curative surgical excision of the tumor. In addition, asymptomatic patients with large (&gt;1 cm) mobile masses especially left sided, as in our case, should also be considered candidates for curative surgical excision due to the increased risk of cardiovascular complications from embolization and sudden cardiac death.[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] On the other hand, according to the bibliography,[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] asymptomatic patients with small left sided nonmobile lesions are being closely followed up with echocardiography until symptoms develop or tumors enlarge and become mobile. In this way, echocardiography proves to be an invaluable tool for decision making. Patients not candidates for surgical treatment should be treated with long-term anticoagulation, despite the lack of guidelines to support this strategy.</p>
      <sec id="sec2-1">
        <title>Financial support and sponsorship</title>
        <p>Nil.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2-2">
        <title>Conflicts of interest</title>
        <p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baikoussis</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Papakonstantinou</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dedeilias</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Argiriou</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Apostolakis</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koletsis</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cardiac tumors: A retrospective multicenter institutional study</article-title>
          <source>J BUON</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1115</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26416065</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Castillo</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silvay</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization and management of cardiac tumors</article-title>
          <source>Semin Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472615</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Long</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiological and pathological characteristics of cardiac tumors: A clinical study of 242 cases</article-title>
          <source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>636</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17670730</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cohn</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cardiac Surgery in the Adult</article-title>
          <year>2008</year>
          <edition>3rd ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>McGraw Hill</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1479</fpage>
          <lpage>509</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kirklin</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barratt-Boyes</surname>
              <given-names>BG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cardiac Surgery</article-title>
          <year>2003</year>
          <edition>3rd ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Churchill Livingstone</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1679</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koniari</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Apostolakis</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baikoussis</surname>
              <given-names>NG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>eComment: Cardiac papillary fibroelastoma: A current assessment</article-title>
          <source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>922</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19828659</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kelpis</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ninios</surname>
              <given-names>VN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Economopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pitsis</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aortic valve papillary fibroelastoma: A three-dimensional transesophageal echocardiographic appearance</article-title>
          <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>2043</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20494087</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Georghiou</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vidne</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sahar</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharoni</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuks</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Porat</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary cardiac valve tumors</article-title>
          <source>Asian Cardiovasc Thorac Ann</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>226</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519288</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parthenakis</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nyktari</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patrianakos</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pitsis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asimaki</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vardas</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Asymptomatic papillary fibroelastoma of the aortic valve in a young woman-a case report</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Ultrasound</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19725951</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gopaldas</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atluri</surname>
              <given-names>PV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blaustein</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bakaeen</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huh</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Papillary fibroelastoma of the aortic valve: Operative approaches upon incidental discovery</article-title>
          <source>Tex Heart Inst J</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>160</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19436815</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
