<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27279944</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4885693</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-23-117</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2016.23.117.9198</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A rare case of dermatomyositis revealed during pregnancy with good outcome</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Awatef</surname>
            <given-names>Kelati</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&amp;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Salim</surname>
            <given-names>Gallouj</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zahra</surname>
            <given-names>Mernissi Fatima</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>University Hospital Hassan II of Fez, Department of Dermatology, Morocco</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>&amp;</label>Corresponding author: Awatef Kelati, University Hospital Hassan II of Fez, Department of Dermatology, Morocco</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>23</volume>
      <elocation-id>117</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Kelati Awatef et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>There are only few case reports in the literature documenting outcome of pregnancy in patients with DM in contrast with those of other connective tissue diseases especially when dermatomyositis is revealed during pregnancy, most of the publications reported a poor prognosis for both the mother and the fetus, yet, in our case we confirmed the results of the rare recent cases that have tended to show a good outcome, after the treatment with glucocorticoid and immunosuppressant therapy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Dermatomyositis</kwd>
        <kwd>pregnancy</kwd>
        <kwd>good outcome</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Dermatomyositis (DM) is an idiopathic connective tissue disease characterized by specific cutaneous findings and inflammatory lesions in the muscle biopsy [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The onset of dermatomyositis during pregnancy is a rare event [<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. 17% of DM known before pregnancy will relapse during the pregnancy period and when the DM begins or relapses during pregnancy, the prognosis is pejorative with fetal death in 50% of cases, but successful therapy will permit a satisfactory result [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. We report a rare case of DM revealed during pregnancy with a good outcome after using oral corticosteroids.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Patient and observation</title>
      <p>A 28-year-old woman in the third month of pregnancy, who presented with a pruritic rash of the face, hands, buttocks and the thighs that appeared at 4 weeks of gestation. She had not taken any medicine before the rash appeared. She did not complain of muscle pain, with a slight fatigue and there was no personal or family history of connective tissue disease. Examination revealed a pink liliace periocular erythro edema of the face (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>), pruritic papules on the dorsal hands, elbows and a purplish erythema of the buttocks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>), the external surface of the thighs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>) and arms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>), neck and neckline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005">Figure 5</xref>), congestive erythema of the posterior nail fold with Periungual telangiectasia and hyperkeratosis of the cuticle were also observed, neuromuscular examination revealed a slight deficit of the pelvic girdle. Results of complete blood counts, blood biochemistry analysis, and urine analysis were within normal limits. Although antinuclear antibody titer (1:160) was positive, other auto antibodies were negative. A skin and muscle biopsy was compatible with DM with electric signs confirming the DM in the electromyogram. Based on these findings, this patient was diagnosed as DM revealed during pregnancy. Potent topical steroids with Hydroxychloroquine were prescribed, but the eruption did not improve with exacerbation of the erythroedema of the skin and the muscle weakness and the elevation of muscle enzymes, so we prescribed corticosteroid therapy for the patient with good evolution and she delivered a healthy newborn at term. The rash began to disappear progressively after delivery, so, the dose reduction of the corticosteroids was maintained gradually; also; both the mother and the newborn were plugged into the consultation department for regular monitoring.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>DM showing pink liliaceperiocularerythro edema of the face</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-23-117-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>DM showing purplish erythema of the buttocks</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-23-117-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>DM showing erythema of the external face of the thighs</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-23-117-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>DM showing erythema of the external face of the arms</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-23-117-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>DM showing purplish erythema of the neck and neckline</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="PAMJ-23-117-g005"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0003">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Dermatomyositis is a rare medical disease complicating pregnancy [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], various factors have been considered as triggers for development of DM during pregnancy; for example, exposure of the mother to fetal antigens, changes in maternal hormonal status, and the reactivation of certain viruses by pregnancy. Recently it has been proposed that microchimerism may contribute to the pathogenesis of autoimmune diseases [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. There are only few case reports in the literature documenting outcome of pregnancy in patients with DM in contrast with those of other connective tissue diseases, yet, most of the publications reported a poor prognosis for both the mother and the fetus; maternal death has been described and attached to complications of hypertension and the disease evolution [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In addition, prematurity may occur or even fetal death in 50% of cases [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] or the occurrence of Juvenile DM after post partum [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Some authors suggest that the outlook for the fetus is unfavorable when DM is first diagnosed during pregnancy [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], for example, in the study of Gutiearrez et al [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] of 18 women with polymyositis/ dermatomyositis, there was 55% of increase in the rate of fetal loss and 50% of pregnancies ended prematurely and there was no correlation between disease activity and fetal loss.</p>
      <p>Other authors consider that fetal prognosis parallels the activity of maternal disease, which was also reported in the study of Silva et al [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] who published a more detailed series of pregnancy in 28 women with dermatomyositis and polymyositis and concluded that the more active the myositis during pregnancy, the greater the chances of fetal loss. Generally, Optimal pregnancy success can be anticipated when pregnancy is undertaken with disease in remission. Some rare cases [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] have tended to show a good outcome, after the treatment with oral corticosteroids. The use of steroids as first-line therapy is indicated for maternal disease exacerbation during pregnancy, as in the non-pregnant state. Other chemotherapeutic agents, such as intravenous immunoglobulins and antineoplastic agents can be used as second-line drugs to control disease activity and to maintain pregnancy.</p>
      <p>These cases and studies concerns mostly patients followed for DM and became pregnant, but there is only a few data concerning the management, the fetal and maternal prognosis in DM revealed during pregnancy. For example, in the largest series reported in the literature, there were only 2 patients among 98 who developed dermatomyositis during pregnancy with good control of the disease after glucocorticoid and immunosuppressant therapy [<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In our case, we administered corticosteroids after the failure of steroid ointment and Hydroxychloroquine with good outcome, and the prospective maternal and fetal evaluation is undertaken.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="S0004">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Our case documents the theory that, DM onset during pregnancy had good outcome after drug therapy especially corticosteroids.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="S0005">
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The Authors declare no competing of interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0006">
      <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
      <p>Conception and design: Kelati A, Gallouj S. Acquisition, analysis and interpretation of data: Kelati A, Gallouj S, Mernissi FZ. Drafting the article: Kelati A. Revising it critically for important intellectual content: Mernissi FZ. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papakonstantinou</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kapp</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raap</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A mildform of dermatomyositis as a prodromalsign of lungadenocarcinoma: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Med Case Rep.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26851947</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xE9;aux-Ruault</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gil</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Curlier</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Magy-Bertrand</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatomyosite r&#xE9;v&#xE9;l&#xE9;e au cours d'une grossesse et gu&#xE9;rie en post-partum</article-title>
          <source>La Revue de m&#xE9;decine interne</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>S404</fpage>
          <lpage>S501</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chopra</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suri</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagga</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thami</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bambery</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Autoimmune inflammatory myopathy in pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Medscape J Med</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <month>1</month>
          <day>24</day>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18324327</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chow</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatomyositis and pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Obstet Gynecol.</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>589</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3900842</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morihara</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katoh</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Amyopathic dermatomyositis presenting during pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>JAAD</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <month>11</month>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>838</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Another case of polymyositis in pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <month>8</month>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1123</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7396626</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tsai</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindheimer</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lamberg</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatomyositis completing pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <month>4</month>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>570</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4696976</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Satoh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ajmani</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirakata</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suwa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Winfield</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reeves</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Onset of polymyositis with autoantibodies to threonyl tRNA synthetase during pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>J Rheumatol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <month>8</month>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1564</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7983666</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huong</surname>
              <given-names>DLT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wechsler</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Maladies syst&#xE9;miques pendant la grossesse</article-title>
          <source>Revue du Rhumatisme.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>744</fpage>
          <lpage>749</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gutierrez</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dagnino</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mintz</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polymyositis/dermatomyositis and pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <month>3</month>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6704192</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kofteridis</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Malliotakis</surname>
              <given-names>PI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stsiu</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vardakis</surname>
              <given-names>NK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vamvakas</surname>
              <given-names>LN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Emmanouel</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute onset of dermatomyositis presenting in pregnancy with rhabdomyolysis and fetal loss</article-title>
          <source>Scand J Rheumatol.</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10380845</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Satoh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ajmani</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirakata</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suwa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Winfield</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reeves</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Onset of polymyositis with autoantibodies to threonyl-tRNAsynthetase during pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>J Rheumatol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <month>8</month>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1564</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7983666</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Webley</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Usherwood</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burge</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dermatomyositispresenting in pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <month>11</month>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8555034</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Madu</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Omih</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baguley</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindow</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Juvenile Dermatomyositis in Pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Case Rep Obstet Gynecol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>2013</volume>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <comment>ID 890107</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rotmensch</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Binette</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phillippe</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary idiopathic polymyositis and dermatomyositis complicating pregnancy: diagnosis and management</article-title>
          <source>Obstet Gynecol Surv</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <month>3</month>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>162</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2652010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gutiearrez</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dagnino</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mintz</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>&#x201C;Polymyositis/dermatomyositis andpregnancy&#x201D;</article-title>
          <source>Arthritis&amp;Rheumatism.</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6704192</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0017">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sultan</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isenberg</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pregnancy outcome in adult-onset idiopathic inflammatory myopathy</article-title>
          <source>Rhematology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <month>10</month>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1168</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0018">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ohno</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imai</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamaya</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Successful outcomes of pregnancy complicated with dermatomyositis: case reports</article-title>
          <source>Gynecol Obstet Invest.</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1612533</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0019">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kaddour</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snoussi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pregnancy in dermatomyositis and polymyositis</article-title>
          <source>Tunis Med</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <season>Aug-Sep</season>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <issue>8-9</issue>
          <fpage>606</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22987374</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0020">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Missumi</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Souza</surname>
              <given-names>FH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrade</surname>
              <given-names>JQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shinjo</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pregnancy outcomes in dermatomyositis and polymyositis patients</article-title>
          <source>Rev Bras Reumatol.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          <lpage>102</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25577487</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
