<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Trop Med Hyg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Trop. Med. Hyg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0002-9637</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1476-1645</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24990960</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4080567</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.13-0441</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Images in Clinical Tropical Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Intraoperative Finding of Neurocysticercosis in a Patient with a Fourth Ventricular Mass</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">KAVANAUGH AND OTHERS</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">INTRAOPERATIVE FINDING OF NEUROCYSTICERCOSIS</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kavanaugh</surname>
            <given-names>Michael J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fox</surname>
            <given-names>W. Christopher</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Maves</surname>
            <given-names>Ryan C.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AFF1">Division of Infectious Diseases, Naval Medical Center San Diego, San Diego, California; Department of Neurological Surgery, Neurological Institute, Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, New York</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">*Address correspondence to Michael J. Kavanaugh, Division of Infectious Diseases, Naval Medical Center San Diego, Building 1, 2nd Floor (Infectious Diseases), 34800 Bob Wilson Drive, San Diego, CA 92134. E-mail: <email>Michael.kavanaugh@med.navy.mil</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <volume>91</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>5</fpage>
      <lpage>6</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
    <notes notes-type="disclaimer">
      <p>Disclaimer: The views expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the official policy or position of the Department of the Navy, Department of Defense, or the United States Government. The authors are or were military service members. This work was prepared as part of their official duties. Title 17 USC &#xA7;105 provides that &#x201C;Copyright protection under this title is not available for any work of the United States Government.&#x201D; Title 17 USC &#xA7;101 defines a U.S. Government work as a work prepared by a military service member or employee of the U.S. Government as part of that person's official duties.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A 33-year-old male presented for resection of an intracranial mass after 1 year of recurrent headaches and dizziness. Cerebrospinal fluid testing had shown a lymphocytic pleocytosis (163 cells/mm<sup>3</sup>, 59% lymphocytes, 20% neutrophils) with normal protein (42 mg/dL), glucose (54 mg/dL), cultures, and serologic testing. Multiple brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) studies showed enlarged ventricles but no masses. Immediately before surgery, a discrete cystic structure was visible on imaging (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Gadolinium-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain showing evidence of a fourth ventricular cystic structure. (<bold>B</bold>) Histopathology of a surgically removed cyst with i) cuticular layer with microvilli, ii) cellular layer, and iii) reticular layer. (<bold>C</bold>) Dissected cyst (neurocysticercosis) protruding from fourth ventricle. (<bold>D</bold>) Cyst post-excision.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tropmed-91-5-g001"/></fig>). A large cyst consistent with neurocysticercosis was identified intraoperatively. No additional lesions were observed, and he had complete resolution of symptoms. He received 7 days of albendazole, dexamethasone, and levetiracetam per guidelines for a solitary lesion.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Follow-up imaging using higher resolution (1 mm versus 6 mm planes) and volumetric sequencing displayed an extra-parenchymal cyst with a visible scolex lateral to the fourth ventricle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Axial T2. Follow-up imaging 2 months post-surgical. (<bold>A</bold>) 1.2 cm cyst located at the right Foramen of Luschka (lateral recess of the fourth ventricle) consistent with neurocysticercosis cyst with internal scolex. (<bold>B</bold>) Post-surgical image displaying post-surgical changes to the fourth ventricle without evidence of residual cyst.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tropmed-91-5-g002"/></fig>). As a result of surgical excision, there was no evidence of a residual fourth ventricle cyst. His MRI spine was negative, and he received two additional months of therapy until radiographic resolution, per guidelines for extra-parenchymal lesions.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> This thin walled extra-parynchymal cyst was uncovered with higher quality imaging using both finer planes and an ultrafast MRI technique known as volumetric imaging (e.g., fast imaging employing steady-state acquisition [FIESTA] sequencing). Ideally, higher quality imaging would have revealed these cysts preoperatively. However, his films were suggestive of mass lesion and thus volumetric imaging was not performed until the surgical pathology provided a definitive diagnosis. This case displays the role that high quality volumetric imaging plays in the diagnosis of neurocysticercosis.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <p>We thank Daniel Hawley of the NMCSD Department of Radiology and Jeffrey Tomlin NMCSD Department of Neurosurgery for their assistance with interpretation of the magnetic resonance imaging.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="present-address">
        <p>Authors' addresses: Michael J. Kavanaugh and Ryan C. Maves, Naval Medical Center San Diego - Internal Medicine/Infectious Diseases, San Diego, CA, E-mails: <email>michael.kavanaugh@med.navy.mil</email> and <email>ryan.maves@med.navy.mil</email>. W. Christopher Fox, Columbia University - Department of Neurological Sugery, New York, New York, E-mail: <email>chrisfox@gmail.com</email>.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajshekhar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Proa&#xF1;o</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Takayanagui</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Butman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>DeGiorgio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Brutto</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado-Escueta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pretell</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Teale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Treatment of neurocysticercosis: current status and future research needs</article-title>
<source>Neurology</source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>1120</fpage>
<lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030744</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
