<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am J Case Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amjcaserep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The American Journal of Case Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1941-5923</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>International Scientific Literature, Inc.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26262994</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4536868</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12659/AJCR.894394</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">894394</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Rare Association of Sinus Venosus-Type Atrial Septal Defect and Persistent Left Superior Vena Cava Detected by Transthoracic Echocardiography and Cardiac Magnetic Resonance Imaging</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mousa</surname>
            <given-names>Tarek M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>A</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>D</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>E</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn6-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>F</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Akinseye</surname>
            <given-names>Oluwaseun A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>A</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>D</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>E</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn6-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>F</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-amjcaserep-16-528"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kerwin</surname>
            <given-names>Todd C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>A</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>D</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>E</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn6-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>F</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Akinboboye</surname>
            <given-names>Olakunle O.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>A</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn2-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>B</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn4-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>D</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>E</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn6-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>F</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-amjcaserep-16-528">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1-amjcaserep-16-528"><label>1</label>Department of Cardiology, Queens Heart Institute, Laurelton, NY, U.S.A.</aff>
      <aff id="af2-amjcaserep-16-528"><label>2</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, Queens Hospital Center, Jamaica, NY, U.S.A.</aff>
      <aff id="af3-amjcaserep-16-528"><label>3</label>Department of Cardiology, The New York Hospital Medical Center of Queens/Cornell University Medical College, Flushing, NY, U.S.A.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn>
          <p>Authors&#x2019; Contribution:</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn1-amjcaserep-16-528">
          <label>A</label>
          <p>Study Design</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn2-amjcaserep-16-528">
          <label>B</label>
          <p>Data Collection</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn3-amjcaserep-16-528">
          <label>C</label>
          <p>Statistical Analysis</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn4-amjcaserep-16-528">
          <label>D</label>
          <p>Data Interpretation</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn5-amjcaserep-16-528">
          <label>E</label>
          <p>Manuscript Preparation</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn6-amjcaserep-16-528">
          <label>F</label>
          <p>Literature Search</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn7-amjcaserep-16-528">
          <label>G</label>
          <p>Funds Collection</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn8-amjcaserep-16-528">
          <p><bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> None declared</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="c1-amjcaserep-16-528">Corresponding Author: Oluwaseun A. Akinseye, e-mail: <email>oluwaseun.akinseye@mssm.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <fpage>528</fpage>
      <lpage>531</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Am J Case Rep, 2015</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license>
          <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>
          <bold>Patient: Male, 60</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Final Diagnosis: Persistent left superior vena cava</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Symptoms: &#x2014;</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Medication: &#x2014;</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Clinical Procedure: Transthoracic echocardiogram and cardiac magnetic resonance imaging</bold>
        </p>
        <p>
          <bold>Specialty: Cardiology</bold>
        </p>
        <sec>
          <title>Objective:</title>
          <p>
            <bold>Congenital defects/diseases</bold>
          </p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>Association of persistent left superior vena cava (PLSVC) and sinus venosus-type atrial septal defect (SVASD) is rare. We describe a patient with dilated coronary sinus (CS) found to have PLSVC and SVASD.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case Report:</title>
          <p>The patient is a 60-year-old man with history of stroke who underwent a transthoracic echocardiogram (TTE) for evaluation of shortness of breath. TTE demonstrated a markedly dilated CS. Agitated saline was injected into the left antecubital vein to further assess CS. The parasternal long axis view demonstrated immediate filling of the CS and confirmed the presence of a PLSVC. Apical 4-chamber view with injection of agitated saline into the right antecubital vein demonstrated immediate contrast opacification of both atria, consistent with a right to left cardiac shunt. Cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR) was performed, which confirmed the TTE findings of PLSVC and defined the cardiac shunt as SVASD.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions:</title>
          <p>PLSVC should be suspected in a patient with an abnormally dilated CS. In this case we identified a rare association of PLSVC with a SVASD. TTE with agitated saline contrast injection and CMR are useful diagnostic tools for PLSVC and associated cardiac congenital anomalies, respectively.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>MeSH Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Cardiac Imaging Techniques</kwd>
        <kwd>Echocardiography</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart Defects, Congenital</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Persistent left superior vena cava (PLSVC) is the most commonly described thoracic venous anomaly in the medical literature [<xref rid="b1-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]; however, the association with sinus venosus-type atrial septal defect (SVASD) is very rare [<xref rid="b2-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. SVASD, if left unrepaired, may eventually lead to right-heart volume overload and subsequent hypertensive pulmonary vascular disease, highlighting the need for heightened awareness of this association when PLSVC is diagnosed. We describe a case of PLSVC identified in a patient with markedly dilated coronary sinus (CS) and a rare association with SVASD.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>The patient was a 60-year-old male with history of stroke who underwent a transthoracic echocardiogram (TTE) for evaluation of shortness of breath. Initial TTE demonstrated a markedly dilated CS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-amjcaserep-16-528">Figure 1</xref>) and elevated pulmonary artery systolic pressure. To define the cause of the dilated CS, agitated saline was injected into the left antecubital vein. The parasternal long axis view demonstrated immediate filling of the CS and confirmed the presence of a PLSVC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-amjcaserep-16-528">Figures 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2-amjcaserep-16-528">2</xref>). Imaging from the apical 4-chamber view with injection of agitated saline into the right antecubital vein demonstrated immediate contrast opacification of both atria, consistent with a right-to-left cardiac shunt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-amjcaserep-16-528">Figures 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-amjcaserep-16-528">4</xref>). Cardiac computed tomography (CT) was considered for better delineation of the venous anomaly and to define the location of the shunt; however, the patient had impaired renal function. Therefore, cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR) was performed on a 1.5T cardiac magnetic resonance imaging scanner, which confirmed the TTE findings of PLSVC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5-amjcaserep-16-528">Figure 5</xref>, (arrow)), and defined the cardiac shunt as SVASD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6-amjcaserep-16-528">Figure 6</xref>). Moreover, CMR helped to rule out some cardiac anomalies more commonly reported in association with PLSVC such as bicuspid aortic valve, coarctation of the aorta, coronary sinus osteal atresia, and cor triatriatum [<xref rid="b1-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>PLSVC is the most common thoracic vein anomaly, occurring in approximately 0.3&#x2013;0.5% of the normal population [<xref rid="b1-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="b3-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and about 3&#x2013;10% in those with congenital heart disease (CHD) [<xref rid="b1-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. There are variable insertions of the PLSVC. It drains into the right atrium via the coronary sinus in 80&#x2013;90% of individuals, resulting in no hemodynamic consequence, but can cause a right-to-left-sided shunt when it drains into the left atrium [<xref rid="b4-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. During the diagnostic procedure for our patient, SVASD, another congenital anomaly, was found. SVASD accounts for 5&#x2013;10% of all atrial septal defects [<xref rid="b2-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It is located along the superior aspect of the atrial septum in most cases, near the entry of the superior vena cava. SVASD is caused by abnormal fusion between the embryonic sinus venosus and the atrium [<xref rid="b5-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. It may be asymptomatic in childhood but may become symptomatic with age. Unrepaired SVASD eventually leads to right-heart volume overload and can ultimately lead to hypertensive pulmonary vascular disease as was present in our patient.</p>
      <p>PLSVC have practical implications when performing procedures such as right-heart catheterization or new therapeutic techniques that make use of the cardiac veins overlying the left ventricle, such as left ventricular pacing or percutaneous <italic>in situ</italic> coronary venous arterialization [<xref rid="b4-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="b6-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Swan-Ganz catheter placement can also be challenging as it is performed at the bedside. PLSVC can complicate permanent pacemaker and implantable cardioverter defibrillator placement. Serious complications such as arrhythmia, cardiogenic shock, cardiac tamponade, and coronary sinus thrombosis have been reported when pacemaker leads or catheters have been inserted via PLSVC [<xref rid="b4-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, the association of PLSVC and SVASD is very rare [<xref rid="b2-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and few cases have been reported in the literature. The presence of dilated CS in the absence of elevated right-sided filling pressure, enhancement of dilated CS before the right atrium (RA) following the injection of contrast into the left arm vein, and normal transit of contrast with RA opacification before the CS after injection of contrast in right arm are echocardiographic criteria for PLSVC diagnosis [<xref rid="b4-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Transesophageal echocardiogram (TEE) improves diagnostic accuracy of SVASD [<xref rid="b7-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and it has also been shown to be superior to TTE in this regard [<xref rid="b8-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Cardiac CT was not performed due to our patient&#x2019;s poor renal function. Cardiac CT has been used by numerous studies to assess congenital cardiac malformations [<xref rid="b9-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="b10-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and PLSVC [<xref rid="b6-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. It is a non- invasive test that allows for accurate and rapid evaluation of cardiac and vascular structures [<xref rid="b11-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and shows a clear spatial relationship of the heart with its surrounding structures [<xref rid="b12-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. A recent study pointed out the usefulness of cardiac CT, especially 3D helical CT angiography, in the evaluation of extracardiac anomalies in infants with complex CHD [<xref rid="b13-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>CMR can achieve a detailed cardiac morphologic imaging, assess vascular flow and cardiac function, and can also be applied in the work-up of CHD [<xref rid="b14-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. It is capable of providing qualitative and quantitative information regarding the anatomic layout and function of the heart due to recent technical advances in data acquisition and reconstruction, spatial and temporal resolution, and radiation dose reduction [<xref rid="b15-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In a recent study comparing the use of CMR in place of diagnostic cardiac catheterization in the management of pediatric patients with CHD, CMR was associated with shorter hospital stay and lower rate of complications, and, importantly, the use of CMR-acquired images in guiding surgical intervention did not result in a statistically significant decline in 30-day postsurgery survival when compared to catheterization [<xref rid="b16-amjcaserep-16-528" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>PLSVC should be suspected in a patient with an abnormally dilated CS. In this case we identified a rare association of PLSVC with a SVASD. TTE is a useful diagnostic tool and agitated saline contrast injected into the right and left antecubital veins can establish the diagnosis of PLSVC. CMR is an alternative to cardiac CT in identifying venous and cardiac congenital anomalies.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References:</title>
      <ref id="b1-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhatti</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hakeem</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Persistent left superior vena cava (PLSVC) with anomalous left hepatic vein drainage into the right atrium: Role of imaging and clinical relevance</article-title>
          <source>Vasc Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>319</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048468</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vercruysse</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fran&#xE7;ois</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Wolf</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Persistent left superior vena cava (PLSVC) connected to the left atrium</article-title>
          <source>Acta Anaesthesiol Belg</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>39</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20593643</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Biffi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boriani</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frabetti</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Left superior vena cava persistence in patients undergoing pacemaker or cardioverter-defibrillator Implantation. A 10-year experience</article-title>
          <source>Chest</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11451829</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goyal</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Punnam</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verma</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ruberg</surname>
              <given-names>FL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Persistent left superior vena cava: A case report and review of literature</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Ultr</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sadler</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Langman&#x2019;s Medical Embryology</source>
          <edition>7th</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Williams and Wilkins</publisher-name>
          <year>1995</year>
          <fpage>221</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gerber</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuzo</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Images in cardiovascular medicine. Persistent left superior vena cava demonstrated with multislice spiral computed tomography</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>105</volume>
          <issue>14</issue>
          <fpage>e79</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11940557</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Donovan</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kassop</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liotta</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hulten</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sinus venosus atrial septal defect as a cause of palpitations and dyspnea in an adult: A diagnostic imaging challenge</article-title>
          <source>Case Rep Med</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>2015</volume>
          <fpage>128462</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25705227</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kronzon</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tunick</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freedberg</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transesophageal echocardiography is superior to transthoracic echocardiography in the diagnosis of sinus venosus atrial septal defect</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>537</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1991912</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suh</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Helical CT angiography and three-dimensional reconstruction of total anomalous pulmonary venous connections in neonates and infants</article-title>
          <source>Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>175</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>1381</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11044048</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ropers</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moshage</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daniel</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Visualization of coronary artery anomalies and their anatomic course by contrast-enhanced electron beam tomography and three-dimensional reconstruction</article-title>
          <source>Am J Cardiol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          <lpage>97</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152838</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gen&#xE7;</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okur</surname>
              <given-names>FF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tavl&#x131;</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solak</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Truncus arteriosus with persistent left superior vena cava: Cardiac computed tomography findings in an unrepaired adult patient</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Imaging Sci</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24228215</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jao</surname>
              <given-names>Fang C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeun Tarl Fresner</surname>
              <given-names>Ng</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Persistent left superior vena cava: Multi-slice CT images and report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Int J Cardiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>121</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>112</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17137647</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kawano</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishii</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takagi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Three-dimensional helical computed tomographic angiography in neonates and infants with complex congenital heart disease</article-title>
          <source>Am Heart J</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>139</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>653</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Assessment of cardiovascular anatomy in patients with congenital heart disease by magnetic resonance imaging</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Cardiol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>18</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10672611</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Javidan-Nejad</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomasian</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Najafpour</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cardiac imaging in adults with congenital heart disease: Unknowns and issues related to diagnosis</article-title>
          <source>Curr Treat Options Cardiovasc Med</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>663</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24101413</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16-amjcaserep-16-528">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heathfield</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hussain</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qureshi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging in congenital heart disease as an alternative to diagnostic invasive cardiac catheterization: A single center experience</article-title>
          <source>Congenit Heart Dis</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>322</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23331640</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f1-amjcaserep-16-528" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Parasternal long axis view of the CS without saline contrast injection into the left antecubital vein.</p>
        <p>CS &#x2013; coronary sinus.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-16-528-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f2-amjcaserep-16-528" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Parasternal long axis view with saline contrast injected into the left antecubital vein demonstrating immediate filling of the coronary sinus consistent with the presence of a persistent left superior vena cava.</p>
        <p>* Filling of coronary sinus.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-16-528-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f3-amjcaserep-16-528" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Apical 4-chamber view without saline contrast injection into the right antecubital vein. RA &#x2013; right atrium, LA &#x2013; left atrium.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-16-528-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f4-amjcaserep-16-528" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Apical 4-chamber view with saline contrast injected into the right antecubital vein demonstrating immediate contrast opacification of both atria, consistent with a right-to-left cardiac shunt. RA &#x2013; right atrium, LA &#x2013; left atrium.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-16-528-g004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f5-amjcaserep-16-528" position="float">
      <label>Figure 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Cardiac magnetic resonance confirming the findings of persistent left superior vena cava (arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-16-528-g005"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f6-amjcaserep-16-528" position="float">
      <label>Figure 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Cardiac magnetic resonance confirming the cardiac shunt as sinus venosus-type atrial septal defect (arrow head).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="amjcaserep-16-528-g006"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
