<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arq. Bras. Cardiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Arq. Bras. Cardiol.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cardiologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0066-782X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1678-4170</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24217435</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4062378</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/abc.20130194</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Renal Denervation by Ablation with Innovative Technique in Resistant
Hypertension</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bortolotto</surname>
            <given-names>Luiz Aparecido</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Midlej-Brito</surname>
            <given-names>Thiago</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pisani</surname>
            <given-names>Cristiano</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Costa-Hong</surname>
            <given-names>Val&#xE9;ria</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Scanavacca</surname>
            <given-names>Maur&#xED;cio</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff>INCOR - Instituto do Cora&#xE7;&#xE3;o da Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de S&#xE3;o
Paulo, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP - Brazil</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c01"><bold>Mailing Address: Thiago Midlej-Brito,</bold> Rua Dr. En&#xE9;as de Carvalho
Aguiar, 44, Cerqueira C&#xE9;sar. Postal Code 05403-000, S&#xE3;o Paulo - SP - Brazil.
E-mail: <email>thiagomidlej@gmail.com</email>,
<email>thiagomidlej@yahoo.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>101</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>e77</fpage>
      <lpage>e79</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>04</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any
medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Denervation</kwd>
        <kwd>Hypertension</kwd>
        <kwd>Catheter Ablation</kwd>
        <kwd>Sympathetic Nervous System</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Hypertension is the cause of thousands of deaths annually<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>, and half of the patients treated present
controlled blood pressure (BP)<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>.
Resistant hypertension (RH)is defined when the BP remains above the recommended
targets with the use of three antihypertensive drugs with synergistic actions at
maximum doses recommended and tolerated, preferably one being a diuretic, or when in
use of four or more anti-hypertensive drugs, even with controlled BP<sup><xref rid="r03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. It is estimated that 12%-15% of
persons with hypertension are considered resistant, with high risk of cardiovascular
morbidity and mortality<sup><xref rid="r04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The pathogenesis of hypertension is multifactorial, but the sympathetic activity
plays an important role, especially in patients with resistant
hypertension<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Efferent
renal sympathetic activity stimulates renin release, increases sodium reabsorption
and reduces renal blood flow and may be a mechanism for the development and
maintenance of hypertension<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>.
Genetic, behavioral and environmental factors influence increased sympathetic
activity in persons with hypertension<sup><xref rid="r05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>New therapies aiming to reduce sympathetic activity have been developed. Renal
Sympathetic Denervation (RSD) by radiofrequency catheter ablation of renal arteries
has been shown to control BP in resistant hypertension<sup><xref rid="r06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> and in
associated clinical conditions such as sleep destructive apnea<sup><xref rid="r08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> and insulin resistance<sup><xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>The main RSD clinical studies used a specific catheter not yet available in Brazil,
but the radiofrequency ablation of arrhythmias is a procedure that has been
performed by electrophysiologists through appropriate catheters for years in our
country. Experimental studies of RSD with catheters used for ablation of arrhythmias
indicated the possibility of using these to replace those used in international
studies, considering the unavailability of those in our reality. Based on this, for
the procedure to be reported, the model used for ablation in children (4 mm tip and
5F), which was proven to be more appropriate, was chosen. The objective of the
report is to show the result of the first RSD in our community, with the aid of
technology used in cardiac arrhythmias.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>39-year-old woman was admitted to our institution with a history of hypertension
since age 17. At age 29, the patient began to experience episodes of hypertensive
crisis associated with tachycardia, pallor, sweating and dry mouth, and
pheochromocytoma was ruled out. After three years, the patient presented
Cerebrovascular Accident (CVA) without neurological sequelae. Since then, it was
harder to control hypertension and the patient has to use multiple antihypertensive
drugs, while maintaining high levels of BP. In the last year, the patient was
hospitalized due to hypertensive crises, reaching BP of 230/130 mmHg. On admission,
she was using seven antihypertensive drugs at maximum dose (amlodipine, valsartan,
furosemide, spironolactone, clonidine, hydralazine and atenolol). She denied the use
of illegal drugs or other medications that would worsen hypertension. Her mother was
hypertensive, died at age 40 from CVA, and two brothers were hypertensive.</p>
      <p>Physical examination revealed BP 180/110 mmHg (lying position), 182/112 mmHg
(standing position) and heart rate 120 bpm. Cardiovascular examination revealed no
abnormalities and the remainder of the physical examination was normal.
Investigation of secondary hypertension ruled out all probable causes. Doppler
echocardiography showed no abnormalities and 24-hour Holter showed no
arrhythmias.</p>
      <p>As the patient presented hypertension resistant to several medications, the medical
staff suggested RSD by ablation and the patient accepted after explanation of risks
and benefits. The patient read and signed the Informed Consent Form, since it was
the first procedure in Brazil.</p>
      <p>The RSD procedure was conducted on August 25, 2011 by the Electrophysiology team.
Access to the renal artery was through the femoral artery and anatomy eligible for
the procedure was confirmed by angiography after selective catheterization. For
renal ablation, a 5F catheter was used (Mariner Series AblationCatheters,
Medtronics) and positioned in the aorta, retrograde in the renal artery, guided by
radioscopy and connected to a radiofrequency (RF) generator. An electroanatomic map
(EnSite System, StJude Medical) of the aorta and the renal arteries was constructed
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>) and four RF applications in
each renal artery were planned, distal to proximal, separated longitudinally and in
rotation (helical), with markings on the map (white dots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure 1</xref>). After that, the catheter was introduced into each
renal artery and four RF applications were made (8W, 60 &#xBA;C, 120s) per artery in the
regions previously marked (red dots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Figure
1</xref>). The patient was under general anesthesia, with BP monitored during
the procedure, which occurred without complications. At the end, the patient was
awakened from anesthesia reporting mild lower back discomfort that improved after
administration of painkiller. A new selective angiography showed no
abnormalities.</p>
      <fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Electroanatomic map of the aorta and renal arteries with markings for
ablation. The white dots show areas manually marked where application of RF
was planned, and the red dots show the areas where RF application was done.
On the left, anteroposterior view and on the right, posteroanterior
view.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="abc-101-04-0e77-g01"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Six months after the procedure, the patient had lower office and ABPM BP, in use of
four classes of antihypertensive drugs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table
1</xref>). After one year, the patient remained little symptomatic, with
improved quality of life, without any serious hypertensive crisis. Evolutionary
office and ABPM BP data, as well as the arterial properties are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>. After six months, angiography of
renal arteries showed no stenosis.</p>
      <table-wrap id="t01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Office and 24-h ABPM blood pressure, and arterial function parameters before
and after renal denervation</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="rows">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Variables</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>Pre</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>6 months</bold>
              </th>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>1 year</bold>
              </th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Office BP (mmHg)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180/110</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160/100</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150/100</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daytime BP (mmHg)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190/121</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162/107</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146/100</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nighttime BP (mmHg)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170/ 117</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 / 77</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 /75</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carotid distension (%)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,65</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,95</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">APWV (m/s)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,3</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn>
            <p>APWV: aortic pulse wave velocity; BP: blood pressure.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This is the first experience of RSD held in Brazil with catheter ablation used for
arrhythmias in children. The results showed the safety of the procedure, and
satisfactory BP control and quality of life results.</p>
      <p>The first study using this technique demonstrated safety and significant BP reduction
in 58 patients with resistant hypertension<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Average reduction in systolic and diastolic BP,
respectively, was 22/11 mmHg in six months, and 27/17 mmHg in twelve months.</p>
      <p>In 2010, an international multicenter trial studied 106 patients, 52 assigned to
intervention and 54 assigned to clinical treatment. After six months, there was a
decrease in office BP of 33/11 mmHg in those undergoing the procedure compared to
the medical group. Among patients undergoing denervation, 20% reduced
antihypertensive drugs and in 84% BP decreased 10 mmHg or more<sup><xref rid="r02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. There were no serious
complications related to the procedure.</p>
      <p>All studies show high success rate after RSD in patients with resistant hypertension,
with significant reduction in BP, decreased dose and/or number of drugs, without
causing damage to the renal artery or impaired renal function<sup><xref rid="r01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Regarding the case reported, RSD using conventional electrophysiology catheter for
ablation in children (5F) is safe and effective. Adding electroanatomic mapping, we
can accurately assess renal artery sites where the applications were made, since the
strategy used in the denervation procedures is based on the anatomy without
immediate functional evaluations.</p>
      <p>In the evolution, we observed improvement in 24-h, daytime and especially nighttime
BP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>). Increased sympathetic activity
is one of the most important mechanisms of the absence of nocturnal blood pressure
falls during sleep, which could explain the effect of a significant reduction in
nocturnal BP in our patient.</p>
      <p>We also assessed arterial properties through measurements of pulse wave velocity and
carotid distension. These rates are markers of arterial function, whose changes may
be involved in the mechanisms of difficulty in controlling BP. Increased sympathetic
activity can increase arterial stiffness in patients with resistant hypertension and
improvement of these parameters in the patient after denervation reinforces this
interaction.</p>
      <p>Ablation RSD is a safe and promising approach in reducing blood pressure, and
improves quality of life in patients with resistant hypertension, even with
catheters used in cardiac electrophysiology.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="con">
        <p>
          <bold>Author contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>Conception and design of the research: Bortolotto LA, Midlej-Brito T, Scanavacca
M; Acquisition of data and Analysis and interpretation of the data: Bortolotto
LA, Midlej-Brito T, Pisani C, Costa-Hong V, Scanavacca M; Statistical analysis:
Bortolotto LA, Midlej-Brito T; Writing of the manuscript and Critical revision
of the manuscript for intellectual content: Bortolotto LA, Midlej-Brito T,
Pisani C, Scanavacca M.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>
          <bold>Potential Conflict of Interest</bold>
        </p>
        <p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>
          <bold>Sources of Funding</bold>
        </p>
        <p>There were no external funding sources for this study.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>
          <bold>Study Association</bold>
        </p>
        <p>This study is not associated with any post-graduation program.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r01">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>Symplicity HTN-1 Investigators</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Catheter-based renal sympathetic denervation for resistant
hypertension: durability of blood pressure reduction out to 24
months</article-title>
          <source>Hypertension</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>911</fpage>
          <lpage>917</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21403086</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r02">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Esler</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krum</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sobotka</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schlaich</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmieder</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xF6;hm</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Symplicity HTN-2 Investigators Renal sympathetic denervation in
patients with treatment-resistant hypertension (The Symplicity HTN-2 Trial):
a randomised controlled trial</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>376</volume>
          <issue>9756</issue>
          <fpage>1903</fpage>
          <lpage>1909</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21093036</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r03">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Souza</surname>
              <given-names>WS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alessi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cordeiro</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>da Rocha Nogueira</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feitosa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amodeo</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>First Brazilian position on resistant
hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>576</fpage>
          <lpage>585</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22948302</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r04">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pimenta</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calhoun</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Resistant hypertension: incidence, prevalence, and
prognosis</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <issue>13</issue>
          <fpage>1594</fpage>
          <lpage>1596</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22379111</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r05">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Esler</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The sympathetic system and hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hypertens</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <issue-part>Pt 2</issue-part>
          <fpage>99S</fpage>
          <lpage>105S</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10921528</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r06">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DiBona</surname>
              <given-names>GF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The sympathetic nervous system and hypertension: recent
developments</article-title>
          <source>Hypertension</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14707153</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r07">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DiBona</surname>
              <given-names>GF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kopp</surname>
              <given-names>UC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neural control of renal function</article-title>
          <source>Physiol Rev</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>75</fpage>
          <lpage>197</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9016301</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r08">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baguet</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barone-Rochette</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>P&#xE9;pin</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hypertension and obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome: current
perspectives</article-title>
          <source>J Hum Hypertens</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>431</fpage>
          <lpage>443</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19129854</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r09">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Witkowski</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prejbisz</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Florczak</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kadziela</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sliwinski</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bielen</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of renal sympathetic denervation on blood pressure, sleep
apnea course, and glycemic control in patients with resistant hypertension
and sleep apnea</article-title>
          <source>Hypertension</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>559</fpage>
          <lpage>565</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21844482</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krum</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schlaich</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whitbourn</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sobotka</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sadowski</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bartus</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal>et al</etal>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Catheter-based renal sympathetic denervation for resistant
hypertension: a multicentre safety and proof-of-principle cohort
study</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>373</volume>
          <issue>9671</issue>
          <fpage>1275</fpage>
          <lpage>1281</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19332353</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
