<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27281079</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4907657</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000003777</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">03777</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>6300</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Diagnosis and rehabilitation of deep wound infection and internal fixation rejection in elbow</article-title>
        <subtitle>A case report</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Huiping</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MM</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Lin</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MB</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin</surname>
            <given-names>Ying</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MM</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Azim.</surname>
            <given-names>Anser</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Rehabilitation, Fuzhou 2nd Hospital,Xiamen University</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Medical Technology and Engineering Institution of Fujian Medical University</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Ultrasound, Fuzhou 2nd Hospital, Xiamen University, Fuzhou, China.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">&#x2217;Correspondence: Huiping Lu, Department of Rehabilitation ,Fuzhou 2nd hospital, Xiamen University; Medical Technology and Engineering Institution of Fujian Medical University, China (e-mail: <email>lhp75905@sina.com</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>95</volume>
      <issue>23</issue>
      <elocation-id>e3777</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial License 4.0 (CCBY-NC), where it is permissible to download, share, remix, transform, and buildup the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be used commercially. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-95-e3777.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>This study aims at diagnosis and rehabilitation of a rare case of deep wound infection and internal fixation rejection in elbow. The patient sustained a distal fracture in the humerus 1 year ago, which was internal fixed. The wound always effused and the elbow had pain and swelling; joint motion was limited. Blood sedimentation rate and C reactive protein level increased, bacterial culture suggested deep wound infection, and ultrasound indicated inflammation. The main diagnoses were deep wound infection and internal fixation rejection. Therapeutics interventions were antibiotic agents, physical therapy, operative debridement, incision, drainage, and exercise and physical therapy. One year later, the internal fixation was taken out. His elbow was fully mobilized and the fracture healed. He got back to his former job. When encountered deep wound infection again and again after internal fixation, rejection should be considered. Except for anti-infection treatment, rehabilitation cannot be neglected, or the healing process may be delayed.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>deep wound infection</kwd>
        <kwd>foreign body reaction</kwd>
        <kwd>rejection</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Deep wound infection and foreign body rejection are 2 serious internal fixation complications. The incidences of the complications are 1.9% (closed) /6.2%(open)<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> and 9.7%(metal)/ 3%(polymer absorbable).<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> If dealt improperly, they will disturb rehabilitation and bony callus growth, resulting in bad prognoses. There are some clinical manifestations in common.</p>
      <p>Local incision red swelling and fever, effusion, pain inside, seriously with general infection. Lab exam shows increased white blood cell counts and erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR). X-rays suggest bony callus undergrowth.</p>
      <p>There is a peculiar phenomenon: both exist. It is troublesome to analyze, diagnose, and treat the state, which was seldom reported.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> We present a case of deep wound infection and fixation rejection in a patient with fracture of distal end of humerus after internal fixation surgery.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Presentation</title>
      <p>In October 2013, a 23-year-old man presented with an hour history of left elbow pain and limitation of activity following a fall. His left elbow was intensely painful, swelling, deformed, and joint motion limited without injury in other systems (including nerves and blood vessels). X-ray imaging performed in a community hospital revealed a distal comminuted fracture in the humerus. After left upper extremity plaster fixed, he was transferred to the orthopedics department in our hospital. When he was admitted to our hospital, he signed informed consent. The patient was a builder, right handedness, without any abnormal past history.</p>
      <p>After hospitalization, 3D CT confirmed the diagnosis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The patient experienced the operation of olecroanon osteotomy, distal humerus open reduction, plate internal fixation in 2 days (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). After that, therapy of pain relief and swelling elimination were executed. Ten days post operation, he was transferred to the department of rehabilitation owing to left elbow mobility restriction. Then the left elbow was a little swelling with skin color deep and skin temperature high. The operation incision remained untouched with a little exudation. The elbow was tenderness. The elbow joint range of motion: (flex) 80&#xB0;, (extend) 20&#xB0;, (pronation) 40&#xB0;, (supination) 90&#xB0;. He was arranged exercise therapy, including continues passive motion (CPM) and muscle power therapy. The dressing of the wound was changed. Also physical therapy (ultraviolet, infrared rays, and pulse magnetic therapy) was exerted on the wound. In addition, medicine was used to subside swelling. Two weeks after operation, the stitches were removed. The effusion was apparently decreasing. Also, the swelling subsided. From then on, joint mobilization and muscle stretching were added to prior exercise therapy. One week later, the symptoms were increasing again. Effusion turned into purulent. His C-reactive protein level was 13.67&#x200A;mg/L and his sedimentation rate was 41&#x200A;mm/h. His blood routine test was normal. The culture grew <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. His color ultrasound showed: (1) hydrops in elbow articular cavity and fluidity surroundings suggest inflammation and abscess around the fixation; (2) thickened hypodermis around elbow (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The diagnosis was infection inside. He was treated with antibiotic and cold compress. All rehabilitation techniques were ceased including exercise and physical therapy. With the swelling and pain decreasing, effusion reduced, and the wound healed. So rehabilitation was recovered gradually. One month later, the symptoms were increasing again. His C-reactive protein level was 44.48&#x200A;mg/L and his sedimentation rate was 27&#x200A;mm/h. His blood routine test was normal. His color ultrasound showed: (1) low level echo encasement around elbow suggests inflammation granulation tissue; (2) high-level echo in surrounding muscles around distal plate suggests calcified myositis; (3) thickened hypodermis around elbow (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The diagnosis was infection again. The therapy was the same as before. When these symptoms diminished, he discharged from hospital. During the following 10 months, similar infection and inflammation appeared repeatedly. Except for medicines, some operations such as debridement, incision, and drainage were exerted. One year after fixation, internal fixation was taken out and these symptoms never happened again. Via systematic rehabilitation, he was fully mobilized and the fracture healed. He got back to his former job.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Comminuted fracture in the humerus.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e3777-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>After operation of olecroanon osteotomy, humerus open reduction and plate internal fixation.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e3777-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Hydrops in elbow articular cavity with the low-echo area.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e3777-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Granulation tissue hyperplasia, abundant blood supply.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e3777-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of Fuzhou 2nd Hospital.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Deep wound infection in the presence of hardware after open reduction and internal fixation is a common complication. Staphylococcus spp. are the most common causative organisms of infections.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> Although lots of wounds are closed, asepsis demands of surgery are strict and quality of implants is more and more superior, infections happened sometimes. The implant relevant infection may caused by micro-organism growing in biomembrane. Pathogens adhere to the surface of implants at the beginning, then gather to form biomembrane.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> Free active micro-organism is sensitive to antibiotics and the defense mechanism (antibody and macrophages) of host. Although pathogens living in biomembrane is tolerant to those factors due to protection of biomembrane,<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> exhaustion of metabolite and accumulation of waste in biomembrane make pathogens delaying growth even entering the silence period. Compared with the active phase, the endurance of pathogens to antibiotics increased 1000 times.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> So the existence of fixation make patient susceptible to infection. If the situation cannot be dealt properly, fracture would not be union, even developing to osteomyelitis. Therefore, treatment in early stage is especially important. It was reported that most patients (71%) with postoperative infection within 6 weeks had fracture union after operative debridement, retention of hardware, and culture-specific antibiotic treatment and suppression, whereas predictors of treatment failure were open fracture and the presence of an intramedullary nail.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Rejection is another common complication following internal fixation. As a kind of biological response, it is caused by the tissue injury that results from implantation of the device as well as the continual presence of the device in the body, including the inflammatory reaction and the foreign body reaction. The main stages in inflammation process include acute inflammation, chronic inflammation, and the formation of granulomatous tissue.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> The acute inflammation phase is responsible for provisional matrix formation and cleaning of the wound site.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> The chronic inflammation phase is generally characterized by the presence of macrophages, monocytes, as well as the proliferation of blood vessels and connective tissue to restructure the affected area.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> The foreign body reaction is induced by implantation. The degree of this reaction depends on the properties of the device. Metallic implant belongs to biologically inactive materials. Compared with metallic implant, biomaterial implant has a higher incidence of foreign body reaction.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> As to rejection, the only thorough solution is unloading internal fixation. Although fixation exerts important function, it should be remained in body. To suppress inflammation, anti-inflammation agents can be applied, such as steroid or nonsteroid anti-inflammation drugs,<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> or biocompatible &#x201C;coat&#x201D; around implant.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> In addition to suppressing the inflammatory reaction, improving properties of implant material, suppressing fibrosis and calcification, as well as facilitating neoangiogenesis can eliminate the foreign body reaction.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Improvement of biomaterials has become a &#x201C;hot&#x201D; point in the area of orthopedics and biomaterials.</p>
      <p>From the case, deep wound infection was diagnosed by clinical syndromes, laboratory examination, and imaging examination. He was treated with many programs including antibiotic agents, physical therapy, operative debridement, incision, and drainage. Local infections were eradicated just after the fixation removed. It is rare in rehabilitation clinic. So we should consider the necessary relation between repeated infections and implant. The mechanism of repeated infections induced by rejection may be as following: the foreign body reaction in the local area around implant due to fixation forms effusion and granuloma. Inflammation and hydrops provide suitable circumstance for growth of bacteria, resulting in infection.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>To identify local pathological changes, high frequency colorful ultrasound is suggested. It can clearly image inflammation, granulation tissue, and calcification. When compared with traumatic methods such as puncture and incision, it is noninvasive. When compared with other imaging techniques (radiography, computer tomography, and magnetic resonance imaging), ultrasound offers numerous advantages. It offers a hands-on, dynamic, 3-dimensional, convenient, cheap examination, without radiation. It can also be used to guide percutaneous interventions. It is emerging as a powerful diagnostic and clinical decision-making tool in the musculoskeletal system for physicians.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>How can we effectively control repeated infections induced by rejection without influencing union of fracture and recovering maximum function. To the troublesome situation, we need to deal with infections. Should implant be removed? It was reported that most deep infection after internal fixation of a fracture can be treated successfully with operative debridement, antibiotic suppression, and retention of hardware until fracture union occurs. Just very few implants should be removed only under the conditions of severe, broad, uncontrollable infections. The case is special. Though repeated infections delayed fracture healing and rehabilitation process, the implant was removed till fracture fast union occurs in case the bone lost stabilization leading to uncontrollable infection.<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup> During the stage of implant retention, we terminated rehabilitation except cold treatment when infections appeared and kept active rehabilitation when infections disappeared. So the patient's joint range of motion and muscle power were kept in favorable condition, avoiding some complications disadvantage to function such as joint contracture.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviation: ESR = erythrocyte sedimentation rate.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochsner</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirkin</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Trampuz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>AO Principles of Fracture Management</article-title>. <edition>2nd ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Stuttgart, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thieme</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A prospective, randomised trial comparing the use of absorbable and metallic screws in the fixation of distal tibiofibular syndesmosis injuries: mid-term follow-up</article-title>. <source><italic>Bone Joint J</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>548</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24692626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozkanli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soylemez</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Unusual implant-related soft tissue reaction presenting as a swollen leg: a case report</article-title>. <source><italic>J Med Case Rep</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24927814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arciola</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cervellati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococci in orthopedic surgical wounds</article-title>. <source><italic>New Microbiol</italic></source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>365</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>369</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11718374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trampuz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Osmon</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanssen</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular and antibiofilm approaches to prosthetic joint infection</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Orthop Relat Res</italic></source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>414</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12966280</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bacterial biofilms: a common cause of persistent infections</article-title>. <source><italic>Science</italic></source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>284</volume>:<fpage>1318</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1322</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10334980</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soultanis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantelos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagiatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Late infection in patients with scoliosis treated with spinal instrumentation</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Orthop Relat Res</italic></source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>411</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12782866</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Obremskey</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Scannell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Maintenance of hardware after early postoperative infection following fracture internal fixation</article-title>. <source><italic>J Bone Joint Surg Am</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>823</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>828</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20360504</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshinori</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Upkar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fotios</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A review of the biocompatibility of implantable devices: current challenges to overcome foreign body response</article-title>. <source><italic>J Diabetes Sci Technol</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1003</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1015</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19885290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biological responses to materials</article-title>. <source><italic>Annu Rev Mater Res</italic></source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Current concepts: immunology, monocytes and macrophages</article-title>. <source><italic>N Engl J Med</italic></source>
<year>1988</year>; <volume>318</volume>:<fpage>747</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>752</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3279314</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A prospective, randomised trial comparing the use of absorbable and metallic screws in the fixation of distal tibiofibular syndesmosis injuries: mid-term follow-up</article-title>. <source><italic>Bone Joint J</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>548</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24692626</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadimitrakopoulos</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Dexamethasone-loaded poly(lactic-co-glycolic) acid microspheres/poly(vinyl alcohol) hydrogel composite coating for inflammation control</article-title>. <source><italic>Diabetes Technol Ther</italic></source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>887</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>897</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15684644</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhenyu</surname><given-names>Yao</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The future of biologic coatings for orthopaedic implants</article-title>. <source><italic>Biomaterials</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>3174</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23391496</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Venugopalan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Corrosion on spinal implants</article-title>. <source><italic>J Spinal Disord Tech</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15905769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubousset</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shufflebarger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Late &#x201C;infection&#x201D; with CD instrumentation</article-title>. <source><italic>Orthop Trans</italic></source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Eugene</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Basic appearance of ultrasound structures and pitfalls</article-title>. <source><italic>Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>479</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20797545</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Principles of management of septic non-union of fracture</article-title>. <source><italic>Injury</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
