<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Behav Addict</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Behav Addict</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JBA</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Behavioral Addictions</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2062-5871</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2063-5303</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Akad&#xE9;miai Kiad&#xF3;</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>journals@akkrt.huhttp://www.akademiaikiado.hu</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25786497</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4394851</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JBA_4(2015)1/7</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/JBA.4.2015.1.7</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Psychology &amp; Psychiatry">
          <subject>Behavioral Science</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Fortune telling addiction: Unfortunately a serious topic. About a
case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>GRALL-BRONNEC</surname>
            <given-names>MARIE</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
          <aff>
            <institution><sup>1</sup>Addictology Department, Nantes University
Hospital</institution>
            <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
            <country>France</country>
          </aff>
          <aff>
            <institution><sup>2</sup>EA 4275 &#x201C;Biostatistics, Pharmacoepidemiology and Subjective
Measures in Health Sciences&#x201D;, Nantes University</institution>
            <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
            <country>France</country>
          </aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>BULTEAU</surname>
            <given-names>SAMUEL</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <aff>
            <institution><sup>3</sup>Psychiatry Department, Nantes University
Hospital</institution>
            <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
            <country>France</country>
          </aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>VICTORRI-VIGNEAU</surname>
            <given-names>CAROLINE</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <aff>
            <institution><sup>2</sup>EA 4275 &#x201C;Biostatistics, Pharmacoepidemiology and Subjective
Measures in Health Sciences&#x201D;, Nantes University</institution>
            <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
            <country>France</country>
          </aff>
          <aff>
            <institution><sup>4</sup>Pharmacology Department, Nantes University
Hospital</institution>
            <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
            <country>France</country>
          </aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>BOUJU</surname>
            <given-names>GA&#xCB;LLE</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
          <aff>
            <institution><sup>1</sup>Addictology Department, Nantes University
Hospital</institution>
            <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
            <country>France</country>
          </aff>
          <aff>
            <institution><sup>2</sup>EA 4275 &#x201C;Biostatistics, Pharmacoepidemiology and Subjective
Measures in Health Sciences&#x201D;, Nantes University</institution>
            <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
            <country>France</country>
          </aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SAUVAGET</surname>
            <given-names>ANNE</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <aff>
            <institution><sup>3</sup>Psychiatry Department, Nantes University
Hospital</institution>
            <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
            <country>France</country>
          </aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1">
        <institution><sup>1</sup>Addictology Department, Nantes University Hospital</institution>
        <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
        <country>France</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A2">
        <institution><sup>2</sup>EA 4275 &#x201C;Biostatistics, Pharmacoepidemiology and Subjective Measures
in Health Sciences&#x201D;, Nantes University</institution>
        <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
        <country>France</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A3">
        <institution><sup>3</sup>Psychiatry Department, Nantes University Hospital</institution>
        <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
        <country>France</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="A4">
        <institution><sup>4</sup>Pharmacology Department, Nantes University Hospital</institution>
        <addr-line>Nantes</addr-line>
        <country>France</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="FN1">
          <p>
<sup>*</sup>Corresponding author: Marie Grall-Bronnec; Addictology
Department, Nantes University Hospital, Pavillon Louis Philippe, H&#xF4;pital
Saint Jacques, 85, rue Saint Jacques, 44093 Nantes cedex 1, France; Phone:
+33(0)240846116; Fax: +33(0)240846118; E-mail:
marie.bronnec@chu-nantes.fr</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>27</fpage>
      <lpage>31</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2015, Akad&#xE9;miai Kiad&#xF3;,
Budapest</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="st1">
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Constant social change brings about new forms of behavior, such as smartphone
use, social networking, indoor tanning, cosmetic surgery, etc., that could
become excessive or even lead to new forms of addictive disorders.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st2">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>We report the case of a woman who starts consulting for &#x201C;clairvoyance
addiction&#x201D;. We then discuss the addictive nature of her disorder, based on
several classifications of addiction.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st3">
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The patient fulfilled the criteria for addiction and her clinical features
were typical of that of addicted people. Other differential diagnoses were
discussed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st4">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>As for any addictive behavior, the interaction of several risk factors should
be considered. They are related to the individual himself, but also to the
object of addiction and to the socio-environmental context. In this case,
all the conditions were met for fortune telling use to become addictive.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="simple">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>behavioral addiction</kwd>
        <kwd>behavioral problems</kwd>
        <kwd>clairvoyance</kwd>
        <kwd>fortune telling</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement><italic>Funding sources:</italic> Nothing
declared.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="Introduction">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Addictions cannot be reduced to substance use disorders (SUD). Indeed, it is now
widely agreed that they can also be related to non-drug behaviors (e.g. gambling or
shopping) and to substances that had not until then been viewed as addictive (e.g.
food) (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Gearhardt, White &amp; Potenza, 2011</xref>).
Whether they are linked to SUDs or non-drug behaviors, these addictions actually
have a great deal in common despite their apparent clinical heterogeneity.
Mainstream thinking on the subject increasingly views addictions as a coherent
whole. This can be observed in the latest version of the DSM. The DSM-5 (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">APA, 2013</xref>) now includes a section entitled
&#x201C;Substance-related and addictive disorders&#x201D;, which combines SUDs and gambling
disorders (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">O&#x2019;Brien, 2011</xref>). Although they are
not included in the DSM-5, several other disorders that are linked to the Internet,
sex, exercise and shopping (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Grant, Potenza, Wienstein
&amp; Gorelick, 2010</xref>) are considered in this section. It should be
expected that this list is non-exhaustive; indeed, constant social change brings
about new forms of behavior, such as smartphone use, social networking, indoor
tanning, cosmetic surgery, etc., that could lead to new forms of addictive disorder
(<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Andreassen &amp; Pallesen,2013</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Harth &amp; Hermes, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Kwon etal., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Petit,
Lejoyeux, Reynaud &amp; Karila, 2013</xref>). Clairvoyance consulting, also
known as fortune teller consulting, is a behavior that may seem harmless, but can
also become excessive. Fortune telling is defined as the practice of predicting
information about a person&#x2019;s life, using for example horary astrology, cartomancy or
crystallomancy. To date, research on fortune telling has only focused on the
sociological or psychological aspects (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Hughes,
Behanna &amp; Signorella, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Irwin,
1993</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Shein, Li &amp; Huang, 2014</xref>;
<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Taneda, 2000</xref>). To the best of our
knowledge, we could not find any study or case report about an addictive use of
clairvoyance. However, blogs and discussion forums on the Internet indicate that
such a form of addictive disorder could exist, since parallels can be drawn with
other more common types of addictions, such as the existence of adverse
consequences, and the help some people with a problematic use of fortune telling
decide to seek from professionals. For these reasons, we found interesting to report
the case of a woman seeking treatment for an excessive use of fortune tellers
consulting. Indeed, this case arouses significant diagnostic issues, but also risk
factors issues, which are discussed later on in this paper.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>Helen is a 45-year-old woman who declares early on suffering from &#x201C;a clairvoyance
addiction&#x201D;. That is precisely why she consults at our department, which is
specialized in the field of addictive disorders. She has no particular medical
history, except for two major depression episodes after romantic breakups, and does
not take any medication. She regularly sees a psychiatrist for support psychotherapy
because of negative life events (sexual abuse and death in her family). She is
divorced and does not have any children. Her career as a manager seems to fully
satisfy her. She decides to seek treatment on account of her excessive financial
expenditures due to the consultation of fortune tellers. Another motivation that
explains her decision is her age. Indeed, she says she is entering a new phase in
her life, after renouncing to the idea of becoming a mother one day.</p>
      <p>Helen first consulted a fortune teller when she was 19. She was then looking for
advice on her secondary education orientation. She points out that she has always
had difficulties making decisions because she is always afraid to make the wrong
choices. She kept a good memory of this consultation, because of the reassuring
feeling it gave her. She episodically consulted fortune tellers over the next few
years. Between the ages of 25 to 27, however, she intensified the consultations,
ending up losing control of her use of fortune telling. She was then in a
relationship and was hoping that the fortune tellers could answer her obsessive
doubts: <italic>&#x201C;Does he really love me?&#x201D; &#x201C;How long will our relationship last?&#x201D;
</italic>and after their breakup: <italic>&#x201C;Will he come back?&#x201D;</italic></p>
      <p>The episode she is currently undergoing dates back to the beginning of her marriage
when she was 37. She repeatedly returned to fortune telling to reassure herself
about the future of her relationship, and increasingly so as it deteriorated. The
breakup worsened the disorder. Since her divorce, she consults fortune tellers&#x2013; not
always the same person &#x2013; on the phone or online, in a compulsive way, more and more
often (up to every day), for longer and longer periods of time (up to 8 hours a day)
and spends each time more and more money (up to 200 euros per session). As she is
never satisfied with the fortune tellers&#x2019; predictions, she will consult again very
soon after the latest call or connection. Every choice she has to make, from the
most trivial (going to the movies) to the most important (making relationship
decisions), leads her to irrationally consult a fortune teller. During the
consultation, she is absolutely convinced that the fortune teller can guess the
future and that his/her predictions will come true. She says feeling excitement
before each consultation, but also nervous tension and anxiety. Consulting fortune
tellers relieves her of this psychological discomfort, but only temporarily so,
after which she feels guilty. This excessive behavior gives her some kind of
reassurance and allows her to make up for her lack of self-confidence. In that
sense, the excessive behavior could be considered as an attempt at self-medication
or as a way to cope with negative emotions. However, Helen knows that her belief in
the fortune tellers&#x2019; ability to predict the future is completely irrational. This
brings major adverse consequences, particularly in financial terms: despite a
comfortable income, she is indebted. She also says having low self-esteem, due to
her inability to resist her strong urge to consult fortune tellers, and due to her
being isolated from the others because of the time spent consulting fortune tellers.
Helen succeeds in limiting the consultation of fortune tellers during short periods
of time, when her financial situation becomes too critical. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> provides further information on this behavior.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>This case report arises three main issues: its consideration as an addictive-like
phenomenon, its differential diagnoses and the individual vulnerability for an
addictive behavior.</p>
      <p>Considering the first issue, addictions might be defined as &#x201C;a condition in which a
behavior that can function both to produce pleasure and to reduce painful affects is
employed in a pattern that is characterized by two key features: (1) recurrent
failure to control the behavior (here, fortune tellers&#x2019; consultation), and (2)
continuation of the behavior despite significant harmful consequences (here,
financial losses and social isolation)&#x201D; (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Goodman,
2008</xref>). We checked that the disorder met the criteria proposed by Goodman
when he described sexual addiction, since those criteria are relevant to all
addictions, whether they are behavioral addictions or drug addictions (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Goodman, 1990</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The addictive behavior is learned by operant
conditioning, with expectation of positive effects (the behavior is then arousal
driven: Helen describes that she is sometimes excited before a consultation) and
with expectation of the release of negative effects (the behavior is then
anxiety-driven and aimed at alleviating anxiety and doubt). More recent concepts
could also be used ((<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Demetrovics &amp; Griffiths,
2012</xref>) &amp; Griffiths, 2012). Griffiths conceptualized addiction using a
&#x201C;component model&#x201D;, with distinct common components (salience, mood modifications,
tolerance, withdrawal, conflict and relapse) (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Griffiths, 2005</xref>). According to the DSM-5, only gambling disorder has
sufficient data to be included in the &#x201C;Substance-related and addictive disorders&#x201D;
section (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">APA, 2013</xref>). But its diagnostic
criteria can be applied to the problematic fortune telling use, with minor
adjustments (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <p>
<table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Relevant models of addiction applied to the case report</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellpadding="0" id="Table1"><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">DSM-5 model (based on the Gambling Disorder
diagnostic criteria)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">A. Persistent and recurrent gambling behavior
leading to clinically significant impairment or distress, as
indicated by the individual exhibiting four (or more) of the
following in a 12-month period:<hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Needs to gamble with increasing amounts of money in
order to achieve the desired excitement</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Is restless or irritable when attempting to cut down
or stop gambling.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Has made repeated unsuccessful efforts to control,
cut back, or stop gambling.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Is often preoccupied with gambling.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Often gambles when feeling distressed.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">After losing money gambling, often returns another
day to get even.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Lies to conceal the extent of involving with
gambling.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Has jeopardized or lost a significant relationship,
job, or educational or career opportunity because of
gambling.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Not fulfilled</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Relies on others to provide money to relieve
desperate financial situations caused by gambling.</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">B. The gambling behavior is not better explained by
a manic episode<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Griffith&#x2019;s &#x201C;components&#x201D; model<hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Salience</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Consulting fortune tellers becomes the most
important activity in Helen&#x2019;s life and dominates her thinking
(preoccupation and cognitive distorsions), feelings (cravings)
and behavior (she has progressively quit all her leisure
activities, particularly going out with friends).</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mood modification</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Helen says feeling excitement before each
consultation, but also feels nervous tension and anxiety. This
excessive behavior gives her some kind of reassurance and the
excessive behavior could be considered as an attempt at
self-medication or a way to cope with negative emotions.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Tolerance</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Over time, Helen has been feeling a growing need to
consult fortune tellers, and the consultations have to last
longer to obtain the same effect of relief.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Withdrawal</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">When she attempts to resist the urge to consult or
has to refrain from consulting fortune tellers (in the case of
her financial situation being too critical, for example), she
feels tense and nervous.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Conflict</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Helen knows that her use of fortune telling is
problematic, and that it brings very negative consequences.
However, she cannot refrain from consulting fortune tellers,
leading to an intra-psychic conflict and guilt.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Relapse</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Over the years, Helen has made repeated efforts to
reduce and stop this problematic behavior. Her clinical course
is characterized by relapses and remissions.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">Goodman&#x2019;s model<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Recurrent failure to resist impulses to engage in a
specified behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Increasing sense of tension immediately prior to
initiating the behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Pleasure or relief at the time of engaging in the
behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">A feeling of lack of control while engaging in the
behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">At least five of the following:</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E1. Frequent preoccupation with the behavior or with
activity that is reparatory to the behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E2. Frequent engaging in the behavior to a greater
extent or over a longer period than intended.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E3. Repeated efforts to reduce, control or stop the
behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E4. A great deal of time spent in activities
necessary for the behavior, engaging in the behavior or
recovering from its effects.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E5. Frequent engaging in the behavior when expected
to fulfill occupational, academic, domestic or social
obligations.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E6. Important social, occupational or recreational
activities given up or reduced because of the behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E7. Continuation of the behavior despite knowledge
of having a persistent or recurrent social, financial,
psychological or physical problem that is caused or exacerbated
by the behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E8. Tolerance: need to increase the intensity or
frequency of the behavior in order to achieve the desired effect
or diminished effect with continued behavior of the same
intensity.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">E9. Restlessness or irritability if unable to engage
in the behavior.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F.</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Some symptoms of the disturbance must have persisted
for at least 1 month or have occurred repeatedly over a longer
period.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x221A;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Regarding the second issue, the only few differential diagnoses that would better
explain the described clinical situation are an obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD),
a generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) and an unspecified anxiety disorder (UAD). As
regards the OCD, Helen is indeed an undecided woman: she obsesses over her doubts
about relationships and more generally, about every choice she has to make. She
makes irrational decisions when she consults fortune tellers, highlighting her poor
decision making abilities. Moreover, she unsuccessfully attempts to resist her
craving to consult fortune tellers and acts in a compulsive way when she phones them
for a consultation. The effect of consulting a fortune teller seems to be a
transient doubt alleviation more than the feeling of escape we can observe in
addictive behaviors. However, she does not meet the diagnosis criteria for OCD,
according to the DSM-5 (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">APA, 2013</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Her doubts and preoccupations with
her behavior do not belong to the conventional obsessive thoughts (such as
contamination obsessions for instance) and she does not find these ideas difficult
to resist. What she does find difficult to resist is the urge to consult fortune
tellers. The ego-syntonic nature of her behavior contrasts with the usual
ego-dystonic nature of OCD &#x2013; although the ego-dystonic nature of OCD is not always
present (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Grant et al., 2010</xref>). Consulting
fortune tellers, even in a compulsive way, does not make her behavior stereotyped,
since she does not have a chosen way of having these consultations: it can be either
by phone or on the Internet. Moreover, Helen wishes to resist her compulsive
behavior only because of its deleterious consequences. Lastly, a clinical course
composed of periods of relative control or abstinence alternating with periods of
relapse can be observed here. On the other hand, the natural course of OCD usually
consists in a progressive worsening. However, some authors consider that the
obsessive compulsive spectrum includes some addictive behaviors, such as
pathological gambling (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Hollander, 1993</xref>). We
can also evoke a GAD, which is defined as an excessive anxiety state about a variety
of events and situations. However, this disorder can be easily eliminated because
Helen does not think things will always go badly. She simply worries about the
decisions she has to make. Moreover, she does not exhibit symptoms such as
irritability, muscular tension or restlessness. Finally, Helen could indeed suffer
from an UAD insofar as her primary symptom appears to be anxiety. However, the main
diagnosis criteria for each specified anxiety disorder is lacking.</p>
      <p>
<table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Diagnostic criteria for Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (DSM-5) applied to
the case report</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellpadding="0" id="Table2"><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Presence of
obsessions, compulsions, or both</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="3" align="left" valign="top"><italic>Obsessions are defined by (1) and
(2):</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">1.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Recurrent and
persistent thoughts, urges, or images that are experienced, at
some time during the disturbance, as intrusive and unwanted, and
that in most individuals cause marked anxiety or distress.</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"> Helen
experiences obsessive doubts about the future of her
relationship, but also about the choices she has to make in her
daily life. It would be an exaggeration to talk of obsessions,
because her thoughts are not recurrent and persistent, but
change over time.<break/> Moreover, Helen doesn&#x2019;t consider these
thoughts as intrusive and they don&#x2019;t belong to the conventional
obsessive thoughts.<break/> She attempts to respond to her
doubts by consulting fortune tellers. </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">The individual
attempts to ignore or suppress such thoughts, urges, or images,
or to neutralize them with some other thought or action.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="3" align="left" valign="top"><italic>Compulsions are defined by (1) and
(2):</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">1.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Repetitive
behaviors or mental acts that the individual feels driven to
perform in response to an obsession or according to rules that
must be applied rigidly.</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top"> Consulting
fortune tellers is described as an acting-out, resulting from a
loss of control. Helen criticizes her use of fortune telling.
She attempts to quit but fails to resist.<break/> Consulting
fortune tellers is not designed to neutralize her obsessive
doubts. Consulting fortune tellers, even in a compulsive way,
does not make her behavior stereotyped, since she does not have
a chosen way of having these consultations: it can be either by
phone or on the Internet. </td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">2.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">The behaviors
or mental acts are aimed at preventing or reducing anxiety or
distress, or preventing some dreaded event or situation;
however, these behaviors or mental acts are not connected in a
realistic way with what they are designed to neutralize or
prevent, or are clearly excessive.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="2" align="left" valign="top">The obsessions
or compulsions are time-consuming or cause clinically
significant distress or impairment in social, occupational, or
other important areas of functioning.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Her obsessive
doubts and compulsive fortune telling consultations are
time-consuming and cause clinically significant anxiety. During
the worst periods, most of Helen&#x2019;s free time is spent on fortune
telling, to the detriment of domestic or leisure
activities.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">C </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="2" align="left" valign="top">The
obsessive-compulsive symptoms are not attributable to the
physiological effects of a substance or another medical
condition.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Helen doesn&#x2019;t
use any substance or doesn&#x2019;t have any medical history that could
explain her symptoms.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">D </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="2" align="left" valign="top">The
disturbance is not better explained by the symptoms of another
mental disorder.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1" align="left" valign="top">The case
report is better explained by symptoms of an addictive-like
phenomenon.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
      <p>Besides, although it may be tempting to mention the presence of psychotic symptoms
(because of her irrational, unusual thoughts), we would be inclined to favor
cognitive distortions focused on a very specific field of her life. In order to
adopt a systematic and rigorous approach, we have associated our clinical assessment
to a structured diagnostic interview. According to the results of the MINI
(Lecrubier et al., 1997), the main current psychiatric diagnoses (mood disorders,
anxiety disorders, psychotic syndrome) were eliminated.</p>
      <p>Considering the third issue, Helen&#x2019;s clinical features are typical of that of
addicted people <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Goodman, 2008</xref>, whose
personality is characterized by impulsivity (which particularly comes out in cases
of an intense emotional context), and by sensation seeking. Other pathological
personality traits can be pointed out: emotional lability, separation insecurity and
low self-esteem. Moreover, Helen exhibits a decision making profile that is
characterized by poor decision making abilities and failure to make the right and
rational choices. This profile is suggestive of a predominantly executive
dysfunction and is very frequent in addictive disorders (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahn et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Zois et al.,
2014</xref>), even if it is not specific since other disorders involve decision
making deficits, such as OCD (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Kashyap, Kumar,
Kandavel &amp; Reddy, 2013</xref>), Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder
(<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Hauser et al., 2014</xref>) and schizophrenia
(<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Orellana &amp; Slachevsky, 2013</xref>). In
addition, her life is punctuated by traumatic events, with a history of major
depression episodes. Her addictive behavior was onset during young adulthood and her
clinical course is characterized by relapses and remissions (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Grant et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <p>As for any addictive behavior, the interaction of several risk factors should be
considered. These risk factors are related to the individual himself, but also to
the object of addiction and to the socio-environmental context. Individual risk
factors were described above. Regarding the risk factors related to the object of
addiction (i.e. fortune telling use), one might mention, inter alia, the possibility
to consult online, which guarantees anonymity. Furthermore, the Internet increases
both accessibility and availability. Finally, the money spent during fortune telling
sessions seems virtual, which makes it all the more easy to spend. Increased risks
related to the Internet have already been described on gambling (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Griffiths, Wardle, Orford, Sproston &amp; Erens,
2009</xref>). Regarding socio-environmental risk factors, today&#x2019;s society
encourages the need for control and does not give way to uncertainty. In Helen&#x2019;s
case, all the conditions were met for the fortune telling use to become excessive,
and we are tempted to conclude that it is an addictive-like phenomenon. Future
investigations are needed to confirm the relevance of this disorder and to estimate
its prevalence.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN2">
        <p><italic>Authors&#x2019; contributions:</italic> Discussion about the case (MGB, SB, CVV,
GB and AS), manuscript drafting (MGB and AS), manuscript approval (MGB, SB, CVV,
GB and AS).</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict">
        <p><italic>Conflict of interest:</italic> The authors declare no financial or other
related relationship relevant to the subject of this article.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Ahn, W. Y., Vasilev, G., Lee, S. H.,
Busemeyer, J. R., Kruschke, J. K., Bechara, A. &amp; Vassileva, J. (2014).
Decision-making in stimulant and opiate addicts in protracted abstinence:
Evidence from computational modeling with pure users. <italic>Frontiers in
Psychology, 5,</italic> 849.</styled-content>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Andreassen, C. S. &amp; Pallesen, S.
(2013). Social network site addiction&#x2013;An overview. <italic>Current
Pharmaceutical Design, 20</italic>(25),
4053&#x2013;4061.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/13816128113199990616</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">APA (2013). <italic>Diagnostic and
statistical manual of mental disorders</italic>, 5th edition (p. 947).
Association AP, editor. Washington, DC, USA, 947 pp.</styled-content>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Demetrovics, Z. &amp; Griffiths, M.
(2012). Behavioral addictions: Past, present and future. <italic>Journal of
Behavioral Addictions 1</italic>(1), 1&#x2013;2.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/JBA.1.2012.1.0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Gearhardt, A. N., White, M. A. &amp;
Potenza, M. N. (2011). Binge eating disorder and food addiction.
<italic>Current Drug Abuse Reviews, 4</italic>(3),
201&#x2013;107.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1874473711104030201</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Goodman, A. (1990). Addiction:
Definition and implications. <italic>British Journal of Addiction,
85</italic>(11), 1403&#x2013;1408.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1360-0443.1990.tb01620.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Goodman, A. (2008). Neurobiology of
addiction. <italic>An integrative review. Biochemical Pharmacology,
75</italic>(1), 266&#x2013;322.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2007.07.030</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Grant, J. E., Potenza, M. N., Weinstein,
A. &amp; Gorelick, D. A. (2010). Introduction to behavioral addictions.
<italic>The American Journal of Drug and Alcohol Abuse, 36</italic>(5),
233&#x2013;241.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00952990.2010.491884</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Griffiths, M. (2005). A
&#x201C;components&#x201D; model of addiction within a biopsychosocial
framework. <italic>Journal of Substance Use, 10</italic>(4),
191&#x2013;197.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14659890500114359</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Griffiths, M., Wardle, H., Orford, J.,
Sproston, K. &amp; Erens, B. (2009). Sociodemographic correlates of internet
gambling: Findings from the 2007 British gambling prevalence survey.
<italic>CyberPsychology &amp; Behavior, 12</italic>(2),
199&#x2013;202.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cpb.2008.0196</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Harth, W. &amp; Hermes, B. (2007).
Psychosomatic disturbances and cosmetic surgery. <italic>Journal der
Deutschen Dermatologischen Gesellschaft, 5</italic>(9),
736&#x2013;743.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1610-0387.2007.06293.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Hauser, T. U., Iannaccone, R., Ball, J.,
Mathys, C., Brandeis, D., Walitza, S. &amp; Brem, S. (2014). Role of the
medial prefrontal cortex in impaired decision making in juvenile
attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder. <italic>JAMA Psychiatry,
71</italic>(10), 1165&#x2013;1173.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2014.1093</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Hollander, E. (1993).
<italic>Obsessive-compulsive related disorders</italic>. Washington, DC:
American Psychiatric Press.</styled-content>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Hughes, M., Behanna, R. &amp;
Signorella, M. L. (2001). Perceived accuracy of fortune telling and belief
in the paranormal. <italic>Journal of Social Psychology, 141</italic>(1),
159&#x2013;160.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00224540109600543</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Irwin, H. J. (1993). Belief in the
paranormal: A review of the empirical literature. <italic>The Journal of the
American Society for Psychical Research, 87</italic>(1),
39.</styled-content>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Kashyap, H., Kumar, J. K., Kandavel, T.
&amp; Reddy, Y. C. (2013). Neuropsychological functioning in
obsessive-compulsive disorder: Are executive functions the key deficit?
<italic>Comprehensive Psychiatry, 54</italic>(5),
533&#x2013;540.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.comppsych.2012.12.003</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Kwon, M., Lee, J. Y., Won, W. Y., Park,
J. W., Min, J. A., Hahn, C., Gu, X., Choi, J. H. &amp; Kim, D. J. (2013).
Development and validation of a smartphone addiction scale (SAS).
<italic>PLoS One, 8</italic>(2), e56936.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056936</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Lecrubier, Y., Sheehan, D., Weiller, E.,
Amorim, P., Bonora, I., Harnett Sheehan, K., Janavs, J. &amp; Dunbar, G. C.
(1997). The Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI). <italic>A
short diagnostic structured interview: Reliability and validity
according to the CIDI. European Psychiatry, 12,</italic>
224&#x2013;231.</styled-content>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">O&#x2019;Brien, C. (2011). Addiction and
dependence in DSM-V. <italic>Addiction, 106</italic>(5),
866&#x2013;867.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2010.03144.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Orellana, G. &amp; Slachevsky, A.
(2013). Executive functioning in schizophrenia. <italic>Frontiers in
Psychiatry, 4,</italic> 35.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2013.00035</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Petit, A., Lejoyeux, M., Reynaud, M.
&amp; Karila, L. (2014). Excessive indoor tanning as a behavioral addiction:
A literature review. <italic>Current Pharmaceutical Design, 20</italic>(25),
4070&#x2013;4075.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/13816128113199990615</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Shein, P. P., Li, Y. Y. &amp; Huang, T.
C. (2014). Relationship between scientific knowledge and fortune-telling.
<italic>Public Understing of Science, 23</italic>(7),
780&#x2013;796.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0963662514522169</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Taneda, H. (2000). [Fortune-telling and
women &#x2014; contemporary characteristics of fortune-telling in Japanese
society]. <italic>Journal of UOEH, 22</italic>(4), 351&#x2013;362. (In
Japanese)</styled-content>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <element-citation publication-type="other">
          <styled-content specific-use="web-only">Zois, E., Kortlang, N., Vollstadt-Klein,
S., Lemenager, T., Beutel, M., Mann, K. &amp; Fauth-Buhler, M. (2014).
Decision-making deficits in patients diagnosed with disordered gambling
using the Cambridge Gambling task: The effects of substance use disorder
comorbidity. <italic>Brain and Behavior, 4</italic>(4),
484&#x2013;494.</styled-content>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/brb3.231</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
