<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJO</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4738</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1998-3689</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25005211</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4131336</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJO-62-739</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0301-4738.136266</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Brief Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Scleral buckle infection with Alcaligenes xylosoxidans</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hsu</surname>
            <given-names>Chih-Kang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chang</surname>
            <given-names>Yun-Hsiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Jiann-Torng</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center, Taipei, Taiwan</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Armed Forces Tao-Yuan General Hospital, Taoyaun, Taiwan</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence to:</bold> Dr. Yun-Hsiang Chang, No. 325, Section 2, Cheng-Gung Road, Taipei- 11490, Taiwan. E-mail: <email xlink:href="yunhsiangchang@yahoo.com.tw">yunhsiangchang@yahoo.com.tw</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>62</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>739</fpage>
      <lpage>741</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>09</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Indian Journal of Ophthalmology</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We describe a rare case of extraocular inflammation secondary to scleral buckle infection with <italic>Alcaligenes xylosoxidans</italic>. A 60-year-old female with a history of retinal detachment repair with open-book technique of scleral buckling presented with purulent discharge and irritation in the right eye that had begun 4 weeks earlier and had been treated ineffectively at another hospital. Conjunctival erosion with exposure of the scleral buckle was noted. The scleral buckle was removed and cultured. The explanted material grew gram-negative rod later identified as <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic>. On the basis of the susceptibility test results, the patient was treated by subconjunctival injection and fortified topical ceftazidime. After 4 weeks of treatment, the infection resolved.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Alcaligenes xylosoxidans</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>conjunctivitis</kwd>
        <kwd>scleral buckle infection</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><italic>Alcaligenes xylosoxidans</italic> (formerly <italic>Achromobacter xylosoxidans</italic>) is an opportunistic, aerobic, gram-negative, rod-shaped bacterium. It is found frequently in hospitals and can be transmitted by contaminated fluids.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] Ocular infections with <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> are rare, and fewer than 30 cases have been reported. We presented an open-book technique of scleral buckling, a modified technique of scleral buckling using a narrow buckle to close a wider retinal tear.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] Now, we report a case of open-book scleral buckle infection with <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic>.</p>
    <sec id="sec1-1">
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 60-year-old female presented with a 4-week history of foreign body sensation, mucopurulent discharge, redness, and swelling of the right eye. She had been treated by her referring eye specialist for 4 weeks. She had a past history of ocular surgery for rhegmatogenous retinal detachment in the right eye 2.5 years earlier, consisting of cryopexy and scleral buckling using the open-book technique.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] On examination, her visual acuity was 20/50 in the right eye and 20/25 in the left eye. Severe follicular hypertrophy and mucopurulent discharge with pseudomembrane formation in the right palpebral conjunctiva were noted. Exposure of the silicone sponge of the previous implant with surrounding conjunctival erosion was evident [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>]. Examination of the fundus showed a clear view and an attached retina with good buckle support. We sampled some discharge and removed the sponge for bacterial tests. A gram stain of the specimen showed gram-negative bacilli, and the culture grew <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic>. Further biochemical systems (VITEK 2 colorimetric card; from bioM&#xE9;rieux, Marcy l&#x2019;Etoile, France) was used for identification of the nonfermentative gram-negative rod. <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> with excellent identification was also reported. Further, it was susceptible to ceftazidime but resistant to gentamicin, ampicillin, amikacin, and ciprofloxacin. We treated the patient with one subconjunctival injection of ceftazidime 100 mg/0.5 mL and topical application of fortified ceftazidime 5% (50 mg/mL) four times a day for 4 weeks, and she recovered well.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The silicone sponge was opened like a book and buckled onto the sclera. The raised edges may rub the conjunctiva, leading to conjunctival erosion, secondary exposure of the explant, and infection</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="IJO-62-739-g001"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-2">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Scleral buckling is a common procedure to repair a rhegmatogenous retinal detachment. Infection of the scleral explant is a well-recognized postoperative complication threatening the eye and jeopardizing retinal attachment and visual outcome. The reported incidence varies between 0.5% and 5.6%. The surgical technique, synthetic materials in scleral explants, duration of surgery, and size and position of buckle affect the rate of infection.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</p>
      <p>We reported the open-book technique for closing horseshoe-shaped retinal tears of one to two times the width of available silicone sponges.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] In this technique, an incomplete cut was made along the longitudinal axis of a silicone sponge, which then can be opened like a book and buckled onto the sclera by matrix sutures in the corresponding position of the retinal tear. During the past 3 years, we have used this technique in six eyes, and this is the first serious buckle-related complication. We speculate that an incompletely cut silicone sponge may have a tendency to close [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>]. The margin of the cut edges may rub the conjunctiva, leading to conjunctival erosion, secondary exposure of the explant, and infection. We, therefore, should smooth the edges of the four corners to avoid complications when we use this surgical method.</p>
      <p>Most infections due to <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> have been reported to occur in immunocompromised hosts,[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] but it has also been reported in healthy individuals after occupation-related exposure.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Ocular infections with <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> are rare and often associated with trauma, surgery, contact lens wear, and topical corticosteroid therapy.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] To our knowledge, this is the first <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic>-induced scleral buckle infection ever reported.</p>
      <p>Ocular infection with <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> usually induces keratitis; isolated conjunctivitis is rare.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] It is often confused with other gram-negative organisms, particularly <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, on bacterial culture. Because of increased resistance against a range of antimicrobial agents, <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> must be fully identified and differentiated from other gram-negative isolates from ocular infections. Corneal superinfection and ulcer may occur after an undiagnosed <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> conjunctivitis.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] Use of topical corticosteroids to treat conjunctivitis or associated keratopathy can also predispose an already compromised cornea to develop microbial keratitis. According to the previous report,[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] excellent or very good species identification by VITEK 2 colorimetric card assays are reliable to be reported. Polymerase chain reaction also has been suggested as useful to confirm the identity of <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic>.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</p>
      <p>Infections with <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> do not respond to conventional antibiotic therapy, including first-generation cephalosporins, aminoglycosides, and fluoroquinolones.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] Resistance to later-generation quinolones has been less often reported.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] A US-based epidemiological database reports that more than 80% of <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> isolates from blood are susceptible to imipenem (92%), piperacillin (84.8%), and ceftazidime (80%).[<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] According to the antimicrobial susceptibility pattern in Taiwan, <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> is usually susceptible to ceftazidime, piperacillin, and imipenem but highly resistant to ciprofloxacin and cefepime.[<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Empiric antimicrobial therapy with ceftazidime, piperacillin, or imipenem may be appropriate before the results of susceptibility testing are available, and treatment of <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> infection should be extended to 4 weeks to prevent the possibility of recurrence.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</p>
      <p>In conclusion, <italic>A. xylosoxidans</italic> rarely induces ocular infection. Careful history taking, complete ocular examination, laboratory tests, and proper treatment are important in cases of unusual ocular infection.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Nil</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="conflict">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Forbes</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weissfeld</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bailey and Scott's diagnostic microbiology</article-title>
          <year>1998</year>
          <publisher-loc>St. Louis</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name>
          <fpage>476</fpage>
          <lpage>85</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pao</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A narrow silicone sponge to close a wider retinal tear: The open-book technique of scleral buckling</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmic Surg Lasers Imaging</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>263</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21366186</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rold&#xE1;n-Pallar&#xE9;s</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>del CastilloSanz</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Awad-El</surname>
              <given-names>Susi S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Refojo</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Long-term complications of silicone and hydrogel explants in retinal reattachment surgery</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>197</fpage>
          <lpage>201</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10037564</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kiernan</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chin</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sclafani</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saidel</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiple drug-resistant Alcaligenesxylosoxidans keratitis in a sanitation worker</article-title>
          <source>Eye Contact Lens</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>212</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19516143</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>ZL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>KK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsiao</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Recurrent Alcaligenesxylosoxidans keratitis</article-title>
          <source>Cornea</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>489</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829812</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lucatelli</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cantarelli</surname>
              <given-names>VV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Picoli</surname>
              <given-names>SU</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Conjunctivitis due toachromobacterxylosoxidans: Case report</article-title>
          <source>Arq Bras Oftalmol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>261</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19466343</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pan</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heidemann</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dunn</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chow</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gossage</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Delayed onset and recurrent Alcaligenesxylosoxidans keratitis</article-title>
          <source>Cornea</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>243</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10746461</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bosshard</surname>
              <given-names>PP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zbinden</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abels</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xF6;ddinghaus</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Altwegg</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xF6;ttger</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>16S rRNA gene sequencing versus the API 20 NE system and the VITEK 2 ID-GNB card for identification of nonfermentingGram-negative bacteria in the clinical laboratory</article-title>
          <source>JClinMicrobiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>1359</fpage>
          <lpage>66</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weissgold</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kirkpatrick</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iverson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute postoperative Alcaligenesxylosoxidansendophthalmitis</article-title>
          <source>Retina</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>578</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12972784</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shie</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leu</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characteristics of Achromobacterxylosoxidans bacteremia in northern Taiwan</article-title>
          <source>J MicrobiolImmunol Infect</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
