<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abd</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26734872</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4689079</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20153877</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Clinical exuberance of classic Kaposi's sarcoma and response to
radiotherapy<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trujillo</surname>
            <given-names>Jeniffer Mu&#xF1;oz</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alves</surname>
            <given-names>Nat&#xE1;lia Ribeiro de Magalh&#xE3;es</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Medeiros</surname>
            <given-names>Paula Mota</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Azulay-Abulafia</surname>
            <given-names>Luna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alves</surname>
            <given-names>Maria de F&#xE1;tima Guimar&#xE3;es Scotelaro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gripp</surname>
            <given-names>Alexandre Carlos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro (UERJ) - Rio de
Janeiro (RJ), Brazil</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">MAILING ADDRESS: Jeniffer Mu&#xF1;oz Trujillo, Rua Estocolmo, 101
Apto 101 F Jardim Carioca, 21.931-480 Rio de Janeiro, RJ. E-mail:
<email>jeniffer848@gmail.com</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>Conflict of Interest: None</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Nov-Dec</season>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>90</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>883</fpage>
      <lpage>886</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2015 by Anais Brasileiros de
Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of
the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted
use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kaposi's sarcoma (KS) is a multicentric vascular neoplasm, with cutaneous and
extracutaneous involvement. Different clinical and epidemiological variants
have been identified. The classic form is manifested mainly in elderly men
with indolent and long-term evolution, with lesions localized primarily in
the lower extremities. We present two cases of classic Kaposi's sarcoma
(CKS) in two female patients with extensive, exuberant skin involvement and
rapid evolution, with good response to radiotherapy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Aged</kwd>
        <kwd>Herpesvirus 8, human</kwd>
        <kwd>Radiotherapy</kwd>
        <kwd>Sarcoma, Kaposi</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>KS is a vascular endothelium multifocal angioproliferative disorder, of preferred
mucocutaneous location, with potential to reach internal organs. It was
described by Moritz Kaposi as idiopathic multiple pigmented sarcoma of the skin,
in 1872.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Currently, four clinical-epidemiological forms are recognized: classic, endemic,
iatrogenic and epidemic, each one with its own natural history, preferred
location and prognosis.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> CKS mainly affects the skin of
lower limbs in aged people. It has a long-term course with typical clinical
presentation of macules, papules, erythematous-violaceous plaques or
nodules.<sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> In the
absence of treatment, clinical course of KS varies from innocuous lesions seen
in its classic variant to rapidly progressing and fatal lesions in epidemic
KC.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Two cases of CKS in female patients are presented, with extensive and exuberant
cutaneous involvement, of rapid progression and good response to
radiotherapy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 1</title>
        <p>Female patient, 82 years old, black, born in and from Rio de Janeiro. She has
presented for 9 months painful and pruritic nodular lesions, initially in
the left inframammary region which spread to abdomen, back and buttocks
regions. At the dermatological examination, she presented multiple
exophytic, erythematous-violaceous nodules and tumors lesions, some
ulcerated, located in the left inframammary region and left breast, left
flank, back and buttocks region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure
1</xref>). She did not present lesions in the mucosae and internal
organs.</p>
        <fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Multiple erythematous-violaceous, exophytic nodules of different
diameters, located in the inframammary region and left flank. In
greater detail, ulceration on the surface of one the nodules</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-06-0883-g01"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Case 2</title>
        <p>Female patient, white, 90 years old, born in and from Rio de Janeiro. She
resported a condition of approximately 18 months of progression since the
onset of a few violaceous nodules in the upper right limb. After one month,
there was the onset of multiple lesions of similar characteristics to
previous ones on the abdomen and lower and upper limbs. Edema and sensation
of lower limb fatigue were associated with clinical features. At the
dermatological examination, she presented plaques and violaceous nodules of
different diameters located on the upper and lower limbs, trunk, dorsum of
feet and plantar region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>).
This last location included reports of pain.</p>
        <fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Irregular violaceous plaques involving legs and dorsum of feet.
Violaceous plaques of keratotic surface, located in right plantar
region</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-06-0883-g02"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In both cases a cutaneous biopsy was performed, which revealed numerous
vessels of varied sizes in the dermis, exhibiting endothelial cells with
nuclear hyperchromatism and some atypias, proliferation of fusiform cells,
showing endothelial markers and diapedesis of red blood cells and
histopathological picture compatible with Kaposi's sarcoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>). Immunohistochemistry for HHV
8 was positive in both cases. Serologies for HIV 1 and 2, hepatitis B and C
were negative. Thorax and abdomen tomography and upper digestive endoscopy
did not reveal changes.</p>
        <fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Non-encapsulated dermal nodular proliferation composed by irregular
vascular channels with extravasated red blood cells and
proliferation of fusiform cellsrface, located in right plantar
region</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-06-0883-g03"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Case 1 patient had the left mammary region and abdomen treated with
radiotherapy, which was also used to treat the lower limbs of case 2
patient. They received three 800 centigray fractions on days 0-7-21. The
first patient responded well with reduction of some lesions and regression
of others, but had radiodermititis in the treated site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>). Two months after
radiotherapy, new nodular lesions appeared in these sites.</p>
        <fig id="f4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Extensive erosion due to acute radiodermititis. Hyperchromic
macules and plaques can be observed in the area treated with
radiotherapy (Patient 1)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-06-0883-g04"/>
        </fig>
        <p>In case 2, there was satisfactory response to radiotherapy, with improvement
of lesions and symptomatology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure
5</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="f5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Resolution of KS lesions, with only hyperchromic macules remaining
after three sessions of radiotherapy (Patient 2)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-90-06-0883-g05"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Kaposi's sarcoma is a low-grade vascular tumor that may involve the skin, mucosa
and viscera, developing in one of four different clinical-epidemiological
contexts.<sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> The
patients described presented CKS in accordance with clinical history, age
bracket and exclusively cutaneous location.</p>
      <p>Chang et al. discovered the human herpesvirus 8 (HHV8) in 93% of KS lesions
through Polymerase Chain Reaction in 1994.<sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> However, its
role is not clear, whether a causative agent or present only in those lesions
with a function not yet defined,.<sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> In our patients, HHV8 was detected as described in
literature.</p>
      <p>CKS is a rare disease with indolent course, involving preferably men between 40
and 70 years of age and of Mediterranean and Eastern Europe origin.<sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> It involves mainly the skin,
starting with violaceous macules in the distal portion of lower limbs,
progressing to plaques, nodules and tumors lesions.<sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> As the disease develops, lesions become
hardened, with irregular surface, where there may be ulceration and perilesional
edema.<sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Our patients are an exception
to this pattern regarding sex, geographic origin and distribution of
lesions.</p>
      <p>About 10% of patients suffer mucous and visceral involvement, usually compromising
lymph nodes and the gastrointestinal tract.<sup><xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The course of CKS is slow, but progression of lesions may be variable; macules or
tumors may not change for months to years or present a fast growth in weeks and
disseminate. A rapid progression may lead to central necrosis and ulceration of
lesions, as in case 2.<sup><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Unlike epidemic KS, CKS does not have a universally accepted staging
classification. The staging system proposed by Brambilla et al in 2003 is based
on objective criteria which follow closely the clinical variability of CKS. This
system is composed of four stages based on cutaneous lesions: location, presence
or absence of complications and visceral involvement (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Chart 1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>
Both cases 1 and 2 were evaluated as stage IVB due to fast progression,
characteristics, location and behavior of lesions, presenting local
complications nevertheless, Case 1 with pain and ulceration and Case 2 with pain
in the plantar region upon walking.</p>
      <table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Chart 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Staging of Classic Kaposi's Sarcoma</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage</th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cutaneous Lesions</th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavior</th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Progression</th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complications</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I. Maculonodular</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macules or nodules or both</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower limbs</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-aggressive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow (A) Fast (B)</td>
              <td rowspan="4" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">a</xref>Lymphedema, hemorrhage, pain, functional
involvement, ulceration</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II. Infiltrative</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plaques</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower limbs</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locally aggressive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow (A) Fast (B)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III. Florid</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angiomatous nodules and plaques</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extremities, particularly the lower ones</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locally aggressive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slow (A) Fast (B)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV. Disseminated</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angiomatous nodules and plaques</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extremities, trunk, head</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disseminated, aggressive</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fast (B)</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="TFN1">
            <p>Stage V: visceral involvement (oropharynx, gastrointestinal tract,
lymph nodes, bone marrow, lungs).</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="TFN2">
            <p>Fast: Increase in total number of nodules/plaques or in total area
of plaques, in 3 months.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="TFN3">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>All prevail in stage III and IV; lymphedema and lymphorrhea are
observed in stage II and rarely in stage I</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="TFN4">
            <p><bold>Source:</bold> Bambrilla et al 2003<sup><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>In localized forms of CKS, the available therapeutic alternatives are
radiotherapy, surgery, intralesional injections and observation. When there is
internal involvement or local complications, systemic therapy with
antiproliferative medication is required.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Even though there is not enough evidence in
literature for recommending a therapeutic strategy, radiotherapy studies have
reported a complete response in approximately 60-93% of the cases, being
effective in localized cutaneous forms.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Although the disease of the patients here presented
was in stage IV, radiotherapy was the option, justified by the age of the
patients.</p>
      <p>In both cases clinical exuberance and rate of progression emphasized the idea of
CKS variability. Over recent years an increase in reported cases of CKS with
different behavior has been noted. All data about these cases must be gathered
for evaluating possible new clinical KS classifications.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>Financial Support: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>How to cite this article: Mu&#xF1;oz Trujillo J, Alves NRM, Medeiros PM,
Azulay-Abulafia L, Alves MFGS, Gripp AC. Clinical exuberance of classic
Kaposi's sarcoma and response to radiotherapy. An Bras Dermatol.
2015;90(6):883-6.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn1" fn-type="other">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Study carried out at Hospital Universit&#xE1;rio Pedro Ernesto - Universidade do
Estado do Rio de Janeiro (HUPE-UERJ) - Rio de Janeiro (RJ), Brazil.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fatahzadeh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Kaposi sarcoma: review and medical management
update</article-title>
          <source>Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          <lpage>16</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22677687</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mohanna</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maco</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bravo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gotuzzo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiology and clinical characteristics of classic
Kaposi's sarcoma, seroprevalence, and variants of human herpesvirus 8
in South Am&#xE9;rica: a critical review of an old disease</article-title>
          <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>250</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16095940</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mohanna</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bravo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrufino</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gotuzzo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Classic Kaposi's sarcoma presenting in the oral cavity of
two HIV-negative Quechua patients</article-title>
          <source>Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>E365</fpage>
          <lpage>E368</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17767100</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Altunay</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kucukunal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demirci</surname>
              <given-names>GT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ates</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Variable clinical presentations of Classic Kaposi Sarcoma in
Turkish patients</article-title>
          <source>J Dermatol Case Rep</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22514583</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanni</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sprinz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machado</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santana Rde</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fonseca</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwartsmann</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Systemic treatment of AIDS-related Kaposi sarcoma: current
status and perspectives</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Treat Rev</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>445</fpage>
          <lpage>455</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16860939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Radu</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pantanowitz</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Kaposi Sarcoma</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pathol Lab Med</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>289</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23368874</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jakob</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Metzler</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garbe</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Non-AIDS Associated Kaposi's Sarcoma: Clinical Features and
Treatment Outcome</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <elocation-id/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kolios</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaloterakis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Filiotou</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakos</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hadziyannis</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gastroscopic findings in Mediterranean Kaposi's sarcoma
(non-AIDS)</article-title>
          <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>336</fpage>
          <lpage>339</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8536903</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brambilla</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boneschi</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taglioni</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrucci</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Staging of classic Kaposi's sarcoma: a useful tool for
therapeutic choices</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609790</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>R&#xE9;gnier-Rosencher</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guillot</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dupin</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatments for classic Kaposi sarcoma: a systematic review
of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>313</fpage>
          <lpage>331</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22695100</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
