<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Einstein (Sao Paulo)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Einstein (Sao Paulo)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eins</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Einstein</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1679-4508</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2317-6385</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Instituto Israelita de Ensino e Pesquisa Albert Einstein</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Sao Paulo</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24728256</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4898249</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1679-45082014RC2689</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1679-45082014RC2689</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Recurrence of acute myeloid leukemia in cryptorchid testis: case report</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="pt">
          <trans-title>Recidiva de leucemia mieloide aguda em test&#xED;culo criptorqu&#xED;dico: relato de caso</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de G&#xF3;es</surname>
            <given-names>Luccas Santos Patto</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lopes</surname>
            <given-names>Roberto Iglesias</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Campos</surname>
            <given-names>Octavio Henrique Arcos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Oliveira</surname>
            <given-names>Luiz Carlos Neves</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sant'Anna</surname>
            <given-names>Alexandre Crippa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dall'Oglio</surname>
            <given-names>Marcos Francisco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Srougi</surname>
            <given-names>Miguel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Hospital do Servidor P&#xFA;blico Municipal de S&#xE3;o Paulo, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brazil.</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Hospital das Cl&#xED;nicas, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de S&#xE3;o Paulo, S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brazil.</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">Corresponding author: Roberto Iglesias Lopes &#x2013; Division of Urology, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de S&#xE3;o Paulo, Rua Dr. En&#xE9;as de Carvalho Aguiar, 455, 7th floor &#x2013; Cerqueira C&#xE9;sar &#x2013; Zip code: 05403-000 &#x2013; S&#xE3;o Paulo, SP, Brazil &#x2013; Phone: <phone>(55 11) 3069-8080</phone> &#x2013; E-mail: <email>robertoiglesias@terra.com.br</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Jan-Mar</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Jan-Mar</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>109</fpage>
      <lpage>111</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p> This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>ABSTRACT</title>
        <p>A 23-year-old male with a history of bone marrow transplant for acute myeloid leukemia. He presented a large mass in the right inguinal region 5 years ago. Upon physical examination, right-sided cryptorchidism was observed. The tumor markers alpha-fetoprotein and beta-HCG were within normalcy range and lactate dehydrogenase was raised. Computed tomography of the abdomen and pelvis revealed right testicular mass in contiguity with the inguinal canal to the ipsilateral retroperitoneum, associated with right hydronephrosis. Due to the risk of germ-cell tumor in undescended testicle, the patient underwent radical right orchiectomy. The pathological examination showed recurrence of acute myeloid leukemia in the testis. He was referred to oncology for adjuvant therapy. Our literature review found no similar cases described.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="pt">
        <title>RESUMO</title>
        <p>Paciente de 23 anos, masculino, com antecedente de transplante de medula &#xF3;ssea por leucemia mieloide aguda. H&#xE1; 5 anos, apresentou volumosa massa em regi&#xE3;o inguinal direita. No exame f&#xED;sico, foi constatada criptorquidia &#xE0; direita. Os marcadores tumorais alfafetoprote&#xED;na e beta-HCG encontravam-se dentro da normalidade, e a desidrogenase l&#xE1;ctica estava aumentada. A tomografia computadorizada de abdomen e pelve revelou massa testicular direita com contiguidade pelo canal inguinal, at&#xE9; o retroperit&#xF4;nio ipsilateral, associada a hidronefrose direita. Devido ao alto risco de neoplasia germinativa em test&#xED;culo criptorqu&#xED;dico, o paciente foi submetido &#xE0; orquiectomia radical direita, cujo anatomopatol&#xF3;gico revelou recidiva de leucemia mieloide aguda em test&#xED;culo. Foi encaminhado para oncologia para terapia adjuvante. Nossa revis&#xE3;o n&#xE3;o revelou nenhum caso semelhante na literatura.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords:</title>
        <kwd>Leukemia</kwd>
        <kwd>acute myeloid</kwd>
        <kwd>Cryptorchidism</kwd>
        <kwd>Orchiectomy</kwd>
        <kwd>Testicular neoplasms</kwd>
        <kwd>Recurrence</kwd>
        <kwd>Chemotherapy</kwd>
        <kwd>adjuvant</kwd>
        <kwd>Case reports</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="8"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="10"/>
        <page-count count="3"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is a myeloproliferative syndrome and accounts for 20% of acute leukemias in childhood, and for 50% in patients aged up to 20 years, mainly white males. Treatment is based on bone marrow transplant and chemotherapy.<sup>(<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)</sup>
</p>
      <p>Cryptorchidism is the absence of testis in the scrotum and is one of the most common disorders in childhood, affecting 0.8 to 1% of young adults. Its diagnosis and treatment with orchidopexy must be made early, since the condition is associated to testicular torsion, hernias, infertility and malignization. The risk of degeneration and developing a germ-cell tumor is 40-fold higher as compared to the general population.<sup>(<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>)</sup>
</p>
      <p>Approximately 4% of pediatric patients with lymphoma may have a primary testicular involvement or relapse. The testis is considered to have a vascular barrier that hinders chemotherapeutical action, and orchiectomy is the standard treatment.<sup>(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>
</p>
      <p>The objective was to report a case of unidentified testicular mass in a clinical evaluation before bone marrow transplant and difficulty in making diagnosis and treat this condition. Based on our literature review, this might be the only case reported of AML recurrence in cryptorchidism.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 23-year-old male patient diagnosed as AML in 2003. He was submitted to allogeneic bone marrow transplant (donor: sister) in February 2004. One hundred days later he developed graft <italic>versus</italic> host disease presenting diffuse sclerodermiform plaques. He was treated with pulse therapy, and progressed with partial regression of the lesions. Five years later, a hard bulky mass, fixed to adjacent tissues, was observed in the right inguinal region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). On physical examination, the ipsilateral testis was not identified.</p>
      <fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Right inguinal mass, hard and fixed to adjacent tissues</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1679-4508-eins-12-01-0109-gf01"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The hypothesis of testicular cancer associated to right cryptorchidism was raised. The tumor markers were alpha fetoprotein: 2.5ng/mL (reference value (RV): up to 7ng/mL), beta-HCG: normal (RV: &lt;3U/mL) and lactate dehydrogenase: increased 483UI/L (100 a 190UI/L). Computed tomography (CT) of abdomen and pelvis showed a right testicular mass with contiguity to the inguinal canal up to the ipsilateral retroperitoneum, associated to right hydronephrosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figures 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">2B</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>(A) Computed tomography showed a right testicular mass in contiguity with the ipsilateral inguinal canal; (B) hydronephrosis on the right due to compression by the scrotal mass that extended to the retroperitoneum</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1679-4508-eins-12-01-0109-gf02"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Right radical orchiectomy was indicated due to suspected primary tumor or recurrence of AML. Inguinotomy was performed and an enlarged and hard peritesticular lymph node was excised (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figures 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">3B</xref>). The frozen biopsy revealed epithelial-cell lineage with high mitotic index, but with no defined histological pattern. The pathological report was diffuse infiltration by AML in testis and peritesticular lymph node (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figures 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">4B</xref>). The patient had no postoperative intercurrent events, and was discharged two days after surgery. He was referred to oncology for adjuvant therapy.</p>
      <fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>(A) Right radical orchiectomy of an inguinal mass related to a cryptorchid testis tumor. (B) Testicular mass and peritesticular lymph node after orchiectomy</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1679-4508-eins-12-01-0109-gf03"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="f4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>(A) Histology demonstrating anarchic cell hyperproliferation suggestive of leukemia. (B) Immunohistochemistry for myeloperoxidase revealed acute myeloid leukemia</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1679-4508-eins-12-01-0109-gf04"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Testicular cancer is frequent in young adult population, with an annual incidence of 4 per 100 thousand, and 95% are germ-cell tumors.<sup>(<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup> In this case reported, a rare type of neoplasm is observed and it corresponds to less than 0.5% of testicular tumors, caused by infiltration of leukemia/lymphoma of the testis. The most frequent subtype in testis is lymphoid leukemia. In the young adult population with acute lymphoid leukemia, up to 5% of patients can have primary involvement or relapse in testis.<sup>(<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup> There are case reports in the literature of recurrent acute lymphoid leukemia after bone marrow transplant, in whom chemotherapy and radiation therapy were not efficient and orchiectomy was the treatment chosen for remission of the disease.<sup>(<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>)</sup>
</p>
      <p>Testicular involvement is extremely rare in AML, and there are few cases reported, mainly in children; in that, bone marrow involvement occurred later in almost all patients. In these cases, the interval between remission and testicular recurrence ranged from 4 to 60 months, in average 21 months.<sup>(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup> In our patient, the interval was of 60 months. Several studies stated that testicular involvement in leukemias must be treated with orchiectomy due to the vascular barrier that hinders the action of chemotherapy.<sup>(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>
</p>
      <p>In this present case orchiectomy was indicated because of undefined testicular tumor, since the tumor markers did not suggest the diagnosis. Computed tomography of abdomen and pelvis is mandatory in cases of testicular tumors for staging and searching primarily retroperitoneal adenomegaly, for these lymph node basins are more affected in such neoplasms.<sup>(<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)</sup> The intraoperative frozen biopsy was performed to verify the presence of malignant lesion. The literature shows that relapsed AML or primary tumor of the testis should be addressed by orchiectomy, and the treatment complemented with adjuvant chemotherapy, based on the pathological examination.<sup>(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup> The case was managed according to the current recommendations, considering the peculiar recurrence of AML, a rare event that affected a patient with cryptorchidism, which hindered making diagnosis.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Villela</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bola&#xF1;os-Meade</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute myeloid leukaemia: optimal management and recent developments</article-title>
          <source>Drugs</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1537</fpage>
          <lpage>1550</lpage>
          <comment>Review</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21861539</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Walsh</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dall' Era</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Croughan</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carroll</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turek</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prepubertal orchiopexy for cryptorchidism may be associated with lower risk of testicular cancer</article-title>
          <source>J Urol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>178</volume>
          <issue>4 Pt 1</issue>
          <fpage>1440</fpage>
          <lpage>1446</lpage>
          <comment>discussion 1446. Review</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17706709</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pettersson</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richiardi</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nordenskjold</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaijser</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akre</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Age at surgery for undescended testis and risk of testicular cancer</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>356</volume>
          <issue>18</issue>
          <fpage>1835</fpage>
          <lpage>1841</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17476009</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grier</surname>
              <given-names>DD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eskew</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLean</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An unusual case of acute myeloid leukemia: late isolated testicular relapse followed by isolated central nervous system relapse</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1231</fpage>
          <lpage>1233</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20589624</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kulkarni</surname>
              <given-names>KP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marwana</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trehan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bansal</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testicular relapse in childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia: the challenges and lessons</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Cancer</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>134</fpage>
          <lpage>138</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20448374</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gutjahr</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Humpl</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testicular lymphoblastic leukemia/lymphoma</article-title>
          <source>World J Urol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>230</fpage>
          <lpage>232</lpage>
          <comment>Review</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8528297</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shaw</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of testicular cancer</article-title>
          <source>Am Fam Physician</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>469</fpage>
          <lpage>474</lpage>
          <comment>Review</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18326165</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jemal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siegel</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hao</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2008</article-title>
          <source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>71</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18287387</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kodama</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okamoto</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ijichi</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shinkoda</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishikawa</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanabe</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Continued complete remission without systemic therapy for isolated testicular relapse after bone marrow transplantation in a boy with acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Transplant</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>769</fpage>
          <lpage>772</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19067929</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>CK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shing</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chik</surname>
              <given-names>KW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwan</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lai</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leung</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolated testicular relapse after bone marrow transplant with total body irradiation and testicular boost in acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>
          <source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>397</fpage>
          <lpage>399</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9722077</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
