<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Med Res</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J. Med. Res</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJMR</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Indian Journal of Medical Research</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0971-5916</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Medknow Publications &amp; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26997028</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4822356</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJMR-143-116</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0971-5916.178624</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinical Images</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Bilateral acute ophthalmic artery occlusion in a case of giant cell arteritis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Roy</surname>
            <given-names>Rupak</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Saurabh</surname>
            <given-names>Kumar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Aditya Birla Sankara Nethralaya, 147, Mukundapur, E.M. Bypass, Kolkata 700 099, West Bengal, India</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Shri Bhagwan Mahavir Vitreoretinal Services, 18, College Road, Sankara Nethralaya, Chennai 600 006, Tamil Nadu, India</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><italic>For correspondence</italic>: <email xlink:href="rayrupak@gmail.com">rayrupak@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>143</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>116</fpage>
      <lpage>117</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#xA9; Indian Journal of Medical Research</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial ShareAlike 3.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non commercially, as long as the author is credited and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A 52 year old female presented with complaints of sudden, painless loss of vision in both eyes (right eye followed by left eye with in a gap of 3 days) since preceding one week to Aditya Birla Sankara Nethralaya, Kolkata in August 2014. Her visual acuity in both eyes was &#x2018;no perception of light&#x2019;. She gave a history of fever, weight loss and scalp tenderness one month prior to the visual loss. She had tenderness on temporal artery palpation on right side. Fundus examination showed disc oedema in both eyes along with retinal oedema at the posterior pole and a cherry red spot (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">B</xref>). Fundus fluorescein angiography showed no filling of retinal arteries at 30 sec after injection (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1 C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">D</xref>). Full field electroretinography showed non-recordable scotopic and photopic responses. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Erythrocyte sedimentation rate was 140 mm/h by Westergren method and C-reactive protein level was markedly elevated at 96 mg/l. She was diagnosed to be a case of bilateral ophthalmic artery occlusion with anterior ischaemic optic neuropathy secondary to giant cell arteritis (GCA). She was started on three days of pulse methyl prednisolone followed by oral systemic corticosteroids in consultation with her physician. At final follow up after three months there was no improvement in visual acuity. This case highlights the importance of early diagnosis and prompt treatment of giant cell arteritis in order to prevent the blinding complications like ophthalmic artery occlusion, and in case of unilateral involvement, to save the other eye.</p>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p><bold>A, B</bold>. Fundus photograph showing disc oedema in both eyes (white arrow), with retinal oedema at the posterior pole along with cherry red spot at the fovea (black arrowhead). <bold>(C)</bold>. Fundus fluorescein angiography of the right eye at 30 sec shows no choroidal filling and no filling of the retinal arteries. <bold>(D)</bold>. Left eye shows no filling of retinal arteries with patchy choroidal filling (white arrow).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="IJMR-143-116-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p><bold>A, B</bold>. Full field electroretinogram (ERG) of right <bold>(A)</bold> and left <bold>(B)</bold> eye shows extinguished scotopic and photopic responses. <bold>Fig. 2C</bold> shows ERG responses in normal eye.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="IJMR-143-116-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </body>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
