<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Trop Med Hyg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Trop. Med. Hyg</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0002-9637</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1476-1645</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26843610</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4751961</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.15-0664</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Images in Clinical Tropical Medicine</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Persistent Fever and Skin Lesions Due to Histoplasmosis in a Boy from Rural Nepal</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">THAPA AND OTHERS</alt-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">HISTOPLASMOSIS IN A BOY FROM RURAL NEPAL</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thapa</surname>
            <given-names>Shovit</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jha</surname>
            <given-names>Sunil Chandra</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trotter</surname>
            <given-names>Andrew B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AFF1">Department of Internal Medicine, Tribhuvan University Teaching Hospital, Kathmandu, Nepal; Department of Cardiology, Manmohan Cardiothoracic and Vascular Transplant Centre, Tribhuvan University Teaching Hospital, Kathmandu, Nepal; Department of Public Health and Community Medicine, Tufts University School of Medicine, Boston, Massachusetts</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">*Address correspondence to Andrew B. Trotter, Department of Internal Medicine, Tribhuvan University Teaching Hospital, C/O Dean's Office, Institute of Medicine, P.O. Box 1524, Maharajgunj, Kathmandu, Nepal. E-mail: <email>atrotter18@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>03</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>03</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <volume>94</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>249</fpage>
      <lpage>250</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>A 14-year-old Nepali male with a history of rheumatic heart disease complicated by severe mitral stenosis presented with a 2-week history of high-grade fever, dry cough, and hepatosplenomegaly on examination. He described chronic exposure to chickens but no other significant exposure history. Computerized tomography scan of the chest revealed a bilateral diffuse miliary pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Computerized tomography of the chest after initial hospitalization showing a diffuse, bilateral, miliary pattern in the lung fields.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tropmed-94-249-g001"/></fig>). A transthoracic echocardiogram showed no change in his valvular disease from previous studies and multiple blood cultures were negative. He was diagnosed with miliary tuberculosis; started on isoniazid, rifampicin, ethambutol, and pyrazinamide; and discharged. After 3 weeks, he was readmitted for persistent high-grade fever, chills, dry cough, and a 7-kg weight loss. He also developed small papular lesions on his face that became ulcerative after steroids were introduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Multiple skin lesions on the face that were found during the second hospital admission.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tropmed-94-249-g002"/></fig>). He underwent a video-assisted thoracoscopic lung biopsy, and skin biopsy, which showed small organisms consistent with <italic>Histoplasma</italic> spp. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Skin biopsy of a representative skin lesion using periodic acid&#x2013;Schiff staining reveals small organisms consistent with <italic>Histoplasma</italic> spp. Similar organisms were seen in the lung biopsy (not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="tropmed-94-249-g003"/></fig>). Initially, the patient was treated with oral itraconazole 200 mg three times daily for 3 days then twice daily, but by day 7 of treatment, he still continued to have persistent high-grade fever, cough, and chest pain. He was subsequently treated with amphotericin B deoxycholate with clinical improvement within 2 days of initiating therapy. He was treated with amphotericin B for 2 weeks and transitioned to oral itraconazole. Human immunodeficiency virus testing was negative.</p>
    <p>Histoplasmosis has only been described twice in Nepal: once in an Indian national who traveled to Nepal for medical care<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> and once in a Nepali in Nepal,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> making this the second case described in the literature in a Nepali citizen. Increased recognition of infectious diseases in areas where it was previously not thought to be prevalent and changing global distribution of infectious diseases can be an important clue to guide diagnostic workup and direct public health awareness. This case not only highlights the presence of histoplasmosis in Nepal but further supports a recent review describing increased recognition of histoplasmosis in other parts of Asia.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> In tuberculosis-endemic regions, disseminated histoplasmosis can easily be mistaken for tuberculosis owing to its similar clinical presentation and must be considered in patients who do not respond to empiric antitubercular therapy.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <p>We would like to acknowledge the Department of Pathology at Tribhuvan University Teaching Hospital, especially Ram Chandra Adhikari, for assistance in providing photomicrographs of pathology specimens. We would also like to thank Farhad Askarian in the Department of Pathology at Tufts Medical Center for review of the pathology slides.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="present-address">
        <p>Authors' addresses: Shovit Thapa, Department of Internal Medicine, Tribhuvan University Teaching Hospital, Kathmandu, Nepal, E-mail: <email>thapashovit@gmail.com</email>. Sunil Chandra Jha, Department of Cardiology, Manmohan Cardiothoracic and Vascular Transplant Center, Tribhuvan University Teaching Hospital, Kathmandu, Nepal, E-mail: <email>drscjha59@gmail.com</email>. Andrew B. Trotter, Department of Internal Medicine, Tribhuvan University Teaching Hospital, Maharajgunj, Kathmandu, Nepal, and Department of Public Health and Community Medicine, Tufts University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, E-mail: <email>atrotter18@gmail.com</email>.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amatya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Koirala</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurung</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rijal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhakal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Histoplasmosis: first case from Nepal</article-title>
<source>Health Renaissance</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>61</fpage>
<lpage>63</lpage></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sookpranee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanthachaiwat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaidee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Panjapiyakul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhupornwiwat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vannasaeng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Suwanraks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Chronic fever in Nepali diabetic</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis Antimicrob Agents</source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>35</fpage>
<lpage>38</lpage></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antinori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title><italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic>: more widespread than previously thought</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>982</fpage>
<lpage>983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24778192</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
