<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Ophthalmol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>BMC Ophthalmology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2415</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28100180</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5241988</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">400</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12886-017-0400-z</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Extensive bilateral corneal edema 6&#xA0;weeks after cataract surgery: Keratopathy due to <italic>Asclepias physocarpa</italic>: a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Matsuura</surname>
            <given-names>Kazuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+81-858-22-6231</phone>
            <email>matsuura.kzk@gmail.com</email>
            <email>matsu224@ncn-k.net</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hatta</surname>
            <given-names>Shiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>muddyhatta@yahoo.co.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Terasaka</surname>
            <given-names>Yuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>tera8002@yahoo.co.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Inoue</surname>
            <given-names>Yoshitsugu</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>yoinoue@grape.med.tottori-u.ac.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Nojima Hospital, 2714-1, Sesaki-machi, Kurayoshi-city, Tottori 682-0863 Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Maejima ganka, 226, Motomachi, Tottori-city, Tottori 680-0037 Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0663 5064</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.265107.7</institution-id><institution/><institution>Tottori University, </institution></institution-wrap>36-1, Nishi-cho, Yonago-city, Tottori 683-504 Japan </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <elocation-id>5</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Surgeons may be unaware of the ability of plant toxins to cause corneal damage. Therefore, corneal damage following intraocular surgery due to plant toxins may be misdiagnosed as postoperative infection.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 74-year-old man presented with hyperemia and reduced visual acuity in both eyes 6&#xA0;weeks after uneventful cataract surgery. We observed extensive hyperemia and corneal stromal edema with Descemet&#x2019;s folds in both eyes.</p>
          <p>After obtaining a detailed patient history, we diagnosed plant toxin-induced corneal edema due to <italic>Asclepias physocarpa</italic>, which can induce corneal edema by inhibiting the Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> ATPase activity of the corneal endothelium.</p>
          <p>Antimicrobial and steroid eye drops and an oral steroid were prescribed accordingly. Symptons began to improve on day 3 and had almost completely resolved by day 6. At 1&#xA0;month, the patient had fully recovered without any sequelae.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>The correct diagnosis was possible in the present case as symptoms were bilateral and the patient was able to report his potential exposure to plant toxins. However, if the symptoms had been unilateral and the patient had been unaware of these toxins, he may have undergone unnecessary surgical interventions to treat non-existent postoperative endophthalmitis.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Cataract surgery</kwd>
        <kwd>Endophthalmitis</kwd>
        <kwd>Asclepias physocarpa</kwd>
        <kwd>Case report</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Bacterial endophthalmitis is a clinically significant condition that should be considered in patients complaining of vision loss accompanied by acute extensive inflammation in the anterior segment of the eye within a few weeks of cataract surgery. Frequent examinations are generally required in addition to antibiotic treatment, with emergency surgery often required. We experienced case of corneal edema accompanied by extensive inflammation occurring 6&#xA0;weeks after uneventful bilateral cataract surgery. In the present case, we successfully diagnosed plant toxin-induced corneal edema [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] by obtaining a detailed patient history and thereby avoiding unnecessary surgical interventions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 74-year-old man with no history of uveitis, keratitis, or allergic eye disease underwent uneventful bilateral cataract surgery with one day interval in August 2015. His best corrected distant visual acuity (CDVA) following surgery was 1.0 and 1.2 in the right and left eyes, respectively (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Intraocular pressures and the number of corneal endothelial cells (2301/mm<sup>2</sup> in the right eye and 2171/mm<sup>2</sup> in the left) were within the normal range. The patient reported hyperemia and reduced visual acuity in both eyes one evening at 6&#xA0;weeks postoperatively and visited Maejima eye clinic the following day. On examination, extensive hyperemia and corneal stromal edema with Descemet&#x2019;s folds were observed in both eyes. His CDVA was 0.2 in both eyes, and central corneal thicknesses were 786&#xA0;&#x3BC;m and 756&#xA0;&#x3BC;m in the right and left eyes, respectively (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Intraocular pressure measurements and detailed observations of the anterior chamber were not possible due to the presence of corneal edema. We first suspected bacterial endophthalmitis; however, we considered this an atypical case due to the simultaneous development of symptoms in both eyes 6&#xA0;weeks postoperatively. No apparent vitreous opacity, retinal hemorrhage, or vasculitis was evident. After obtaining a detailed patient history, it was apparent the patient had performed gardening work during the day of onset. The patient had been engaged in the cultivation and sale of ornamental plants and had heard of eye toxicity on exposure to certain plants. We requested the patient list the plants he had handled and conducted a literature search. His clinical symptoms were consistent with those reported for corneal damage due to <italic>Asclepias physocarpa</italic>
<sup>1</sup>. We therefore diagnosed plant toxin-induced corneal edema accordingly. His eyes were initially thoroughly rinsed with normal saline. Topical levofloxacin 1.5% (6 times/day) and bethamethasone 0.1% (6 times/day) were administered, and he was re-evaluated daily on an outpatient basis. Small doses (10&#xA0;mg) of oral steroids were added as the presence of retinal and vitreal inflammation could not be completely excluded.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Uneventful cataract surgeries were conducted in both eyes. CCT: central corneal thickness, CDVA: corrected distant visual acuity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12886_2017_400_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Conjunctival injection and corneal edema with Descemet&#x2019;s folds (day 1)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12886_2017_400_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p>
      <p>The next day, conjunctival injection and corneal edema had increased, and his CDVA had decreased to 0.05 and 0.03 in the right and left eyes, respectively (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Corneal edema began to improve on day 3 and had almost completely resolved by day 6. The oral steroid was ceased immediately after recovery of the visibility (day5).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold>. Conjunctival injection and severe corneal edema with Descemet&#x2019;s folds (day 2). <bold>b</bold>. Anterior segment optical coherence tomography (SS-1000, TOMEY Inc, Aichi, Japan). Central corneal thickness measurements were 829&#xA0;&#x3BC;m and 845&#xA0;&#x3BC;m for the right and left eyes, respectively (day 2). CCT: central corneal thickness, CDVA: corrected distant visual acuity n. c: non corrigunt</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12886_2017_400_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p>
      <p>On day 8, his CDVA had recovered to 1.0 in both eyes (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). No clinical signs were evident at 1&#xA0;month. The intraocular pressure and number of corneal endothelial cells (2171/mm<sup>2</sup> in the right eye and 2247/mm<sup>2</sup> in the left) were within the normal range.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold>. Almost complete resolution of conjunctival injection and corneal edema (day 8). <bold>b</bold>. Anterior segment optical coherence tomography. Central corneal thickness measurements were normalized at 486&#xA0;&#x3BC;m and 482&#xA0;&#x3BC;m for the right and left eyes, respectively (day 8). CCT: central corneal thickness, CDVA: corrected distant visual acuity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12886_2017_400_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>
<italic>A. physocarpa</italic>, commonly known as tropic and subtropic milkweed, is a plant species native to tropical America and belongs to the genus <italic>Asclepias</italic> of the family <italic>Apocynaceae</italic> (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The plants of the <italic>Asclepias</italic> genus are widely distributed as horticultural or ornamental plants in Japan and other countries, and latex from their stems has been shown to contain toxic components termed cardenolides. To our knowledge, only a few cases of cardiolides toxicity have been previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], and general ophthalmologists are unaware of these plants. In corneal endothelial cells, the Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> ATPase actively transports Na<sup>+</sup> from inside of the cells into the anterior chamber to create an osmotic pressure gradient; thereby resulting in the active transport of water from inside the corneal stroma to the anterior chamber. The corneal stromal edema obsereved in the present case was attributable to corneal endothelial dysfunction caused by suppression of the Na<sup>+</sup> active transport by cardenolides in the stem latex, thereby inhibiting the Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> ATPase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold>. Flower and leaves of <italic>Asclepias physocarpa.</italic>
<bold>b</bold>. Follicle of <italic>A. physocarpa</italic>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12886_2017_400_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p>
      <p>Chakraborty et al. reported a case of <italic>A. curassavica</italic> exposure in which the patient rapidly attained remission with the use of artificial tear eye drops only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Amiran et al. reported a case of <italic>A. fruticosa</italic> exposure in which the clinical signs showed marked rapid improvement after the use of 0.1% topical dexamethasone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Pina et al. reported a case of <italic>A. physocarpa</italic> exposure in which almost complete resolution was obtained using topical dexamethasone, ofloxacin, and artificial tears. Pina et al. suggested the possibility of abnormal endothelial morphology as a sequelae at 6&#xA0;months follow-up, although the cell count was within the normal range (2119 cells/mm<sup>2</sup>). The use of topical steroids may increase the activity of the Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup> pump in corneal endothelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and thus have utility in the treatment of plant-induced corneal edema. Therefore, we modelled our treatment on the approach reported by Pina et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], with the patient almost completely recovering within 6&#xA0;days. Our patient fully recovered without any sequelae including any damage to corneal endothelial cells.</p>
      <p>Few plants such as those in the genus <italic>Asclepias</italic> have been reported to cause corneal damage. In a report of 7 cases of eye damage caused by <italic>Euphorbia</italic> plants, aggressive antibacterial and anti-inflammatory treatments were considered necessary as the patients presented with defects in the corneal epithelium and stromal edema, iritis, and other symptoms; with one case ultimately leading to blindness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>In a report on 29 cases of eye damage due to <italic>Calotropis procera</italic>, the patients recovered within 3&#x2013;14 days with maintenance of corneal transparency. Although visual acuity also recovered satisfactorily in the majority cases, endothelial cell counts were decreased in 74% of these cases. Epithelial defects, iritis, and increased ocular pressure were observed in 10, 31, and 24% of cases, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
      <p>In the present case, the patient did not remember any direct entry of latex into his eyes. As in the present case, corneal damage may be caused by contact between the eyes and hands that have been contaminated with latex, even without direct entry of latex droplets into the eyes. Therefore, physicians should proactively determine the involvement of plant toxins and conduct a detailed patient interview in such cases.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Although plants of the genus <italic>Asclepias</italic> are widely distributed, the number of the reports of ophthalmic disease due to plant toxins is surprisingly low. This may be attributable to the unfamiliarity of ophthalmologists to plant-based toxicity. In the present case, the correct diagnosis was possible as symptoms were bilateral and the patient could report his exposure to plant toxins. However, if the symptoms had been unilateral or developed more immediately postoperatively, or if the patient had been unaware of plant toxins, he may have undergone unnecessary surgical interventions. Although plant toxin-induced corneal damage is rarely encountered, all surgeons should be aware of this significant clinical condition.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviation</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>CDVA</term>
          <def>
            <p>Corrected distant visual acuity</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>Not applicable</p>
      <sec id="FPar1">
        <title>Funding</title>
        <p>There was no funding support.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar2">
        <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
        <p>All data supporting our findings are contained within the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar3">
        <title>Authors&#x2019; contributions</title>
        <p>KM and YI carried out the writing of the manuscript. SH and YT participated in the collection and interpretation of data. KM and YI carried out critical revision and correction of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar4">
        <title>Competing interests</title>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar5">
        <title>Consent for publication</title>
        <p>Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report accompanying images. A copy of written consent is available for review by the Editor of this journal.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="FPar6">
        <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
        <p>The present case report was approved by the ethics committee of Nojima hospital.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pina</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pedrosa</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feij&#xF3;o</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pego</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vendrell</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santos</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prieto</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ocular toxicity secondary to asclepias physocarpa: the balloon plant</article-title>
          <source>Case Rep Ophthalmol Med</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>2014</volume>
          <fpage>829469</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25105044</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siegenthaler</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xFC;chi</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Corneal edema due to Asclepias curassavica</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>974</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archopht.1995.01100080024013</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7639668</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amiran</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeung</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Corneal endothelial toxicity secondary to Asclepias fruticosa</article-title>
          <source>Eye (Lond)</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>961</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/eye.2011.59</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21423142</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tian</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>TY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>XH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Middleton</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fedosova</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Esmann</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tzen</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structures, chemotaxonomic significance, cytotoxic and Na(+), K(+)-ATPase inhibitory activities of new cardenolides from Asclepias curassavica</article-title>
          <source>Org Biomol Chem</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>8919</fpage>
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C4OB01545B</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25270760</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hatou</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamada</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mochizuki</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shiraishi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joko</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishida</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effects of dexamethasone on the Na, K-ATPase activity and pump function of corneal endothelial cells</article-title>
          <source>Curr Eye Res</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>347</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02713680902829624</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19401877</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eke</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Husainy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raynor</surname>
              <given-names>MK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The spectrum of ocular inflammation caused by euphorbia plant sap</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>13</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archopht.118.1.13</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10636407</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Basak</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhaumik</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mohanta</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singhal</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ocular toxicity by latex of Calotropis procera (Sodom apple)</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>232</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0301-4738.49402</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19384022</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
