<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28099337</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5279082</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-16-03150</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000005830</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">05830</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>5800</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Phototoxic maculopathy induced by quartz infrared heat lamp</article-title>
        <subtitle>A clinical case report</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zheng</surname>
            <given-names>Xinhua</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Xie</surname>
            <given-names>Ping</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Zizhong</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Weiwei</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Kang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MS</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Xiuying</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Qinghuai</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Pany.</surname>
            <given-names>Satyabrata</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Ophthalmology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China.</aff>
      <author-notes id="cor1">
        <corresp><label>&#x2217;</label>Correspondence: Ping Xie and Qinghuai Liu, Department of Ophthalmology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University, Nanjing, China (e-mails: <email>xieping9@126.com</email> [PX]; <email>liuqh@njmu.edu.cn</email> [QL]).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>96</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <elocation-id>e5830</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-No Derivatives License 4.0, which allows for redistribution, commercial and non-commercial, as long as it is passed along unchanged and in whole, with credit to the author. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-96-e5830.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Rationale:</title>
          <p>A large proportion of the output of quartz infrared heat lamps is emitted as infrared radiation (IR). Retinal damage induced by IR-A and visible light on arc welders has been reported. However, case reports of retinal damage caused by quartz infrared heat lamps are rare. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first reported case of phototoxic maculopathy induced by quartz infrared heat lamps.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Patient concerns:</title>
          <p>We report a female with a 1-month history of progressive blurred vision and dysmorphopsia in her right eye after improper staring at the tubes of a quartz infrared heater. Her best corrected visual acuity of the right eye was 20/32. Optical coherence tomography revealed a defect from the ellipsoid zone to retinal pigment epithelium (RPE)/Bruch's complex layer with a diameter of 360mmat its widest. P1 amplitudes in the two central concentric rings were reduced as assessed by multifocal electroretinography.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnoses:</title>
          <p>The patient was diagnosed with phototoxic maculopathy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Interventions:</title>
          <p>The patient was advised to cease all exposure to the infrared heater and was treated with peribulbar injections of methylprednisolone, oral Pancreatic Kininogenase, and oral Mecobalamin.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Outcomes:</title>
          <p>Ten months later, her BCVA improved to 20/20. All examination results returned to normal except for a small residual defect in the interdigitation zone and RPE/Bruch's complex layer in her optical coherence tomography.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Lessons:</title>
          <p>Light emitted by quartz infrared heat lamps may cause damage to the retina through photothermal and photochemical means. The public is insufficiently aware of the hazard potential of infrared heat lamps and other IR-A sources on human retina.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>maculopathy</kwd>
        <kwd>phototoxicity</kwd>
        <kwd>quartz infrared heat lamp</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Quartz infrared heat lamps are of wide use in many households for heating.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> A large proportion of the output of quartz infrared heat lamps is emitted as infrared radiation (IR).<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> Retinal damage induced by IR-A and visible light on arc welders has been reported.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> However, case reports of retinal damage caused by quartz infrared heat lamps are rare. In this case report, we described a phototoxic maculopathy induced by quartz infrared heat lamps.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>In March 2015, a 41-year-old female presented to our clinic with a 1-month history of progressive blurred vision and dysmorphopsia in her right eye. She had previously been healthy and had no relevant medical history such as high myopia, toxic exposure, laser exposure, solar exposure, known parasitic infection, or trauma. Blurred vision with dysmorphopsia is associated with maculopathy and retinopathy or choroidopathy located near the macula, such as central serous chorioretinopathy, age-related macular degeneration, macular hole, epimacular membrane, or macular pigmentary degeneration.</p>
      <p>Further questioning revealed that she had been intentionally staring at the tubes of a quartz infrared heater (NSB-80, Huajiu; Yiwu, China), which was operating 0.5 to 0.8 meter away on her right side at her workplace. According to its manufacture factory, the heater had a power of 800 W. It measured about 220&#x200A;W/m<sup>2</sup> in irradiance and about 180 lux in illuminance under her using conditions. During work breaks, she would stare at the tubes while warming her hands. She would also stare at the tubes while daydreaming. This intermittent exposure accumulated to an estimated 2 hours per day for 2 months.</p>
      <p>Her best corrected visual acuity (BCVA) of the right eye was 20/32. Optical coherence tomography (OCT)&#x2014;an imaging technique that uses light to capture micrometer-resolution images of the anterior segment of the eye and the retina&#x2014;revealed a defect from the ellipsoid zone to retinal pigment epithelium (RPE)/Bruch's complex layer with a diameter of 360&#x200A;&#x3BC;m at its widest. There was a pigment disorder in the adjacent area from the external limiting membrane to the RPE/Bruch's complex layer (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The color fundus photograph demonstrated a light-yellow lesion with obscure boundaries at the inferior nasal region of the fovea. Fundus autofluorescence revealed mottled hypofluorescence in the inferior nasal fovea, consistent with fundus fluorescein angiography demonstrating mottled hyperfluorescence in the same location. There was no fluorescence leakage. Visual field analysis was unremarkable. P1 amplitudes in the 2 central concentric rings were reduced as assessed by multifocal electroretinography (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Intraocular pressure was 14.3 mm Hg. Examination of her left eye was normal with BCVA of 20/20 and intraocular pressure of 16.2 mm Hg.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Optical coherence tomography scan of the right eye at the first visit. Optical coherence tomography revealed a defect (wide transparent white arrow) from the ellipsoid zone to the RPE/Bruch's complex layer with a diameter of 360&#x200A;&#x3BC;m, with a pigment disorder in adjacent areas from the external limiting membrane to RPE/Bruch's complex layer. The inset image at the bottom right corner shows the normal appearance of the macular region. RPE&#x200A;=&#x200A;retinal pigment epithelium.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5830-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Color fundus photograph, fundus autofluorescence, fundus fluorescein angiography, visual field, and multifocal electroretinography images of the right eye at the first visit. The color fundus photograph demonstrated a light-yellow lesion with obscure boundaries at the inferior nasal region of the fovea (2A). Fundus autofluorescence revealed mottled hypofluorescence in the inferior nasal fovea (2B), consistent with fundus fluorescein angiography demonstrating mottled hyperfluorescence in the same location. There was no fluorescence leakage (2C). The visual field analysis was unremarkable (2D). P1 amplitudes in the 2 central concentric rings were reduced as assessed by multifocal electroretinography (2E).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5830-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Based on the history and examination results, the patient was diagnosed with phototoxic maculopathy. She was advised to cease all exposure to the infrared heater. She was treated with 2 peribulbar injections of 20&#x200A;mg methylprednisolone 5-days apart, in addition to oral Pancreatic Kininogenase (240 u t.i.d.) and oral Mecobalamin (0.5&#x200A;mg t.i.d.) for 1 month.</p>
      <p>In follow-up at 1 month, 3 months, and 7 months, her examination showed continual improvement. OCT scans demonstrated that the diameter of the defect gradually shrank from 313&#x200A;&#x3BC;m to 274&#x200A;&#x3BC;m to 232&#x200A;&#x3BC;m, respectively. The pigment disorder abated. A small round lump of high signal appeared in the layer of outer segments of the photoreceptors. Ten months later, at the last visit, her BCVA improved to 20/20. All examination results returned to normal except for a 152&#x200A;&#x3BC;m residual defect in the interdigitation zone and RPE/Bruch's complex layer in her OCT (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Optical coherence tomography scans of the right eye during the follow-up. In follow up at 1 month (3A), 3 months (3B), and 7 months (3C), her optical coherence tomography scans demonstrated that the diameter of the defect gradually shrank from 313&#x200A;&#x3BC;m to 274&#x200A;&#x3BC;m to 232&#x200A;&#x3BC;m, respectively. The pigment disorder abated. A small round lump of high signal appeared in the layer of outer segments of the photoreceptors. Ten months later, at the last visit (3D), a 152&#x200A;&#x3BC;m residual defect could be observed in the interdigitation zone and RPE/Bruch's complex layer. RPE&#x200A;=&#x200A;retinal pigment epithelium.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5830-g003"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The design of the quartz infrared heat lamp consists of a satin milky-white quartz glass tube with an electrical resistance element, usually a tungsten wire, or a thin coil of iron&#x2013;chromium&#x2013;aluminum alloy.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> A large proportion of the output of quartz infrared heat lamps is emitted as infrared radiation (IR).<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> The National Radiological Protection Board (NRPB) in the UK reported that 56.0% of the total radiant output is IR-B (1400&#x2013;3000&#x200A;nm in wavelength) and IR-C (3000 nm&#x2013;1&#x200A;mm), 42.0% IR-A (770&#x2013;1400&#x200A;nm), 2.0% visible light (400&#x2013;770&#x200A;nm), and almost no ultraviolet (&lt;400&#x200A;nm).<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> According to tissue optics of the human eye,<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> IR-B and IR-C are almost entirely absorbed by the vitreous gel, so the radiation reaching the retina is almost entirely within the IR-A and visible bands.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Case reports of retinal damage caused by quartz infrared heat lamps are rare. Retinal damage induced by IR-A and visible light has been reported. The arc welding process emits a wide spectrum of radiation, with strong visible light and IR-A radiation penetrating to the retina.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> Arc welding light-induced macular lesions present with characteristics similar to our case.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Light can cause damage to the retina through photothermal, photomechanical, and photochemical means.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Photothermal damage may have played a role in our patient's pathogenesis. When exposed to radiant energy from light with wavelengths at the upper end of the visible spectrum, as well as of IR-A, molecules in the tissue tend to gain both rotational and vibrational energies, causing molecular collisions and rising tissue temperature.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> On a cellular and molecular level, temperature elevation causes protein denaturation and membrane fluidization,<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> and then cell necrocytosis appears and tissue lesions are induced. Melanin, the most effective absorber of photothermal energy is located primarily in the RPE<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup>; thus, the RPE will more readily absorb photothermal energy and get damaged. This is consistent with the fact that the retinal defect was mainly located at the RPE in this case.</p>
      <p>Photochemical damage is associated with both long-duration exposure times as well as lower-wavelength visible light exposure.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Visible light can be absorbed by exciting an electron in a chromophore from its ground state into an excited state.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> This generates free radicals that can attack many molecule types, resulting in lipid peroxidation and protein oxidation.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> Retinal photoreceptor outer segments possess large amounts of membrane and are thought to be especially susceptible to free radical-induced damage.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Photomechanical damage is probably not involved in this case, because it is caused by high irradiances in the range of megawatts or terawatts per cm squared and exposure times in the range of nanoseconds to picoseconds.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>The lesion was unilateral in this case. Some arc-welding-induced phototoxic maculopathy cases are also unilateral.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> Here, it likely results from the location of the heater on the right side of her office table, and therefore her right eye suffered from more light exposure.</p>
      <p>The International Commission on Non-ionizing Radiation Protection (ICNIRP) Statement on Far Infrared Radiation Exposure provides safety guidance and criteria for infrared heat lamps and other IR-A sources.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> ICNIRP recommendations may be overly conservative, as the brightness of a lamp is sufficient to reduce the pupil size from that assumed for ICNIRP calculations. Additionally, the high aspect ratio of the filament image will cause less temperature rise than the circular image assumed in the ICNIRP calculation methodology.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> To our knowledge, there is an absence of controlled clinical trials or prospective epidemiological studies concerning the influence of commercially available quartz infrared heat lamps on the human retina. The public is insufficiently aware of this issue.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>We reported a case with progressive blurred vision and dysmorphopsia after improper use of quartz infrared heat lamps. IR-A and visible light emitted by quartz infrared heat lamps may cause phototoxic maculopathy through photothermal and photochemical means. The public should be more aware of the hazard potential of infrared heat lamps and other IR-A sources on human retina.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>5</label>
      <title>Consent</title>
      <p>This study adhered to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki, and the ethics committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University approved the study. Informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this report and its related images.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: BCVA = best corrected visual acuity, ICNIRP = The International Commission on Non-ionizing Radiation Protection, IR = infrared radiation, NRPB = The National Radiological Protection Board, OCT = optical coherence tomography.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p>Funding: This research was supported by the National Basic Research Program of China (973 Program, No.2013CB967500 and No.2011CB510200), General Project of the National Natural Science Fund (No.81170855), Jiangsu Provincial Special Program of Medical Science (BL2014089), and Six Talent Peaks Project in Jiangsu Province (2013-WSW-015). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>[1]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Charman</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Visual safety of quartz linear lamps</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup Hyg</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8317854</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>[2]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brittain</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Retinal burns caused by exposure to MIG-welding arcs: report of two cases</article-title>. <source>Brit J Ophthalmol</source>
<year>1988</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>570</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3415950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>[3]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Macular degeneration in an arc welder</article-title>. <source>Ind health</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>371</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485886</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>[4]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic phototoxic maculopathy caused by welding arc in occupational welders</article-title>. <source>Can J Ophthalmol</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22333851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>[5]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fledelius</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Maculopathy caused by welding arcs</article-title>. <source>Acta Ophthalmol</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>402</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8362643</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>[6]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><publisher-name>Life Support Systems Laboratory, 6570th Aerospace Medical Research Laboratories, Aerospace Medical Division, Air Force Systems Command</publisher-name>, <person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boettner</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolter</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Transmission of the Ocular Media</article-title>. <year>1962</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>[7]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>ICoN-IR Protection</collab>. <article-title>ICNIRP statement on far infrared radiation exposure</article-title>. <source>Health Phys</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>630</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17099407</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>[8]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheibani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Retinal light toxicity</article-title>. <source>Eye</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21178995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>[9]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crochet</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnyawali</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Temperature distribution in selective laser-tissue interaction</article-title>. <source>J Biomed Opt</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>34031</fpage><comment>034031-034031-034010</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16822080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>[10]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>F</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>
<article-title>Studies of thermal injury; the predictability and the significance of thermally induced rate processes leading to irreversible epidermal injury</article-title>. <source>Arch Pathol</source>
<year>1947</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>502</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>[11]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pathologic findings of photic retinopathy in the human eye</article-title>. <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>520</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1951588</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>[12]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seregard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Algvere</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Photochemical damage of the retina</article-title>. <source>Surv Ophthalmol</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16950247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>[13]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#xF3;&#x17C;anowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarna</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Light-induced damage to the retina: role of rhodopsin chromophore revisited</article-title>. <source>Photochem Photobiol</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1305</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16120006</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
