<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">An Bras Dermatol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abd</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0365-0596</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1806-4841</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Dermatologia</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27828638</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5087223</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/abd1806-4841.20164477</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Dermatopathology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Histological variability and the importance of clinicopathological
correlation in cutaneous Rosai-Dorfman disease<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gameiro</surname>
            <given-names>Ana</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gouveia</surname>
            <given-names>Miguel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cardoso</surname>
            <given-names>Jos&#xE9; Carlos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tellechea</surname>
            <given-names>Oscar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Coimbra University Hospital &#x2013; Coimbra, Portugal</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1">Mailing address: Ana Gameiro, Hospital da Universidade de Coimbra,
Servi&#xE7;o de Dermatologia, Praceta Mota Pinto, 3000-075 Coimbra, Portugal.
E-mail: <email>anaportelinhag@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>91</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>634</fpage>
      <lpage>637</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9;2016 by Anais Brasileiros de
Dermatologia</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Anais Brasileiros de Dermatologia</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits
unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any
medium provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rosai-Dorfman disease is a benign histiocytic proliferative disorder of unknown
etiology. The disease mainly affects lymph node tissue, although it is rarely
confined to the skin. Here, we describe a 53-year-old woman with purely
cutaneous Rosai-Dorfman disease. The patient presented with a large pigmented
plaque on her left leg, and sparse erythematous papules on her face and arms. A
complete clinical response was achieved with thalidomide, followed by recurrence
at the initial site one year later. The histological examination displayed the
typical features of Rosai-Dorfman disease in the recent lesions but not in the
older lesions. In the setting of no lymphadenopathy, the histopathological
features of Rosai-Dorfman disease are commonly misinterpreted. Therefore,
awareness of the histological aspects present at different stages, not always
featuring the hallmark microscopic signs of Rosai-Dorfman disease, is
particularly important for a correct diagnosis of this rare disorder.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Emperipolesis</kwd>
        <kwd>Histiocytosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Histiocytosis, sinus</kwd>
        <kwd>Thalidomide</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Rosai-Dorfman disease (RDD) is a benign histiocytic proliferative disorder of unknown
etiology. Typically, it presents as a painless, bilateral, massive, cervical
lymphadenopathy, commonly in association with systemic symptoms, such as fever,
weight loss, night sweats, leukocytosis, polyclonal gammopathy and increased
erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR).<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Although originally described as a nodal disorder, extranodal disease occurs in up to
40% of cases, with skin affected in about 10% of cases.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> More rarely, cutaneous lesions are
the sole manifestation, with purely cutaneous-RDD (CRDD) representing a small
minority (3%) of RDD described cases.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> CRDD is considered a distinct entity, based on the
exclusive involvement of the skin, different demographic features and better
prognosis, compared with systemic RDD.<sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>As the cutaneous lesions are clinically nonspecific, the diagnosis of CRDD is
histological, and essentially relying on the presence of an infiltrate containing
large pale histiocytes, commonly displaying emperipolesis, accompanied by
lymphocytes and abundant plasma cells. In the setting of no lymphadenopathy, the
histopathological features of RDD are commonly misinterpreted, and it is important
to consider that histological features vary in correlation with the cutaneous
lesions duration.<sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 53-year-old female presented with a 1 year-history of a poorly circumscribed,
erythematous to brown, slightly verrucous, indurated 15cm plaque with superimposed
violaceous papules and additional satellite erythematous papules, located on her
left leg. The plaque progressed for 1 year, starting as a small, dark area,
gradually enlarging (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). In addition,
she had sparse domeshaped erythematous papules located on her face and arms, which
appeared two months before (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). The skin
lesions were asymptomatic, and the general physical examination was unremarkable,
with no lymphadenopathy, organomegaly, or systemic symptoms like fever, malaise or
weight loss. Her past medical history included obesity, hypertension and bipolar
disorder. The first clinical impression was Kaposi's sarcoma and skin biopsies were
taken from her arm and leg.</p>
      <p>
        <fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Hyperpigmented, indurated plaque with superimposed and satellite papules
on the left leg</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-91-05-0634-g01"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>
        <fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Sparse, unspecific, erythematous papules on the arms and face</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-91-05-0634-g02"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>Histological examination of a papule located on the arm that had evolved for
approximately 2 months revealed a dense nodular infiltrate in the dermis, extending
focally to the hypodermis. The infiltrate was mainly composed of large histiocytes
with pale cytoplasm and variably sized vesicular nuclei, with large nucleoli,
occasionally exhibiting intact inflammatory cells in their cytoplasm &#x2013; emperipolesis
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>). The hystiocitic infiltrate was
intermixed with plasma cells, lymphocytes and few neutrophils and eosinophils.
Lymphocytes tended to constitute aggregates within or at the periphery of the
infiltrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
      <p>
        <fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Emperipolesis- clear halos around intact cells within the cytoplasm of
histiocytes. (H/E, original magnification x200)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-91-05-0634-g03"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>
        <fig id="f4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Dense, confluent population of large histiocytes with pale cytoplasm,
located in the dermis and focally in the hypodermis; and nodular,
lymphocytic aggregates within the infiltrate and at the periphery. (H/E,
original magnification x25)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-91-05-0634-g04"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>The histological examination of the leg plaque, which had been present for 1 year,
revealed a more superficial dense dermal infiltrate, composed by fewer histiocytes,
and accompanied by a relatively higher number of lymphocytes, plasma cells,
eosinophils and neutrophils. Emperipolesis was not identified, and there was
moderate fibrosis surrounding the infiltrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure
5</xref>). In both specimens, the histiocyte population was positive for S100
and CD68, but negative for CD1a, confirming the diagnosis of RDD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
      <p>
        <fig id="f5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Dense, dermal infiltrate, presenting a triangular shape with its base
oriented towards the surface, composed of fewer histiocytes; absence of
emperiolesis and prominent fibrosis surrounding the infiltrate. (H/E,
original magnification x40)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-91-05-0634-g05"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>
        <fig id="f6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Diffuse anti-S100 cytoplasmic staining of histocytic population. (S100
stain, original magnification x200)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-91-05-0634-g06"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>Blood tests, including HIV1/2 and herpes virus 8, were normal or negative; and
positive for IgG anti-Epstein-Bar virus and cytomegalovirus. A full-body CT scan
excluded internal organ involvement and lymphadenopathy, and the patient was
diagnosed with CRDD. Since the lesions were progressing and involved the face,
thalidomide (300mg/d) was initiated. After 2 months, the leg plaque became flat,
with no induration, leaving a residual, brownish discoloration. Lesions on the face
and arms completely regressed with no pigmentary changes or scarring, and
thalidomide was withdrawn.</p>
      <p>One year later, the patient noticed the recurrence of induration on the previous leg
plaque and new satellite erythematous papules, which were biopsied 1 month after
they appeared. The histopathological picture was superposable to what was previously
found in the leg plaque; and in addition, suppurative focci were seen within the
infiltrate of the new satellite papule, that also displayed increased vascularity,
focal emperipolesis and perivenular extension of plasma cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7</xref>). Since there was no recurrence in other body areas, we
decided to treat the leg lesions with topical corticosteroids, with good
response.</p>
      <p>
        <fig id="f7" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Suppurative foci within the histocytic infiltrate, observed in a
satellite papule of the leg lesion recurrence. (H/E, original
magnification x100)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="abd-91-05-0634-g07"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>There are three main hypotheses for RDD etiology: i) an immune dysfunction induced by
viral infection, namely HHV6, EBV or parvovirus B19. However, virus expression is
inconsistently identified in nodal disease and has not yet been conclusively
identified in CRDD; ii) RDD may be part of the spectrum of IgG4-related disease,
based on recent reports and case series showing an increased number of IgG4 positive
plasma cells.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> However, there is no
clear evidence to support this hypothesis, and a large number of conditions outside
the IgG4-related disease spectrum can be associated with an increased number of
IgG4-positive plasma cells; iii) RDD may belong to a spectrum of disorders with
SLC29A3 mutations, namely H syndrome.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> The evidence of a germline mutation in SLC29A3 in patients with
familial RDD, as well as the finding of emperipolesis in cutaneous lesions of H
syndrome would support this hypothesis, but this association has not been
demonstrated in the cutaneous forms of the disease.<sup><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The classic clinical features described in CRDD were reproduced in our patient.
Systemic RDD is more common in males and in children or young adults of African
descent, whereas CRDD predominates in older females, of non-black
ancestry.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Rare
fatalities can occur in systemic RDD, resulting from vital organ infiltration,
progression to lymphoproliferative disorders, or the development of solid tumors.
CRDD, contrarily, is typically self-limiting, does not require aggressive
treatments, and it generally remains confined to the skin despite frequently running
a recurrent course.<sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The cutaneous lesions can be protean (yellowish to reddish brown/violaceous macules,
patches, plaques, nodules or tumors, pustules, acneiform, or transient
paniculitis-like lesions), with a wide distribution (head and neck, trunk, upper and
lower limbs, by decreasing order).<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Our patient
exhibited a typical semiologic aspect of CRDD: a plaque, surrounded by satellite
papules, and other clinical aspects commonly observed in CRDD, the multiplicity and
combination of distinct lesions, and their tendency toward regression and
recurrence.<sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> However, these clinical and
evolutive features, albeit characteristic of CRDD, are seldom evocative of the
diagnosis, which in this case was initially thought to be Kaposi's sarcoma. The
absence of systemic/extracutaneous signs and symptoms, as documented in our patient,
although essential for the diagnosis of CRDD, further rendered the clinical picture
unspecific.<sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>It is the microscopic picture that allows the diagnosis. The histopathologic features
of CRDD are akin to those found in the lymph nodes in systemic RDD.<sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Typically, as featured in the arm
lesion of our patient, a dermal/hypodermal infiltrate of large pale hystiocytes
exhibiting variable emperioplesis admixed with plasma cells, lymphocytes and
occasional neutrophils and eosinophils is observed.<sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> However, this picture can change according to the age of the
lesions: in early developing lesions, as found in the satellite papules of the
recurrent leg lesion, collections of neutrophils and increased vascularity can be
pronounced. On the other hand, in old/regressive lesions, as observed in the
proctated leg plaque, emperipolesis may be absent, and surrounding fibrosis may be
prominent, overshadowing the presence of histiocytic cells and hindering the
diagnosis. In the absence of emperipolesis, the extension of plasma cells around
thick wall venules and the peripheral arrangement of lymphoid aggregates, as
observed in our case, are important clues for the histologic suspicion of
CRDD.<sup><xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The coexpression by the histiocytic CRDD cells of S-100 protein and
monocyte/macrophage markers, such as lysozyme, &#x3B1;1-antitrypsin, CD68 and
CD163, the non-reactivity to Langerhans cell markers, including CD1 and langerin,
which was also featured in this case, is an important tool for diagnosis.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Histologically, CRDD may be confused with other histiocytic
proliferations. In reticulohistiocytosis, histiocytes have an eosinophilic ground
glass cytoplasm and are most often S100 protein-negative. Langerhans cell
histiocytosis can be distinguished from CRDD by the smaller size of the histiocytes,
characteristic reniform folded nucleus, epidermotropism and positivity for CD1a and
langerin. In juvenile xanthogranuloma, histiocytes are negative or only focally
positive for S100 protein and, in contrast to CRDD, are positive for factor XIIIa.
Eruptive xanthoma also lacks S100 protein immunoreactivity. It should be emphasized
that in these histiocytic disorders, emperipolesis is not a feature.<sup><xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Nevertheless, although virtually
diagnostic of RDD/CRDD in the appropriate clinical and pathologic setting,
histiocytic emperipolesis is not unique to this condition. Emperipolesis can be
found in examples of B-cell lymphomas and in the cutaneous lesions of the H
syndrome, both easily discarded in our patient.<sup><xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Furthermore, the pathologic findings allow to most of the clinical differential
diagnoses for CRDD, including storage disorders, granulomatous diseases, histiocytic
sarcoma, infections like mycobacteriosis and hystoplasmosis, as well as Kaposi's
sarcoma (in our case).<sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The utility of a further workup in a patient with cutaneous RDD and no further
systemic manifestations is not well-defined. As skin lesions can be the initial
manifestation of systemic disease, we believe that CT-scans should be performed in
patients presenting solely cutaneous lesions, to screen for visceral involvement.
<sup><xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Generally, CRDD has a benign course and is self-limiting, although patients may
experience local relapse or persistent disease.<sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Accordingly, therapy may be needed for cosmetic reasons and
relapsing cases, as in our patient. Therapeutic options for CRDD are multiple, and
due to the rarity of the condition, randomized trials are not available. Surgical
excision remains the therapy of choice for solitary or small lesions.<sup><xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> In addition, corticosteroids (the most widely used therapy in
CRDD), thalidomide, interferon, cryosurgery, radiotherapy and chemotherapy have been
assayed. In our patient (a hypertensive, obese, post-menopausal woman), thalidomide
induced rapid remission, confirming previous reports<sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>, with
positive aesthetic results with absence of facial residual changes.</p>
      <p>We described a case of CRDD where emperipolesis was present only in recently
developed lesions, but not found in older lesions, which instead revealed variable
fibrosis surrounding a scanter histiocytic proliferation. Initial lesions
additionally displayed neutrophil microabcesses and increased vascularity. Awareness
of the histological aspects present in different lesions, which do not always
contain the hallmark microscopic signs of CRDD, is particularly important to
correctly diagnose this rare disorder.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>Conflict of Interests: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>Financial Support: None</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other" id="fn1">
        <label>*</label>
        <p>Work performed at the Coimbra University Hospital &#x2013; Coimbra, Portugal.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>Histiocytesociety.org</collab>
          </person-group>
          <comment>Internet</comment>
          <source>Rosai-Dorfman Disease Review: Outline. Histiocyte Society</source>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2015 Jan 12</date-in-citation>
          <comment>Avaiable in: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.histiocytesociety.org/document.doc?id=54">http://www.histiocytesociety.org/document.doc?id=54</ext-link></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rizwan</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chhabra</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mishra</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kapadia</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rai</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of isolated cutaneous
Rosai-Dorfman-Syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Gulf J Oncolog</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>89</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldsmith</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilchrest</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paller</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leffell</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolff</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Fitzpatricks's Dermatology in general medicine</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <edition>8th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kutlubay</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bairamov</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sevim</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Demirkesen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mat</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rosai-Dorfman disease a case report with nodal and cutaneous
involvement and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermatopathol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>353</fpage>
          <lpage>357</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23863552</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chu</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>LeBoit</surname>
              <given-names>PE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Histologic features of cutaneous sinus histiocytosis
(Rosai-Dorfman disease) study of cases both with and without systemic
involvement</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Pathol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>201</fpage>
          <lpage>206</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1401344</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dalia</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sagatys</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sokol</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kubal</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rosai-Dorfman disease tumor biology, clinical features,
pathology, and treatment</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Control</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>322</fpage>
          <lpage>327</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25310213</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>WY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>HN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>WR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cutaneous Rosai-Dorfman disease clinicopathological profiles,
spectrum and evolution of 21 lesions in six patients</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>154</volume>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>286</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16433797</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ortonne</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fillet</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kosuge</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagot</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frances</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wechsler</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cutaneous Destombes-Rosai-Dorfman disease absence of detection of
HHV-6 and HHV-8 in skin</article-title>
          <source>J Cutan Pathol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          <lpage>118</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12150132</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hyjek</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vardiman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A subset of Rosai-Dorfman disease exhibits features of
IgG4-related disease</article-title>
          <source>Am J Clin Pathol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>139</volume>
          <fpage>622</fpage>
          <lpage>632</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23596114</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perry</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cao</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsi</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship between Rosai-Dorfman disease and IgG4-related
disease study of 32 cases</article-title>
          <source>Am J Clin Pathol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <fpage>395</fpage>
          <lpage>402</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955459</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Colmenero</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Molho-Pessach</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torrelo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zlotogorski</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Requena</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Emperipolesis an additional common histopathologic finding in H
syndrome and Rosai-Dorfman disease</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermatopathol</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>315</fpage>
          <lpage>320</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22356918</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brenn</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Calonje</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Granter</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leonard</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grayson</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fletcher</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cutaneous Rosai-Dorfman disease is a distinct clinical
entity</article-title>
          <source>Am J Dermatopathol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>385</fpage>
          <lpage>391</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12357197</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lopes</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bacchi</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coelho</surname>
              <given-names>KI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Filho</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bacchi</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Emperipolesis in a case of B-cell lymphoma a rare phenomenon
outside of Rosai-Dorfman disease</article-title>
          <source>Ann Diagn Pathol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>310</fpage>
          <lpage>313</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14571435</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vuong</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moulonguet</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cordoliani</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crickx</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bezier</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vignon-Pennamen</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cutaneous revelation of Rosai-Dorfman disease 7
cases</article-title>
          <source>Ann Dermatol Venereol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23395488</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
