<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28033275</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5207571</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-16-02773</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000005717</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">05717</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>3600</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Pregnancy complicated with agranulocytosis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Hai</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sun</surname>
            <given-names>Jiang-Li</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Zheng-Liang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pei</surname>
            <given-names>Hong-Hong</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Shankar.</surname>
            <given-names>Esaki M.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Emergency Department, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi&#x2019;an Jiaotong University, Xi&#x2019;an, Shaanxi, PR China.</aff>
      <author-notes id="cor1">
        <corresp><label>&#x2217;</label>Correspondence: Zheng-Liang Zhang; Hong-Hong Pei, Emergency Department, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi&#x2019;an Jiao Tong University, 710004 Xi&#x2019;an, Shaanxi, PR China (<email>e-mails: 18991204398@163.com; 15109276591@163.com</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>95</volume>
      <issue>52</issue>
      <elocation-id>e5717</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives License 4.0, which allows for redistribution, commercial and non-commercial, as long as it is passed along unchanged and in whole, with credit to the author. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-95-e5717.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Rationale:</title>
          <p>Pregnancy is a complicated physiological process. Physiological leukocytosis often takes place and it is primarily related to the increased circulation of neutrophils, especially during the last trimester of pregnancy. Noncongenital agranulocytosis during pregnancy is rare and reported only occasionally, while in most of the cases, the agranulocytosis has already occurred prior to pregnancy or induced by identified factors such as antibiotics, antithyroid agents, or cytotoxic agents. Gestation-induced agranulocytosis has not been reported, so we present a case of gestation-induced agranulocytosis in this article.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="subjects">
          <title>Patients concern:</title>
          <p>In this case, we present a Chinese woman (aged 25) in her 38th week of the first gestation who had the complication of agranulocytosis. No abnormality was detected in regular examinations before pregnancy and in the first trimester. Since the last trimester of pregnancy, the patient began to suffer from agranulocytosis and intermittent fever, the maximum being temperature 38.8&#xB0;C. At admission, the neutrophil granulocytes were 0.17&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> and the bone marrow biopsy showed that agranulocytosis was detected, but the levels of red blood cell and megalokaryocyte were normal. In addition, antinuclear antibodies were detected at a dilution of 1:40, but anti-dsDNA, antiphospholipid antibody, and neutrophil granulocyte antibody were negative.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Diagnoses:</title>
          <p>The patient was empirically treated as having pneumonia.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Interventions:</title>
          <p>We tried to use granulocyte colony-stimulating factor, &#x3B3;-globulin, glucocorticoids, antibiotics, and antifungi agents to treat the patient, but her symptoms were not alleviated until the patient had a cesarean section.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Outcomes:</title>
          <p>After 24 hours of cesarean section, the temperature and neutrophil granulocyte returned to normal. After a year of follow-up, we found that the patient and the baby were healthy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Lessons:</title>
          <p>Agranulocytosis during pregnancy seems to be associated with immunosuppression induced by immunoregulations and termination of pregnancy may be effective for refractory pregnancy complicated with agranulocytosis, but further studies are needed to confirm this.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>agranulocytosis</kwd>
        <kwd>hypothyroidism</kwd>
        <kwd>immunosuppression</kwd>
        <kwd>pregnancy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Pregnancy is a complicated physiological process.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> In pregnant women, local adaptation of the maternal immune system allows for successful coexistence between the mother and the fetus/placenta.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> There are multiple strategies for the adaptive immunity, including altered human leukocyte antigen expression, synthesis of immunosuppressive molecules (progesterone, prostaglandins), and expression of high levels of complement regulatory proteins and alterations in the relative proportions, phenotype, and functions of leukocyte subpopulations, cytokine profiles across gestation, etc.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> These alterations make mother and infant reach a state in which cytotoxic adaptive immune responses are diminished, bypassed, or even abrogated, while regulatory adaptive immunity is enhanced.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> At the same time, pregnancy is associated with leukocytosis, primarily related to an increased circulation of neutrophils.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> The neutrophil count begins to increase in the second month of pregnancy and plateaus in the second or third trimester, at which time the total white blood cell counts range from 9000 to 15,000&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;106/L.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> During the gestational period, internal environmental changes can cause poor immunological functions. Simultaneous agranulocytosis makes the pregnant women more vulnerable to infection, which is one of the risk factors of intrauterine infection,<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> miscarriage, premature delivery, fetal growth restriction, fetus death, or, in extreme cases, death of both mother and baby.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Noncongenital agranulocytosis during pregnancy is rare and reported only occasionally, while in most of the cases, the agranulocytosis has already occurred prior to pregnancy or induced by identified factors such as genetic factors, antibiotics, antithyroid agents, or cytotoxic agents.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> Gestation-induced agranulocytosis has not been reported, so we present a case of gestation-induced agranulocytosis in this article.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A Chinese woman (aged 25) in her 38th week of the first gestation, whose blood type was type B and RH-positive, had regularly received thyroid function tests and used levothyroxine sodium 75&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/d for her condition of hypothyroidism for 13 years. Latest thyroid function tests were conducted 4 months after pregnancy and no abnormal change was observed. She did not have any personal and family history of hyperthyroidism, agranulocytosis, and antithyroid medicinal drugs. During her gestational period, the repeated blood routine tests showed that the counts of white blood cell and neutrophil granulocyte were within the normal range. A month before being admitted to the hospital, she suffered intermittent fever, the maximum temperature being 38.8&#xB0;C, and had other symptoms including oral ulcers, shivering, cough, and a small amount of white phlegm. The symptoms usually became serious at night. She was given symptomatic relief and supportive treatments, but the treatments did not work. Thus, the patient was transferred to several other medical centers; during this period, routine blood tests indicated a low level of the counts of white blood cell and neutrophil granulocyte. The result of the bone marrow biopsy conducted by another hospital showed that agranulocytosis was detected, but the levels of red blood cell and megalokaryocyte were normal. At admission, the counts of white blood cell were 1.63&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, the counts of the neutrophil granulocyte were 0.17&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, the hemoglobin concentration was 86&#x200A;g/L, and the counts of platelet were 247&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. Thyroid function tests&#x2014;free thyroxine, total thyroxine, and thyroid-stimulating hormone&#x2014;were within the normal range; free triiodothyronine was 2.22&#x200A;pmol/L and total triiodothyronine was 1.05&#x200A;nmol/L. Ultrasonography of abdomen, fetus, and urine showed that all tested areas were normal. The tests of immunoglobulin M (IgM) against cytomegalovirus, IgM against rubella virus, IgM against <italic>Toxoplasma</italic>, herpes simplex type I virus, herpes simplex type II virus, and interferon &#x3B3; release assay were negative. Neutrophil granulocyte antibody was negative. Antinuclear antibodies (ANA) were detected at a dilution of 1:40, while anti-dsDNA, antiphospholipid antibody, and neutrophil granulocyte antibody were negative. Erythrocyte sedimentation rate was 113&#x200A;mm/h; C-reactive protein was 8.74&#x200A;mg/dL; hepatitis, human immunodeficiency virus, and <italic>Treponema pallidum</italic> were negative; and Epstein&#x2013;Barr virus DNA was &lt;1.0E+003. Women are more vulnerable to infections during the gestational period, and infections in pregnant women are often more hazardous. The patient was diagnosed as having pneumonia based on the symptoms (fever, cough, phlegm, and positive signs in the lungs), high procalcitonin shown by laboratory examinations, and positive results of phlegm cultivation.</p>
      <p>During hospitalization, wide-spectrum antibiotics and fluconazole were given as anti-infective therapy. Pulse therapy of granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF), &#x3B3;-globulin, white blood cell&#x2013;boosting agents, and glucocorticoids were given as auxiliary treatment. Four days after therapy, the counts of white blood cell and neutrophil had no obvious changes (white blood cell 2.33&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, neutrophil 0.3&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). Bone marrow biopsy was reperformed; the results of bone marrow biopsy reperformed by our hospital also showed that agranulocytosis was detected, and levels of red blood cell and megalokaryocyte were normal. Then the tests of autoimmune antibody, cardioultrasonography, and ultrasonography of abdomen, fetus, and urine were performed to reassure that no abnormality was missed. Since pregnancy was a contraindication of x-ray examination, x-ray was not performed. After receiving all therapy, the patient experienced a decrease of body temperature and procalcitonin level, but the levels of white blood cell and neutrophil did not increase (see Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Six days later, the patient had a cesarean section and delivered a healthy infant in her 39th week of gestation. Apgar scores of the infant were 9, 10, and 10, respectively, at 1, 5, and 10 minutes.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Variation tendency of body temperature. (&#x2217;) The operative day.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e5717-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Variation tendency of leukocyte and neutrophil. (&#x2217;) The operative day.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e5717-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Anti-infective therapy was continued (no schemes were changed). The patient had a good recovery after 24 hours; her temperature returned to normal; the count of white blood cell rose to 2.41&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> and the count of neutrophils rose to 1.38&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup> days. Her counts of white blood cell and neutrophils gradually returned to a normal state. Three days later, the count of white blood cell was 5.39&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> and the count of neutrophil was 1.49&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;10<sup>9</sup>&#x200A;L<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. A week later, the patient was successfully discharged without any complications. One-year postoperational follow-up showed that the tests of routine blood test, C-reactive protein, and neutrophil antibody were all within normal range and the baby was healthy, without any deformations or other diseases. The present case report was published on the premise of the patent's informed consent, and informed consent form was filled and signed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this case report, the patient was a young woman who was regularly using levothyroxine sodium for her hypothyroidism for a long time. The patient did not suffer from agranulocytosis until the third trimester, in spite of the fact that levothyroxine sodium is safe for pregnant women and no evidence shows the side effects of levothyroxine sodium including agranulocytosis.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> Hypothyroidism has been associated with an increased risk of several complications including preeclampsia, gestational hypertension, placental abruption, preterm delivery, etc.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> At the same time, there is no evidence showing that hypothyroidism can lead to agranulocytosis and the patient had no history of using antibiotics, antithyroid drugs, cytotoxic drugs, or other medications that are the definite cause of agranulocytosis. Therefore, we believe that drug-induced agranulocytosis is less possible in this case.</p>
      <p>The test of autoantibodies showed that ANA was detected at a dilution of 1:40, but double-stranded DNA, antiphospholipid antibody, and neutrophil granulocyte antibody were negative. The literatures suggest that approximately 30% of the normal population with ANA detected at a dilution of 1:40 has a false-positive result.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> At the same time, the treatments of G-CSF, &#x3B3;-globulin, white blood cell&#x2013;boosting agents, and glucocorticoids almost had no effect on the patient's condition.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> So, we think that it is less likely that the patient was experiencing systemic lupus erythematosus or other autoimmune diseases.</p>
      <p>In the second and third trimesters of gestation, the counts of neutrophil gradually fell, and pneumonia occurred in the third trimester, namely, neutropenia prior to lung infection. The anti-infection therapeutic strategy was not effective until 24 hours after delivery. In terms of time, the turning point at which the symptoms and counts of neutrophil returned to normal was the termination of pregnancy and anti-infective therapy was relatively short. Thus, we conclude that agranulocytosis seems to be associated with pregnancy itself and immune tolerance induced by the fetus during pregnancy. The maternal immune system may inhibit the immune response or generate some kinds of inhibitor to protect the fetus during pregnancy.<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup> With the termination of pregnancy, the released immune suppression and some certain elevated related biomarkers may be the reason for the patient's rehabilitation. We also suggest that termination of pregnancy may be an effective treatment for pregnancy complicated with agranulocytosis.</p>
      <sec>
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Potential defects</title>
        <p>First, agranulocytosis was prior to pneumonia, but the possibility that agranulocytosis was caused by pneumonia cannot be excluded. The patient received integrated treatment including anti-infection treatment, G-CSF, &#x3B3;-globulin, hormone, antibiotics, antifungi agents, etc. However, her symptoms were not alleviated until the patient had a cesarean section, so we tend to believe that the pneumonia was an additional manifestation of agranulocytosis.<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> Second, due to the relatively long disease duration, the patient may have taken some drugs inducing agranulocytosis, but she could not remember, namely, the existence of information risk of bias.<sup>[<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Agranulocytosis during pregnancy seems to be associated with immunosuppression induced by immunoregulations and termination of pregnancy may be effective for refractory pregnancy complicated with agranulocytosis, but further studies are needed to confirm this.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: ANA = antinuclear antibodies, G-CSF = granulocyte colony-stimulating factor.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="equal">
        <p>HW and J-LS contributed equally to the article.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>Authorship: HW wrote the manuscript; J-LS organized related information; Z-LZ and H-HP were responsible for checking and modification.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>[1]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Medicine DCCO</collab><article-title>Physiology of Pregnancy. Chapter 41</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>[2]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Immune regulation of conception and embryo implantation&#x2014;all about quality control?</article-title>
<source>J Reprod Immunol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20347158</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>[3]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Teles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenclussen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulatory T cells and their role in pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Am J Reprod Immunol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20331584</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>[4]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rukavina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Immunology of the Pregnancy</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Zagreb</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>Medicinska Naklada</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>[5]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weetman</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Immunity, thyroid function and pregnancy: molecular mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20421883</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>[6]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The Clinical significance of procalcitonin in hematological malignancies with agranulocytosis and infection after chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Basic &amp; Clinical Oncology</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>01</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>[7]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Infection and pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Rev Prat</source>
<year>1991</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>543</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>[8]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomimatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A case of pregnancy associated with cyclic neutropenia</article-title>. <source>Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand</source>
<year>1995</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>836</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8533571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>[9]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Candido</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bortolotto</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Strabelli</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Case 4/2011&#x2014;agranulocytosis and puerperal sepsis in women after the use of ceftriaxone</article-title>. <source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>e20</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22002032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>[10]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pregnancy in bone marrow failure syndromes: Diamond&#x2013;Blackfan anaemia and Shwachman&#x2013;Diamond syndrome</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>
<year>1999</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10520024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>[11]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polcz</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiller</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Whetham</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pregnancy in patients with cyclic neutropenia</article-title>. <source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>169</volume><issue>(2 pt 1)</issue>:<fpage>393</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8362953</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>[12]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chevassut</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pregnancy in Shwachman&#x2013;Diamond syndrome: a novel genetic mutation with minimal consequence</article-title>. <source>BMJ Case Rep</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>2012</volume>: </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>[13]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulte-Pelkum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Limited reliability of the indirect immunofluorescence technique for the detection of anti-Rib-P antibodies</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res Ther</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>R131</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19000323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>[14]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tajiri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antithyroid drug-induced agranulocytosis: how has granulocyte colony-stimulating factor changed therapy?</article-title>
<source>Thyroid</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>292</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15785251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>[15]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryosuke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsuhiro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazunori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Exposure of drugs for hypertension, diabetes, and autoimmune disease during pregnancy and perinatal outcomes: an investigation of the regulator in Japan</article-title>. <source>Medicine</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>[16]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubalewskadydejczyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Treatment and screening of hypothyroidism in pregnancy: results of a European survey</article-title>. <source>Eur J Endocrinol</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>166</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22023792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>[17]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#xE4;nnist&#xF6;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Thyroid diseases and adverse pregnancy outcomes in a contemporary US cohort</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>2725</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23744409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>[18]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Immune system modifications and feto-maternal immune tolerance</article-title>. <source>Chin Med J (Engl)</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>3171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25189965</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>[19]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Urinary tract infection (UTI) caused by <italic>Fusarium proliferatum</italic> in an agranulocytosis patient and a review of published reports</article-title>. <source>Mycopathologia</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26442855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R20">
        <label>[20]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prophylactic first-line antibiotics reduce infectious fever and shorten hospital stay during chemotherapy-induced agranulocytosis in childhood acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>. <source>Acta Haematol</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24525963</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
