<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27603373</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5023896</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000004756</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">04756</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>4300</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>First case report of an adrenocortical carcinoma caused by a <italic>BRCA2</italic> mutation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>El Ghorayeb</surname>
            <given-names>Nada</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grunenwald</surname>
            <given-names>Solange</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nolet</surname>
            <given-names>Serge</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Primeau</surname>
            <given-names>Vanessa</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>C&#xF4;t&#xE9;</surname>
            <given-names>St&#xE9;phanie</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Maugard</surname>
            <given-names>Christine M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lacroix</surname>
            <given-names>Andr&#xE9;</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gaboury</surname>
            <given-names>Louis</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bourdeau</surname>
            <given-names>Isabelle</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref>
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Dora.</surname>
            <given-names>Zelena</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of Endocrinology</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Pathology</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Division of Clinical Genetics, Department of Medicine and Research Center (CRCHUM), Centre hospitalier de l&#x2019;Universit&#xE9; de Montr&#xE9;al, Montreal, QC, Canada.</aff>
      <author-notes id="cor1">
        <corresp><label>&#x2217;</label>Correspondence: Isabelle Bourdeau, Department of Medicine, H&#xF4;tel-Dieu du CHUM, 3840 rue Saint-Urbain, Montr&#xE9;al, Qu&#xE9;bec, Canada H2W 1T8 (e-mail: <email>isabelle.bourdeau@umontreal.ca</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>95</volume>
      <issue>36</issue>
      <elocation-id>e4756</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-95-e4756.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <sec sec-type="background">
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>Adrenocortical carcinoma (ACC) may rarely be a component of inherited cancer syndromes such as Li-Fraumeni syndrome and Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome. ACC caused by a <italic>BRCA2</italic> mutation has never been reported.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
          <title>Methods:</title>
          <p>Nucleotide sequencing of <italic>BRCA2</italic> in lymphocyte and tumoral DNA of a 50-year-old male who presented with an androgen-secreting ACC and a strong family history of breast, ovarian, and pancreatic cancers.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="results">
          <title>Results:</title>
          <p>A germline <italic>BRCA2</italic> 2&#x200A;bp heterozygous deletion at nucleotide 8765 (8765delAG) leading to a frameshift mutation (p.Glu2846GlyfsX23) was detected. Only the <italic>BRCA2</italic> deleted allele was retained in the ACC tumoral DNA compared with the control DNA supporting a loss of heterozygosity in the tumor.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="conclusion">
          <title>Conclusion:</title>
          <p>This is the first reported case of a patient with ACC associated with a <italic>BRCA2</italic> germline mutation. Loss of heterozygosity in ACC DNA suggests a causal link with the <italic>BRCA2</italic> 8765delAG mutation.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>adrenocortical carcinoma</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>BRCA2</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>TP53</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Adrenocortical carcinomas (ACC) are mainly sporadic, but may be found in 3% to 5% of some genetic syndromes such as Li-Fraumeni syndrome (LFS), Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome (BWS), Lynch syndrome, familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP), and in &lt;1% of multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) syndromes.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> Germline mutations in <italic>BRCA1</italic> (MIM 113705) and <italic>BRCA2</italic> (MIM 600185) genes account for cancer predisposition in majority of families with breast only or breast&#x2013;ovarian cancer families.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> To date, <italic>BRCA2</italic> mutation in ACC has never been reported. We describe here a case of ACC associated with a germline <italic>BRCA2</italic> mutation in a family whose cancer history was compatible with a Li-Fraumeni-like (LFL) syndrome.</p>
      <sec>
        <label>1.1</label>
        <title>Clinical case</title>
        <p>A 50-year-old French Canadian male with no previous medical history was evaluated for a palpable lesion in his left flank. He denied abdominal pain; his review of systems and physical examination were only pertinent for the palpable mass that was hard and nontender. Ultrasound and MRI showed a retroperitoneal mass of 18.8&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;11&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;14.9&#x200A;cm (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A, B) suspicious of an adrenal tumor. The endocrine work-up was negative except for increased levels of DHEA-S (9.9&#x200A;&#x3BC;mol/L N: 0.5&#x2013;5.5). Following surgical resection, pathology confirmed an ACC of 18&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;17&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;13&#x200A;cm with negative margins (Weiss score &gt;3) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>C). The patient was referred to us postoperatively with a unique lytic lesion of the right acetabulum present on fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) scan. Bone CT scan and scintigraphy suggested a bone metastasis, which was confirmed by biopsy, consequently establishing a diagnosis of stage IV ACC.</p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Abdominal MRI in sagittal (A) and transverse (B) sections of the patient showing an 18.8&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;11&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;14.9&#x200A;cm mass in the left anterior pararenal space with a hyperintense signal in T1 and several hypointense nodules. (C) ACC, macroscopic picture. Nucleotide sequencing of <italic>BRCA2</italic> gene exon 20 revealed a 2&#x200A;bp heterozygous deletion 8765delAG or c.8537_8538delAG leading to a frameshift (p.Glu2846Glyfs) and a stop codon in the leucocyte DNA from the patient (D). Only the deleted allele was retained in the ACC tumoral DNA (E) compared with a nonmutated control DNA (F), suggesting a loss of heterozygosity in the tumor. (G) The frame shift changes on the amino acid sequences (amino acids in green) compared with the normal amino acid sequences (amino acids in black).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e4756-g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The patient was offered genetic counseling; his family history revealed that his mother was diagnosed with breast cancer at 53 years old (yo). Among his maternal aunts, one developed breast cancer at 46 yo, one was affected by ovarian cancer at 61 yo, and another one had pancreatic cancer (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Nine female maternal cousins were affected with breast cancer between 29 and 53 yo, 2 of them were early-onset breast cancers diagnosed before the age of 35. Another cousin was suspected to be affected by an osteosarcoma at 11 yo (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The 8765delAG <italic>BRCA2</italic> mutation was identified in this family.</p>
        <fig id="F2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Familial pedigree of the patient's maternal branch, in which the French Canadian founder mutation <italic>BRCA2</italic> 8765delAG was found to be associated with a predisposition for breast, ovarian, and pancreatic cancers. The arrow shows the index patient. Squares: men, circles: women, black figures: individuals with cancers. Diagonal line = deceased person. Ages upper levels: age at diagnosis, ages lower levels: age of death. Br = breast cancer, Brbil = bilateral breast cancer, Bone = osteosarcoma, Co = colon cancer, Lg = lung cancer, Ov = ovarian cancer, Thr = throat cancer, Pan = pancreatic cancer.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e4756-g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>1.2</label>
        <title>Molecular genetic analysis</title>
        <p>After giving his written informed consent, the patient had genetic analysis for the 8765delAG <italic>BRCA2</italic> mutation and the <italic>TP53</italic> gene. Exon numbering is based on the NCBI references sequences U43746 and NC_000017.9, respectively. Lymphocyte DNA was obtained and tumoral DNA was extracted from microdissected formalin-fixed paraffin embedded ACC tumor after a 56&#xB0;C overnight Proteinase K digestion in an extraction buffer (50&#x200A;mM Tris&#x2013;HCl, pH 7.5; 1&#x200A;mM EDTA; 0.5% Tween 20, 1&#x200A;mg/mL Proteinase K) using a laboratory-developed method. <italic>BRCA2</italic> exon 20 was amplified by a polymerase chain reaction and directly sequenced (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, USA). <italic>TP53</italic> gene was analyzed by multiplex ligation-dependent probe amplification and direct sequencing. The germline <italic>BRCA2</italic> 2&#x200A;bp heterozygous deletion at nucleotide 8765 (8765delAG) (Breast Cancer Information Core nomenclature) or c.8537_8538delAG (human genome variation society nomenclature) was identified. The deletion leads to a frameshift mutation (p.Glu2846Glyfs) and a stop codon (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>D, G). Only the <italic>BRCA2</italic> deleted allele was retained in the ACC tumoral DNA compared with the control DNA suggesting a loss of heterozygosity in the tumor (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>E&#x2013;G). In addition, <italic>TP53</italic> gene analysis revealed a previously reported heterozygous polymorphism in exon 4 (c.215C&gt;G, p.Pro72Arg) (rs1042522, NM_000546.5).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>1.3</label>
        <title>Interventions and outcome</title>
        <p>Surgical resection of the ACC metastasis was followed by irradiation. Mitotane therapy was initiated, and it was well tolerated with no serious side effects with doses escalating progressively up to 6&#x200A;g/d. He was replaced by hydrocortisone (60&#x200A;mg/d) for adrenal insufficiency. Unfortunately 9 months later, 2 new hepatic lesions and 3 pulmonary nodules were identified by FDG-PET scan. He received several regimens of chemotherapy: 3 cycles of EDP (etoposide, doxorubicin and cisplatin), and then Streptozocin followed by sunitinib with no serious adverse events related to therapy. Unfortunately, therapeutic failure was evident by disease progression, so he received palliative care until he passed away 3 years after his initial diagnosis and surgery.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>ACC is rare with an incidence of 0.7 to 2.0 cases per million populations per year.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> Analyses of inherited syndromes related to ACC led to the progress in the pathogenesis of ACC including the LFS due to germline <italic>TP53</italic> mutations, the BWS due to the deregulation of imprinted genes in the chromosome 11p15.5 region, which contains the insulin-like growth factor 2 and the closed linked <italic>H19</italic> gene in the imprinting center 1, the Lynch syndrome due to a defect in the mismatch repair system (<italic>MSH2, MSH6, MLH1</italic>), and more rarely the MEN1 (<italic>menin</italic>) and FAP syndromes (<italic>APC</italic>).<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>LFS results from a germline mutation in the <italic>TP53</italic> gene predisposing individuals to cancers with early onset, including breast cancer, soft tissue and osteosarcomas, brain cancers, leukemia, and ACC. TP53 mutations account for up to 50% to 70% of the families with classic LFS.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> Patients presenting with incomplete features of LFS are referred as having LFL syndrome. Up to 20% to 40% of LFL families carry TP53 mutations.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> Of all the cancers associated with mutations of <italic>TP53</italic>, ACC is the one whose frequency is the most increased compared with the general population.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> The family history of our patient prompted us to search for a genetic cause of his ACC. Two genes were studied: <italic>BRCA2</italic> because the French Canadian founder mutation 8765delAG was previously found to be associated with breast, ovarian, and pancreatic cancers in his maternal family, and <italic>TP53</italic> because of his family history and his diagnosis of ACC; recently the prevalence of germline <italic>TP53</italic> mutations in apparently sporadic adult ACC patients was found to be between 3% and 6%<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> supporting to propose <italic>TP53</italic> genetic analysis to all patients with ACC.</p>
      <p>We found that our patient was a heterozygous carrier of the 8765delAG <italic>BRCA2</italic> mutation. The <italic>BRCA2</italic> 8765delAG or c.8537_8538delAG mutation was first described in breast cancer families from French-Canadian and Jewish-Yemenite populations<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> and is one of the most frequent founder mutations reported in French Canadian breast-only or breast-ovarian cancer families; many of the families had members with cancers at other sites but no ACC was described in <italic>BRCA2</italic>-linked families to this date.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Two cases of adrenal tumors in <italic>BRCA1/BRCA2</italic> mutation carriers have been described previously: the first was a cystic lymphangioma in a 46 yo Ashkenazi woman diagnosed with breast and ovarian cancer and carrying the 185delAG mutation in the <italic>BRCA1</italic> gene; the second was a pheochromocytoma in a 61 yo Ashkenazi woman diagnosed with breast cancer and harboring the <italic>BRCA2</italic> 6174delT mutation. Both masses were removed, but no tumoral DNA was available for genetic studies.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> Adrenal tumors in these cases could have occurred by coincidence. In the case of our patient, loss of heterozygosity in ACC tumoral DNA as described previously in most tumors related to <italic>BRCA2</italic> gene mutations<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> suggests a causal link between the <italic>BRCA2</italic> 8765delAG mutation and the ACC. The simultaneous presence of <italic>TP53</italic> gene p.Pro72Arg polymorphism and the <italic>BRCA2</italic> 8765delAG mutation may suggest a potential interaction between these 2 genetic defects.</p>
      <p>This case of ACC suggests that a detailed medical and family history may reveal an unsuspected underlying hereditary condition and should be performed in all patients with ACC. Patients should be referred for specialized genetic counseling to understand the risks and benefits of genetic testing; adequate informed consent should be obtained as well as posttest genetic counseling. Based on recent findings, in the absence of family history suggesting any other genetic conditions, at least the <italic>TP53</italic> gene analysis should be offered to all ACC patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, the efficacy of ACC surveillance strategy among children found to have a <italic>TP53</italic> mutation was proven with better outcome and survival.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> Thus, the identification of an unsuspected germline <italic>TP53</italic> mutation may entail a clinical surveillance protocol for the detection of asymptomatic nonadrenal neoplasms in individuals with germline <italic>TP53</italic> mutations.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>This is the first reported case of ACC associated with a <italic>BRCA2</italic> germline mutation. Loss of heterozygosity in tumoral DNA confirms that the <italic>BRCA2</italic> 8765delAG mutation plays a role in adrenal oncogenesis supporting that ACC may be included in the spectrum of cancer-related <italic>BRCA2</italic> gene.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors thank the patient and the patient's family, and also thank Christine Caron, Laurence Buisseret, John Stagg, and Katia Kaceres for technical assistance.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: ACC = Adrenocortical carcinoma, BWS = Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome, FAP = familial adenomatous polyposis, FDG-PET = fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography, LFL = Li-Fraumeni-like, LFS = Li-Fraumeni syndrome, MEN1 = multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="equal">
        <p>NEG and SG equally contributed to this work as first authors.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>Authorship: Conception and design&#x2014;SG, CMM, SN, and IB; collection and assembly of data&#x2014;NEG, SG, CMM, SN, VP, SC, and IB; data analysis and interpretation&#x2014;NEG, SG, CMM, SN, LG, AL, and IB; manuscript writing&#x2014;NEG, SG, SN, and IB; final approval of manuscript&#x2014;all authors.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="supported-by">
        <p>Funding: This study was supported by a salary Grant FRQS (Fonds de la recherche du Qu&#xE9;bec-Sant&#xE9; (IB).</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>Disclosure: The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzuco</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Genetic aspects of adrenocortical tumours and hyperplasias</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Endocrinol</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Else</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabolch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Adrenocortical carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Endocr Rev</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>282</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>326</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24423978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmigiani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Meta-analysis of BRCA1 and BRCA2 penetrance</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Oncol</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1329</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1333</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416853</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kebebew</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Duh</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Extent of disease at presentation and outcome for adrenocortical carcinoma: have we made progress?</article-title>
<source><italic>World J Surg</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>872</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>878</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16680602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>McGown</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorncroft</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Germ-line mutations of TP53 in Li-Fraumeni families: an extended study of 39 families</article-title>. <source><italic>Cancer Res</italic></source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>3245</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3252</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9242456</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alston</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Relative frequency and morphology of cancers in carriers of germline TP53 mutations</article-title>. <source><italic>Oncogene</italic></source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>4621</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4628</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11498785</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fassnacht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>TP53 germline mutations in adult patients with adrenocortical carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>E476</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>E485</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22170717</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Else</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of germline TP53 mutations in a prospective series of unselected patients with adrenocortical carcinoma</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>E119</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>E125</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23175693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mutation analysis of the BRCA2 gene in 49 site-specific breast cancer families</article-title>. <source><italic>Nat Genet</italic></source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>120</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8673090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lerer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Peretz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The 8765delAG mutation in BRCA2 is common among Jews of Yemenite extraction</article-title>. <source><italic>Am J Hum Genet</italic></source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>274</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9634522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tonin</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mes-Masson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Futreal</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Founder BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations in French Canadian breast and ovarian cancer families</article-title>. <source><italic>Am J Hum Genet</italic></source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1341</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1351</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9792861</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiri-Svredlov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruchim-Bar Sade</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Adrenal tumors in BRCA1/BRCA2 mutation carriers</article-title>. <source><italic>Am J Med Genet</italic></source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>279</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11169568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>BRCA1 and BRCA2: different roles in a common pathway of genome protection</article-title>. <source><italic>Nat Rev Cancer</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22193408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Custodio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Parise</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiesel Filho</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Impact of neonatal screening and surveillance for the TP53 R337H mutation on early detection of childhood adrenocortical tumors</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Oncol</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>2619</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2626</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23733769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabori</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiffman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Biochemical and imaging surveillance in germline TP53 mutation carriers with Li-Fraumeni syndrome: a prospective observational study</article-title>. <source><italic>Lancet Oncol</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>559</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>567</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21601526</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
