<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27893666</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5134859</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-16-01426</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000005304</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">05304</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>4900</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Four weeks of paritaprevir/ritonavir/ombitasvir plus dasabuvir encountering dengue fever resulted in sustained virological response in an HCV patient</article-title>
        <subtitle>A case report</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Chung-Feng</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>f</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jang</surname>
            <given-names>Tyng-Yuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            <given-names>Po-Liang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>d</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Ming-Lung</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>e</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Borg.</surname>
            <given-names>Brian</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Hepatobiliary Division, Department of Internal Medicine and Hepatitis Center, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical University</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Faculty of Internal Medicine, College of Medicine, Center for Infectious Disease and Cancer Research, Lipid Science and Aging Research Center, Kaohsiung Medical University</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Occupational Medicine, Kaohsiung Municipal Ta-Tung Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical University</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, and Department of Internal Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical University</aff>
      <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Institute of Biomedical Sciences, National Sun Yat-Sen University, Kaohsiung</aff>
      <aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Health Management Center, Kaohsiung Municipal Ta-Tung Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical University, Taiwan.</aff>
      <author-notes id="cor1">
        <corresp><label>&#x2217;</label>Correspondence: Ming-Lung Yu, Hepatobiliary Division, Department of Internal Medicine, Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital, Kaohsiung, Taiwan (e-mail: <email>fish6069@gmail.com</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>95</volume>
      <issue>47</issue>
      <elocation-id>e5304</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-95-e5304.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <sec sec-type="background">
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>Direct antiviral agent (DAA) has been the standard of care for patients with hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection. Twelve weeks of paritaprevir/ritonavir/ombitasvir plus dasabuvir (PROD) with or without ribavirin has shown to have a sustained virological response at post-treatment 12 weeks (SVR12) rate of &gt;90% in HCV genotype 1 (HCV-1) patients.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
          <title>Methods:</title>
          <p>We report a HCV-1b patient who received only 25 days of PROD treatment.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="results">
          <title>Results:</title>
          <p>The patient early terminated treatment due to dengue fever but eventually achieved SVR12. It may attribute to low baseline viral loads and extraordinarily rapid suppression of HCV after treatment day1.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="conclusion">
          <title>Conclusions:</title>
          <p>The finding may shed light for possible response-guided-therapy for so-called ultra-super-responders in the DAA era. Whether the dengue virus, the Flaviviridae family as with HCV, enhanced the HCV clearance remains unclear and needs further exploration.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>DAA</kwd>
        <kwd>dengue fever</kwd>
        <kwd>HCV</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Direct antiviral agent (DAA) has been the standard of care for patients with hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection. The current strategy has moved to interferon-free regimens. The mainstream treatment duration are 12 to 24 weeks depending on regimens and patient characteristics.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> Paritaprevir/ritonavir/ombitasvir plus dasabuvir (PROD) with or without ribavirin has shown to have a sustained virological response at post-treatment 12 weeks (SVR12) rate of &gt;90% in HCV genotype 1 (HCV-1) patients. In addition to the development of pangenotypic, high potency DAAs, efforts now are made trying to abbreviate treatment duration to 4 to 8 weeks without compromising efficacy. We herein report an HCV-1b patient who received only 25 days of PROD treatment. The patient early terminated treatment due to dengue fever but eventually achieved SVR12.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Patient information, therapeutic Intervention, follow-up, and outcome</title>
      <p>The 81-year-old female had the history of chronic HCV infection for &gt;30 years and co-morbidity of depressive disorder and dementia under regular treatment with Quetiapine 50&#x200A;mg/day. Due to fear of adverse events and underlying psychiatric disorder, she was ineligible to pegylated interferon/ribavirin, the current reimbursed regimen in Taiwan. The genotype and pretreatment viral loads was HCV-1b and 17,019&#x200A;IU/mL (real-time HCV; Abbott Molecular, Des Plaines IL; detection limit: 12&#x200A;IU/mL). The sonography revealed heterogeneous liver parenchyma without splenomegaly and visible collateral vessels. The result of the acoustic radiation force impulse (ARFI) was 1.3&#x200A;m/s, which corresponded to fibrosis stage 2.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> Daily fixed-dose combination of paritaprevir/ritonavir/ombitasvir (150&#x200A;mg/100&#x200A;mg/25&#x200A;mg) plus twice-daily dasabuvir (250&#x200A;mg) was administered for the treatment of chronic HCV infection. Quetiapine was held transiently before antiviral therapy to avoid drug&#x2013;drug interactions. The HCV ribonucleic acid (RNA) became rapidly undetectable on day 1, followed by day 7 and day 14 after dosing. Unfortunately, she was admitted due to fever, progressive thrombocytopenia, and elevated liver enzymes. Dengue fever infection with dengue virus genotype 2 (SYBR Green-based quantitative RT-PCR) infection was impressed on day 25 of treatment. She received supportive treatment with antipyretics (paracetamol 500&#x200A;mg/time as needed) and intravenous fluids supply during hospitalization. PROD were terminated due to severe thrombocytopenia (7000/mm<sup>3</sup>). The patient discharged after 7 days supportive inpatient care for dengue fever. Dramatically, the serial testing of serum HCV RNA showed that the patient achieved SVR4, SVR8, and SVR12 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The patients provided written informed consent. The institutional review board in Kaohsiung Medical University Hospital approved the survey.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Serial change of laboratory data and HCV RNA level of the patient.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e5304-g001"/>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>To our knowledge, this is the first report of DAA prescription that encountered dengue fever, and the patient benefited from HCV eradication only by 4 weeks of all oral DAA regimens. The current evidence support 12 to 24 weeks of interferon-free DAAs in treating CHC.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> An 8-week sofosbuvir/ledipasvir is recommended for naive, noncirrhotic HCV-1 patients with baseline viral loads &lt;8 million IU/mL.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> As observed in a phase 2b study that 8 weeks of PROD plus ribavirin had very high SVR rates for naive, noncirrhotic patients of HCV-1b (96%, 23/24) or with low viral loads (&lt;800,000&#x200A;IU/mL, 100%, 9/9).<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> The patient did not take any drug with potential drug&#x2013;drug interaction with PROD. The achievement of SVR to only 25 days of PROD in this patient may attribute to HCV-1b with low baseline viral loads and extraordinarily rapid suppression of HCV after treatment Day 1. As with interferon-based therapy, the finding may shed light for possible response-guided-therapy for so-called ultra-super-responders in the DAA era.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> The strategy may be particular imperative in resource constrained countries. Notably, viral interference might exist in the same host. There are reciprocal suppressions between hepatitis B virus and HCV infections.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Whether the dengue virus, the Flaviviridae family as with HCV, enhances the HCV clearance remains unclear and needs further exploration.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: DAA = direct antiviral agents, HCV = hepatitis C virus, PROD = paritaprevir/ritonavir/ombitasvir/dasabuvir, SVR = sustained virological response.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>[1]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>AASLD/IDSA HCV Guidance Panel</collab>. <article-title>Hepatitis C guidance: AASLD-IDSA recommendations for testing, managing, and treating adults infected with hepatitis C virus</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>932</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26111063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>[2]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvaruso</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cacopardo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of transient elastography and acoustic radiation force impulse for non-invasive staging of liver fibrosis in patients with chronic hepatitis C</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>2112</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21971536</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>[3]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kowdley</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Ledipasvir and sofosbuvir for 8 or 12 weeks for chronic HCV without cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>370</volume>:<fpage>1879</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24720702</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>[4]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kowdley</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Poordad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Phase 2b trial of interferon-free therapy for hepatitis C virus genotype 1</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>370</volume>:<fpage>222</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24428468</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>[5]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>New treatments for HCV: perspective from Asia</article-title>. <source>Clin Liver Dis</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>[6]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>High hepatitis B virus surface antigen levels and favorable interleukin 28B genotype predict spontaneous hepatitis C virus clearance in uremic patients</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24096049</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>[7]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hepatitis C viremia interferes serum hepatitis B virus surface antigen and DNA levels in hepatitis B uremics</article-title>. <source>Hepatol Int</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26202503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
