<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Yonsei Med J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Yonsei Med. J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">YMJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Yonsei Medical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0513-5796</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1976-2437</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Yonsei University College of Medicine</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27593885</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5011289</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3349/ymj.2016.57.6.1523</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
          <subj-group subj-group-type="subheading">
            <subject>Pediatrics</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Case of Pulmonary Interstitial Emphysema Treated by Percutaneous Catheter Insertion in Extremely Low Birth Weight Infant</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Changsin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Jeong Eun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Soon Min</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Eun</surname>
            <given-names>Ho Seon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Min Soo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Kook In</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Namgung</surname>
            <given-names>Ran</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Sungsoo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoon</surname>
            <given-names>Choon Sik</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, Severance Children's Hospital, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Diagnostic Radiology, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>
Corresponding author: Dr. Soon Min Lee, Department of Pediatrics, Yonsei University College of Medicine, 50-1 Yonsei-ro, Seodaemun-gu, Seoul 03722, Korea. Tel: 82-2-2019-3350, Fax: 82-2-3461-9473, <email>smlee@yuhs.ac</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>57</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>1523</fpage>
      <lpage>1526</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Copyright: Yonsei University College of Medicine 2016</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The pulmonary interstitial emphysema (PIE) is a life-threatening illness in premature infants with mechanical ventilation. While most are managed conservatively, decompression would be necessary. Here, we report the first case of PIE treated by percutaneous catheter insertion in an extremely low birth weight (ELBW) infant in Korea. The patient, born with 660 g in 23+2 weeks of gestation, showed PIE in left lower lung on postnatal day 12. Percutaneous catheter insertion was performed on postnatal day 25. The size of PIE decreased, but didn't disappear completely. On postnatal day 42, we exchanged catheter and inserted additional catheter in pleural space. However, sudden desaturation and pneumothorax occurred on postnatal day 44. We changed catheter in pleural space, and pneumothorax and PIE improved. Finally, we successfully removed catheters, and weaned patient out. As in our case, percutaneous catheter insertion would be a useful option for ELBW infants with PIE.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Pulmonary emphysema</kwd>
        <kwd>catheters, indwelling</kwd>
        <kwd>premature infant</kwd>
        <kwd>extremely low birth weight infant</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>The pulmonary interstitial emphysema (PIE) is known as a risk factor of mortality and morbidity related with mechanical ventilation in premature infants with extremely low birth weight (ELBW). By surgical resection, ventilator strategies, steroid administration and selective intubation, PIE can be treated, but percutaneous catheter insertion is also considered as a treatment option for PIE. Herein, we report a case of PIE in an infant with ELBW treated by percutaneous catheter insertion.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A female of 660 g, at a 23+2 weeks of gestation, was born through cesarean section to 38-year-old, gravida 1, para 0 with acute choriodeciduitis, immature synchronous placenta. Antenatal steroid administration was completed. The Apgar scores of the baby were 1 and 3 at 1 and 5 minutes, respectively. Therefore, positive pressure ventilation was applied immediately after birth. Surfactant replacement therapy with synchronized intermittent mandatory ventilation was also applied to the patient when admitted to neonatal intensive care unit. Surfactant replacement therapy was administered one more time at 57 hours after birth due to relapse of respiratory distress syndrome. High frequency oscillatory ventilation (HFOV) was provided by a Drager Babylog VN500 (Dragerwerk Ag &amp; Co., Lubeck, Germany) for adequate ventilation since postnatal day 3. Steroid was administered for adequate ventilation in short period (hydrocortisone 1 mg/kg on day 9, 0.5 mg/kg twice on day 10). On postnatal day 12, a PIE in the left lower lobe was observed on chest X-ray, and the size of emphysema increased gradually (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Mean airway pressure used on the HFOV was 7 cm H<sub>2</sub>O. Frequency was set at 12 Hz and amplitude was 14 cm H<sub>2</sub>O with 0.6 of FiO<sub>2</sub>. Despite of HFOV with low oscillatory frequency and intermittent one lung ventilation, the PIE expanded progressively which shifted of the mediastinum to the right side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). We decided to try percutaneous catheter insertion to evacuate the PIE. Thus, with local anesthesia, a central venous catheter (14 Gauge, Arrow International, Reading, PA, USA) was inserted at left lower side of lung on day 25. After insertion, the size of PIE decreased, but it still remained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). We tried clamping of catheter drainage on day 30 for catheter removal, but PIE was aggravated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). On day 42, we changed catheter at the same location for proper positioning, and additional central intravenous catheter was inserted into pleural space to avoid air leakage. Chest computed tomography (CT) taken on the same day showed multilobulat-ed cystic mass, consistent with PIE in left lower lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). On day 44, sudden desaturation and respiratory distress occurred due to tension pneumothorax. On day 45 the central venous catheter in pleural space was changed to trocar catheter (10 French, Pacific Hospital Supply, Taipei, Taiwan) with suction pressure of -20 mm H<sub>2</sub>O for the sufficient evacuation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E and F</xref>). As pneumothorax was alleviated, the catheter in the pleural space was removed on day 53. We clamped the catheter inserted in PIE on the same day. There was no in-crease in the size of PIE for 48 hours. After assuring no recurrence, we successfully removed the drainage on day 56 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G</xref>). She was weaned from HFOV successfully on day 57 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1H</xref>), and nasal continuous positive airway pressure was applied on day 59. Moderate grade of chronic lung disease was diagnosed. As co-morbidities, patent ductus arteriosus was closed by oral ibuprofen, and retinopathy of prematurity with stage II was treated by ranibizumab injection. She was discharged on day 109 without any support.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>PIE is a life threatening condition of prematurity with the respiratory distress syndrome with mortality reported as high as 53&#x2013;67%.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> PIE derives from air leakage into interstitium from alveolus due to disruption of the alveolar wall basement membrane.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> About 2% of premature infants in neonatal intensive care unit experience PIE.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> For premature infants with respiratory distress syndrome, the incidence rate goes up to 20&#x2013;32%.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> In a retrospective case-controlled study, 24% of ELBW infants developed PIE.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p>
      <p>Prematurity, low birth weight, low Apgar score, high peak inspiratory pressure over 25 cm H<sub>2</sub>O of mechanical ventilation, and in utero exposure to MgSO<sub>4</sub> are known risk factors of PIE.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> In our case, the patient was 23+2 weeks of gestation, and 660 g with Apgar score 1 and 3 at 1 and 5 minutes, respectively. Maximal peak inspiratory pressure was 15 cm H<sub>2</sub>O, and maximal mean airway pressure was 10 cm H<sub>2</sub>O. At the day of PIE first detected, mean airway pressure used on the HFOV was 7 cm H<sub>2</sub>O. Also, there was no prenatal exposure to MgSO<sub>4</sub>. PIE is associated with late development of chronic lung disease in prematurity.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> In our case, the patient was diagnosed as moderate grade of chronic lung disease.</p>
      <p>Prenatal steroids and postnatal surfactant replacement independently and additively reduce mortality, the severity of respiratory distress syndrome, and air leaks in preterm infants.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Antenatal steroid administration (dexamethasone 5 mg bid) on a day before delivery and surfactant replacement (immediate after birth, 57 hours after birth) was done in our case.</p>
      <p>Chest X-ray has been commonly used for diagnosis of PIE. Chest CT is the definitive diagnostic tool that shows characteristic appearance of a soft tissue attenuation nodule or dot-like structures in air-filled cysts.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> However, its use has been limited in ELBW infant. In our case, chest CT was taken on day 42. CT scan was not followed because of marked improvement of chest X-ray and clinical symptom.</p>
      <p>Standard treatment strategy for PIE has not yet been established. Surgical resection was shown to be a treatment of choice for localized PIE when nonsurgical options failed.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Lateral decubitus positioning with uninvolved side down and selective intubation of the main bronchus on the unaffected side are relatively safe and effective. In a review, 43 cases of PIE, pneumatocele, pneumothorax of all 46 cases were successfully treated by unilateral intubation. Mild and reversible complications occurred during the procedure in 52% of cases.<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> In our case, lateral decubitus positioning and unilateral intubation were not beneficial to reduce PIE. Systemic steroid administration for 3 days is known to be associated with significant clinical improvement. In a retrospective case review, 7 of 10 premature infants with PIE after 3 day course of dexamethasone (0.5 mg/kg/day) showed improvement on chest X-ray and 9 of them survived to the term.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Hydrocortisone 1 mg/kg was used on day 9, and 0.5 mg/kg twice on day 10 in our case, and we expected improvement of the gas analysis and clinical symptom, however, chest X-ray showed no improvement. HFOV with a low os-cillatory frequency may provide benefit to preterm infants with severe PIE. By applying HFOV with a low oscillatory frequency to ELBW infant, 71% of infants with bilateral emphysema and all of the infants with unilateral emphysema survived. Therefore, we applied HFOV from 12 Hz oscillation to 6 Hz gradually, keeping the low oscillatory frequency (6&#x2013;8 Hz) for several days, however, there's no significant change of the PIE.</p>
      <p>There are a few reports to describe percutaneous catheter insertion as treatment of PIE, especially in ELBW infants. Milligan, et al.<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> described that 75% of premature infant with PIE were treated by chest tube insertion, Watanabe, et al.<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> reported an ELBW infant (420 g) whose diffuse PIE was evacuated. And Fujii and Moulton<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> reported ELBW infant (533 g) with PIE treated by pigtail catheter insertion into pneumatocele and chest tube to pleural cavity. In our ELBW infant (660 g), PIE was evacuated by insertion of central venous catheter into the PIE.</p>
      <p>To our best knowledge, this is the first report in Korea that describes a case of ELBW infant with PIE refractory to conservative management by percutaneous catheter insertion. In summary, percutaneous catheter insertion into the PIE with consecutive tension release of the overinflated lung by drainage would be a therapeutic option for premature infants suffering from diffuse PIE.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors have no financial conflicts of interest.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morisot</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kacet</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bouchez</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rouland</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dubos</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gremillet</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Risk factors for fatal pulmonary interstitial emphysema in neonates</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <fpage>493</fpage>
          <lpage>495</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2347343</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jassal</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benson</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mogayzel</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous resolution of diffuse persistent pulmonary interstitial emphysema</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>615</fpage>
          <lpage>619</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18433048</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jeng</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsao</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soong</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neonatal air leak syndrome and the role of high-frequency ventilation in its prevention</article-title>
          <source>J Chin Med Assoc</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>551</fpage>
          <lpage>559</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23158032</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Greenough</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dixon</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roberton</surname>
              <given-names>NR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary interstitial emphysema</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>1046</fpage>
          <lpage>1051</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6508339</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hart</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McNair</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gamsu</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Price</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary interstitial emphysema in very low birthweight infants</article-title>
          <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>612</fpage>
          <lpage>615</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6351760</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bawa</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soontarapornchai</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perenyi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldfisher</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amodio</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development of localized pulmonary interstitial emphysema in a late preterm infant without mechanical ventilation</article-title>
          <source>Case Rep Pediatr</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>2014</volume>
          <fpage>429797</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24744939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verma</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chandra</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niwas</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komaroff</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Risk factors and clinical outcomes of pulmonary interstitial emphysema in extremely low birth weight infants</article-title>
          <source>J Perinatol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>197</fpage>
          <lpage>200</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16493434</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Study of the risk factors for pulmonary interstitial emphysema related to mechanical ventilator care</article-title>
          <source>Korean J Pediatr</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>1179</fpage>
          <lpage>1184</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cochran</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pilling</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shaw</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The relationship of pulmonary interstitial emphysema to subsequent type of chronic lung disease</article-title>
          <source>Br J Radiol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>1155</fpage>
          <lpage>1157</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7874412</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Polin</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carlo</surname>
              <given-names>WA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <collab>Committee on Fetus and Newborn</collab>
          <collab>American Academy of Pediatrics</collab>
          <article-title>Surfactant replacement therapy for preterm and term neonates with respiratory distress</article-title>
          <source>Pediatrics</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>156</fpage>
          <lpage>163</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379227</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Donnelly</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frush</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Localized radiolucent chest lesions in neonates: causes and differentiation</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>172</volume>
          <fpage>1651</fpage>
          <lpage>1658</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10350310</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>St Cyr</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>TR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burke</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foker</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The changing spectrum of cystic pulmonary lesions requiring surgical resection in infants</article-title>
          <source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>332</fpage>
          <lpage>339</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3974268</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Joseph</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bromiker</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toker</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schimmel</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldberg</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Picard</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unilateral lung intubation for pulmonary air leak syndrome in neonates: a case series and a review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Am J Perinatol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>151</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20703979</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzgerald</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Willis</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Usher</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Outerbridge</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dexamethasone for pulmonary interstitial emphysema in preterm infants</article-title>
          <source>Biol Neonate</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>34</fpage>
          <lpage>39</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9458940</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Milligan</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Issler</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Massam</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reynolds</surname>
              <given-names>EO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment of neonatal pulmonary interstitial emphysema by lung puncture</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>1010</fpage>
          <lpage>1011</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6143922</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Momoi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Go</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imamura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaneko</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Percutaneous evacuation of diffuse pulmonary interstitial emphysema by lung puncture in a baby with extremely low birth weight: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Med Case Rep</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>325</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23013845</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fujii</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moulton</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Percutaneous catheter evacuation of a pneumatocele in an extremely premature infant with respiratory failure</article-title>
          <source>J Perinatol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>516</fpage>
          <lpage>518</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13679944</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Chest radiographic findings. (A) Initial finding of the PIE on day 12. (B) PIE aggravated on day 25. (C) Decreasing size of the PIE on day 30. (D) The size of the PIE increased after stopping the drainage on day 30. (E) Tension pneumothorax on day 45. (F) Improved PIE after decompression on day 45. (G) Removal of both tubes and stopping the drainage on day 56. (H) Endotracheal extubation on day 57. PIE, pulmonary interstitial emphysema.</title>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-57-1523-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>CT scan findings. About 3.7&#xD7;2.9 cm multilobulated cystic mass is noted at left lower lobe.</title>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ymj-57-1523-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
