<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Chemother</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Chemother</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IC</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Infection &amp; Chemotherapy</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2093-2340</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2092-6448</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Society of Infectious Diseases and Korean Society for Chemotherapy</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27659433</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5048008</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3947/ic.2016.48.3.234</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Olecranon Osteomyelitis due to <italic>Actinomyces meyeri</italic>: Report of a Culture-Proven Case</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8713-1497</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Ji-Yeon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>Eun Kyung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Moon</surname>
            <given-names>Song Mi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Seo</surname>
            <given-names>Yiel-Hea</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeong</surname>
            <given-names>Juhyeon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>Hyuni</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Dongki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4640-9525</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Yoon Soo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Gachon University School of Medicine, Gil Medical Center, Incheon, <country>Korea</country>.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Gachon University School of Medicine, Gil Medical Center, Incheon, <country>Korea</country>.</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Pathology, Gachon University School of Medicine, Gil Medical Center, Incheon, <country>Korea</country>.</aff>
      <aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Physiology, Gachon University School of Medicine, Gil Medical Center, Incheon, <country>Korea</country>.</aff>
      <aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, National Health Insurance Service Ilsan Hospital, Goyang, <country>Korea</country>.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Corresponding Author: Yoon Soo Park, MD, PhD. Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, National Health Insurance Service Ilsan Hospital, 100 Ilsan-ro Ilsan-donggu Goyang-si 10444, Gyeonggi-do, Korea. Tel: +82-31-900-0500, Fax: +82-31-900-0049, <email>ysparkok2@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>48</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>234</fpage>
      <lpage>238</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>03</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 by The Korean Society of Infectious Diseases and Korean Society for Chemotherapy</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>
<italic>Actinomyces meyeri</italic> is a Gram positive, strict anaerobic bacterium, which was first described by Meyer in 1911. Primary actinomycotic osteomyelitis is rare and primarily affects the cervicofacial region, including mandible. We present an unusual case of osteomyelitis of a long bone combined with myoabscess due to <italic>A. meyeri</italic>. A 70-year-old man was admitted for pain and pus discharge of the right elbow. Twenty-five days before admission, he had hit his elbow against a table. MRI of the elbow showed a partial tear of the distal triceps tendon and myositis. He underwent open debridement and partial bone resection for the osteomyelitis of the olecranon. Biopsy showed no sulfur granules, but acute and chronic osteomyelitis. The excised tissue grew <italic>A. meyeri</italic> and <italic>Peptoniphilus asaccharolyticus</italic>. Intravenous ceftriaxone was administered and switched to oral amoxicillin. Infection of the extremities of actinomycosis often poses diagnostic difficulties, but it should not be neglected even when the characteristic pathologic findings are not present.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <kwd>
          <italic>Actinomyces</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Osteomyelitis</kwd>
        <kwd>Olecranon</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Members of the genus <italic>Actinomyces,</italic> originally classified as a fungus because of its branching characteristic, were first described in the early nineteenth century [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. <italic>Actinomyces meyeri,</italic> a Gram positive anaerobic bacterium, is common inhabitant of the oral cavity and human pharynx region, rarely affecting long bones [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Reported cases of osteomyelitis caused by <italic>Actinomyces</italic> spp<italic>.</italic> were mainly the cervicofacial area, usually mandible. Few cases of long bone osteomyelitis caused by <italic>Actinomyces</italic> spp. have been reported.</p>
      <p>In this case report, we present a rare case of olecranon osteomyelitis caused by <italic>A. meyeri</italic> confirmed by culture, not by pathology.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case Report</title>
      <p>A 70-year-old man was referred to our hospital for severe pain, swelling, and pus discharge in his right elbow. Twenty five days prior to admission, he had fallen and injured his right elbow, with a puncture of the elbow with a tear three centimeters long. Five days later, he underwent incision and drainage of his right elbow for an infected abscess at a private clinic. However, despite treatment, the pain and swelling showed rapid progression.</p>
      <p>His medical history was remarkable for uncontrolled type 2 diabetes mellitus for twenty years. He had smoked ten cigarettes daily for 40 years. He denied a history of drug abuse and had not undergone any specific dental treatment.</p>
      <p>At admission, his temperature was 36.6&#xB0;C, blood pressure was 125/80 mmHg, pulse rate was 80 beats/min, and respiration rate 16 breaths/min. His mental status was alert. The wound on the right elbow had a laceration of three centimeters in size. The olecranon was exposed with signs of inflammation of the adjacent muscles with draining discharge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The wound on the right elbow with three-centimeter of laceration and signs of inflammation.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ic-48-234-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>His leukocyte count was 7,280/mm<sup>3</sup>, with 70% neutrophils, 20% lymphocytes, and 6% monocytes. Blood test showed C-reactive protein of 4.69 mg/dl (normal &lt;0.5 mg/dl), an erythrocyte sedimentation rate of 65 mm/h, a high glucose level of 231 mg/dl, aspartate transaminase of 26 U/L and alanine transaminase of 36 U/L. Glucosuria was also noted in the urine analysis and HbA1c was 9.8%.</p>
      <p>Magnetic resonance imaging showed osteomyelitis of olecranon and myoabscess (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A and B</xref>). Empirical ceftriaxone (2 g q24h) and metronidazole (500 mg q8h) were administered intravenously. The patient underwent surgical interventions consisting of debridement of affected bone and partial bone resection on the first hospital day.</p>
      <fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(A) MRI T2 coronal slide of the epicondyle showing partial tear of the distal triceps tendon, from olecranon insertional portion to 5 cm above. (B) MRI T2 axial slide (enhanced). Complicated hematoma with myositis and cellulites is also noted (arrow).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ic-48-234-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Pus from the excised medial and deep triceps tissue biopsy specimens yielded <italic>A. meyeri</italic> and <italic>Peptoniphilus asaccharolyticus</italic> using a VITEK II ANC card (bioM&#xE9;rieux, Marcy l&#x2019;Etoile, France).</p>
      <p>Histological examination of the biopsy specimen revealed inflammatory cellular infiltration with abscess formation, but no colonies of sulfur granules were observed, even with repeated examination by pathologists (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Abscess is noted, mostly composed of neutrophils. Abscess surrounds mature bone fragments. (Hematoxylin and eosin stain, x200)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ic-48-234-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient&#x2019;s antibiotic regimen was switched to oral amoxicillin-clavulanic acid (500 mg/125 mg q8h for seven months) and he was discharged home with ambulation on hospital day 29.</p>
      <p>After a follow-up period of seven months, there were no clinical signs or symptoms of recurrence.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p><italic>Actinomyces</italic> spp. normally colonize the mouth, colon and vagina [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and usually cause osteomyelitis of head and neck [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The most commonly infected body regions are cervicofacial (55%), abdominopelvic (20%) and pulmonothoracic (15%) [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Involvement of other parts of the body is uncommon, and because of the exclusively endogenous habitat of the bacteria, actinomycosis of an extremity is very rare [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. One percent of reported case of anaerobic osteomyelitis had <italic>Actinomyces</italic> spp. [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, among 15 English-language reports of long bone osteomyelitis of the extremity, only one case of primary upper extremity actinomycotic osteomyelitis was reported in 1954 [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. This is the first case of olecranon osteomyelitis due to <italic>A. meyeri</italic> in Korea.</p>
      <p>The source of actinomycotic organisms and the mechanism whereby the bacteria are transmitted to the site of infection in cases involving a long bone are usually unclear [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. However, most of the long bone osteomyelitis due to <italic>A. meyeri</italic> occurred after traumatic injury which creates an anaerobic environment predisposing to this bacterial growth [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In this case reported here, the patient did not have oral cavity injury nor did have poor dental hygiene. There was no evidence of other organs involvement, which can cause disseminated infection, either. Although environmental sources have been implicated on rare cases [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], it is presumed that possible routes of infection is piercing trauma from an environmental source.</p>
      <p>A combination of appropriate microbiologic, molecular and pathologic studies would maximize the chances of successful diagnosis of actinomycosis [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Half of the primary actinomycosis cases were diagnosed clinicopathologically, and in the remaining cases<italic>, Actinomyces</italic> spp. were grown from culture specimens [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Thus, actinomycosis should not be excluded even though the characteristic pathologic findings are not present, though the single most helpful diagnostic clue for actinomycosis is presentation of sulfur granules in the specimens [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. One case of pulmonary actinomycosis has been reported in which pleural biopsy tissue showed only reactive fibroblastic tissue with fibrin and acute inflammation, but the specimens grew actinomycosis [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Our patient had an olecranon osteomyelitis due to <italic>A. meyeri</italic> with <italic>P. asaccharolyticus,</italic> which was identified by VITEK II, not by sulfur granules in multiple sections. As a result of fibrosis with or without inflammation, sulfur granules are easily missed in the histologic sections of a surgical specimen [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Identification of <italic>Actinomyces</italic> spp. is difficult. Commonly, identification in clinical laboratories is based upon a limited range of conventional biochemical test. Colonial morphology and gas-liquid chromatography can be used. Recent advances in microbiologic identification technique, 16s rRNA gene amplification is known to increase the sensitivity and specificity of diagnosis [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In this case, however, further evaluation was not possible because specimen was discarded after identification by VITEK II card.</p>
      <p>In review of 203 case reports in Korea, tissue cultures were performed in only 6.9% (14 cases among 203). Most cases of actinomycosis (93%, 189 cases among 203)were diagnosed only histopathologically. We found two actinomycosis cases diagnosed only by tissue culture, meaning that the actinomycosis might have been underestimated or neglected by diagnostic maneuver. For successful diagnosis of actinomycosis, not only pathologic studies, but also microbiologic studies should be performed.</p>
      <p>It is interesting that other bacteria have been cultured together, called companion microbes and these bacteria may serve as copathogens by aiding in the inhibition of host defenses or by reducing oxygen tension [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Companion anaerobic bacteria facilitate <italic>Actinomyces</italic> spp. infection by establishing a microaerophillic environment [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>
<italic>Peptoniphilus</italic>, companion microbes, Gram-positive anaerobic cocci, originally classified in the genus <italic>Peptostreptococcus</italic>, is a part of the normal microflora in human beings and animals. <italic>Peptoniphilus</italic> spp<italic>.</italic> are usually associated with opportunistic human infections [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Although studies of Gram-positive anaerobic cocci have been limited due to the lack of a valid identification scheme, recently they are increasingly recognized as important pathogens [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p>
      <p>Treatment of osteomyelitis due to <italic>Actinomyces</italic> spp. requires prolonged use of antibiotics with &#x3B2;-lactam ring such as high dose penicillin or amoxicillin [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Tetracycline, erythromycin and clarithromycin are effective alternatives [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Surgical intervention should be considered in some complicated cases [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The duration of antibiotic therapy is debated and individualized, intravenous penicillin for two to six weeks, followed by oral therapy with penicillin or amoxicillin for six to twelve months, is a reasonable guideline for serious infections [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Our patient was treated successfully with three weeks of intravenous ceftriaxone and a seven month course of oral amoxicillin.</p>
      <p>In this case report, we present the first case of olecranon osteomyelitis due to <italic>A. Meyeri</italic> with <italic>P. asaccharolyticus</italic> with an emphasis on the diagnostic maneuver of actinomycosis. Traditionally, actinomycotic infection was considered, when the typical pathologic findings were present. However, bacteriologic identification is as necessary as pathologic findings to prevent treatment failure of actinomycosis infection.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> No conflicts of interest.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smego</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Foglia</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Actinomycosis</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1255</fpage>
          <lpage>1261</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9636842</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Russo</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Agents of Actinomycosis</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blaser</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Principles and Practice of Infectious Diseases</source>
          <edition>8th ed</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Elsevier Saunders</publisher-name>
          <year>2015</year>
          <fpage>2864</fpage>
          <lpage>2872</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ha</surname>
              <given-names>YE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sung</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kang</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peck</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Osteomyelitis of a long bone due to Fusobacterium nucleatum and Actinomyces meyeri in an immunocompetent adult: a case report and literature review</article-title>
          <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>161</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22817336</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bettesworth</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary actinomycosis of the foot: a case report and literature review</article-title>
          <source>J Am Col Certif Wound Spec</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24527123</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pang</surname>
              <given-names>DK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdalla</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Osteomyelitis of the foot due to Actinomyces meyeri: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Foot Ankle</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>169</fpage>
          <lpage>171</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3440560</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Padhi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dash</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turuk</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sahu</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panda</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary actinomycosis of hand</article-title>
          <source>Adv Biomed Res</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>225</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25538911</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reiner</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harrelson</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hill</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gallis</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary actinomycosis of an extremity: a case report and review</article-title>
          <source>Rev Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>581</fpage>
          <lpage>589</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3602796</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vandevelde</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jenkins</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hardy</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sclerosing osteomyelitis and Actinomyces naeslundii infection of surrounding tissues</article-title>
          <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1037</fpage>
          <lpage>1039</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7795046</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fazili</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blair</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riddell</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kiska</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagra</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Actinomyces meyeri infection: case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J Infect</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>357</fpage>
          <lpage>361</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22406688</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sung</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>YS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Woo</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of disseminated infection due to Actinomyces meyeri involving lung and brain</article-title>
          <source>Infect Chemother</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>269</fpage>
          <lpage>273</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25566409</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hall</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Talbot</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stubbs</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duerden</surname>
              <given-names>BI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of clinical isolates of actinomyces species by amplified 16S ribosomal DNA restriction analysis</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>3555</fpage>
          <lpage>3562</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11574572</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Holm</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Studies on the aetiology of human actinomycosis. The &#x201C;other&#x201D; microbes of actinomycosis and their importance</article-title>
          <source>Acta Pathol Microbiol Scand</source>
          <year>1950</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>736</fpage>
          <lpage>751</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smego</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Actinomycosis of the central nervous system</article-title>
          <source>Rev Infect Dis</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>855</fpage>
          <lpage>865</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3317731</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Murdoch</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gram-positive anaerobic cocci</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>81</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9457430</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Valour</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>S&#xE9;n&#xE9;chal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dupieux</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karsenty</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lustig</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breton</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gleizal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boussel</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laurent</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braun</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chidiac</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ader</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferry</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Actinomycosis: etiology, clinical features, diagnosis, treatment, and management</article-title>
          <source>Infect Drug Resist</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>183</fpage>
          <lpage>197</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25045274</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fass</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scholand</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hodges</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saslaw</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clindamycin in the treatment of serious anaerobic infections</article-title>
          <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>853</fpage>
          <lpage>859</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4713566</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
