<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCHIMP</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Community Hospital Internal Medicine Perspectives</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2000-9666</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Co-Action Publishing</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27987288</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5161802</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">33361</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/jchimp.v6.33361</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Spontaneous pneumomediastinum, pneumoretroperitoneum, and cervicofacial subcutaneous emphysema after repeatedly and forcefully blowing into a bottle</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Swe</surname>
            <given-names>Thein</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Naing</surname>
            <given-names>Akari Thein</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lixon</surname>
            <given-names>Antony</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Quist</surname>
            <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Interfaith Medical Center, Brooklyn, NY, USA</aff>
      <aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Division of Pulmonary Medicine, Interfaith Medical Center, Brooklyn, NY, USA</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Thein Swe, 400 Herkimer Street, Apt 1K, Brooklyn, NY 11213, USA, Email: <email xlink:href="mglay2004@gmail.com">mglay2004@gmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <elocation-id content-type="doi">10.3402/jchimp.v6.33361</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2016 Thein Swe et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License, permitting all non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Spontaneous pneumomediastinum (SPM) is an uncommon, self-limiting condition associated with increased intra-thoracic pressure resulting in alveolar rupture. Search of the literature revealed no detailed case report about a 26-year-old psychiatric patient who repeatedly and forcefully blew air into a bottle for 5 days resulting in a combined condition of spontaneous pneumoretroperitoneum, pneumomediastinum, and cervicofacial subcutaneous emphysema. It is crucial to find a primary source and treat appropriately. Psychiatric patients may have psychotic behaviors mimicking Valsalva's maneuver that increases intra-thoracic pressure and causing SPM. Optimal medications should be given to control psychotic behaviors. Family members and caregivers should be explained about this unusual behavior so that they can prevent this rare condition.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>pneumomediastinum</kwd>
        <kwd>pneumoretroperitoneum</kwd>
        <kwd>subcutaneous emphysema</kwd>
        <kwd>blowing bottle</kwd>
        <kwd>valsalva maneuver</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Spontaneous pneumomediastinum (SPM) is characterized by the presence of air in the mediastinum without underlying lung disease, and it is a rare situation with incidence of 1 in 30,000 emergency department (ED) referrals (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Alveolar rupture is caused by high intra-alveolar pressures, low peri-vascular pressures, or both. In this situation, air escaping from the alveoli tracks into the mediastinum during the respiration cycle because the pressure in the mediastinum decreases relative to the pulmonary parenchymal pressure. As a result, air may track into the cervical subcutaneous tissues and peritoneal cavity (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p>
    <p>Spontaneous pneumoretroperitoneum is an infrequent condition without apparent underlying abdominal pathology such as perforation, iatrogenic instrumentation, or infections. Interestingly, the spaces between the retroperitoneum, mediastinum and subcutaneous tissue are anatomically continuous, and air emerging from a lesion in any of these areas can travel to another place along the fascial planes (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 26-year-old male patient with past medical history of schizoaffective disorder, hypertension, and dyslipidemia was brought to ED by his mother after she noticed swelling of his face and neck. According to his mother, patient was blowing into a water bottle with great force repeatedly for many times. Patient was under stress at work recently for about 5 days; he became irritable, agitated, and acting strangely like looking to ceiling, making some movement by his hands, and he was blowing into a bottle forcefully many times per day. Patient was not talking much but he denies cough, dyspnea, dysphagia, chest pain, palpitation, abdominal pain, nausea, excessive belching, vomiting, bowel problems, urinary problems, and suicidal or homicidal ideas. He has no previous medical history of lung diseases or any recent trauma. He denied any recreational drug use or smoking. Home medications include enalapril 2.5 mg per os daily and simvastatin 40 mg per os daily. According to his mother, he was not taking any psychiatric medications.</p>
      <p>Initial vital signs included temperature 98&#xB0;F, pulse rate 130 beats per minute, respiratory rate 23 breaths per minute, blood pressure 104/72 mm Hg, and oxygen saturation 98% on room air.</p>
      <p>Head and neck examination was significant for facial swelling and diffuse crepitus on palpation around the neck without orbital swelling or lymph node enlargement. Respiratory examination revealed moderate crepitus to palpation in the upper anterior chest bilaterally extending to neck and up to distal arms bilaterally. His chest wall was not hyper-resonant to percussion. There was no stridor or rhonchi. Peripheral pulses were equal and symmetric bilaterally. The remaining examinations including cardiovascular, abdominal, and central nervous system examinations were within normal limits.</p>
      <p>Laboratory test showed normal arterial blood gas. Complete blood count and basal metabolic profile were unremarkable. Electrocardiogram was normal except sinus tachycardia. An initial chest X-ray (CXR) revealed extensive subcutaneous emphysema in chest and neck (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Fig. 1</xref>). Soft tissue neck computed tomography (CT) scan showed cervicofacial soft tissue emphysema contiguous with the pneumomediastinum. CT scan of head revealed normal brain with extensive parapharyngeal, retropharyngeal, and scalp soft tissue emphysema. CT scan of chest with intravenous contrast showed extensive bilateral soft tissue chest wall emphysema with pneumomediastinum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figs. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">3</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">4</xref>). Echocardiogram was within normal limits. CT scan of abdomen and pelvis revealed minimal punctate retroperitoneal air around left kidney without evidence of acute intra-abdominal pathology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005">Fig. 5</xref>). According to imaging studies, esophageal or tracheal rupture was ruled out.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Anteroposterior (AP) view of chest X-ray showing extensive subcutaneous emphysema in the chest and neck.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCHIMP-6-33361-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0002" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Axial view of CT chest revealing cervical and facial subcutaneous emphysema.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCHIMP-6-33361-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0003" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Axial view of CT chest revealing extensive pneumomediastinum and subcutaneous emphysema.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCHIMP-6-33361-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0004" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Coronal view of CT chest, abdomen, and pelvis revealing pneumomediastinum and subcutaneous emphysema from neck area to left flank of abdomen.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCHIMP-6-33361-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0005" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Axial view of CT abdomen showing punctate retroperitoneal air around left kidney.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCHIMP-6-33361-g005"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Patient was managed conservatively in the intensive care unit with humidified oxygen 5 l/min <italic>via</italic> mask to facilitate clearance of SPM. Psychiatric medications were given to control his mood and psychotic behaviors. CT scan of chest 24 h later showed minimal improvement in SPM. CXRs were repeated daily and showed gradual improvement of subcutaneous emphysema and SPM. Patient's clinical condition continued to improve and he was discharged on day 7 of hospitalization. At a follow-up visit 2 weeks later, patient's symptoms improved and repeated CXR showed a normal chest with resolution of the previous subcutaneous emphysema and pneumomediastinum.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0003">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>SPM usually occurs from bronchial hyper-reactivity or barotraumas. Risk factors for bronchial hyper-reactivity are asthma and inhalation of illicit drugs (e.g., cocaine (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and marijuana). Barotrauma may result from instrumentation, mechanical ventilation, or Valsalva's maneuver, which is the process of expiration through resistance that increases intra-thoracic pressure during coughing (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), straining during labor (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), or vomiting (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Blowing into a closed space such as a bottle is also considered as a Valsalva's maneuver. Our patient had psychiatric disorder that led him to blow repeatedly and forcefully into the bottle for 5 days until his mother noticed swelling around his face, neck, and chest.</p>
      <p>Secondary pneumomediastinum should be excluded first before diagnosing as SPM. The former has specific underlying pathologic event, such as trauma, esophageal rupture after vomiting, and infection by gas-forming organism (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). SPM should also be suspected in patients with dysphagia. Cho and Kim (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) reported two patients developed dysphagia after swallowing a peach seed and boned rib of pork, respectively.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, Macia et al. published a retrospective study of 41 cases. The mean age of SPM is 21 years. Most common symptoms are chest pain (85%) and dyspnea (49%), and most common sign is subcutaneous emphysema in 71% of patients. Most of the patients respond well to medical treatment including analgesia, rest, and/or initial oxygen therapy. The average length of hospital stay was 5 days (range, 1&#x2013;9 days) with only one case of early recurrence, which was improved satisfactorily. Imaging studies such as CXR can detect pneumomediastinum in all patients. CT scan, contrast-enhanced swallow, or bronchoscopy was performed in some cases (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). However, Kaneki et al. (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) reported a study of 33 cases; CXR alone was normal in 3 patients with mild SPM, and CT scan with contrast was needed to diagnose accurately. Antibiotics are not recommended in the absence of signs and symptoms of infection, and normal white blood cell count.</p>
      <p>In order to diagnose spontaneous pneumoretroperitoneum, secondary causes such as prior history of endoscopy (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), gas-producing infections, trauma, and iatrogenic should be excluded. Witzig et al. reported a retrospective study of 15 cases of secondary pneumoretroperitoneum. Etiologies were infectious in six patients, traumatic in five, and iatrogenic in four. Surgical treatment was used in 12 patients. Conservative management was applied for the remaining three patients whose etiology was due to endoscopy (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Gleeson and McMullin (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) reported a rare case of prednisolone-induced spontaneous pneumoretroperitoneum in a renal transplant patient.</p>
      <p>Moreover, dental and oral procedures are known to be culprits for some cases of cervicofacial emphysema. Koukoutsis et al. (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) described a case of subcutaneous emphysema and pneumomediastinum after tonsillectomy.</p>
      <p>It is important to note that there is anatomical connection of fascial planes because there are no barriers on the subcutaneous tissues in the body. Therefore, if the air pressure surpasses the strength of the tissues, or the time between the aggression and the imaging is too long, the air can travel to other areas hindering its primary location. The mediastinum is continuous directly with the visceral and retropharyngeal spaces (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The reason behind using 100% oxygen is to replace nitrogen in the escaped air with oxygen; nitrogen is absorbed slowly by capillaries, however, oxygen is absorbed rapidly (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Although Sato et al. reported a case of secondary pneumoretroperitoneum, pneumomediastinum, and subcutaneous emphysema after colorectal endoscopy, we believe that there is no detailed case about spontaneously occurring pneumoretroperitoneum, pneumomediastinum, and cervicofacial emphysema in a psychiatric patient after repeatedly and forcefully blowing a bottle.</p>
      <p>Spontaneously occurring air in the three different anatomical areas in the human body is a challenging medical vignette for a physician. It is crucial to find a primary source and treat properly. Psychiatric patients may have psychotic behaviors mimicking Valsalva's maneuver that increases intra-thoracic pressure and causing SPM. Optimal medications should be given to control psychotic behaviors. Family members and caregivers should be explained about this unusual behavior so that they can prevent this rare condition.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflict of interest and funding</title>
      <p>The authors have not received any funding or benefits from industry or elsewhere to conduct this study.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Newcomb</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous pneumomediastinum: A benign curiosity or a significant problem?</article-title>
          <source>Chest</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>128</volume>
          <fpage>3298</fpage>
          <lpage>302</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16304275</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Mufarrej</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Badar</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gharagozloo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tempesta</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strother</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Margolis</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous pneumomediastinum: Diagnostic and therapeutic interventions</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiothorac Surg</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18980688</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Itoh</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shigiyama</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kitagawa</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maetani</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pneumoretroperitoneum, pneumomediastinum and subcutaneous emphysema after colorectal endoscopic submucosal dissection (ESD) with air insufflation</article-title>
          <source>J Interv Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>136</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22163085</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kloss</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Broton</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pneumomediastinum from nasal insufflation of cocaine</article-title>
          <source>Int J Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>435</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21373317</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>DY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aaron</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shepard</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous retropharyngeal and mediastinal emphysema</article-title>
          <source>Clin Exp Otorhinolaryngol</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>178</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27090269</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khoo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahanta</surname>
              <given-names>VR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous pneumomediastinum with severe subcutaneous emphysema secondary to prolonged labor during normal vaginal delivery</article-title>
          <source>Radiol Case Rep</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>713</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27326303</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Unusual presentation of spontaneous pneumomediastinum</article-title>
          <source>Lung India</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21139723</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Macia</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moya</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramos</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morera</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Escobar</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saumench</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous pneumomediastinum: 41 cases</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1110</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17420139</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kaneki</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kubo</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawashima</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koizumi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sekiguchi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sone</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous pneumomediastinum in 33 patients: Yield of chest computed tomography for the diagnosis of the mild type</article-title>
          <source>Respiration</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>408</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10940795</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ruiz-Tovar</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lobo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanjuanbenito</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mart&#xED;nez-Molina</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Case series: Pneumoretroperitoneum secondary to duodenal perforation after endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography</article-title>
          <source>Can J Surg</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>68</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19234656</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Witzig</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pr&#xEA;tre</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robert</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirescu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rohner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pneumoretroperitoneum: Diagnostic and therapeutic approach]</article-title>
          <source>Helv Chir Acta</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <issue>1&#x2013;2</issue>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8226081</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gleeson</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McMullin</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spontaneous pneumoretroperitoneum in a renal transplant recipient</article-title>
          <source>Postgrad Med J</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <issue>757</issue>
          <fpage>897</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3076669</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koukoutsis</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balatsouras</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ganelis</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fassolis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moukos</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katotomichelakis</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Subcutaneous emphysema and pneumomediastinum after tonsillectomy</article-title>
          <source>Case Rep Otolaryngol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>2013</volume>
          <fpage>154857</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379978</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frias Vila&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reis</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vidal</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The anatomical compartments and their connections as demonstrated by ectopic air</article-title>
          <source>Insights Imaging</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>759</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24065628</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Udupa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hameed</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kovesi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pneumomediastinum and subcutaneous emphysema associated with pandemic (H1N1) influenza in three children</article-title>
          <source>CMAJ</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>183</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>220</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.100099">http://dx.doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.100099</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21135087</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
