<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Intern Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Vet. Intern. Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1939-1676</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVIM</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0891-6640</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1939-1676</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27519845</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5032862</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.14555</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JVIM14555</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="overline">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>SMALL ANIMAL</subject>
          <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
            <subject>Case Report</subject>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
              <subject>Oncology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Axial Multicentric Osteosarcoma in an English Cocker Spaniel</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Parzefall et al</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="jvim14555-cr-0001" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Parzefall</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim14555-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim14555-cr-0002" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>De Decker</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim14555-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim14555-cr-0003" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carvalho</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim14555-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim14555-cr-0004" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Terry</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim14555-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim14555-cr-0005" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Leach</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim14555-aff-0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim14555-cr-0006" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
            <given-names>K.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim14555-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="jvim14555-cr-0007" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Lara&#x2010;Garcia</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3672-5460</contrib-id>
          <address>
            <email>algarcia57@rvc.ac.uk</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="jvim14555-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="jvim14555-aff-0001">
        <label>
          <sup>1</sup>
        </label>
        <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Clinical Science and Services</named-content>
        <institution>Royal Veterinary College</institution>
        <institution>University of London</institution>
        <named-content content-type="city">Hatfield</named-content>
        <country country="GB">UK</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="jvim14555-aff-0002">
        <label>
          <sup>2</sup>
        </label>
        <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Pathology and Pathogen Biology</named-content>
        <institution>Royal Veterinary College</institution>
        <institution>University of London</institution>
        <named-content content-type="city">Hatfield</named-content>
        <country country="GB">UK</country>
      </aff>
      <aff id="jvim14555-aff-0003">
        <label>
          <sup>3</sup>
        </label>
        <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Veterinary Diagnostic Services</named-content>
        <named-content content-type="organisation-division">School of Veterinary Medicine</named-content>
        <institution>University of Glasgow</institution>
        <named-content content-type="city">Glasgow</named-content>
        <country country="GB">UK</country>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: A. Lara&#x2010;Garcia, DVM, MSc, PhD, DACVIM &amp; DECVIM&#x2010;CA (Oncology), Department of Clinical Science and Services, Royal Veterinary College, University of London, Hatfield, AL9 7TA, UK; e&#x2010;mail: <email>algarcia57@rvc.ac.uk</email>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <season>Sep-Oct</season>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>30</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.2016.30.issue-5</issue-id>
      <fpage>1720</fpage>
      <lpage>1725</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2016 American College of Veterinary Internal Medicine <copyright-statement>-->
        <copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">Copyright &#xA9; 2016 The Authors. <italic>Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of the American College of Veterinary Internal Medicine</italic>.</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="creativeCommonsBy-nc">
          <license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution&#x2010;NonCommercial</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not used for commercial purposes.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:JVIM-30-1720.pdf"/>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated">
        <kwd id="jvim14555-kwd-0001">Canine</kwd>
        <kwd id="jvim14555-kwd-0002">Multiple</kwd>
        <kwd id="jvim14555-kwd-0003">Neoplasia</kwd>
        <kwd id="jvim14555-kwd-0004">Osteolytic</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="3"/>
        <table-count count="0"/>
        <page-count count="6"/>
        <word-count count="3738"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name>
          <meta-value>2.0</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>component-id</meta-name>
          <meta-value>jvim14555</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
          <meta-value>September/October 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:4.9.4 mode:remove_FC converted:26.09.2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <fn-group id="jvim14555-ntgp-0001">
        <fn id="jvim14555-note-1001">
          <p>The work was done at the Royal Veterinary College, United Kingdom. No financial support was given for this study. This case was presented in part at the 27th Annual Symposium of the European Society of Veterinary Neurology &#x2013; European College of Veterinary Neurology, 18&#x2013;20 September 2014, Madrid, Spain.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <def-list list-content="abbreviations" id="jvim14555-dl-0001">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-item>
        <term>CT</term>
        <def>
          <p>computed tomography</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>OS</term>
        <def>
          <p>osteosarcoma</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MOS</term>
        <def>
          <p>multicentric osteosarcoma</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>MRI</term>
        <def>
          <p>magnetic resonance imaging</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TR</term>
        <def>
          <p>repetition time</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>TE</term>
        <def>
          <p>echo time</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
      <def-item>
        <term>RI</term>
        <def>
          <p>reference interval</p>
        </def>
      </def-item>
    </def-list>
    <p>An 8&#x2010;year&#x2010;old, male neutered English Cocker Spaniel presented to the Royal Veterinary College for evaluation of reluctance to exercise and spinal hyperesthesia of 1&#x2010;year duration. Medical treatment by referring veterinarian with antibiotics and tramadol did not result in clinical improvement. Survey radiographs performed before referral revealed multiple lytic bone lesions involving sternum and ribs. The dog had been fed for several months on a hypoallergenic diet and administered prednisolone for presumed inflammatory bowel disease.</p>
    <p>General physical examination did not reveal abnormalities. Neurological examination revealed a kyphotic posture and a short and stilted pelvic limb gait. Spinal hyperesthesia could be elicited on thoracic, thoracolumbar, and lumbar spinal palpation. A complete blood count and free catch urine analysis did not reveal abnormalities. Serum biochemistry profile revealed hypoalbuminemia (20.3 g/L [RI (reference interval) 28&#x2013;39 g/L]) and increased inorganic phosphorus concentration (2.68 mmol/L [RI 0.8&#x2013;2 mmol/L]), alanine aminotransferase activity (234 U/L [RI 13&#x2013;88 U/L]) and alkaline phosphatase activity (1425 U/L [RI 19&#x2013;285 U/L]). Ionized calcium concentration was within the RI. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) imaging was performed using a protocol that included sagittal and transverse plane T2&#x2010;weighted<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim14555-note-1002">1</xref> (repetition time, TR [ms], echo time, TE [ms], 3000/120) (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A), sagittal T2&#x2010;weighted short&#x2010;tau inversion recovery (TR/TE, 3612/80) (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C) and sagittal and transverse plane T1&#x2010;weighted spectral presaturation with inversion recovery (TR/TE, 533/8) sequences. Sagittal and transverse plane T1&#x2010;weighted (T1W turbo spin echo) (TR/TE, 400/8) images were acquired before and after IV injection with gadolinium contrast<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim14555-note-1003">2</xref> (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B, D). Magnetic resonance imaging demonstrated multiple poorly defined, expansile lytic lesions affecting the spinous processes of the sacrum, L5, L3, T13, T12, T11, T8, and T2, the vertebral bodies of the sacrum, L5, L4, T13, T12, T11, T9, T7, T6, and T2, and multiple sternebrae. These lesions were characterized by a heterogeneous intensity in all sequences and patchy contrast enhancement. A fracture of the vertebral body of T11 with bone remodeling was present without spinal cord compression. After MRI, thorax and abdomen computed tomography (CT) was performed using a 16&#x2010;slice scanner.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim14555-note-1004">3</xref> CT imaging (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A) confirmed the expansile lytic bone lesions and revealed additional lesions affecting multiple ribs and pelvis and accounting for more than 20 bone lytic lesions with variable sizes. CT did not reveal any abnormalities involving thoracic or abdominal visceral structures and no enhancement was seen after IV administration of contrast medium.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim14555-note-1005">4</xref> Based on imaging and laboratory results, nonproductive multiple myeloma was considered the most likely differential diagnosis. The lack of a clear primary lesion, the numerous bones involved and absence of visceral lesions was not typical for axial osteosarcoma (OS), even considering concurrent multiple metastases. The imaging findings were more suggestive of synchronous multicentric osteosarcoma (MOS), a rare OS clinical presentation in people, with simultaneous multiple bone lesions without pulmonary involvement<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1</xref> and extremely rare in domestic animals, which was considered as a rare differential diagnosis.</p>
    <fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jvim14555-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Sagittal magnetic resonance imaging (<styled-content style="fixed-case">MRI</styled-content>) shows multiple heterogeneous lesions within the vertebral column and the sternebrae, <bold>A</bold> (T2&#x2010;weighted), <bold>C</bold> (T2&#x2010;weighted short&#x2010;tau inversion recovery), white arrows indicate examples of these lesions. Transverse T1&#x2010;weighted pre&#x2010; (<bold>B</bold>) and postcontrast (<bold>D</bold>) <styled-content style="fixed-case">MRI</styled-content> illustrates a lesion of T11. The level of T12 is indicated as a white arrowhead in A.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="JVIM-30-1720-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jvim14555-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A full body computed tomography at the time of diagnosis (<bold>A</bold>) and 14 months later (<bold>B</bold>) shows multiple and progressive osteolytic lesions of the vertebral column, sternum and pelvis. The black arrowhead indicates a pathological fracture at the level of T11.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="JVIM-30-1720-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Bone marrow aspirate (left humerus) and serum electrophoresis did not reveal abnormalities and evaluation of urine for Bence&#x2010;Jones proteins was negative. Ultrasound guided fine needle aspirates of affected lesions (dorsal spinous process of L5 and rib) were inconclusive. Subsequently, the dog was anesthetized and a surgical biopsy of the spinous process of L5 was obtained via a standardized dorsal approach. Bacterial and fungal cultures obtained during surgery were negative. The dog was discharged with pain relief consisting of paracetamol/codeine (8 and 0.7 mg/kg, respectively, PO q12 h), buprenorphine 20 &#x3BC;g/kg PO q8&#x2010;12 h, and also prednisolone 0.8 mg/kg PO q12 h. Histopathology of the removed spinous process revealed foci of osteolysis characterized by infiltration and replacement of pre&#x2010;existing bone by plump polygonal to spindle&#x2010;shaped cells. These infiltrating cells displayed mild&#x2010;moderate nuclear atypia with scattered mitoses (average &lt;1 per 10 hpf). The neoplastic cells produced extensive poorly mineralized osteoid (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). Neoplastic cells displayed immunoreactivity for Vimentin and Osteocalcin antigens (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B) and no immunoreactivity for MUM&#x2010;1 and CD79a antigens. Histopathological and immunohistochemical results were compatible with OS making a clinical diagnosis of MOS most likely.</p>
    <fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jvim14555-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Representative images of gross, histologic and immunohistochemical features of the multicentric osteosarcoma (<styled-content style="fixed-case">MOS</styled-content>). (<bold>A</bold>) Photomicrograph of L5 biopsy, H&amp;E, scale bar = 100 &#x3BC;m. There is infiltration and replacement of pre&#x2010;existing bone (star) by plump polygonal to spindle&#x2010;shaped neoplastic cells demonstrating mild to moderate nuclear atypia and formation of poor quality immature osteoid (black arrows). (<bold>B</bold>) Photo&#x2010;micrograph of L5 biopsy, positive immunoreactivity for osteocalcin antigen (brown) exhibited by the neoplastic cells and secreted matrix, scale bar = 100 &#x3BC;m. (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) MOS in the ribs and liver respectively (white arrows). (<bold>E</bold>) Photo&#x2010;micrograph of a rib mass showing the same population as in A with more extensive osteoid production and lysis of pre&#x2010;existing bone, H&amp;E, scale bar = 400 &#x3BC;m. (<bold>F</bold>) Photomicrograph of the liver mass, H&amp;E, scale bar = 400 &#x3BC;m. Spindeloid neoplastic cells producing scant immature osteoid (arrow) infiltrate the hepatic parenchyma (L).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="JVIM-30-1720-g003"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Initial treatment after diagnosis focused on pain control as this was the main clinical sign and cause of deterioration. It consisted of transition from prednisolone to firocoxib (5 mg/kg PO, q24 h), and from buprenorphine to tramadol (3&#x2013;4 mg/kg PO, q8&#x2013;q12 h), continuation of paracetamol/codeine and start of pamidronate (1 mg/kg in 0.9% NaCl IV, every 3&#x2013;4 weeks). Hypofractionated radiation treatment was administered to selected lytic lesions, resulting in a higher degree of pain control based on physical and neurological examinations, with a total of 4 fractions of 6.5 Gray administered each on a weekly basis for a total dose of 26 Gy.</p>
    <p>Toceranib phosphate<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim14555-note-1006">5</xref> (2.75 mg/kg PO, 3 times weekly) was administered. Analgesia (tramadol, paracetamol&#x2010;codeine and firocoxib PO) combined with monthly infusions of pamidronate were continued throughout the treatment period. Serial clinical examinations demonstrated a marked improvement of the dog's clinical signs and quality of life.</p>
    <p>A repeat CT study 4 months later demonstrated mild increase in size of the presenting lesions and progression of the lesion in T8 to pathologic fracture. Medical treatment was switched to carboplatin<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim14555-note-1007">6</xref> (300 mg/m<sup>2</sup> IV, every 3&#x2013;4 weeks) and after 6 cycles of treatment (9 months after diagnosis) further imaging showed mild progressive disease at existing lesions with a new pathologic fracture at T2. Carboplatin was discontinued and the dog was treated with chlorambucil<xref ref-type="fn" rid="jvim14555-note-1008">7</xref> metronomic schedule, (4 mg/m<sup>2</sup> PO, q24 h). Three months later the dog had pelvic limb weakness and increased pain when going upstairs which was controlled by adding gabapentin (5&#x2013;10 mg/kg PO, Q8 h) to the analgesic regimen.</p>
    <p>Upon further deterioration with lethargy and reluctance to walk and increased pain, mild ataxia, paresis, and proprioceptive pelvic limb deficits on physical examination, a further CT scan was performed (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). This showed progressive disease in rib and vertebral lesions, with stable vertebral pathological fractures at T2 and T8, further vertebral collapse of T11 and impingement of spinal cord at T11 fitting with the pain increase noted. A new lesion was observed involving the left scapula in the absence of apparent visceral metastases. Additional analgesia with amitryptiline (1 mg/kg PO, q12 h) and later fentanyl (3&#x2013;5 &#x3BC;g/kg transdermal), did not provide sustained clinical improvement. The dog was euthanized 15 months after diagnosis.</p>
    <p>Postmortem examination revealed multiple lytic lesions involving the thoracic, lumbar, and sacral vertebral column, pelvis, all sternebrae, ribs (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C, E), and the left scapula. A single 1 cm diameter metastasis was found in the right lateral liver lobe (Fig <xref rid="jvim14555-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D, F) whereas there were no secondary lesions in any other organs (specifically, pulmonary involvement was not present). A pathological fracture with mild extradural spinal cord compression and secondary diffuse axonal degeneration was evident at the level of T11 in association with OS invasion. The liver and the multiple lytic bone lesions had a similar histological appearance compared to the previously examined surgical specimen. The numerous slowly progressing lesions with similar histopathologic features of OS, distributed throughout multiple axial bones and no evidence of lung involvement confirmed the clinical diagnosis of axial MOS.</p>
    <p>The present report describes the clinical presentation, diagnostic findings, treatment and long&#x2010;term outcome in an English Cocker Spaniel with axial MOS that exhibited an unusual slow disease progression despite the advanced stage at diagnosis. Multicentric osteosarcoma is a rare presentation of OS in animals, and although described in the horse there has yet to be a published report of axial MOS in the dog.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2</xref> Osteosarcoma in dogs is the most common bone neoplasia in dogs and the appendicular presentation accounts for 75% of cases. The axial presentation involving flat or irregular bones is less common, with vertebral or rib location corresponding only with 15 and 10%, respectively, of all axial OS cases.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>
</p>
    <p>Multicentric osteosarcoma is an uncommon clinical presentation of OS in people; when there is a single dominant tumor and presence of multiple skeletal sites involved at diagnosis in the absence of visceral metastasis it is called synchronous MOS, with an incidence of 0.4&#x2013;4.2% within all OS cases. When additional lesions appear at different intervals after treatment of the dominant lesion, the term metasynchronous MOS is applied.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref> In human medicine there is a debate whether MOS represents multiple primary tumors or metastatic disease. In the past, the theory of multiple tumors was favored because there was no obvious route for spread if the lungs were free of tumor, which was thought to rule out hematogenous dissemination. Alternatively, the presence of cases with a large dominant lesion leading to presentation could account for the primary tumor.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref> Bone&#x2010;to&#x2010;bone metastases can occur through intraosseous embolization through marrow sinusoids or through the vertebral venous plexus, comprised by valveless vessels carrying blood under low pressure, which parallels, connects with and provides bypasses for the portal, pulmonary and caval venous systems. Increased intra&#x2010;abdominal pressure can collapse the vena cava and cause venous flow to be diverted into the vertebral sinus system. This would be a similar mechanism to that occurring with the distribution of prostatic cancer bone metastases.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>
</p>
    <p>In dogs with primary appendicular OS, additional bone lesions at diagnosis have been considered metastatic in nature and described to range in prevalence from 1.4 to 28%.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> However, synchronous appendicular bone tumors in dogs occur without evidence of other metastatic foci within the skeleton or lungs.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref> Scarce information is available regarding prevalence of secondary bone lesions at diagnosis in dogs with primary extracranial axial OS. The overall metastatic rate for axial skeletal OS in dogs is 11.1%, with increased metastatic rate of 27&#x2013;38%, for rib OS compared with other axial locations but mostly to lungs.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref> A dog with a primary vertebral OS of L4 and additional synchronous lesions in adjacent vertebrae demonstrated with CT was euthanized after diagnosis revealing further lesions through L3 to L7 but also pulmonary metastases.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>
</p>
    <p>In the case described here it was impossible to determine at diagnosis if the lesions observed in multiple bones represented synchronous/metasynchronous primary tumors, as the dog had a 1 year history of spinal pain, or a primary vertebral OS with extensive metastasis. The follow&#x2010;up CT studies demonstrated slow progression of existing bone lesions and development of only one new lesion in 14 months without pulmonary involvement. On necropsy only one liver lesion was identified as visceral metastasis. These findings would fit with the description of synchronous MOS and would be uncommon for an aggressive metastatic axial OS, that without local control and even with systemic treatment is usually associated with short survival times because of rapid progression of primary and metastatic lesions.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>
</p>
    <p>Beside MOS, only few other disorders, including multiple myeloma, metastatic neoplasia, or osteomyelitis can result in numerous lytic lesions of multiple bony structures.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref> Multiple myeloma was initially considered the highest differential diagnosis based on the imaging findings. Results of diagnostic tests carried were not suggestive for multiple myeloma and a surgical biopsy with subsequent histological and immuno&#x2010;histochemical analysis provided the final diagnosis of OS. Immunoreactivity for vimentin antigen (mesenchymal marker) and osteocalcin antigen (osteoblast marker) with no immunoreactivity for MUM&#x2010;1 antigen (plasmacytic lineage) and CD79a antigen (B&#x2010;cell marker) supported the diagnosis of an OS and ruled out multiple myeloma.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">21</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref>
</p>
    <p>A multimodal treatment approach with radical surgery and cytotoxic chemotherapy provides the longest survival times for dogs with apendicular OS.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref> Local control of extracranial axial OS can be challenging. Whereas for rib, sternebra, and scapular locations aggressive surgery is possible for vertebral OS only debulking and decompressive laminectomy are possible. Local treatment failure is common in canine vertebral tumors treated with surgery or radiation plus chemotherapy or a combination of the 3, with median survival times of 135 days.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref> Because of the extensive number of lesions in the dog presented here, treatment was aimed to control pain and improve quality of life with analgesia, pamidronate and hypofractionated radiation treatment to selected local lesions. Hypofractionated radiation treatment alone or combined with chemotherapy has been successful in controlling pain and delaying disease progression of OS in dogs, achieving median survival times ranging from 79 to 162 days in a variety of axial OS.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">25</xref> There is little evidence for cytotoxic chemotherapy to improve outcome of dogs with metastatic OS<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">26</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">28</xref> but stabilization of pulmonary metastatic OS can occur with administration of tyrosine kinase inhibitors.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref> It is difficult to establish if medical anticancer treatment in this case contributed to the long survival by having an effect in the low rate of new lesions or visceral metastasis development. In any case, the survival of 15 months was longer than the expected 130 days reported for dogs with stage III OS treated with radiation and chemotherapy.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref> The continued treatment with pamidronate could have also contributed to the outcome by increasing bone density, pain control and perhaps modulation of disease progression as documented in some case reports and given the antiproliferative effects in vitro against canine OS cells.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref>
</p>
    <p>In humans, synchronous MOS is treated with neoadjuvant chemotherapy because of its multicentric presentation, followed by wide excision of primary and secondary bone lesions in cases with limited number of tumoral foci and possibility of local disease control. Response to chemotherapy assessed by quantification of OS necrosis is associated with longer survival times. Median time to progression with complete local control is only around 15 months with a 5 years survival rate of 15%.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref> Prognosis differs depending on MOS type. Type 1 affects children and adolescents, with histologic high grade and multiple lesions involving long bones and with an extremely poor prognosis of 6 months. In type II, patients are usually adults and have low grade synchronous lesions in the axial skeleton with a slightly better prognosis of 5&#x2013;72 months.<xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref>, <xref rid="jvim14555-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref> On histopathology of the case described, the tumor had mild to moderate atypia with a good level of cell differentiation and abundant osteoid production in different areas of the tumor which could be classified as a low grade OS, so it is possible that our case would be similar to the type 2 described in humans and that this would have dictated a more benign clinical course.</p>
    <p>In conclusion, MOS can be considered a differential diagnosis when osteolytic lesions are present in multiple axial bones including vertebral bodies, vertebral spinous process, ribs, sternebrae and pelvis and laboratory results do not support a plasma cell tumor neoplasia. Although it is difficult to draw definitive conclusions from the case presented here, multimodal palliative treatment consisting of appropriate pain management, hypofractionated radiation treatment, and anticancer medical treatment might result in a prolonged survival time with a good quality of life once a definitive diagnosis has been achieved.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack id="jvim14555-sec-0002">
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors thank Lorenzo Ressel from the University of Liverpool for immunohistochemical analyses.</p>
      <p>
<italic>Conflict of Interest Declaration:</italic> Authors disclose no conflict of interest.</p>
      <p>
<italic>Off&#x2010;label Antimicrobial Declaration:</italic> Authors declare no off&#x2010;label use of antimicrobials.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group id="jvim14555-ntgp-0002">
      <title>Footnotes</title>
      <fn id="jvim14555-note-1002">
        <label>1</label>
        <p>1.5 tesla Intera, Philips Medical System, Eindhoven, the Netherlands</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim14555-note-1003">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>0.1 mL/kg Gadovist (gadobutrol), Bayer Pharma AG, Berlin, Germany</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim14555-note-1004">
        <label>3</label>
        <p>PQ 500, Universal Systems, Solon, OH</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim14555-note-1005">
        <label>4</label>
        <p>2 mg/kg Omnipaque (iohexol), GE Healthcare AS, Oslo, Norway</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim14555-note-1006">
        <label>5</label>
        <p>Toceranib, Palladia<sub>TM</sub>, Zoetis, Louvain&#x2010;la&#x2010;Neuve, Belgium</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim14555-note-1007">
        <label>6</label>
        <p>Fresenius Karbi, Bordon, United Kingdom</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="jvim14555-note-1008">
        <label>7</label>
        <p>Aspen, Dublin, Ireland</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="jvim14555-bibl-0001">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Corradi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wenger</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bertoni</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multicentric osteosarcoma: Clinicopathologic and radiographic study of 56 cases</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Pathol</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>799</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>807</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22031320</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Livesey</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wilkie</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Focal and multifocal oseosarcoma in two foals</article-title>. <source>Equine Vet J</source>
<year>1986</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3464422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Chun</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Common malignant musculoskeletal neoplasms of dogs and cats</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Small Anim Pract</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1155</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1167</lpage>, vi.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16129137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Bacci</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fabbri</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Balladelli</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treatment and prognosis for synchronous multifocal osteosarcoma in 42 patients</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>1071</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1075</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16877608</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Currall</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Synchronous multifocal osteosarcoma: Case report and literature review</article-title>. <source>Sarcoma</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>2006</volume>:<fpage>53901</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17251658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Hameed</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vijayan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Naik</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Multicentric osteosarcoma</article-title>. <source>Singapore Med J</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>e214</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>e217</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mathey</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Eggers</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Osteosarcoma in adjacent lumbar vertebrae in a dog</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<year>2000</year>;<volume>217</volume>:<fpage>1038</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1040</lpage>, 1008.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11019712</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>LaRue</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Withrow</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wrigley</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Radiographic bone surveys in the evaluation of primary bone tumors in dogs</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<year>1986</year>;<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>514</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>516</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3457000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Hahn</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hurd</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cantwell</surname>
<given-names>HD</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Single&#x2010;phase methylene diphosphate bone scintigraphy in the diagnostic evaluation of dogs with osteosarcoma</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>1483</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1486</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2341321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Berg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lamb</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>O'Callaghan</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Bone scintigraphy in the initial evaluation of dogs with primary bone tumors</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>917</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>920</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2312389</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Jankowski</surname>
<given-names>MK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Steyn</surname>
<given-names>PF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lana</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nuclear scanning with 99mTc&#x2010;HDP for the initial evaluation of osseous metastasis in canine osteosarcoma</article-title>. <source>Vet Comp Oncol</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19379314</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Selmic</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ryan</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ehrhart</surname>
<given-names>NP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Withrow</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Bilateral appendicular bone tumors in four dogs</article-title>. <source>J Am Anim Hosp Assoc</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>141</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23325591</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Feeney</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Johnston</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Grindem</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Malignant neoplasia of canine ribs: Clinical, radiographic, and pathologic findings</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<year>1982</year>;<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>927</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>933</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6953063</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Heyman</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Diefenderfer</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Goldschmidt</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Newton</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Canine axial skeletal osteosarcoma. A retrospective study of 116 cases (1986 to 1989)</article-title>. <source>Vet Surg</source>
<year>1992</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>310</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1455640</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0015">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Baines</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>White</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Primary thoracic wall tumours of mesenchymal origin in dogs: A retrospective study of 46 cases</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11936882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0016">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Boston</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ehrhart</surname>
<given-names>NP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dernell</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evaluation of survival time in dogs with stage III osteosarcoma that undergo treatment: 90 cases (1985&#x2013;2004)</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>228</volume>:<fpage>1905</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1908</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16784383</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0017">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Trost</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Inkelmann</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Galiza</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Occurrence of tumours metastatic to bones and multicentric tumours with skeletal involvement in dogs</article-title>. <source>J Comp Pathol</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24011903</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0018">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Dorfman</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hurvitz</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Patnaik</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Primary and secondary bone tumours in the dog</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract</source>
<year>1977</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>326</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">267798</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0019">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Rusbridge</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wheeler</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lamb</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vertebral plasma cell tumors in 8 dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>
<year>1999</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10225602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0020">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Vanel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Blond</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vanel</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Imaging of primary bone tumors in veterinary medicine: Which differences?</article-title>
<source>Eur J Radiol</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>2129</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22197093</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0021">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Hoenerhoff</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kiupel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rosenstein</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multipotential osteosarcoma with various mesenchymal differentiations in a young dog</article-title>. <source>Vet Pathol</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>268</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15133175</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0022">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Ramos&#x2010;Vara</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Valli</surname>
<given-names>VE</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Immunohistochemical detection of multiple myeloma 1/interferon regulatory factor 4 (MUM1/IRF&#x2010;4) in canine plasmacytoma: Comparison with CD79a and CD20</article-title>. <source>Vet Pathol</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>875</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>884</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18039900</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0023">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Dernell</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Van Vechten</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Straw</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Outcome following treatment of vertebral tumors in 20 dogs (1986&#x2013;1995)</article-title>. <source>J Am Anim Hosp Assoc</source>
<year>2000</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10825097</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0024">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Dickerson</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Page</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>LaDue</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Retrospective analysis of axial skeleton osteosarcoma in 22 large&#x2010;breed dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>120</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>124</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11300594</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0025">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Forrest</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Four fraction palliative radiotherapy for osteosarcoma in 24 dogs</article-title>. <source>J Am Anim Hosp Assoc</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>451</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12220029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0026">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Ogilvie</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Straw</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jameson</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evaluation of single&#x2010;agent chemotherapy for treatment of clinically evident osteosarcoma metastases in dogs: 45 cases (1987&#x2013;1991)</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<year>1993</year>;<volume>202</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8428842</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0027">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Batschinski</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dervisis</surname>
<given-names>NG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kitchell</surname>
<given-names>BE</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of ifosfamide salvage therapy for metastatic canine osteosarcoma</article-title>. <source>Vet Comp Oncol</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>257</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22985083</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0028">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Bergman</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>MacEwen</surname>
<given-names>EG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kurzman</surname>
<given-names>ID</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Amputation and carboplatin for treatment of dogs with osteosarcoma: 48 cases (1991 to 1993)</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8683484</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0029">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>London</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mathie</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stingle</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Preliminary evidence for biologic activity of toceranib phosphate (Palladia(&#xAE;) in solid tumours</article-title>. <source>Vet Comp Oncol</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>194</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22236194</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="jvim14555-bib-0030">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="jvim14555-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Milner</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Farese</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Henry</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bisphosphonates and cancer</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>597</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>604</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15515572</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
