<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Allergy Asthma Immunol Res</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Allergy Asthma Immunol Res</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AAIR</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology Research</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2092-7355</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2092-7363</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Korean Academy of Asthma, Allergy and Clinical Immunology; The Korean Academy of Pediatric Allergy and Respiratory Disease</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27826967</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5102841</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4168/aair.2017.9.1.92</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Palonosetron-Induced Anaphylaxis During General Anesthesia: A Case Report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Hyungjun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Oh</surname>
            <given-names>Kyunghwan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Hoonhee</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Ji-Hyang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kang</surname>
            <given-names>Sun-myoung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>So-Young</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kwon</surname>
            <given-names>Hyouk-Soo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>You Sook</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Moon</surname>
            <given-names>Hee-Bom</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Tae-Bum</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Allergy and Clinical Immunology, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Seoul, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Correspondence to: Tae-Bum Kim, MD, PhD, Department of Allergy and Clinical Immunology, Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, 88, Olympic-ro 43-gil, Songpa-gu, Seoul 05505, Korea. Tel: +82-2-3010-3280; Fax: +82-2-3010-6969; <email>tbkim@amc.seoul.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>92</fpage>
      <lpage>95</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 The Korean Academy of Asthma, Allergy and Clinical Immunology &#x2022; The Korean Academy of Pediatric Allergy and Respiratory Disease</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palonosetron is a 5-hydroxytryptamine-3 (5-HT-3) receptor antagonist used for preventing postoperative nausea and vomiting. Compared with ondansetron and granisetron, it is a better drug because of prolonged action and minimal side effects. Some adverse effects of palonosetron have been reported. In this report, we describe a 37-year-old male who developed severe hypersensitivity reactions to palonosetron during surgery for kidney donation. His medical history was unremarkable, except for inguinal hernia with herniorrhaphy 8 years ago. The surgery was uneventful until 2 hours 20 minutes. After palonosetron injection, his blood pressure dropped to 80/50 mm Hg, and facial edema, rash, conjunctival swelling, and wheezing developed. The patient was resuscitated by administration of ephedrine, hydrocortisone, and peniramine. Following the surgery, the patient was monitored for 3 days, and there were no subsequent anaphylactic reactions or other complications. The skin test on postoperative day 54 was positive for hypersensitivity to palonosetron. Although palonosetron is known for its safety, other hypersensitivity events have been reported. Ondansetron is another widely used 5-HT-3 antagonist, which has been reported to cause anaphylaxis. Therefore, clinicians should be aware of the possibility of patients experiencing severe adverse reactions to palonosetron.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Anaphylaxis</kwd>
        <kwd>drug hypersensitivity</kwd>
        <kwd>serotonin 5-jydroxytryptamine-3 receptor antagonist</kwd>
        <kwd>palonosetron</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Anaphylactic response to drugs manifests as a respiratory distress due to laryngeal edema and intense bronchospasm, often followed by vascular collapse or shock.<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Several redisposing factors are associated with hypersensitivity reactions to drugs in patients. Antibiotics, anesthetics agents, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, and opiates are common triggers of anaphylaxis.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></p>
      <p>Severe hypersensitivity reaction during general anesthesia is one of the most frequent drug-induced anaphylactic reactions, as recently shown by several studies in the United States.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Diagnosis of perioperative anaphylaxis is complicated as the patient is often sedated and thus unable to alert the physician of symptoms. Additionally, diagnosis can be hampered by obstruction of skin manifestations with surgical drapes, and cardiac events associated with anaphylaxis can be mistaken for other causes of cardiovascular collapse. Furthermore, multiple drugs are frequently administered simultaneously or in rapid succession during surgery. Most hypersensitivity reactions occur within minutes after administration of the drug; however, depending on the agent and time of administration, reactions can be late-onset.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Common drugs causing anaphylaxis include neuromuscular blocking agents, latex, antibiotics, hypnotics, opioids, and colloids.</p>
      <p>Palonosetron is a 5-hydroxytryptamine<sub>3</sub> (5-HT<sub>3</sub>) antagonist used for the prevention and treatment of nausea and vomiting due to cancer chemotherapy and surgery. Other commonly used 5-HT<sub>3</sub> antagonists include ondansetron and granisetron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Additionally, ondansetron- and granisetron-related hypersensitivity reactions have been reported in 8 and 2 patients, respectively.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p>
      <p>In this report, we describe a patient who developed anaphylaxis during general anesthesia following intravenous palonosetron administration.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>CASE REPORT</title>
      <p>A 37-year-old male was admitted for kidney donation. Prior to surgery, he underwent the following tests for routine evaluation: dimercaptosuccinic acid (DMSA) renal scan, pulmonary function test, abdominopelvic computed tomography, and echocardiogram. His left atrium was mildly enlarged (42 mm), as seen from the echocardiogram; however, no other abnormalities were found. Serological tests showed that the patient was negative for cytomegalovirus, human immunodeficiency virus, hepatitis C virus, and hepatitis B virus.</p>
      <p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, for general anesthesia, rocuronium, fentanyl, and sodium pentothal were administered for intubation, and desflurane was used for maintenance. The surgery was uneventful until administration of palonosetron at 2 hours 20 minutes after the start of the surgery. Five minutes later, the patient's blood pressure (BP) decreased from 140/90 at baseline to 80/50 mm Hg, his heart rate increased from 65 to 80 per minutes, and his oxygen saturation was 98%. During resuscitation, 5 mg of ephedrine was administered twice, but no response was achieved; thus, 10 mg of ephedrine was administered 2 more times. Thirty minutes after palonosetron administration, the patient developed facial and lip edema, conjunctival swelling, and rashes on the face and chest. Thus, 100 mg of hydrocortisone and 4 mg of chlorpheniramine were intravenously administered for treating the rash. Physical examination performed at that time revealed generalized wheezing over both lungs. Therefore, a salbutamol nebulizer (Ventolin) was administered. The results of laboratory tests conducted for differential diagnosis were as follows: blood glucose, 156 mg/dL; sodium, 137 mmol/L; potassium, 3.6 mmol/L; chloride, 105 mmol/L; lactate, 2.2 mmol/L; and hemoglobin, 13.6 g/dL. Thus, bleeding and hypovolemia were excluded from the differential diagnosis. No other intraoperative complications were found.</p>
      <p>After the surgery, the patient was admitted to the intensive care unit for close monitoring, and delayed anaphylaxis was not observed. No further reaction was reported over the following 72 hours. Serum tryptase levels measured 3 hours and 1 day after anaphylaxis were 8.60 and 1.20 &#xB5;g/L, respectively.</p>
      <p>The patient had no prior history of allergies to drugs/food or history of allergic dermatitis, rhinitis, or asthma. He had undergone herniorrhaphy eight years ago, with no adverse events. However, given the severity of the hypersensitivity reaction, a skin test was performed to evaluate the patient's response to palonosetron on days 1, 17, and 54 following the surgery. The skin test was negative on days 1 and 17, but was positive at 1:100 dilution of the allergen (0.5 &#xB5;g/mL) on day 54 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>Palonosetron is a second-generation 5-HT<sub>3</sub> receptor antagonist used for postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV). Palonosetron is superior to ondansetron and granisetron for PONV prophylaxis due to prolonged duration and minimal side effects.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The most common adverse effects of palonosetron in PONV are QT prolongation, bradycardia, headache, and constipation.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p>
      <p>This is the first report of a patient who developed anaphylaxis to palonosetron in Korea. While 1 or more of the anesthetics used in the perioperative period, namely rocuronium, sodium pentothal, and fentanyl, could potentially cause anaphylaxis, they were unlikely to cause serious conditions. Anaphylaxis is an immediate reaction, and patient's symptoms, starting with hypotension, emerged 2 hours after anesthesia induction, within a few minutes after palonosetron injection. The incidence of anaphylaxis to palonosetron is low; however, there was a strong correlation between the time after palonosetron administration and the symptoms. Thus, the patient was diagnosed with anaphylactic reactions to palonosetron.</p>
      <p>Review of the literature revealed 2 previous case reports of anaphylactic reactions to palonosetron. One case involved a 40-year-old female who developed hypotension and hypoxia within minutes following palonosetron administration.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The second case was of a 40-year-old female patient who developed hypotension and bradycardia, and was resuscitated with fluid and diphenhydramine.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> No other cases with definitive anaphylaxis diagnosis were reported.</p>
      <p>Palonosetron is a relatively new drug with unexpected side effects reported in a post-marketing survey.<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The other relatively well-known 5-HT<sub>3</sub> antagonist, ondansetron, was also reported to have an association with hypersensitivity.<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Two patients who developed anaphylaxis following ondansetron administration were assessed by using an intradermal test, which was positive at ondansetron doses of 0.02 and 0.002 mg/mL, respectively. Intriguingly, the skin prick test was negative in both patients.</p>
      <p>In recent reports, a patient who experienced ondansetron-related hypersensitivity had no reaction to granisetron or palonosetron.<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Ondansetron, granisetron, and palonosetron do not share a common indole ring, which might be one of the reasons for the lack of cross-reactivity between these 5-HT<sub>3</sub> antagonists.</p>
      <p>In summary, as illustrated in this case of intraoperative anaphylaxis, albeit rare, palonosetron should be considered as a cause of anaphylaxis.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>There are no financial or other issues that might lead to conflict of interest.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brockow</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Przybilla</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aberer</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bircher</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brehler</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickel</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Guideline for the diagnosis of drug hypersensitivity reactions: S2K-Guideline of the German Society for Allergology and Clinical Immunology (DGAKI) and the German Dermatological Society (DDG) in collaboration with the Association of German Allergologists (AeDA), the German Society for Pediatric Allergology and Environmental Medicine (GPA), the German Contact Dermatitis Research Group (DKG), the Swiss Society for Allergy and Immunology (SGAI), the Austrian Society for Allergology and Immunology (&#xD6;GAI), the German Academy of Allergology and Environmental Medicine (DAAU), the German Center for Documentation of Severe Skin Reactions and the German Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Products (BfArM)</article-title>
          <source>Allergo J Int</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>94</fpage>
          <lpage>105</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26120552</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Laemmle-Ruff</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Hehir</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ackland</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anaphylaxis -identification, management and prevention</article-title>
          <source>Aust Fam Physician</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23529459</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mirone</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Preziosi</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mascheri</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Micarelli</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farioli</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balossi</surname>
              <given-names>LG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of risk factors of severe hypersensitivity reactions in general anaesthesia</article-title>
          <source>Clin Mol Allergy</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26101469</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kannan</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bernstein</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Perioperative anaphylaxis: diagnosis, evaluation, and management</article-title>
          <source>Immunol Allergy Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>321</fpage>
          <lpage>334</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25841554</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Demir</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Batu</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yal&#xE7;&#x131;n</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Civelek</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sa&#xE7;kesen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xFC;y&#xFC;kpamuk&#xE7;u</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anaphylactic reaction owing to ondansetron administration in a child with neuroblastoma and safe use of granisetron: a case report</article-title>
          <source>J Pediatr Hematol Oncol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>e341</fpage>
          <lpage>e342</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20921907</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fernando</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Broadfoot</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ondansetron anaphylaxis: a case report and protocol for skin testing</article-title>
          <source>Br J Anaesth</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>286</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19151059</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>YK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shanmugam</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Padhy</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goyal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Palonosetron induced anaphylaxis in an adult female</article-title>
          <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>149</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20642559</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leung</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guyer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banerji</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>IgE-mediated hypersensitivity to ondansetron and safe use of palonosetron</article-title>
          <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>526</fpage>
          <lpage>527</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24565629</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pietkiewicz</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Possible anaphylaxis to palonoestron</article-title>
          <source>J Oncol Pharm Pract</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>296</fpage>
          <lpage>298</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21859745</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehr</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anaphylaxis to an ondansetron wafer</article-title>
          <source>J Paediatr Child Health</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>543</fpage>
          <lpage>544</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21679335</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chauhan</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jain</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rastogi</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Palonosetron, Ondansetron, and Granisetron for antiemetic prophylaxis of postoperative nausea and vomiting - a comparative evaluation</article-title>
          <source>Anesth Essays Res</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>197</fpage>
          <lpage>201</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25886226</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <collab>Helsinn Healthcare SA (CH)</collab>
          <source>Palonosetron prescribing information [Internet]</source>
          <publisher-loc>Woodcliff Lake (NJ)</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Eisai Inc.</publisher-name>
          <year>2014</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited 2015 Oct 27</date-in-citation>
          <comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aloxi.com">http://www.aloxi.com</ext-link></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Chemical structure of antiemetics.</title>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="aair-9-92-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Chart summarizing the vital signs of the patient with anaphylaxis. Arrows indicate drug administrations: the first narrow arrow, 450 mg of pentothal sodium, 60 mg of rocuronium, and 50 &#xB5;g of fentanyl; the second narrow arrow, 50 &#xB5;g of fentanyl; arrowhead, palonosetron; and wide arrow, 5 mg of ephedrine twice, followed by 10 mg of ephedrine twice. Circle indicates the appearance of rash, facial edema, and conjunctival swelling with immediate administration of 4 mg of chlorpheniramine and 100 mg of hydrocortisone. sBP, systolic blood pressure; dBP, diastolic blood pressure.</title>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="aair-9-92-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Skin test to determine hypersensitivity to palonosetron at dilutions of 1:1, 1:10, 1:100, and 1:1,000. H, control (histamine); N, control (saline). On POD 54, the sizes of wheals were as follows: histamine, 9.5 mm; saline, 2 mm; palonosetron 1:1, 13.86 mm; palonosetron 1:10, 8.5 mm; palonosetron 1:100, 9.5 mm; and palonosetron, 1:1,000, no wheal.</title>
        <p>POD, postoperative day.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="aair-9-92-g003"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
