<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28033255</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5207551</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-16-04443</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000005645</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">05645</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>4500</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Primarily isolated hepatic involvement of amyloidosis</article-title>
        <subtitle>A case report and overview</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ye</surname>
            <given-names>Lei</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shi</surname>
            <given-names>Hui</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Hui-Min</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Fang-Yu</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Azmoudeh-Ardalan.</surname>
            <given-names>Farid</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Jinling Hospital, Medical School of Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China.</aff>
      <author-notes id="cor1">
        <corresp><label>&#x2217;</label>Correspondence: Fang-Yu Wang, Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Jinling Hospital, Medical School of Nanjing University, Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China (e-mail: <email>wangfy65@nju.edu.cn</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>95</volume>
      <issue>52</issue>
      <elocation-id>e5645</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-95-e5645.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <sec sec-type="background">
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>Amyloidosis is particularly difficult to diagnose because the signs and symptoms are subtle. Additionally, there are no specific imaging or laboratory tests, except histopathology. Although it is considered to be a systemic disorder, a small portion of cases may be localized.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="intro">
          <title>Introduction of the case:</title>
          <p>A 54-year-old man presented with nonspecific symptoms (jaundice and back pruritus). Biochemical tests showed a high level of bilirubin and elevated serum tumor markers (CA19&#x2013;9 and CA125). Routine imaging showed hepatomegaly without heterogeneous enhancement. Liver biopsy confirmed the diagnosis of hepatic amyloidosis. No cardiac or renal involvement was found. The patient accepted treatment involving oral chemotherapy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="conclusion">
          <title>Conclusion:</title>
          <p>A rare and unique presentation of hepatic amyloidosis was highlighted in this case.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>hepatomegaly</kwd>
        <kwd>jaundice</kwd>
        <kwd>liver</kwd>
        <kwd>primary amyloidosis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Amyloidoses are a group of disorders that primarily consist of 3 forms, namely primary amyloidosis, secondary amyloidosis, and familial amyloidosis. Amyloidosis is characterized by the deposition of abnormal proteins undergoing a conformational change to form insoluble &#x3B2;-sheet protofilaments.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> The difficulty associated with diagnosing amyloidosis relates to the lack of specific imaging or laboratory tests,<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> which poses a great challenge for clinicians. Biopsy is the gold standard in the diagnosis of amyloidosis. Cases of amyloidosis that are primarily localized in the liver rarely have been reported. Here, we report a case involving a patient with primary hepatic amyloidosis who presented with liver dysfunction.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 54-year-old man was admitted to our hospital for gradual jaundice and weight loss over 2 months. His vital signs were stable and afebrile. On physical examination, his skin and sclera were mildly jaundiced, with scratch marks on his arms and back. An enlarged liver was palpitated 3 fingerbreadths in the right hypochondriac region. The spleen was not palpable. Biochemical tests showed a high level of both total and direct bilirubin (97.8&#x200A;&#x3BC;mol/L and 82.6&#x200A;&#x3BC;mol/L, respectively). Serum alkaline phosphatase (ALP) (374&#x200A;&#x3BC;/L) and gamma glutamyl transpeptidase levels (&#x3B3;-GTT) (319&#x200A;&#x3BC;/L) were also elevated (listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Computed tomography (CT) and magnetic resonance (MR) imaging showed hepatomegaly with no suspicious nodules (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). To determine whether there were blockages in the bile ducts, magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography (MRCP) was used and showed hepatomegaly with cholecystitis. He then was treated with ursodeoxycholic acid capsules and compound ammonium glycyrrhetate single S and ademetionine for a week. However, he developed epigastric pain and had no improvement in the biochemical tests. After consent was obtained from the patient, ultrasonography-guided liver biopsy was utilized. The liver biopsy demonstrated a massive amount of amyloid deposition along the sinusoids (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C&#x2013;G).</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Patient's laboratory results on admission.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e5645-g001"/>
      </table-wrap>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>CT and MRI images of the abdomen showed an enlarged liver and no filament. CT = computed tomography, MRI = magnetic resonance imaging.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e5645-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(A) A biopsy specimen from the skin, photomicrograph (H&amp;E stain) showed collagen-type extracellular material, (B) characteristic &#x201C;apple-green&#x201D; birefringence on polarized light microscopy, which is consistent with amyloidosis, (C) biopsy specimen from the liver tissue, photomicrograph (H&amp;E stain) showed collagen-type extracellular material, (D) Congo red stain demonstrated characteristic staining, (E) methyl violet stain revealed strong affinity for the material, (F) immunostaining with antibodies to kappa light chains was negative, (G) immunostaining with antibodies to lambda light chains was positive, (H) the biopsy specimen from the skin, immunofluorescence with antibodies to lambda light chains was positive. Immunofluorescence with antibodies to kappa light chains was negative (not shown). H&amp;E stains = hematoxylin and eosin stains.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e5645-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Since the patient was found to have amyloid deposition in his liver, we had to conduct other tests to determine whether it was localized or systemic. Echocardiographic and renal function tests, bone marrow aspiration, serum-free light chain test, and skin biopsy (from multiple sites) were performed. Histopathological evaluation showed positive staining with Congo red and characteristic &#x201C;apple-green&#x201D; birefringence on polarized microscopy. All these results indicated primary hepatic amyloidosis, and the skin biopsy was positive for lambda light chains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A, B, H), whereas cardiac and renal function were normal. Serum bilirubin and amino transaminases levels measured at admission and afterward are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Bilirubin and aminotransferase level in serum.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e5645-g004"/>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>The patient refused to take melphalan or undergo stem cell transplant; therefore, we provided him with supportive therapies. No obvious improvement in liver function was observed. Subsequently, he was discharged from the hospital and continued to take oral chemotherapy (thalidomide 100&#x200A;mg/d and prednisone 20&#x200A;mg/w).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Immunoglobulin light chain amyloidosis is a clonal plasma cell disorder in which amyloid fibrils that are derived from immunoglobulin light chains are deposited in organs and tissues. The prognosis is often poor if fibril deposits build up in vital organs such as cardiac muscles. With no treatment, the median survival time is 2 years.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> As reported, a patient with primary amyloidosis presented symptoms that were similar to those of Crohn's disease, delaying accurate diagnosis.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> Therefore, early and precise diagnosis is urgently needed. Since the presenting symptoms tend to mimic those of other diseases, physicians should suspect amyloidosis in any patient with generalized fatigue, weight loss, skin lesions, paresthesias, nondiabetic nephrotic syndrome, and hepatomegaly.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> Symptoms may vary according to the organs and tissues involved. The gastrointestinal system, especially the colon, is the most frequently involved system.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Amyloidosis is usually considered to be systemic, but 10% to 20% of cases can be localized.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Here, we reported a case in which a patient presented with jaundice and altered liver function tests. At first, the elevated serum tumor markers and enlarged liver suggested liver cancer or carcinoma of the gall bladder. However, imaging results did not support cancer. Since the patient was allergic to iodine, contrast-enhanced CT was forbidden. Elevated tumor markers in association with amyloidosis rarely are described in the literature. Serum immunofixation electrophoresis provided a clue that primary amyloidosis was the correct diagnosis. Thus, a subsequent liver biopsy was performed.</p>
      <p>The diagnosis of amyloidosis requires 2 components: a generic and a type-specific diagnosis. Invasive organ biopsy is not always necessary, as fat pad aspiration, in particular, is even more sensitive (72%) than bone marrow biopsy in diagnosing amyloidosis.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> However, if a fat pad aspiration fails to demonstrate amyloidosis, then biopsies of involved organs should be considered.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Currently, mass spectrometry-based proteomics have emerged as a new technique to classify systemic amyloidosis and analyze serum transthyretin in patients with potentially amyloidogenic mutations.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Serum-free light chains, protein immunofixation, MR elastographic, shear-wave elastography, and other examinations support the diagnosis of amyloidosis, but they are not sufficient to define it.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> A proposed strategy for evaluating a patient with suspected amyloidosis can be seen in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>.</p>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Algorithm for diagnosing patients with suspected amyloidosis.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e5645-g005"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Treatment for amyloidosis depends on the type of amyloidogenic protein. For amyloid light-chain (AL) amyloidosis, chemotherapy is the mainstay treatment. It has been reported that melphalan and prednisone are superior to colchicine in 2 randomized phase III studies.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> Melphalan in combination with dexamethasone is highly effective in treating AL amyloidosis with minimal toxicity.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> Autologous stem cell transplantation is a reasonable primary option, but only 20% of patients meet the requirements.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> Researchers have explored new drugs (thalidomide, lenalidomide, pomalidomide, and bortezomib) to treat AL amyloidosis in combination with dexamethasone or melphalan and dexamethasone or dexamethasone and cyclophosphamide.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> Melphalan combined with dexamethasone is still considered to be the standard treatment for nontransplant candidates. However, more data are required on treatment options in association with the pathophysiology of the amyloid formation that is generated.</p>
      <p>Amyloidosis is uncommon, and its prognosis is poor, especially when irreversible organ damage occurs. Thus, the most urgent requirement is an early and accurate diagnosis of the disease. Clinicians should be aware of all the possible signs and initiate an effective treatment as early as possible. This case represents a standard diagnostic process of primary hepatic amyloidosis.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: AL = amyloid light-chain, ALP = alkaline phosphatase, CT = computed tomography, GTT = glutamyl transpeptidase, MR = magnetic resonance, MRCP = magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="equal">
        <p>LY and HS equally contributed to this study.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>Consent: The patient signed informed consent for the publication of this case report and all accompanying images.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>[1]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Primary hepatic amyloidosis presenting as nodular masses on the background of diffuse infiltration and extreme liver stiffness on MR elastography</article-title>. <source>J Gastrointestin Liver Dis</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25532004</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>[2]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chee</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacy</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pitfalls in the diagnosis of primary amyloidosis</article-title>. <source>Clin Lymphoma Myeloma Leuk</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20511161</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>[3]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Trueg</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Disease-free survival following high dose or standard dose therapy in patients with amyloidosis</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>174</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1111/bjh.13656</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26314806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>[4]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Primary amyloidosis mimicking Crohn's disease: a case report</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Exp Med</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>16137</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26629126</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>[5]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morie</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Immunoglobulin light chain amyloidosis: 214 update on diagnosis, prognosis, and treatment</article-title>. <source>Am J Hematol</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1133</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>[6]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perfetto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Moggi-Pignone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Livi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Systemic amyloidosis: a challenge for the rheumatologist</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Rheumatol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>29</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20531382</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>[7]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Siegelman</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Amyloidosis: an overview</article-title>. <source>Semin Roentgenol</source>
<year>1986</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3486474</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>[8]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gertz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirahama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Utility of subcutaneous fat aspiration for the diagnosis of systemic amyloidosis (immunoglobulin light chain)</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
<year>1988</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>929</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2451487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>[9]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kastritis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Recent advances in the management of AL amyloidosis</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>170</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26491974</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>[10]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vrana</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Theis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dasari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical diagnosis and typing of systemic amyloidosis in subcutaneous fat aspirates by mass spectrometry-based proteomics</article-title>. <source>Haematologica</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>1239</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24747948</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>[11]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>HR</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Zeldenrust</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An on-line assay forclinical detection of amyloidogenic transthyretin variants directly from serum</article-title>. <source>Amyloid</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14640032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>[12]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trifanov</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhyani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bledsoe</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Amyloidosis of the liver on shear wave elastography: case report and review of literature</article-title>. <source>Abdom Imaging</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>3078</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26254907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>[13]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Treatment of 100 patients with primary amyloidosis: a randomized trial of melphalan, prednisone, and colchicine versus colchicine only</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>290</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8629674</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>[14]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyle</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gertz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Greipp</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A trial of three regimens for primary amyloidosis: colchicine alone, melphalan and prednisone, and melphalan, prednisone, and colchicine</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>336</volume>:<fpage>1202</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9110907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>[15]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palladini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Milani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Foli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Oral melphalan and dexamethasone grants extended survival with minimal toxicity in AL amyloidosis: long-term results of a risk-adapted approach</article-title>. <source>Haematologica</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>743</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24213149</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>[16]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechalekar</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachmann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Safety and efficacy of risk-adapted cyclophosphamide, thalidomide, and dexamethasone in systemic AL amyloidosis</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16990593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>[17]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaccard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Benboubker</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Lenalidomide in comb ination with melphalan and dexamethasone in patients with newly diagnosed AL amyloidosis: a multicenter phase 1/2 dose escalation study</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>116</volume>:<fpage>4777</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20724537</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>[18]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchorawala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>lenalidomide and dexamethasone for the treatment of immunoglo bulin light chain amyloidosis: Results of a phase II trial</article-title>. <source>Haematologica</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>789</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23144200</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>[19]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dispenzieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Buadi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Laumann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Activity of pomalidomide in patients with immunoglobulin light-chain amyloidosis</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>5397</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>404</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22493299</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R20">
        <label>[20]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamm</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Willenbacher</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of the combination of bortezomib and dexamethasone in systemic AL amyloidosis</article-title>. <source>Ann Hematol</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20821326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
