<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28072685</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5228645</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-16-05041</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000005408</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">05408</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>5700</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Nephrotic syndrome associated with metastatic thymoma treated with chemotherapy</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoo</surname>
            <given-names>Shin Hye</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Hyean-Ji</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jeong-Han</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Gyeong-Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Jeong Hee</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>d</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Se Hyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Ji-Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jin Won</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Jeong-Ok</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Yu Jung</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Keun-Wook</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jee Hyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bang</surname>
            <given-names>Soo-Mee</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Jong Seok</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Thajudeen.</surname>
            <given-names>Bijin</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Division of Hemato-medical Oncology, Department of Internal Medicine, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital, Gyeong-gi</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Division of Hematology-Oncology, Department of Internal Medicine, Gyeongsang Institute of Health Science, Gyeongsang National University Hospital, Gyeongsang National University School of Medicine, Jinju</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Pathology, Gyeonsang National University College of Medicine, Jinju, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes id="cor1">
        <corresp><label>&#x2217;</label>Correspondence: Se Hyun Kim, Department of Internal Medicine, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital, 82 Gumi-ro 173, Bundang-gu, Seongnam, Korea (e-mail: <email>sehyunkim@snubh.org)</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>96</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <elocation-id>e5408</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-96-e5408.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <sec>
          <title>Rationale:</title>
          <p>Nephropathy with concurrent invasive thymoma is a type of paraneoplastic syndrome.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Patient concerns and Diagnoses:</title>
          <p>We report a 32-year-old female with nephrotic syndrome that was first diagnosed along with invasive thymoma and treated by means of cisplatin-based chemotherapy for the thymoma. The patient initially presented with dyspnea and generalized edema. Chest radiography and computed tomography scans revealed right pleural effusion and a mass in the right middle lung field, which were confirmed by a percutaneous lung biopsy as metastatic invasive thymoma. Severe hypoalbuminemia, heavy proteinuria, hyponatremia, and hypercholesterolemia were features of the nephrotic syndrome. A kidney needle biopsy suggested focal segmental glomerulosclerosis.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Interventions and Outcomes:</title>
          <p>All of the symptoms of nephrotic syndrome were resolved simultaneously during the first 2 cycles of chemotherapy. The patient was on regular follow-up with no specific treatment for nephrotic syndrome and underwent successful resection of the left pleura and anterior thymoma. The patient has shown no evidence of recurrence for 2 years.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Lessons:</title>
          <p>We conclude that chemotherapy for invasive thymoma is an effective treatment for nephrotic syndrome accompanying the thymoma.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>case reports</kwd>
        <kwd>nephrotic syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>paraneoplastic syndromes</kwd>
        <kwd>thymoma</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Thymomas are uncommon neoplasms that develop from thymic epithelial cells with an annual incidence of 0.13 per 100,000 individuals in 2003 in the United States of America.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> The median 5-year survival rate varies from 45% to 74%, which influenced by histologic staging based on the guidelines of the World Health Organization.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> Reports suggest that paraneoplastic syndromes associated with thymoma are diverse, including myasthenia gravis, Hashimoto thyroiditis, and pure red cell aplasia.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Nephrotic syndrome is characterized by 24-hour proteinuria above 3.5&#x200A;g, hypoalbuminemia, elevated cholesterol level, and edema,<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> and includes primary nephrotic syndrome without clear cause and secondary nephrotic syndrome with various etiologies such as viral infection, autoimmune disease, and diabetes mellitus.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup> Secondary nephrotic syndrome related to malignant neoplasms has also been reported.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> In such cases, patients with decreased renal function may be unable to tolerate treatment-related toxicities, leading to difficulties in neoplasm management.</p>
      <p>Here, we report a case of a metastatic thymoma accompanied by nephrotic syndrome that was resolved after 2 cycles of chemotherapy against the malignancy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 32-year-old, nonsmoking female came to Seoul National University Bundang Hospital with dyspnea and generalized edema. Prior medical history and family history of hypertension and diabetes were not documented. At admission, her vital signs were blood pressure&#x2014;137/84&#x200A;mm Hg, pulse rate&#x2014;89 beats/min, respiration rate&#x2014;18 breaths/min, body temperature&#x2014;36.6&#x200A;&#xB0;C, height&#x2014;162.8&#x200A;cm, and body weight&#x2014;73.35&#x200A;kg. The patient had gained 10&#x200A;kg in body weight over the preceding 1 month. Mental status was alert. Scleral icterus and anemic conjunctiva were not observed. Lymph nodes were not palpated. Auscultatory chest examination revealed fine inspiratory crackles in the bilateral lower lung field with decreased lung sound. The patient had pitting edema on both lower extremities.</p>
      <p>Laboratory results included white blood cell count&#x2014;7490/mm<sup>3</sup>, hemoglobin&#x2014;14.2&#x200A;g/dL, platelet count in peripheral complete blood&#x2014;253,000/mm<sup>3</sup>, blood urea nitrogen&#x2014;13&#x200A;mg/dL, creatinine&#x2014;0.9&#x200A;mg/dL, total protein&#x2014;3.1&#x200A;g/dL, albumin&#x2014;1.1&#x200A;g/dL, total bilirubin&#x2014;0.2&#x200A;mg/dL, aspartate transaminase&#x2014;18&#x200A;IU/L, alanine transaminase&#x2014;6&#x200A;IU/L, alkaline phosphatase&#x2014;81&#x200A;IU/L, total cholesterol&#x2014;480&#x200A;mg/dL, sodium (Na)&#x2014;132&#x200A;mEq/L, potassium&#x2014;2.7&#x200A;mEq/L, and chloride&#x2014;93&#x200A;mEq/L. A dipstick test showed 3+ albuminuria and 3+ hematuria. Twenty-four-hour urine included 37,731&#x200A;mg protein, 34,081&#x200A;mg microalbumin, and 1.0&#x200A;mg creatinine. Serologic markers were negative for hepatitis B and C. Rheumatoid factor, anticytoplasmic antibody, antineutrophil antibody, and anti&#x2013;double-stranded DNA antibody tests were negative. Monoclonality (M-spike) was not found in serum and urine electrophoresis results. Other laboratory results included immunoglobulin (Ig) G/A/M&#x2014;144/112/134&#x200A;mg/dL (reference range: 700&#x2013;1700/90&#x2013;400/45&#x2013;230&#x200A;mg/dL) and complement 3 (C3)/complement 4&#x2014;74.6/20.9&#x200A;mg/dL (reference range: 70&#x2013;150/10&#x2013;35&#x200A;mg/dL). A chest X-ray revealed a mass in the right middle lung. Computed tomography (CT) scans of the chest revealed right pulmonary and pleural metastases with a malignant mass in the anterior mediastinum (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A and B). CT-guided pleural biopsy was performed.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Enhanced chest computed tomography scan of the patient at admission (baseline). (A) Coronal plane view. (B) Transverse plane view.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5408-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Review at Gyeongsang National University Hospital of a fine-needle biopsy specimen taken from the kidney suggested that most glomeruli were normal in size and cellularity. Light-microscopic findings of global glomerulosclerosis and interstitial lymphocytic infiltrations were not compatible with minimal change disease (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A). Electron-microscopic examination showed diffuse effacement of epithelial foot processes compatible with focal segmental glomerulosclerosis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B). Immunofluorescent staining of IgG, IgA, IgM, C3, C1q, and fibrin was negative, which is compatible with focal segmental glomerulosclerosis.</p>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A kidney needle biopsy suggested focal segmental glomerulosclerosis. (A) Upon light-microscopic examination, most glomeruli were normal in size and cellularity, but there were global glomerulosclerosis and interstitial lymphocytic infiltrations, which are not compatible with minimal change disease (hematoxylin and eosin stain, 200&#xD7;). (B) Electron microscopic examination showed diffuse effacement of epithelial foot processes, which is compatible with focal segmental glomerulosclerosis.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5408-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Lymphocytes and epithelial cells from the thymus were confirmed in a right pleural biopsy specimen (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). A final diagnosis of metastatic thymoma was made. Pleuropneumonectomy was planned contingent upon a good response to neoadjuvant chemotherapy. Testing for c-kit mutation was performed to exclude thymic carcinoma and to consider a targeted agent; exons 9, 11, 13, and 17 were unidentified.</p>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Pathology of the right pleural biopsy (hematoxylin and eosin stain seen under light microscopy, 200&#xD7;).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5408-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient was admitted to the hospital for the first cycle of ADOC (Adriamycin (Ildong Pharmaceutical, Seoul, Korea) 40&#x200A;mg/m<sup>2</sup>, Cisplatin (Ildong Pharmaceutical, Seoul, Korea) 50&#x200A;mg/m<sup>2</sup>, Vincristine (Hospira Korea, Seoul, Korea) 0.6&#x200A;mg/m<sup>2</sup>, and Cyclophosphamide (Baxter Korea, Seoul, Korea) 700&#x200A;mg/m<sup>2</sup> every 3 weeks, full dose). At that time, the patient's body weight was 69.8&#x200A;kg, compared with 63&#x200A;kg in her healthy state. Pitting edema on both legs was severely palpated. The patient's serum Na level had decreased to 127&#x200A;mEq/L. For differential diagnosis, the results of a rapid adrenocorticotropic hormone stimulation test were within the normal range, and the results of a thyroid function test were thyroid-stimulating hormone&#x2014;4.5&#x200A;&#x3BC;IU/mL (reference range: 0.3&#x2013;4.0&#x200A;&#x3BC;IU/mL), free T4&#x2014;0.85&#x200A;ng/dL (reference range: 0.89&#x2013;1.79&#x200A;ng/dL), and T3&#x2014;51&#x200A;ng/dL (reference range: 79&#x2013;200&#x200A;ng/dL). Hence, the illness was considered nonthyroidal.</p>
      <p>Following chemotherapy, the patient's urine output decreased to &lt;1&#x200A;L/d, but recovered after 2 days with a dose of aldosterone receptor antagonist added to loop diuretics. Because the recovery appeared to be reliant on the steroid included in the chemotherapy regimen, diuretics were stopped. With no water restriction, hyponatremia improved and body weight returned to normal (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A). The overall trends of proteinuria, hypercholesterolemia, and hyponatremia improved throughout the 2 cycles of chemotherapy (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>B), suggesting that the nephrotic syndrome was paraneoplastic and was associated with the malignant thymoma.</p>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Results of serial follow-up of the patient. (A) Trend of serum sodium level, daily urine output, and body weight. (B) Trend of proteinuria (spot urine protein/creatinine ratio and spot urine microalbumin/creatinine ratio) and serum albumin levels.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5408-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The patient was monitored without further treatment for nephrotic syndrome. After partial remission was achieved following the completion of 6 cycles of ADOC regimen, the left diaphragm, left pleura, and anterior thymomectomy were removed, and the disease was confirmed as malignant thymoma (surgical staging: Masaoka stage IVa, World Health Organization type B3). No evidence of recurrence of thymoma or nephrotic syndrome has been observed to date.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Paraneoplastic nephropathy is a rare disease category with different clinical presentations, pathophysiologic mechanisms, management, and prognoses, depending on the type of associating malignancies.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Paraneoplastic glomerulonephritis associated with solid tumors commonly occurs when the materials induced by the cancer form immune complexes that damage the endothelial cells of the glomerulus.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Membranous nephropathy is the most common pathologic type of paraneoplastic glomerulonephritis associated with solid tumors, which is followed by minimal change disease.</p>
      <p>Cytokines, such as interleukin (IL)-12 and interferon, that are related to T-helper 1 cells, may play a role in the development of membranous nephropathy associated with solid tumors.<sup>[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> However, minimal change disease is the most common pathologic type of paraneoplastic glomerulonephritis associated with hematologic malignancies and thymic neoplasms. Vascular endothelial growth factor and cytokines such as IL-2, IL-4, and IL-13 induced by T-helper 2 cells and macrophages<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> affect the pathogenesis of minimal change disease, resulting in increased permeability of the glomerular basement membrane.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup> T-cell dysregulation is the key point of the pathogenesis because thymoma is a disorder of the thymus that functions in T-lymphocyte maturation.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Paraneoplastic glomerulonephritis affects only 2% of patients with thymic malignancies.<sup>[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> Cases of nephrotic syndrome associated with malignant thymoma have been reported in Korea and in Western countries.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> In early reports, nephrotic syndrome developed several years after thymectomy or other treatments in a majority of cases.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> However, additional reports have indicated that treatment for nephrotic syndrome preceded the diagnosis of thymoma.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> In a systematic review of reported cases of minimal change disease and solid malignant tumors, including thymoma,<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> nephrotic syndrome and malignant thymoma were simultaneously diagnosed in only 20% of the cases, whereas nephrotic syndrome was diagnosed after the diagnosis of thymoma in 65% of the cases. Besides minimal change disease, which is the most common pathologic type of nephrotic syndrome associated with thymoma, focal segmental sclerosis, membranous nephropathy, and membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis are also associated with malignant thymoma.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup> Only a few cases of focal segmental glomerulosclerosis associated with thymoma, such as the case presented here, were reported previously.<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> Most of the previously reported cases showed malignant thymic pathology, except for 1 case that presented with grade-A benign thymoma.</p>
      <p>Among the reported cases of minimal change disease accompanied by thymoma,<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> 43% responded completely to corticosteroid and/or immunosuppressive agents, and 22% responded partially to treatments. Overall patient survival appears to be better in paraneoplastic minimal change disease accompanied by malignant thymoma than in that accompanied by solid tumors (53% and 30%, respectively).<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> There is little prognostic data from cases of focal segmental glomerulosclerosis, because such cases are scarce. Responses to treatments and survival outcomes vary among cases. One patient who received steroid treatment achieved a complete response,<sup>[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> whereas another patient did not respond to steroid therapy and required maintenance hemodialysis.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> Renal function in the latter patient improved after thymectomy, and she stopped hemodialysis eventually. Another patient had a good response to steroid treatment, but died of severe neutropenia followed by neutropenic sepsis and multiorgan failure.<sup>[<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>There are considerations for treating thymoma with nephrotic syndrome. First, we should be particularly cautious of infection after chemotherapy or steroid treatment for thymoma, because nephrotic syndrome usually increases the risk of infection. We should also consider prophylactic administration of granulocyte-colony stimulating factor if possible, although there was no sign of infection in the case reported here. Next, we should consider limiting the use of cisplatin-based chemotherapeutic agents because of patients&#x2019; decreased renal function. In the case presented here, we applied cisplatin because the patient's renal function was in the normal range; however, some physicians have substituted carboplatin<sup>[<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> or paclitaxel-based regimens for cisplatin. Finally, for secondary nephrotic syndrome, the management plan should be tailored by considering that secondary nephrotic syndrome has a chance to get better after management of the primary tumor with chemotherapy or surgical resection. Octreotide treatment has been utilized in certain cases of thymoma, as have targeted agents such as c-kit inhibitors or epidermal growth factor&#x2013;receptor inhibitors.<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> In such situations, dose adjustment or careful selection of the medication is necessary.</p>
      <p>Thymic tumors respond to neoadjuvant chemotherapy in approximately 90% of cases.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> In particular, patients who underwent resection after shrinking of the tumor with preoperative agents showed good prognosis; however, approximately 15% of those patients did not remain in a disease-free state.<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> It is important to trace the symptoms and signs of paraneoplastic syndrome, because they may hint at recurrence during the follow-up period.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>In summary, a case of nephrotic syndrome, which presented initially as a paraneoplastic syndrome with metastatic thymoma, resolved after chemotherapy for the thymoma.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: ADOC = adriamycin cisplatin vincristine and cyclophosphamide, C3 = complement 3, CT = computed tomography, Ig = immunoglobulin, Na = sodium.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>Ethics: The ethical approval from the Ethics Committee was not necessary to report this case because this case was reviewed retrospectively. Informed consent was obtained from the patient.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>[1]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Malignant thymoma in the United States: demographic patterns in incidence and associations with subsequent malignancies</article-title>. <source>Int J Cancer</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12712448</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>[2]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Monden</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Therapy for thymic epithelial tumors: a clinical study of 1,320 patients from Japan</article-title>. <source>Ann Thorac Surg</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>878</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <comment>Discussion 884-875</comment>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>[3]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>RP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Pascuzzi</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Paraneoplastic syndromes in thymoma: an immunological perspective</article-title>. <source>Curr Treat Options Oncol</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19199040</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>[4]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The nephrotic syndrome</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>338</volume>:<fpage>1202</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9554862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>[5]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bacchetta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Juillard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Paraneoplastic glomerular diseases and malignancies</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18790651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>[6]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jhaveri</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Glomerular diseases seen with cancer and chemotherapy: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23364518</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>[7]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pathogenesis, diagnosis and management of paraneoplastic glomerulonephritis</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Nephrol</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21151207</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>[8]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lefaucheur</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stengel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nochy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Membranous nephropathy and cancer: epidemiologic evidence and determinants of high-risk cancer association</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>1510</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16941021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>[9]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tipping</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitching</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Glomerulonephritis, Th1 and Th2: what's new?</article-title>
<source>Clin Exp Immunol</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>142</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16232206</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>[10]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Berre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Herve</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzelin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Renal macrophage activation and Th2 polarization precedes the development of nephrotic syndrome in Buffalo/Mna rats</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>2079</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16221207</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>[11]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shalhoub</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pathogenesis of lipoid nephrosis: a disorder of T-cell function</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>1974</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>556</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4140273</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>[12]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kodner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Nephrotic syndrome in adults: diagnosis and management</article-title>. <source>Am Fam Physician</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>1129</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19904897</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>[13]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Montpreville</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fakhouri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<collab>Groupe d&#x2019;Etudes des Nephropathies Associees aux T</collab><article-title>Renal and thymic pathology in thymoma-associated nephropathy: report of 21 cases and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1075</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15788438</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>[14]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schillinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Milcent</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Nephrotic syndrome as the presenting feature of malignant thymoma</article-title>. <source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2732</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9430883</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>[15]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Itzhak</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Szylman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Minimal-change nephropathy and malignant thymoma</article-title>. <source>Am J Nephrol</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9481441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>[16]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Khow</surname><given-names>KSF</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JYZ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Minimal change disease as a paraneoplastic manifestation of solid malignant tumors</article-title>. <source>Nephrol Rev</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>[17]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ubara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suwabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis associated with invasive thymoma</article-title>. <source>Ther Apher Dial</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21426517</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>[18]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Minimal change nephrotic syndrome associated with invasive thymoma: a case report with literature review</article-title>. <source>Clin Nephrol</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>296</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>301</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23211340</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>[19]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Illeperuma</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayanaga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A rare case of focal segmental glomerulosclerosis in a patient with grade a benign thymoma: A case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>J Clin Case Rep</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>794</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R20">
        <label>[20]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jayasena</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolfson</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Nephrotic syndrome, malignant thymoma, and myasthenia gravis. Case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Am J Nephrol</source>
<year>1995</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>361</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7573199</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R21">
        <label>[21]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teoh</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Modir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Managing a locally advanced malignant thymoma complicated by nephrotic syndrome: a case report</article-title>. <source>J Med Case Rep</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18353189</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R22">
        <label>[22]</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamarca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Feliu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Thymoma and thymic carcinoma in the target therapies era</article-title>. <source>Cancer Treat Rev</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23261165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
