<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Clin Respir J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Clin Respir J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECRJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>European Clinical Respiratory Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2001-8525</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Co-Action Publishing</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27683028</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5040824</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">31726</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/ecrj.v3.31726</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Disseminated lung cancer presenting as a rectal mass</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Noergaard</surname>
            <given-names>Mia M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stamp</surname>
            <given-names>Inger M. H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bodtger</surname>
            <given-names>Uffe</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Department of Pulmonology, Naestved Hospital, Naestved, Denmark</aff>
      <aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Naestved Sygehus, Naestved, Denmark</aff>
      <aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>Institute of Regional Health Research, University of Southern Denmark, Odense, Denmark</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Uffe Bodtger, Department of Pulmonology, Naestved Hospital, 61 Ringstedgade, DK-4700 Naestved, Denmark, Email: <email xlink:href="Ubt@regionsjaelland.dk">Ubt@regionsjaelland.dk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <elocation-id content-type="doi">10.3402/ecrj.v3.31726</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2016 Mia M. Noergaard et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, allowing third parties to copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format and to remix, transform, and build upon the material for any purpose, even commercially, provided the original work is properly cited and states its license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Primary lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer-related deaths globally, and approximately 50% had metastatic disease at the time of diagnosis. A rectal mass and unintended weight loss are common manifestations of rectal cancer. Our case presented with a rectal mass, but workup revealed a metastatic lesion from lung cancer. Lung cancer metastases to the lower gastrointestinal tract imply reduced survival compared with the already poor mean survival of stage IV lung cancer. Despite relevant therapy, the patient died 5 months after referral.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>non-small cell lung cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>endoscopy</kwd>
        <kwd>diagnosis</kwd>
        <kwd>rectum</kwd>
        <kwd>histology</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Primary lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer-related deaths globally. Metastatic disease at diagnosis is very common, typically involving liver, brain, adrenals, and bones. Symptomatic intestinal/colonic metastases affect 0.2&#x2013;0.5% (5% in autopsy studies) but imply a median survival of 3 months compared with 8 months in overall stage IV non-small cell lung cancer (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). This case presented with a rectal mass, a common clinical manifestation of another common malignancy, colorectal cancer. The case illustrates the unpredictability of malignant spread, and the occasional mismatch between clinical presentation and tissue sampling results.</p>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 70-year-old male never-smoker experienced an 8-kg weight loss during 6 months, alternating diarrhoea/obstipation without bloody stools, slight coughing, and dyspnoea. He had a history of hypertension for many years, uncomplicated and treated with losartan/thiazide 50/12.5 mg and amlodipine 10 mg once daily. Nine years earlier, he was diagnosed with a transitiocellular, papillary bladder tumour, grade III with invasion; underwent successful endoscopic resection without need for oncological treatment; and was followed with annual cystoscopy. Three years later, he was surgically treated for a relapse of transitiocellular, papillary bladder tumour (grade I) and was followed for an additional 5 years without signs of recurrent disease at annual cystoscopy.</p>
      <p>He was a retired industrial worker but with no known occupational exposure to asbestosis, silica, or dust. He was living with his spouse and had no hobbies resulting in exposure to hazardous fumes or dusts.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S0003">
      <title>Diagnostic workup</title>
      <p>He was referred to an outpatient colonoscopy (17 months after he ended urological control visits), revealing an obstructing lower rectal mass. Only a paediatric coloscope could pass the lesion, and biopsies revealed adenocarcinoma, immunohistochemical (IHC) analyses positive for CK7 and TTF-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Fig. 1</xref>), and negative for GATA, CK20, CDX2, PLAP, CD117, PSA, and S100P. PCR showed wild-type EGFR status. Direct histological comparison showed no resemblance with his urological cancer.</p>
      <fig id="F0001" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Immunohistochemical staining of histological biopsy from rectal mass: an adenocarcinoma positive for TTF-1 (A) and CK7 (B).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ECRJ-3-31726-g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Thoracoabdominal contrast-enhanced PET-CT scan showed multiple, PET-positive, enlarged mediastinal and retroperitoneal lymph nodes, a right-sided pleural effusion and associated ipsilateral compression lower lobe atelectasis, ascites, and a tumour located in the rectum with invasion to levator muscles and vesicula seminalis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figs. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">3</xref>). Cytological sampling from mediastinal lymph nodes and pleural exudate showed identical adenocarcinoma including IHC profile cells with a high proliferation index assessed by Ki-67. A bronchoscopy showed no visual tumour.</p>
      <fig id="F0002" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Chest PET-CT scan showing no sign of a primary lung lesion but multiple enlarged lymph nodes, a left-sided compression atelectasis, and ipsilateral pleural effusion.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ECRJ-3-31726-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F0003" position="float">
        <label>Fig. 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Abdominal PET-CT scan showing a rectal mass, moderate quantities of ascites, and enlarged lymph nodes in pelvis and groin.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="ECRJ-3-31726-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <p>At a multidisciplinary team conference, it was decided that the final diagnosis was primary lung cancer, stage TxN3M1b with local metastases to mediastinal lymph nodes, pleura, rectum, and peritoneum. The IHC results were considered to rule out primary colorectal cancer or vesical cancer with thoracic dissemination.</p>
      <p>He started palliative carboplatin/vinorelbine and avastin (43 days after referral to gastroenterologist) as 4 series with 3 weeks intervals. Three-month PET-CT showed a mixed response with an overall sign of progression, and second-line chemotherapy was planned. Before onset, he was admitted with acute dyspnoea and died 2 days later.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0004">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The current case describes a rare site of primary lung cancer metastasis with fatal outcome 153 days after referral. Despite an unusual presentation, neither diagnosis nor therapy onset was delayed.</p>
      <p>One can question the validity of the diagnosis as the patient was a never-smoker without evident lung lesions. However, as three key IHC markers for colorectal cancer were negative, positive CK7 and TTF-1, and no upper G-I CT/PET lesions, neither a primary upper or lower G-I cancer seems likely (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). We found three published case reports on rectal metastases from lung cancer: two were late metastases in earlier surgically resected patients (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), and a recently published case on metastatic, poorly differentiated squamous cell lung carcinoma with multiple metastases to liver, skin, bone, and muscle (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p>
      <p>It is unresolved if intestinal spread reflects a more aggressive or more advanced disease. G-I metastasis may occur through haematogenic spread via the mesenteric inferior artery supplying descending colon, sigmoideum and superior part of rectum (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Yet, cancer metastasis is complex, involving coordination of expression/suppression of numerous genes, and is not fully understood. IL-8 overexpression may contribute to a more aggressive phenotype yet our case was negative for CK20, the IL-8 receptor (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p>
      <p>Improved survival after intestinal single-metastasis resection has been demonstrated in carefully selected patients, but for most patients with intestinal metastases, palliation remains the only available therapy (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p>
      <p>An improved understanding of the pathobiological mechanisms involved in cancer metastases is needed to elucidate targets for improved therapy.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Conflict of interest and funding</title>
      <p>The authors have not received any funding or benefits from industry or elsewhere to conduct this study.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mehta</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liman</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Passero</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liman</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lung cancer with gastrointestinal metastasis &#x2013; review of theories of metastasis with three rare case descriptions</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Microenviron</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12307-013-0135-1">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s12307-013-0135-1</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23963996</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kook</surname>
              <given-names>EH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahn</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeon</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoon</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gastrointestinal metastasis of lung cancer with special emphasis on a long-term survivor after operation</article-title>
          <source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>135</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <lpage>301</lpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00432-008-0424-0">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00432-008-0424-0</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18512073</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miura</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishida</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujibuchi</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niikura</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogawa</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differentiating rectal carcinoma by an immunohistological analysis of carcinomas of pelvic organs based on the NCBI Literature Survey and the Human Protein Atlas database</article-title>
          <source>Surg Today</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>515</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00595-012-0167-z">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00595-012-0167-z</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22441574</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miyazu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rectal metastasis from lung cancer; report of a case</article-title>
          <source>Kyobu Geka</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22314176</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martinez</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coursey</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dodd</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martinez</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Simultaneous thigh muscle metastasis from lung cancer and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> gas producing myonecrosis</article-title>
          <source>Skeletal Radiol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>763</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00256-008-0489-5">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00256-008-0489-5</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18496688</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Win</surname>
              <given-names>AZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aparici</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A case of metastatic rectal squamous cell carcinoma initially diagnosed as lung cancer</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Imaging Sci</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4103/2156-7514.156125">http://dx.doi.org/10.4103/2156-7514.156125</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25973286</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kabwa</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mattei</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>No&#xEB;l</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intestinal metastases of bronchopulmonary cancer. Apropos of a case</article-title>
          <source>J Chir (Paris)</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>290</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8949275</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pezzuto</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mariotta</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fioretti</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uccini</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metastasis to the colon from lung cancer presenting with severe hyponatremia and dyspnea in a young male: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>Oncol Lett</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>1477</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23761813</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sunaga</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imai</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimizu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shames</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kakegawa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Girard</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Oncogenic KRAS-induced interleukin-8 overexpression promotes cell growth and migration and contributes to aggressive phenotypes of non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>
          <source>Int J Cancer</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>1733</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ijc.26164">http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ijc.26164</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21544811</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fujiwara</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okami</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tokunaga</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maeda</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Higashiyama</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kodama</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surgical treatment for gastrointestinal metastasis of non-small-cell lung cancer after pulmonary resection</article-title>
          <source>Gen Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>748</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11748-011-0811-3">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11748-011-0811-3</ext-link></comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22083693</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
