<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Urol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>BMC Urology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2490</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15546481</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">535804</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2490-4-13</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2490-4-13</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Testicular seminoma after the complete remission of extragonadal yolk sac tumor : a case report</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kuroda</surname>
            <given-names>Isao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>veq01625@saitama-med.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ueno</surname>
            <given-names>Munehisa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>camtmune@saitama-med.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mitsuhashi</surname>
            <given-names>Tomoko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref>
          <email>mitsut@saitama-med.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nakagawa</surname>
            <given-names>Ken</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref>
          <email>VEQ01625@nifty.ne.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yanaihara</surname>
            <given-names>Hitoshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>yanaiha@saitama-med.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsukamoto</surname>
            <given-names>Takuji</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>007tt@saitama-med.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
        <contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Deguchi</surname>
            <given-names>Nobuhiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>ndeguchi@saitama-med.ac.jp</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Urology, Saitama Medical School, Moroyama, Saitama, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Saitama Medical School, Moroyama, Saitama, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Urology, Keio University, School of Medicine, Shinanomachi, Shinjyuku, Tokyo, Japan</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <fpage>13</fpage>
      <lpage>13</lpage>
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2490/4/13"/>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>31</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2004 Kuroda et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement>
      <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">
        <p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p>
      </license>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Between 2% and 5% of malignant germ-cell tumors in men arise at extragonadal sites. Of extragonadal germ cell tumors, testicular carcinoma in situ (CIS) are present in 31&#x2013;42% of cases, and CIS are reported to have low sensitivity to chemotherapy in spite of the various morphology and to have a high likelihood of developing into testicular tumors. A testicular biopsy may thus be highly advisable when evaluating an extragonadal germ cell tumor.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Case presentation</title>
          <p>A 36-year-old man was diagnosed as having an extragonadal non-seminomatous germ cell tumor, that was treated by cisplatin-based chemotherapy, leading to a complete remission. In the meantime, testicular tumors were not detected by means of ultrasonography. About 4 years later, a right testicular tumor was found, and orchiectomy was carried out. Microscopically, the tumor was composed of seminoma.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>We herein report a case of metachronous occurrence of an extragonadal and gonadal germ cell tumor. In the evaluation of an extragonadal germ cell tumor, a histological examination should be included since ultrasonography is not sufficient to detect CIS or minute lesions of the testis.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Between 2% and 5% of malignant germ-cell tumors in men arise at extragonadal sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Cytogenetically most extragonadal germ-cell tumors (EGGCTs) i.e., the seminomas and non-seminomas, are similar to their testicular counterparts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. But there are CIS in 31&#x2013;42% of EGGCT patients' testes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Ultrastructural studies indicate that CIS originate from rather primitive cells and can develop into different categories of germ cell carcinomas. Furthermore, since CIS are reported to respond poorly to chemotherapies, a metachronous development of testicular cancer will possibly occur, in spite of the various morphologies of testicular cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In the present case, the etiology of a metachronous appearance of EGGCT and testicular cancer is discussed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Case presentation</title>
      <p>A 36-year-old man was admitted to our hospital with the chief complaint of right-sided scrotal enlargement. He had previously received treatment for an extragonadal germ cell tumor. At the age of 32, he presented with lumbago. CT showed a retroperitoneal tumor (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), and a transabdominal needle biopsy was carried out. Microscopically, the tumor was composed of a yolk sac tumor (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A,2B</xref>). We performed two courses of systemic chemotherapy using bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin, leading to a partial response. As the tumor size was not seemed to decrease after the two courses of the chemotherapy, retroperitoneal lymph node dissection was performed, but failed to show any residual viable cells. An ultrasonic study did not reveal any testicular tumors. About 4 years after the previous treatment, he presented with scrotal enlargement and tumor markers such as AFP and HCG &#x3B2; were within normal limit. A right orchiectomy was performed on 23<sup>rd </sup>July. Pathology showed the resected tumor was a seminoma with CIS (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A,3B</xref>). No recurrence has been seen since the surgery (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>There are reports that approximately 4% of patients with EGGCT develop a metachronous testicular cancer despite the use of cisplatin-based chemotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], and the cumulative risk of developing a metachronous testicular cancer 10 years after a diagnosis of EGGCT is 10.3% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. However, there is disagreement over whether EGGCT is a primary disease or metastatic from the burned-out primary testicular lesion. Actually, burned-out tumors have been detected in 76% of cases of EGGCT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. CIS is also found via biopsy in 31&#x2013;42% cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Testicular CIS is thought to have resistance to systemic chemotherapies and to develop later to metachronous testicular cancer. In the present case, the EGGCT was a non-seminomatous germ cell tumor including a yolk sac component, whereas the testicular cancer was a seminoma. We believe CIS was present at the time of the treatment of EGGCT and testicular CIS is so primitive that it could differentiate into any type of germ cells. It is also possible that these metachronously developing germ cell tumors developed independently. A testicular biopsy could clarify the relationship between these tumor cells and the expansion of the disease. In the present case no biopsy was done, but an ultrasonic examination ruled out the possibility of testicular CIS. Giwercman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] emphasized the necessity of histological examinations of the testis upon an evaluation of EGGCT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and also urged a careful follow-up for patients with EGGCT who do not have simultaneous testicular cancer.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, there is an opinion that any patients with retroperitoneal masses should undergo scrotal ultrasound. Comiter et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] showed definite pathological evidence of a burned-out testicular carcinoma in 5 of 6 patients (83%) with presumed extragonadal germ cell tumors and concluded that scrotal ultrasound studies are useful for the evaluation of the palpably normal testes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Kitahara et al. reviewed the incidence of scrotal echogenic leisions with testicular cancers or burned-out tumors of 22 EGGCT patients and found echogenic changes in 17 patients (77.3%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. This means that disease was overlooked by ultrasonic examinations in 22.7% of cases.</p>
      <p>In our case, it is possibile that metachronous testicular cancer oriented in testicular CIS, grew from a burned-out tumor, or was independent of the EGGCT. We should have performed testicular biopsies at the time of the diagnosis of EGGCT and reflect the strategies of treatments of EGGCT.</p>
      <p>Now we propose a surveillance protocol of EGGCT as Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, concerning with following four points.</p>
      <p>1. As we mentioned, the overall risk of development a testicular tumor is not so high(4&#x2013;10.3%).</p>
      <p>2. The side effect of CIS therapy (whether irradaition, orchiectomy or chemotherapy) are significant, especially concerning fertility and androgen production.</p>
      <p>3. Testicular tumors early detected by adequate surveillance respond well to treatments.</p>
      <p>4. Testicular biopsy is not entitled to detect all the CIS.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Competing interests</title>
      <p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Authors' contribution</title>
      <p>IK, MU, HY, KN, TT and ND carried out clinical treatments.</p>
      <p>TM carried out histopathological studies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Pre-publication history</title>
      <p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p>
      <p>
        <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2490/4/13/prepub"/>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <sec>
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <p>We thank the patient for giving consent for publication of this case report.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dueland</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stenwig</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heilo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoie</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ous</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fossa</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment and outcome of patients with extragonadal germ cell tumours &#x2013; the Norwegian Radium Hospital's experience 1979&#x2013;94</article-title>
          <source>Br J Cancer</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461006</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chaganti</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mathew</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Origin of adult male mediastinal germ-cell tumours</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>343</volume>
          <fpage>1130</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7910232</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(94)90235-6</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Bruin</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slater</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Defferrari</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geurts van Kessel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suijkerbuijk</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jansen</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Jong</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oosterhuis</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isochromosome 12p-positive pineal germ cell tumor</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Res</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>1542</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8137260</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Daugaard</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rorth</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cvon der Maase</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of extragonadal germ-cell tumors and the significance of bilateral testicular biopsies</article-title>
          <source>Ann Oncol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>283</fpage>
          <lpage>289</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1327076</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reinberg</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manivel</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fraley</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carcinoma in situ of the testis</article-title>
          <source>J Urol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>142</volume>
          <fpage>243</fpage>
          <lpage>247</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2545927</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Skakkebaek</surname>
              <given-names>NE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Carcionam in situ of the testis: frequency and relationship to invasive germ cell tumors in infertile men</article-title>
          <source>Histopathology</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27442</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harland</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cook</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fossa</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Risk factors for carcinoma in situ of the contralateral testis in patients with testicular cancer</article-title>
          <source> Eur Urol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>118</lpage>
          <comment>An interim report</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8477771</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bokemeyer</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartmann</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fossa</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Droz</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmol</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horwich</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gerl</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beyer</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pont</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanz</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nichols</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Einhorn</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extragonadal germ cell tumors: relation to testicular neoplasia and management options</article-title>
          <source>APMIS</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
          <comment>discussion 59-63</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12752235</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0463.2003.11101081.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scholz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zehender</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thalmann</surname>
              <given-names>GN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borner</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thoni</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Studer</surname>
              <given-names>UE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extragonadal retroperitoneal germ cell tumor: evidence of origin in the testis</article-title>
          <source>Ann Oncol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11863093</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdf003</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fossa</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aass</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heilo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daugaard</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skakkebaek</surname>
              <given-names>NE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stenwig</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nesland</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Looijenga</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oosterhuis</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testicular carcinoma in situ in patients with extragonadal germ-cell tumours: the clinical role of pretreatment biopsy</article-title>
          <source>Ann Oncol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1412</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12954581</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdg373</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Giwercman</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von der M aase</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skakkebaek</surname>
              <given-names>NE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiological and clinical aspects of carcinoma in situ of the testis</article-title>
          <source>Eur Urol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>104</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <comment>discussion 111-4</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8477770</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mumperow</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lauke</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holstein</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Further practical experiences in the recognition and the management of carcinoma in situ of the testis</article-title>
          <source>Urol Int</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>162</fpage>
          <lpage>166</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1374974</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gleich</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testicular carcinoma in situ and nonpalpable seminoma eight years after contralateral teratocarcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Urology</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>182</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2385889</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kimura</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimizu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakajima</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayakawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primary seminoma of the prostate and embryonal cell carcinoma of the left testis in one patient: a case report</article-title>
          <source>Jpn J Urol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>1497</fpage>
          <lpage>1500</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Comiter</surname>
              <given-names>CV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benson</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Capelouto</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kantoff</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shulman</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richie</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loughlin</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nonpalpable intratesticular masses detected sonographically</article-title>
          <source>J Urol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>154</volume>
          <fpage>1367</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7658540</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005392-199510000-00029</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kitahara</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hori</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tokumitsu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saga</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hashimoto</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaneko</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yachiku</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Retroperitoneal germ cell tumor with testicular calcification indicating tiny testicular origin: consideration of the origin of retroperitoneal germ cell tumors: report of two cases Hinyokika Kiyo</article-title>
          <source>Review Japanese</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec sec-type="display-objects">
      <title>Figures and Tables</title>
      <fig position="float" id="F1">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>CT shows a retroperitoneal bulky mass. (B) The clinical course from the treatment of EGGCT to that of seminoma.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1471-2490-4-13-1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig position="float" id="F2">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Photomicrograph of extragonadal non-seminomatous germ cell tumor with a focus of yolk sac tumor. A: H&amp;E section shows characteristic structures suggestive of Schiller-Duval bodies (&#xD7;200). B: Alpha-fetoprotein immunohistochemical stain is focally positive at the above area (&#xD7;400).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1471-2490-4-13-2"/>
      </fig>
      <fig position="float" id="F3">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Photomicrograph of classic seminoma of the testis. A: H&amp;E section shows compact nests of large tumor cells are separated by thin fibrous septa infiltrated by lymphocytes. B: Intratubular germ cell neoplasia in H&amp;E section (&#xD7;100). A row of atypical germ cells with clear cytoplasm is seen against a thickened basement membrane. No spermatogenesis is occurring in this tubule (&#xD7;200).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1471-2490-4-13-3"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Our proposed surveillance protocol of EGGCT is as below.</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">
                <bold>Testicular Biopsy</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="center">At the time of the diagnosis</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">
                <bold>Self-check of the testis</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="center">Every months</td>
              <td/>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">
                <bold>Scrotal ultrasound study</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="center">-3 years</td>
              <td align="center">-5 years</td>
              <td align="center">-10 years</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td align="center">every 3 months</td>
              <td align="center">every 6 months</td>
              <td align="center">every year</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">
                <bold>Tumor markers</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="center">-3 years</td>
              <td align="center">-5 years</td>
              <td align="center">-10 years</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td align="center">every 3 months</td>
              <td align="center">every 6 months</td>
              <td align="center">every year</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="center">
                <bold>CT(chest-pelvic)</bold>
              </td>
              <td align="center">-3 years</td>
              <td align="center">-5 years</td>
              <td align="center">-10 years</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td align="center">every 3 months</td>
              <td align="center">every 6 months</td>
              <td align="center">every year</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
