<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27603405</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5023928</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000004846</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">04846</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>4300</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Adrenal pheochromocytoma presenting with Takotsubo-pattern cardiomyopathy and acute heart failure</article-title>
        <subtitle>A case report and literature review</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chiang</surname>
            <given-names>Yi-Lun</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Pei-Chi</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Chin-Cheng</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chua</surname>
            <given-names>Su-Kiat</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref>
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Lin.</surname>
            <given-names>Yen-Hung</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of Endocrinology</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Division of Pathology</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Division of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, Shin Kong Wu Ho-Su Memorial Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan.</aff>
      <author-notes id="cor1">
        <corresp><label>&#x2217;</label>Correspondence: Su-Kiat Chua, MD School of medicine, Fu Jen Catholic University, New Taipei City, Taiwan Division of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, Shin Kong Wu Ho-Su Memorial Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan; No. 95, Wen Chang Road, Shih-Lin District, Taipei, Taiwan (e-mail: <email>benchua1131@hotmail.com</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>95</volume>
      <issue>36</issue>
      <elocation-id>e4846</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CCBY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-95-e4846.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <sec sec-type="background">
          <title>Background:</title>
          <p>Pheochromocytoma is an endocrine tumor that causes hypertension, facial pallor, and headache. Pheochromocytoma patients rarely present with acute heart failure or cardiogenic shock.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Method:</title>
          <p>We discuss the case of a female patient with Takotsubo-pattern cardiomyopathy who presented with acute heart failure caused by pheochromocytoma.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Result:</title>
          <p>Treatment was adjusted based on the data of the pulse contour cardiac output system. After intensive hydration and medication for heart failure, the condition of the patient stabilized.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="conclusion">
          <title>Conclusion:</title>
          <p>Before confirming the diagnosis, pulse contour cardiac output data could provide a direction for diagnosis and treatment.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>blood volume</kwd>
        <kwd>heart failure</kwd>
        <kwd>pheochromocytoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Takotsubo cardiomyopathy</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Pheochromocytoma is a rare endocrine tumor that secretes catecholamine and presents with a classic triad of headache, sweating, and palpitation.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> Pheochromocytoma-induced cardiomyopathy has been found to be similar to Takotsubo cardiomyopathy<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> and myocarditis. Therefore, confirming the diagnosis before laboratory data are available is a challenge.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Case</title>
      <p>A 70-year-old woman presented to the emergency department with chest tightness associated with severe dyspnea, nausea, and vomiting. A review of her history revealed that she had intermittent episodic headaches for 1 year. At presentation, her pulse was 110&#x200A;beats/min; blood pressure (BP) 154/96&#x200A;mm Hg; body temperature (BT) 36&#xB0;C; respiratory rate (RR) 30&#x200A;breaths/min; and oxygen saturation 98% in 3&#x200A;L of oxygen administered through a nasal cannula (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Electrocardiography revealed sinus tachycardia with ST-elevation at V<sub>1</sub> through V<sub>4</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). A chest film image showed a borderline heart size and bilateral increased basal lung infiltration. Under the impression of ST-elevation myocardial infarction, the patient underwent emergent cardiac catheterization, which revealed no appreciable coronary artery stenosis. However, left ventricular angiography revealed akinesis of the apical segments of the left ventricle (LV), and excessive basal and middle contractions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The LV end-diastolic pressure was 20&#x200A;mm Hg.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The patient's profile.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e4846-g001"/>
      </table-wrap>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Electrocardiogram obtained on admission showing the sinus tachycardia with ST-segment elevation at V1 through V4.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e4846-g002"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Left ventriculogram obtained on the first day of admission. Discriminating motion of the left ventricle is shown. Akinesis of the apical segment of the left ventricle, and excessive basal and middle motions (arrows) are apparent. A, Right anterior oblique (RAO) view during diastole; B, RAO during systole.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e4846-g003"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The plasma concentration of the pro-B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) was 40,300&#x200A;pg/mL. Other data included the following values: troponin I, 33.4&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/L (&lt;0.5&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/L); creatinine kinase (CK), 738&#x200A;U/L (30&#x2013;223&#x200A;U/L); and CK-MB, 123.6&#x200A;ng/mL (0.6&#x2013;6.3&#x200A;ng/mL).</p>
      <p>Four hours later, her BP suddenly decreased to 72/50&#x200A;mm Hg, and she developed acute shortness of breath, diaphoresis, and a cold appearance. Endotracheal intubation was performed because of respiratory failure, and profound shock was observed. The pulse contour cardiac output (PICCO) system (PULSION Medical Systems AG, Germany) was used to evaluate her hemodynamic condition. Evaluation revealed a cardiac index (CI) of 1.42&#x200A;L/min/m<sup>2</sup>, a systemic vascular resistance index (SVRI) of 5177&#x200A;dyn.sec/cm<sup>5</sup>.m<sup>2</sup>, an intrathoracic blood volume index (ITBVI) of 812&#x200A;mL/m<sup>2</sup> (850&#x2013;1000&#x200A;mL/m<sup>2</sup>), and a global end-diastolic volume index (GEDVI) of 650&#x200A;mL/m<sup>2</sup> (680&#x2013;800&#x200A;mL/m<sup>2</sup>). Echocardiography revealed apical akinesis with relatively preserved LV basal wall motion, and the LV ejection fraction (LVEF) was 11%.</p>
      <p>Owing to the decreased ITBVI and CI, intensive hydration with normal saline and inotropic agents was prescribed. Antibiotics and steroids were administered because of the possibility of myocarditis. After the treatment, the PICCO data showed a CI of 3.69&#x200A;L/min/m<sup>2</sup>, an SVRI of 1929&#x200A;dyn.sec/cm<sup>5</sup>.m<sup>2</sup>, and an ITBVI of 701&#x200A;mL/m<sup>2</sup>. Echocardiography revealed a reduction in abnormal contraction in the apical wall of the LV, and the LVEF was 64%.</p>
      <p>On the fifth hospital day, the urine catecholamine levels (in samples collected on the first hospital day) revealed the following values: epinephrine, 320.1&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/d (0&#x2013;27&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/d); norepinephrine, 305.5&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/d (0&#x2013;97&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/d); dopamine, 80.4&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/d (0&#x2013;500&#x200A;&#x3BC;g/d); and vanillyl mandelic acid (VMA), 25.06&#x200A;mg/d (1&#x2013;7.5&#x200A;mg/d). The alpha blocker was prescribed under the suspicion of adrenal pheochromocytoma. Later, the patient was transferred to the ordinary ward in a relatively stable condition.</p>
      <p>A contrast-enhanced computed tomography scan of the abdomen showed a left adrenal heterogeneous enhanced mass measuring 3.9&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;3.4&#x200A;cm (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The patient underwent an uncomplicated adrenalectomy, and the pathological report confirmed a pheochromocytoma (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The urine VMA was 3.7&#x200A;mg/dL, and the dosage of the hypertension medication was tapered gradually. Patient informed consent was obtained.</p>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Abdominal computed tomographic scan showing a 3.9&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;3.4&#x200A;&#xD7;&#x200A;3.0-cm well-defined heterogeneous enhanced tumor located in the left adrenal glands.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e4846-g004"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Macroscopic and microscopic appearance of the adrenal tumor. A, Normal adrenal and tumor cortex (&#x2217;); B, tumor cells in a nested arrangement and surrounded by fibrovascular stoma; C, tumor cells with basophilic glandular cytoplasm without atypia; D, chromogranin A positivity; E, S-100 positivity; F, synaptophysin positivity. Chromogranin A and synaptophysin are neuroendocrine markers, and S-100 is a marker of neural tissue.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e4846-g005"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We present the case of an old woman with acute LV systolic dysfunction with no occluded coronary arteries. Initial differential diagnosis included Takotsubo cardiomyopathy, myocarditis, and pheochromocytoma with acute heart failure. Owing to the similar presentations of these conditions, diagnosis was difficult.</p>
      <p>Pheochromocytoma is a rare neuroendocrine tumor, typically located unilaterally in the adrenal gland, which may release catecholamine products. Previous studies showed the incidence to be 0.05% to 0.8%.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> Owing to the secretion of catecholamines, patients typically present with a classic triad of headache, palpitation, and sweating. Clinical expression may involve numerous cardiovascular manifestations because of excess catecholamines, but typically present as hypertension.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Pheochromocytoma with acute LV dysfunction is a stress-related cardiomyopathy.<sup>[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> A literature review revealed cases of pheochromocytoma with the presentation of Takotsubo-pattern cardiomyopathy confirmed through ventriculography or echocardiography.<sup>[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> The patients were relatively young. The clinical features varied from palpitation, dyspnea, and abdominal pain to shock and collapse. The electrocardiographic patterns have been heterogeneous, ranging from sinus tachycardia and ST change to bundle branch block. The patients received inotropic agents, intra-aortic balloon pumps, and even extracorporeal life support. Most patients survived if a suitable treatment was provided and a correct diagnosis made.</p>
      <p>Takotsubo cardiomyopathy is characterized by a transient hypokinesis of the LV apex, and is typically induced by stressful emotional or physical events.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Patients with Takotsubo cardiomyopathy tend to be older and are more commonly women.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> The clinical course resembles that of acute coronary syndrome or acute decompensated heart failure, and resolves within days to weeks. The prognosis is generally favorable.</p>
      <p>Patients with myocarditis may have a viral prodrome, and various clinical scenarios can occur, such as acute coronary syndrome, acute dilated cardiomyopathy, and heart failure.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> Male patients are slightly more common than female patients,<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> and a previous study revealed that the inflammation-related cardiac diastolic dysfunction was associated with plasma levels of tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-&#x3B1; and interleukin (IL)-6.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> These inflammatory factors down-regulated the expression of the sarcoplasmic reticulum Ca<sup>2+</sup>-ATPase gene and delayed diastolic calcium reuptake. Whereas the diastolic function improved, the levels of these cytokines decreased.<sup>[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Among the Chinese population, risk-conferring genetic variants of the angiotensin II type 1 receptor gene for diastolic heart failure were found, which were previously identified.<sup>[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Based on clinical presentation alone, diagnosis is difficult to make, and collection of urine data of catecholamine and VMA takes time. Before the urinalysis results become available, PICCO data could provide an indication of the diagnosis. The hemodynamic status showed low CI and high SVRI among the 3 conditions. However, the intravascular volumes of Takotsubo cardiomyopathy and myocarditis were increased, whereas the intravascular volume of pheochromocytoma with acute heart failure was depleted. The low intravascular volume was attributable to the catecholamine-induced volume contraction. Therefore, volume expansion should be performed with caution in patients with pheochromocytoma. Hence, PICCO data could provide a direction for diagnosis and treatment before the data of urine VMA and catecholamine become available.</p>
      <p>Our case indicated that a diagnosis of pheochromocytoma should be considered when echocardiography or angiography reveals Takotsubo-pattern cardiomyopathy. Moreover, PICCO data should be evaluated when patients have acute LV systolic dysfunction with heart failure and no coronary artery stenosis. Finally, for patients presenting with acute heart failure, pheochromocytoma should always be considered.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: BP = blood pressure, BT = body temperature, CI = cardiac index, CK = creatinine kinase, GEDVI = global end-diastolic volume index, ITBVI = intrathoracic blood volume index, LV = left ventricle, LVEF = LV ejection fraction, PICCO = pulse contour cardiac output, RR = respiratory rate, SVRI = systemic vascular resistance index, VMA = vanillyl mandelic acid.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer-Rochow</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pheochromocytoma: current approaches and future directions</article-title>. <source><italic>Oncologist</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>779</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>793</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18617683</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcovitz</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Czako</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pheochromocytoma presenting with Takotsubo syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic>J Interv Cardiol</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>442</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21029177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNeil</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blok</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Koelmeyer</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Phaeochromocytomas discovered during coronial autopsies in Sydney, Melbourne and Auckland</article-title>. <source><italic>Aust N Z J Med</italic></source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>648</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>652</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11198571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prejbisz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenders</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenhofer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cardiovascular manifestations of phaeochromocytoma</article-title>. <source><italic>J Hypertens</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>2049</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>2060</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21826022</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Stress-related cardiomyopathies</article-title>. <source><italic>Ann Intensive Care</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21933374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zegdi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Parisot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleilaty</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pheochromocytoma-induced inverted Takotsubo cardiomyopathy: a case of patient resuscitation with extracorporeal life support</article-title>. <source><italic>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>434</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18242283</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kant</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hans</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Takotsubo-like cardiomyopathy in pheochromocytoma</article-title>. <source><italic>Int J Cardiol</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>153</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21474192</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaku</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Takotsubo cardiomyopathy: pathophysiology, diagnosis and treatment</article-title>. <source><italic>World J Cardiol</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>602</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>609</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25068020</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bybee</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Stress-related cardiomyopathy syndromes</article-title>. <source><italic>Circulation</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>397</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>409</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18645066</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>LT</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>
<article-title>Myocarditis</article-title>. <source><italic>New Engl J Med</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>360</volume>:<fpage>1526</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1538</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19357408</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Plasma levels of tumor necrosis factor-alpha and interleukin-6 are associated with diastolic heart failure through downregulation of sarcoplasmic reticulum Ca2+ ATPase</article-title>. <source><italic>Crit Care Med</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>984</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>992</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21263314</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Genetic polymorphisms of the angiotensin II type 1 receptor gene and diastolic heart failure</article-title>. <source><italic>J Hypertens</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>502</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>507</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19330904</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
