<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27472717</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5265854</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000004340</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">04340</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>6300</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
          <subject>Clinical Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Obturator internus pyomyositis manifested as sciatica in a patient with subacute bacterial endocarditis</article-title>
        <subtitle>A rare case report</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hsu</surname>
            <given-names>Wei-Ching</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hsu</surname>
            <given-names>Jin-Yi</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Michael Yu-Chih</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>c</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref>
            <sup>&#x2217;</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Liang</surname>
            <given-names>Chung-Chao</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>a</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>b</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Wilhelm.</surname>
            <given-names>Mistiaen</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>School of Medicine, Tzu Chi University</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Division of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital, Hualien, Taiwan.</aff>
      <author-notes id="cor1">
        <corresp><label>&#x2217;</label>Correspondence: Michael Yu-Chih Chen, Division of Cardiology, Department of Internal Medicine, Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital, 707 Chung Yang Rd., Sec. 3, Hualien 970, Taiwan (e-mail: <email>michaelchen@tzuchi.com.tw</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>29</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>95</volume>
      <issue>30</issue>
      <elocation-id>e4340</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2016 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-95-e4340.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>Pyomyositis is a pyogenic infection of the skeletal muscles causing myalgia and fever in patients. Hematogenous seeding engendered by persistent bacteremia and septic embolism is usually the underlying cause of the disease. Trauma, intravenous drug use, and immunodeficiency are the main predisposing factors.</p>
        <p>Obturator internus pyomyositis with sciatica has not previously been reported. We report a rare case of a patient with subacute bacterial endocarditis presenting with left buttock pain and sciatica.</p>
        <p>Computed tomography confirmed the diagnosis of obturator internus pyomyositis. The patient was discharged uneventfully after successful antibiotic treatment.</p>
        <p>The mortality rate of patients who have pyomyositis comorbid with another condition or disease is extremely high. Early diagnosis and aggressive management are imperative.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>endocarditis</kwd>
        <kwd>obturator internus</kwd>
        <kwd>pyomyositis</kwd>
        <kwd>sciatica</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name>
          <meta-value>TRUE</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Pyomyositis is an infectious disease of the skeletal muscles and is mostly caused by bacterial infection. It is an infrequent complication of bacterial endocarditis.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> In a prospective case series comprising 11 patients diagnosed with staphylococcal pyomyositis between 1998 and 2007, only 1 patient had bacterial endocarditis. Recent trauma, immunodeficiency, and intravenous drug use are considered to be the main predisposing factors.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> Most pyomyositis presents with muscle pain and fever. Although some studies have described piriformis pyomyositis manifested as sciatica,<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> obturator internus pyomyositis with sciatica has not previously been reported. We herein present a case of obturator internus pyomyositis manifested as sciatica in a patient with subacute bacterial endocarditis. The related literature is also reviewed.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Ethics statement</title>
      <p>The Research Ethics Committee of Hualien Tzu Chi Hospital approved the case report.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 49-year-old man with a history of chronic liver cirrhosis presented with intermittent fever and chills for 2 days. He had a history of high alcohol intake but had stopped drinking several months earlier. A grade II systolic ejection murmur was detected in the aortic region during auscultation. Transthoracic cardiac echography revealed a small oscillating vegetation at the aortic valve. He was treated empirically with intravenous vancomycin 1000&#x200A;mg every 12&#x200A;hours for a diagnosis of subacute bacterial endocarditis. Three pairs of blood cultures were obtained and yielded <italic>Staphylococcus haemolyticus</italic>. Subsequent blood cultures were sterile after 12 days of antibiotic treatment. However, the patient complained of left lower back pain radiating through his buttock to the posterior aspect of the left thigh. A deep tender point over the left gluteal region was found without swelling, warmth, or ecchymosis. A straight leg raise test was administered, but the result was equivocal. The symptoms rapidly deteriorated despite analgesics and the antibiotics. Contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) revealed an enlarged left obturator internus muscle with heterogeneous contrast enhancement (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Pyomyositis of the left obturator internus was confirmed and intravenous gentamicin 80&#x200A;mg every 12&#x200A;hours was administered. Because no well-liquefied abscess was present, drainage was not considered. The sciatica and myalgia subsided gradually with antibiotics treatment. After a complete course of antibiotics for subacute endocarditis, the patient improved and was discharged uneventfully.</p>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) results for the patient: (A) CT conducted at the emergency room, indicating no specific finding of the left obturator internus muscle (arrow); and (B) CT conducted after the patient complained of buttock pain, revealing an enlarged and heterogeneously enhanced soft tissue mass in the left obturator internus muscle (arrow).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="medi-95-e4340-g001"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Pyomyositis mostly occurs in tropical areas; however, the incidence in temperate climates has increased in recent years.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Its predisposing factors include trauma, intravenous drug use, and immunodeficiency such as HIV infection, diabetes mellitus, malignancy, rheumatologic disorder, liver cirrhosis, and renal insufficiency.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> Bacteremia is associated with pyomyositis, though the mechanism remains to be elucidated.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> One hypothesized mechanism is initial muscular trauma followed by bacteremia and finally infection of the traumatized muscle.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> A review reported that a third of pyomyositis cases were associated with local trauma or intensive exercise, approximately 30% had a positive blood culture, and approximately 60% involved HIV or another underlying condition.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Because pyomyositis is a soft tissue infectious disease, muscle pain and fever are the initial symptoms and are followed by abscess formation and sepsis.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</sup> The infection usually affects the extremities and pelvic muscles.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> Sciatica cause by pyomyositis of the piriformis or gluteal muscles has been reported in a few patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is the most common pathogen; other pathogens have been reported but are rare.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup><italic>S haemolyticus</italic> is one of the coagulase-negative staphylococci, a major nosocomial pathogen, but is rarely reported as a cause of community-acquired native valve infective endocarditis. <italic>S haemolyticus</italic> is mostly isolated from axillae and pubic areas associated with foreign body-related infection and bloodstream infection in neonates.<sup>[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> Our patient underwent debridement 3 times and received a split-thickness skin graft operation for a compartment syndrome because of a trauma-related left thigh hematoma 2 months before admission. His bacterial endocarditis and pyomyositis may have been related to this trauma and the following procedure. Magnetic resonance imaging is the first choice for diagnosing pyomyositis because it yields a superior soft tissue contrast compared with CT.<sup>[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> The initial management of pyomyositis should be intravenous antibiotics, and drainage should be performed if an abscess forms.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup></p>
      <p>Because the initial presentation of pyomyositis is acute pain in the pelvis or extremities, early diagnosis is sometimes difficult.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> When the patient has other preexisting medical conditions, the symptoms can be difficult to characterize. In a previous case report, a patient with acute lymphoblastic leukemia was hospitalized for induction chemotherapy and developed pyomyositis that rapidly progressed to quadriparesis and septic shock. The patient presented initially with right hand and left knee pain only.<sup>[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup> Approximately 80% of patients with pyomyositis, whether immunocompromised or immunocompetent, experience fever.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> White blood cell count is not a favorable marker for pyomyositis, especially for immunocompromised patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> For immunocompetent patients, C-reactive protein (CRP) and erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) may be good laboratory tests for excluding pyomyositis.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> A retrospective review of 199 children with a mean age of 8 years found that no child with a CRP level of less than 3.6&#x200A;mg/dL or ESR less than 22&#x200A;mm/h had pyomyositis.<sup>[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> For immunocompromised patient, because pyomyositis can progress quickly, early image studies must be performed. Our patient initially reported left buttock pain with sciatica. The symptoms mimicked those of many other diseases and conditions such as simple muscle strain, piriformis syndrome, lumbar spondylosis, and intervertebral disc displacement. The history of liver cirrhosis, bacteremia, and rapidly deteriorated symptoms prompted us to quickly investigate to confirm the diagnosis and prescribe an aggressive antibiotics treatment. The antibiotic regimen was based on empiric therapy for native or prosthetic valve endocarditis according to American Heart Association guideline.<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup> Gentamicin was added empirically because infective endocarditis from enterococcal infection is not uncommon in patients with chronic liver disease.</p>
      <p>In summary, if a patient with bacteremia complains of local muscular pain with sciatica, the possibility of pyomyositis should be considered, particularly if the patient has predisposing factors. Early diagnosis and prompt medical intervention are crucial in treating such patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: CRP = C-reactive protein, CT = computed tomography, ESR = erythrocyte sedimentation rate.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococcal pyomyositis in a temperate region: epidemiology and modern management</article-title>. <source><italic>Med J Aust</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>189</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>325</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18803536</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooers</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pyomyositis complicating acute bacterial endocarditis in an intravenous drug user</article-title>. <source><italic>N Engl J Med</italic></source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>342</volume>:<fpage>1614</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1615</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10841689</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crum</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bacterial pyomyositis in the United States</article-title>. <source><italic>Am J Med</italic></source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>117</volume>:<fpage>420</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>428</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15380499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokkaku</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Sciatica caused by pyomyositis of the piriformis muscle in a pediatric patient</article-title>. <source><italic>Orthopedics</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>e257</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>e259</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23383745</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moharam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Gluteal pyomyositis in a non-tropical region as a rare cause of sciatic nerve compression: a case report</article-title>. <source><italic>J Med Case Rep</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>204</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18549491</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colmegna</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Justiniano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinoza</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Piriformis pyomyositis with sciatica: an unrecognized complication of &#x201C;unsafe&#x201D; abortions</article-title>. <source><italic>J Clin Rheumatol</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17414537</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stopka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimityongskul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Transgluteal approach for drainage of obturator internus abscess in pediatric patients</article-title>. <source><italic>J Pediatr Orthop</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>; <comment>Epub ahead of print. DOI: 10.1097/BPO.0000000000000681</comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montazeri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Athale</surname><given-names>UH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pyomyositis causing temporary quadriparesis during induction therapy for acute lymphoblastic leukemia: case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic>J Pediatr Hematol Oncol</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24755835</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unnikrishnan</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Tropical primary pyomyositis in children of the UK: an emerging medical challenge</article-title>. <source><italic>Int Orthop</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>113</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19340425</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Yohannes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wladyka</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pyomyositis caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source><italic>N Engl J Med</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>352</volume>:<fpage>1488</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>1489</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15814887</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navinan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yudhisdran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandeepan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Tropical pyomyositis as a presenting feature of subclinical leukemia: a case report</article-title>. <source><italic>J Med Case Rep</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25889902</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Atherton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Obturator externus pyomyositis</article-title>. <source><italic>Pediatr Emerg Care</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>638</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>639</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25186506</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savvidou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalogiannis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsakiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Primary pyomyositis and disseminated septic pulmonary emboli: a reactivated staphylococcal infection?</article-title>
<source><italic>Braz J Infect Dis</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>461</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24794885</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Coagulase-negative staphylococci</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Microbiol Rev</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>870</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>926</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25278577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisno</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Practice guidelines for the diagnosis and management of skin and soft tissue infections: 2014 update by the Infectious Diseases Society of America</article-title>. <source><italic>Clin Infect Dis</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>e10</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>e52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24973422</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arjandas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Obturator internus pyomyositis in a child: a case report</article-title>. <source><italic>Malays Orthop J</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25347752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Optimal imaging strategy for community-acquired Staphylococcus aureus musculoskeletal infections in children</article-title>. <source><italic>Pediatr Radiol</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>841</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>847</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18560822</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baddour</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Infective endocarditis: diagnosis, antimicrobial therapy, and management of complications: a statement for healthcare professionals from the Committee on Rheumatic Fever, Endocarditis, and Kawasaki Disease, Council on Cardiovascular Disease in the Young, and the Councils on Clinical Cardiology, Stroke, and Cardiovascular Surgery and Anesthesia, American Heart Association: endorsed by the Infectious Diseases Society of America</article-title>. <source><italic>Circulation</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>e394</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>e434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15956145</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
