<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCHIMP</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Community Hospital Internal Medicine Perspectives</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2000-9666</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Co-Action Publishing</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27609719</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5016751</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">31750</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/jchimp.v6.31750</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Thyroid storm presenting as psychosis: masked by diabetic ketoacidosis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Memon</surname>
            <given-names>Raafia</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
            <given-names>WuQiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Snyder</surname>
            <given-names>Richard</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>DO</degrees>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Krishnamurthy</surname>
            <given-names>Mahesh</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, FACP, SFHM</degrees>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Easton Hospital, Academic Affiliate of Drexel University College of Medicine, Easton, PA, USA</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Raafia Memon, Department of Internal Medicine, Easton Hospital, Academic Affiliate of Drexel University College of Medicine, 250 South 21st Street, Easton, PA 18042, USA, Email: <email xlink:href="Raafia_memon@chs.net">Raafia_memon@chs.net</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>07</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <elocation-id content-type="doi">10.3402/jchimp.v6.31750</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2016 Raafia Memon et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License, permitting all non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="st1">
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>While extremely uncommon, diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) and thyroid storm (TS) are endocrine emergencies that can coexist. We describe a case with a confounding clinical presentation that identifies these two emergencies within the setting of sepsis and influenza.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st2">
          <title>Case</title>
          <p>A 69-year-old diabetic female was found by the paramedic staff to be disoriented. She demonstrated tachycardia and had a foul-smelling abdominal wound. Laboratory evaluation revealed DKA, leukocytosis, influenza B, and urinary tract infection. After appropriate management in the intensive care unit, the DKA resolved the following morning. However, the patient developed a fever, and her psychosis became more pronounced. Extensive analysis was performed but did not explain her mental status. The patient was found to have thyroid stimulating hormone of 0.06 mIU/mL, free T4 (thyroxine) of 2.38 ng/dL, and total T3 (triiodothyronine) of 72 ng/dL. Based on the Burch and Wartofsky criteria (score of 65), TS was diagnosed. Based on more recent diagnostic criteria suggested by Akamizu et al., the patient met criteria for TS grade 1. Within several hours of initiating treatment, the patient's mental state and tachycardia improved, and her psychosis resolved by the third day.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="st3">
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>This case highlights the importance of recognizing the clinical diagnosis of TS, as the magnitude of thyroid hormone derangements may not correlate with clinical severity. While rare, DKA and TS can simultaneously occur and are associated with increased morbidity and mortality if not promptly recognized and treated.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>thyroid storm</kwd>
        <kwd>diabetic ketoacidosis</kwd>
        <kwd>hyperthyroidism</kwd>
        <kwd>thyrotoxicosis</kwd>
        <kwd>diabetes mellitus</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Thyroid storm (TS) is a life-threatening metabolic emergency that can cause significant dysfunction of multiple organ systems. The frequency of TS in the United States is not well defined but has been reported to be 0.2 cases per 100,000 individuals annually, occurring in less than 10% of patients hospitalized for thyrotoxicosis (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). If unrecognized and untreated, however, it can be associated with a mortality rate in the range of 10&#x2013;25% (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). It can develop in patients with chronic, untreated hyperthyroidism or may be precipitated by infection, surgery, trauma, iodine load, parturition, and/or non-adherence to antithyroid medications (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) and TS have been identified as coprecipitants, which can coexist (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). We report the complex case of a female with known type 2 diabetes mellitus who presented with DKA, influenza B, and sepsis symptoms simultaneously, which made the diagnosis of TS a challenge. Additionally, this was her first clinical manifestation of thyroid disease.</p>
    <sec id="S0002">
      <title>Case description</title>
      <p>A 69-year-old female, with a history of type 2 diabetes mellitus on insulin therapy, was brought to the hospital by emergency medical services due to encephalopathy. The patient also had a history of hypertension, hyperlipidemia, asthma, and panniculitis of the abdominal wall. She was post-surgery, which was complicated by a chronic non-healing abdominal wound. The patient, who at baseline was ambulatory and independent in activities of daily living, was found by her neighbors to be confused, agitated, and yelling incoherently. Upon arrival, paramedic staff found the patient to be disheveled and lying on the floor in a pool of her urine and feces. Upon physical examination, she was tachycardic, only oriented to self, with a foul-smelling discharge emanating from her abdominal wound. Laboratory evaluation revealed the following readings: white cell count of 12.6&#xD7;10<sup>9</sup> cells/L, blood glucose level at 444 mg/dL, bicarbonate reading of 17 mmol/L, anion gap level of 17, positive ketones, pH of 7.26, and base excess of &#x2212;8.3. She tested positive for influenza B, and urinalysis indicated urinary tract infection (UTI). The patient was admitted to the medical intensive care unit and initially managed with intravenous insulin infusion for DKA, broad-spectrum intravenous antibiotics (vancomycin and piperacillin/tazobactam) for UTI and the abdominal wound infection, and oseltamivir for influenza B. DKA resolved by the next morning, and the patient was transitioned to a subcutaneous insulin regimen.</p>
      <p>On the second day of her hospitalization, the psychosis of the patient became more evident and was characterized by hallucinations, paranoia, incoherence, screaming, inappropriate laughter, and combativeness with the staff. That afternoon she had a fever (101.2&#xB0;F) with worsening sinus tachycardia (and her heart rate was greater than 130 bpm). The symptoms the patient showed were attributed to delirium associated with sepsis and DKA. However, there was concern for a possible underlying central nervous system infection, and after a diagnostic lumbar puncture, the patient was empirically started on acyclovir. Cerebrospinal fluid studies, however, were not suggestive of infection. The patient was evaluated by multiple consultants for psychiatry, neurology, and infectious diseases. For symptomatic management, quetiapine and haloperidol were initiated, but she continued to manifest severe psychosis. Magnetic resonance imaging of the brain revealed an old right pontine infarct, which did not correlate with her symptoms. Additionally, vitamin B12 and ammonia levels were within normal limits. On the third day, the initial diagnostic workup was revisited and showed low thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) (0.06 mIU/mL). Further thyroid analysis was performed, which showed high free T4 at 2.38 ng/dL and low total T3 at 72 ng/dL; suggestive of hyperthyroidism. Based on the Burch and Wartofsky scoring (BWS) system for TS (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), our patient's score was 65, which a result of 45 or greater is considered highly suggestive of TS (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="T0001" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Burch and Wartofsky scoring system for thyroid storm</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnostic criteria</th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scoring points</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature &#xB0;C (&#xB0;F)</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2&#x2013;37.7 (99&#x2013;99.9)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8&#x2013;38.2 (100&#x2013;100.9)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3&#x2013;38.8 (101&#x2013;101.9)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>15</bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9&#x2013;39.4 (102&#x2013;102.9)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5&#x2013;39.9 (103&#x2013;103.9)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;40 (&#x2265;104)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS effects</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (agitation)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate (delirium/psychosis)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>20</bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe (seizure/coma)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal&#x2013;</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate (diarrhea)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x2003;hepatic dysfunction</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe (jaundice)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tachycardia</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99&#x2013;109</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110&#x2013;119</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120&#x2013;129</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130&#x2013;139</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>20</bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;140</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congestive heart failure</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (pedal edema)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate (bibasilar rales)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe (pulmonary edema)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atrial fibrillation</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Precipitant history</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                <bold>10</bold>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn>
            <p>CNS, central nervous system. Bolded values represent the patient's score.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Based on more recent diagnostic criteria suggested by Akamizu et al. (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), our patient also met the criteria for TS grade 1. Immediate treatment with methimazole, Lugol's iodine solution, hydrocortisone, and propranolol was started. Within several hours, the patient's mental state and tachycardia improved. She appeared more lucid, calm, and her speech became coherent. By the third day of treatment, the mental state of the patient had returned to her baseline. She behaved appropriately, and her psychosis resolved. Her overall condition improved, and the patient was discharged to a skilled nursing facility, in a stable condition, after three days.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S0003">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The pathogenesis of the coexistence of DKA and TS is multifaceted. Normal thyroid function is essential for maintaining equilibrium in glucose metabolism. However, hyperthyroidism can worsen glycemic control in patients with diabetes mellitus (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Thyroid hormone excess has been implicated in increasing intestinal glucose absorption, increased hepatic production of glucose from glycogen, decreased insulin secretion from the pancreas, increased insulin resistance, and increased renal clearance of insulin. Untreated thyrotoxicosis can also predispose a patient with type 2 diabetes mellitus to DKA by affecting adipokines and altering carbohydrate metabolism (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p>
      <p>The simultaneous presentation of these two endocrine emergencies, DKA and TS, can pose a diagnostic challenge as this combination is exceedingly rare. Several factors could mask or delay the diagnosis of either, including their co-existence, and sepsis. When considering the diagnosis of TS, it is important to bear in mind that a fever may be suppressed (as was the case in our patient) at the initial presentation due to DKA and may develop only after the resolution of the DKA (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Another important element which can delay diagnosis is that severely uncontrolled diabetes may falsely decrease blood levels of thyroxine and triiodothyronine (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p>
      <p>In our patient, the initial clinical features of tachycardia and fever were confounding factors for systemic inflammatory response syndrome and TS, given that there were sources of infection (abdominal wound and UTI) and influenza B. The patient fulfilled diagnostic criteria for sepsis, and it is likely that this masked the presence of coexisting TS. However, the lack of improvement in her mental state, despite antibiotic therapy for more than 48 hours, prompted consideration of an alternative diagnosis with a thorough diagnostic analysis revealing the thyroid disorder.</p>
      <p>The initial analysis revealed low TSH level, but it was not suppressed to the degree which one would expect to see in overt clinical hyperthyroidism. Therefore, this case highlights the importance of recognizing the clinical diagnosis of TS as the magnitude of thyroid hormone excess may not correlate with clinical severity. To date, there are no universally accepted diagnostic criteria for TS; however, the BWS system suggested by Burch and Wartofsky in 1993 is one of the most widely used diagnostic tools to differentiate uncomplicated hyperthyroidism from TS (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Based on this scoring system, diagnoses are related to clinical assessment, rather than laboratory abnormalities (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>). More recently, the Japanese Thyroid Association (JTA) criteria were proposed by Akamizu et al. (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). According to one study, BWS selects a higher percentage of patients for aggressive treatment, in comparison to JTA (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). While differences do exist between BWS and JTA, both remain essential tools in the clinical evaluation for TS.</p>
      <p>The present case also illustrates the neuropsychiatric manifestations of TS, which have been associated with high mortality risk (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In a recently published retrospective study by Angell et al., the altered mental state was the only significant clinical feature distinguishing TS from compensated hyperthyroidism (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). TS is an under-recognized cause of the altered mental state and should be considered earlier in patients with a history of thyroid disease, diabetes mellitus, or other autoimmune pathologies. It is crucial to be aware of the coexistence of DKA and TS in order to prevent life-threatening complications, such as cardiac arrest (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="S0004">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Contributing factors must be taken into consideration when encountering a patient who may have both DKA and TS. They can simultaneously occur and are associated with significant morbidity and mortality if not promptly recognized and treated. This case emphasizes the importance of actively considering the presence of other endocrine disorders when encountering a patient with an endocrine disease. This is particularly important when the patient fails to improve with initial management or there is a worsening of the underlying clinical condition.</p>
      <p>Thorough clinical assessment remains the cornerstone of diagnosing TS as the derangements in thyroid hormones may not correlate with clinical severity.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <sec id="S0005">
      <title>Conflict of interest and funding</title>
      <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest or disclosures to declare.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CIT0001">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akamizu</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Satoh</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isozaki</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suzuki</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wakino</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iburi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnostic criteria, clinical features, and incidence of thyroid storm based on nationwide surveys</article-title>
          <source>Thyroid</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>661</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22690898</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0002">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Swee du</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lim</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical characteristics and outcome of thyroid storm: A case series and review of neuropsychiatric derangements in thyrotoxicosis</article-title>
          <source>Endocr Pract</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>182</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25370315</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0003">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Osada</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hiroi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sue</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Masai</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iga</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shigemitsu</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid storm associated with Grave's disease covered by diabetic ketoacidosis: A case report</article-title>
          <source>Thyroid Res</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21492449</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0004">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiles</surname>
              <given-names>PG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diabetic ketoacidosis precipitated by thyrotoxicosis</article-title>
          <source>Postgrad Med J</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <issue>883</issue>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10533635</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0005">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kearney</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diabetic and endocrine emergencies</article-title>
          <source>Postgrad Med J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <issue>976</issue>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17308209</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0006">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burch</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wartofsky</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Life-threatening thyrotoxicosis. Thyroid storm</article-title>
          <source>Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>263</fpage>
          <lpage>77</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8325286</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0007">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cooppan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kozak</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hyperthyroidism and diabetes mellitus. An analysis of 70 patients</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>370</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6767456</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0008">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bratusch-Marrain</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komjati</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waldhausl</surname>
              <given-names>WK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Glucose metabolism in noninsulin-dependent diabetic patients with experimental hyperthyroidism</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1063</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3889028</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0009">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Potenza</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Via</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yanagisawa</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Excess thyroid hormone and carbohydrate metabolism</article-title>
          <source>Endocr Pract</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>254</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19364696</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0010">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lakin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bradley</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
              <given-names>GO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute hyperthyroidism in severe diabetic ketoacidosis</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med Sci</source>
          <year>1961</year>
          <volume>241</volume>
          <fpage>443</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13758382</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0011">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kunishige</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sekimoto</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Komatsu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bando</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uehara</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Izumi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyrotoxicosis masked by diabetic ketoacidosis</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes Care</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>171</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11194224</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0012">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mouradian</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abourizk</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diabetes mellitus and thyroid disease</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes Care</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>512</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6400713</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0013">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Warnock</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burch</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Diagnosing Thyroid storm: A comparison of the Japanese Thyroid Association criteria to the Burch-Wartofsky Point Scale</source>
          <conf-name>Presented at the Endocrine Society 96th Annual Meeting</conf-name>
          <conf-date>21&#x2013;24 June 2014</conf-date>
          <conf-loc>Chicago, IL</conf-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0014">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Angell</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lechner</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salvato</surname>
              <given-names>VL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicoloff</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>LoPresti</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical features and hospital outcomes in thyroid storm: A retrospective cohort study</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>451</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25343237</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0015">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ko</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid storm concealing diabetic ketoacidosis leading to cardiac arrest</article-title>
          <source>Resuscitation</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>345</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15582771</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CIT0016">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Troen</surname>
              <given-names>LP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taymor</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldberg</surname>
              <given-names>BI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid crisis associated with diabetic coma</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>1951</year>
          <volume>244</volume>
          <fpage>394</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14806771</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>
